this is a Harvard University course
taught by Dr David Meen and we are proud
to bring it to the freeo camp YouTube
channel throughout a series of lectures
Dr men will teach you how to think
algorithmically and solve problems
efficiently and make sure to check the
description for a lot of extra resources
that go along with the
[Music]
course
all right this is cs50 Harvard
University's introduction to the
intellectual Enterprises of computer
science and the Arts of programming my
name is David man and I actually took
this course myself back in 1996 I was a
sophomore at the time I was actually
concentrating in government because a
year prior as a first year I'd come into
Harvard thinking that I liked high stre
and constitutional law and sort of
similar classes in high school and so
when I got here I rather gravitated
toward that which was familiar I figured
if I liked and if I were good at that
particular subject in high school then
that's presumably who I'm supposed to be
here but it wasn't until sophomore year
that I got up the nerve to step foot in
the cs50 classroom and even then it was
only out of curiosity like I had no
intention of studying computer science
of even taking cs50 when I got to campus
but people were talking about it and
there was a lot of like beware and it
was it perhaps for the initiated only
and I didn't really know ultimately what
computer science was but for me the sort
of light bulb went off and I found that
contrary to what I had seen in high
school where I saw friends of mine like
programming away in the computer lab
heads down sort of anti-socially just
doing whatever it was they were doing it
really wasn't that once I got to this
particular class in this particular
place it was much more about problem
solving more generally and just learning
how to express yourself in code in
different languages so that you can
actually solve problems of interest to
you even if you have no intention of
being a computer scientist or an
engineer but just want to be able to
solve problems analyze data do
interesting things in the Arts Humanity
social sciences physical sciences or
really any other field and indeed this
particular path led me to computer
science but the hope for cs50 more
generally is that indeed you just find
your way to applying principles that
you'll learn over the coming months to
whatever field is of interest to you
with that said it was definitely a lot
of work and not without its frustrations
for me but there was no better feel
then like banging your head proverbial
against the wall for some number of
hours even days trying to fix a bug a
mistake in your code and then oh my God
the rush of emotion of accomplishment of
pride of exhaustion when you finally
solve some problem that's really been
weighing on you it's just so incredibly
gratifying but also empowering because
unlike a lot of fields the computer
science was built by humans themselves
and so if a human built this surely you
another human can understand it as well
and so even though there's going to be
some distractions along the way you're
going going to see what looks incredibly
cryptic if you've never programmed
before over time and with practice
everything just starts to make more
sense and with time and with practice
you just get better at this particular
field and indeed really the key to
success in programming in general is
just to allow yourself enough time and
so at least thankfully I quickly got
into the habit of starting early in the
week for instance when writing actual
code why because you're going to like
run up against a wall you're not going
to see some bug something's not going to
jump out at you and that's fine that's
when you sort of call it a day take a
break move move on to something else and
then just come back to it and that's
what keeps programming fund for me even
all of these years later whether it's
teaching or actually applying it but
there's uh down the road a history of uh
an MIT hack and it looked a little
something like this in yester year and
there was a little sign the MIT students
when they made this hack uh on the wall
that says getting an education from MIT
is like drinking from a fire hose which
indeed they have connected to what
should have been otherwise just a water
fountain and that's going to be what it
feels like sometimes not just in
computer science per se but just in UNAM
familiar field if you're not from stem
if you're not from CS that's fine but so
much of it ultimately is going to be
absorbed by you and going to be uh
within your grasp by term Zen so just
keep in mind that's that's very much the
intent but you'll be amazed what you're
able to create to accomplish uh just
three or so months hence indeed 2third
of you contrary to what you might think
or assume have never taken a CS class
before so it's absolutely not the case
that the person to the left and to the
right surely must know more than you
indeed it's quite the opposite and as
you'll see in the coming weeks as you
write your own code and solve your own
problems what ultimately matters in this
course is not so much where you end up
relative to your classmates but where
you end up relative to yourself when you
began and it really is all about that
Delta whether you've programmed or not
just getting something out of a class
like this and and if it does take time
and if you do feel those frustrations
but you simultaneously eventually feel
that sense of accomplishment that just
means it's all working and indeed
hopefully all the more worthwhile and
gratifying ultimately as a result so
what are we going to do in the coming
week so here we are in week zero we'll
soon see why computers and computer
scientists start counting if you will
from zero but week zero is which is one
in which we explore computational
thinking sort of thinking like a
computer and starting to clean up your
thought processes getting you to think
to solve problems more methodically and
then ultimately Translating that into
code and some of you might recognize
this environment here AKA scratch
coincidentally also from MIT you might
have used it in in grade school we'll
use it today and a little bit this
weekend in the course's first homework
assignment or problem set but not so
much to kind of play around in a way
that you might have if you did use it in
yester year but to explore ideas of
computer science and programming that
we're going to use and reuse every week
Hereafter as well uh thereafter we're
going to transition just next week to
week one so to speak whereby we'll
introduce you to a more traditional
language a lower level language an older
language called C and in C you're going
to use your keyboard not so much your
mouse and pointing and clicking but
you're going to write code that soon is
going to look a little something like
this and if you programmed before can
probably glean what this is going to do
if you've never programmed before which
is the case for most of you this too
will soon make sense but this is the
most canonical program that most any
programmer ever writes called hello
world and indeed that and all of the
surrounding syntax above and below just
that sentence hello world will soon make
all the more sense you'll learn how to
use industry standard tools so to speak
pictured here something called Visual
Studio code or vs code you'll use a
cloud-based version of it initially so
you don't have to suffer with any
technical difficulties or headaches like
that it'll just work right off the bat
but we'll use that tool and others
ultimately to then explore ideas in
computer science principles that you can
apply and we'll take a look underneath
the hood so to speak of your computer at
your memory or Ram Random Access Memory
where all of the data is ultimately
going to be stored we'll also take a
look thereafter at bugs a bug is a
mistake in a program here is an actual
bug in an actual computer in yester year
but we'll teach you how to debug
programs find your own mistakes find
others mistakes and improve that code as
well we'll transition then to algorithm
step-by-step instructions for solving
some problems which we'll touch on today
too and if you picture here this is
actually a pretty representative
problems odds are you haven't had to
deal with something like this but it's
representative sorting for instance if
you think of each of these small bars as
being a small number each of the bigger
bars as being a bigger number you might
wonder well how is you could do as a
human sort all of these bars like get
all the short bars over here all the big
bars over there well odds are if you're
like me you would probably kind of
eyeball it and if you could physically
interact you might just start grabbing
the smallest elements first put them
over on the left maybe grab the biggest
elements put them over on the right but
what's your algorithm there like how
would you teach someone younger than you
who's never done that before how to do
it how would you compel your Mac or PC
or phone to do something like that you
can't just kind of wave your hand and
say oh you know figure it out move
things around you have to express
yourself more methodically so we'll
translate even ideas like this into code
to and that's what the Googles and
others of the world are doing constantly
as they sort and organize the world's
information we'll use metaphors along
the way if it helps we'll talk about
your computer's memory is kind of being
like a postal address like every mailbox
in the world has some form of postal
address Street city state country and
the like and it turns out that's how
your Mac your PC and your phone also
work you've got a whole bunch of memory
like the picture before but you can
think of it really as individual
mailboxes and you can put anything you
want in those mailboxes and you can go
to a mailbox to grab information that
from it so at the end of the day that's
really all your computer's doing with
information it's just kind of organizing
it not into mailboxes per se but a term
you probably know called bites for
instance instead we'll talk about
problems that arise even nowadays in
fact most of you are familiar with your
Mac PC even phone like spontaneously
rebooting sometimes crashing the little
Annoying spinning beach ball or
Hourglass Icon that Happ like what is
with that well those are just bugs in
programs that humans at Apple and Google
and Microsoft and others they screwed up
and they wrote buggy code and your
computer when it encounters those
mistakes doesn't know what to do and so
nine times out of 10 so to speak it just
crashes or freezes or the like but that
kind of stuff will make more sense so
even the real world will make sense and
pictured here or some lower level terms
will eventually get to Mid semester but
generally speaking when something is
going this way as per this arrow and
something is going this way as per this
Arrow like that does not end well and
that often is what happens when your
computer crashes someone's using memory
up here but someone else is using memory
down here here and then they're not
really talking left hand and right hand
so that is just a high level overview of
some of the problems we'll encounter but
we'll focus to on data ultimately so
picture here is something fairly
technical called a hash table it's an
amalgam of something we're going to soon
call an array and also something we call
a linked list and these are just fancy
terms for describing how you can
organize information even more flexibly
than just putting individual ma values
in mailboxes like how could you build
structures like actual data structures
so to speak speak two-dimensional
structures at that and so what you're
seeing here is a glimpse uh as some of
you might have recognized of some Harry
Potter Universe names but they're
organized somewhat alphabetically and
notice that anytime there's multiple
people with a name that starts with H
like hermion Harry and Hagrid well they
can't all fit in that mailbox if each of
these squares along the left is that
same mailbox so you have to kind of
chain them together well you'll learn
how to do that in code so that even if
you get more data than you expect if
your business is booming and you're some
web-based business how do you keep
adding and adding information to your
software to actually keep up with it but
this again is what codee's going to soon
look like as soon as next week in week
one this here being C but we'll
transition in a few weeks to a more uh
modern higher level language so to speak
called python indeed the course Very
deliberately back in my day and now this
introduces you first to C which funny
enough most many people don't tend to
program and certainly every day I you
see generally September October November
December when teaching C is 50 itself
but it's everywhere nonetheless in fact
even today's other languages with which
you might be familiar like Python and
Java and uh yet others still you see
this same primitive language underneath
the hood because it's so darn fast and
as you'll learn over the coming weeks it
really gives you access to and an
understanding of what's going on
conceptually down here so that
thereafter after cs50 when you're
writing code you can sort of think at a
very high level what's actually going on
so in fact in just a few weeks what
looks like this C is going to look
instead like this in Python and you'll
better understand what's going on
underneath the hood and odds are after
this class you'll reach for a language
like python more frequently than C but
you're going to benefit from that bottom
up understanding thereof thereafter and
toward terms end we'll introduce you to
a few other ideas like where do you put
large amounts of data in things called
databases not things like spreadsheets
like here but actual databases where
using those same kinds of data
structures you lay things out in an
interesting way in memory thereafter
will transition to a very familiar
environment that you and I use every day
the web like the web has become rather
the user interface or UI that we use
everywhere on the uh laptops desktops
and even mobile devices nowadays well
pictured here is a language called HTML
it's not a programming language it's a
markup language and some of you might
have made homepages or portfolios in the
past but you'll understand what's going
on here but more powerfully you'll
understand how the computer sees that
same kind of code builds up a
hierarchical family tree type structure
in memory and then you can manipulate
that tree with code to actually add more
and more information chat messages
anything on the screen that you like and
finally we'll tie all of this together
by introducing what are called
Frameworks and libraries third-party
code that makes it a lot easier to solve
problems of interest to you and so in
particular here this is the very first
web app that I myself made back in like
1997 I was part of the first year
intramural sports program not as an
athlete but as the programmer and I was
teaching myself how to build web
applications I only knew C and maybe a
little bit of something else at the time
but this became for Harvard at least the
very first website for the first year uh
intramural sports program and it wasn't
just a static website with links and
images and the like it was interactive
you could register for sports we could
input exactly who is in a tournament
bracket or the leg and it could actually
automatically keep track of this data so
there two after just three months of a
class like this you'll go from writing
quite simply this week in next hello
world to building things like this for
whether it's web mobile uh or other
platforms as well if you so choose but
we'll get you off of the courses
infrastructure by the end of the term
you won't be using any toy environments
along the way will Empower you
ultimately to write code after cs50
especially if this is the only CS class
you ever take on your own Mac or PC
using the same software but not the
cloud-based version thereof but all of
this software is itself free and can be
used by you uh powerfully after the
course's own end but along the way as
you may know uh is there this tradition
within the class particularly in healthy
times of a number of events that really
brings people get together not just
collaboratively academically but to just
solve problems and generally uh engage
with each other as well coming up first
cs50 puzzle day which is meant to be not
jigsaw puzzles but logic puzzles that
require no prior experience with
computer science or programming but it's
just an opportunity to sort of quietly
work on a packet of puzzles with some
number of friends for for prizes and
more later the semester once you tackle
your final projects the Capstone of the
course where we don't give you a
homework to write you yourself come up
with something to build we'll get
together generally around 7 a uh 700
p.m. in the evening uh wrap up around 7
a.m. if you so choose and it's an
evening a 12-hour opportunity to
collaborate with classmates on your very
own final project in a large space on
campus uh that ends if you're awake with
us at 5:00 a.m. uh we can hop on some
cs50 shuttles and go down the road for
some pancakes at IHOP around 6 uh of
course uh of course this is 6 7 a.m. at
that point but it's an opportunity
finally to lead into What's called the
cs50 fair which is an end of semester
celebration an exhibition of everything
that you'll accomplish over the coming
months and in fact pictured here are
some of your predecessors and healthy
times um the cs50 fair allows you to
come with your laptop or phone and
exhibit a students faculty and staff
across campus put together something in
person and on video that people can
Delight in seeing as you exhibit what it
is you create in what you learned over
the course of the several weeks and
ultimately a chance to just share and
Inspire others as well um and you'll all
walk home ultimately with your own I to
cs50 t-shirt saying as much as well so
with that highlevel overview of the
course I propose that we begin to take a
look at what computer science itself is
and what it is we're going to be doing
over the next several weeks at this
lower level than two so what is computer
science right if you're maybe like me or
new people like my friends and High
School you probably assume that it means
programming and that's absolutely a big
part of it for a lot of people because
with code you can write you can express
ideas and solve actual problems
especially involving data but computer
science itself is really the study of
information if you will how do you
represent it and how do you actually
process it and in that sense
computational thinking is just the
application of ideas from computer
science a course like this to problems
of interest to you again in the Arts
Humanities Sciences social sciences
whatever the domain interest is to you
so with that if computer science is all
about information and with it the
solving of problems well what does it
actually mean to solve a problem let's
see if we can't propose a model into
which all of the Lessons Learned will
ultimately follow and I'd propose that
this is problem solving you've got some
input which is like the problem you want
to solve the goal is to solve it so
that's the so-called output and then
somewhere in here the proverbial black
box is some kind of Secret Sauce that
gets the work done and in the coming
months have to decide well how are we
going to represent these inputs and
outputs and really how do we code up how
do we write solutions for what it is
that's solving the problem of interest
to us so when it comes to representation
of information like there's a lot of
ways we can do this and for instance if
the problem at hand quite simply is to
like take attendance at the beginning of
class on the first day of school well
how could we go about doing this well we
could actually use a system called unary
well what is that well that's a fancy
way of saying 1 2 3 4 5 maybe 6 7 8 9 10
and I can use my digits pun intended on
my fingers to actually count everyone up
and eventually you need toes and whatnot
if you have to count so high but unary
is a very simple system of using a
single symbol a human finger in this
case to just solve some problem like
counting the number of people in the
room let's make this slightly more
technical for a moment a little more
mathy that's just called base one where
the base under which you're operating
has one digit in it like literally a
human finger and maybe multiple such
fingers if you need to count higher but
of course of course all most of you if
not all of you generally vaguely know
that computers use something other than
unary and even you and I probably don't
use this that often they use what
language or alphabet
instead yeah so binary so binary is
indeed the system that computers somehow
use so in this case by implying two and
so computers have two digits it turns
out at their dispos one in fact if
you've ever heard the technical term bit
which is like a smaller version of a
bite more on that soon well a binary
digit is the origin of that term bit
because if you get rid of some of the
letters and you're left from binary
digit with just bit thus is a bit a bit
is just a zero and one it's two more
digits than you might have on your own
finger and of course it's fewer though
than you and I have you and I typically
use as humans the decimal system deck
meaning 10 because you and I generally
use zero through nine so on the one hand
another pun intended you've got unary
computers use binary we humans generally
think and talk in terms of De
but at the end of the day these are
fundamentally going to be the same thing
which is to say that it's all pretty
accessible to us even if you're not a
computer person I dare say you're about
to be so what is a bit well a bit then
is a zero or a one that is a so-called
binary digit but how do computers only
speak in binary how do they solve
problems represent information using
only binary well at the end of the day
if they want to represent zero and one
we need to do so physically somehow and
I dare say that maybe the simplest way
to think about a bit a zero or one is
like a light bulb and so by human
convention let's just assume that if you
are a computer be it a laptop desktop
phone or the like and you want to
represent the number zero you know what
you just keep a light switch off you
keep a light bulb off if by contrast
you're that same computer and you want
to represent the number one you take
that same switch that same light bulb
and just turn it on so a light bulb
that's on represents a one and a light
bulb that's off represents a zero so why
is this relevant into computers well at
the end of the day you and I are
charging our laptops or phones at night
so there's some like physical resource
being replenished there whether you're
on battery or some power cord and so a
inside of a computer are just thousands
millions of tiny little switches
nowadays you can think of them
metaphorically as light bulbs but they
don't yet it's actually shine light but
there are tiny tiny little switches and
those switches if you've ever heard the
term are just called transistors so like
computers have millions of transistors
that can either be flipped on to
represent ones or flipped off to
represent zeros and from that very
simple mechanism electricity is there or
it's not a one or a zero computers can
actually count obviously from zero to
one but it turns out even higher if they
use a little more electricity as well so
how might I do this well let me go ahead
and propose that I just grab one of our
own light bulbs here on stage this one's
off so for instance If This Were
miniaturized inside of your Mac PC or
phone this would be a transistor and
indeed here's the little switch on the
bottom and if your computer wants to
represent a zero it just leaves the
switch off and the light is not shining
if you want to represent a one well now
I've counted as high as one because the
switch is now on I've grabbed a little
electricity I'm holding on to it inside
of the computer and so now I see that
this is a one all right but
unfortunately with just one switch one
light bulb I can only count from zero to
one how do I count out higher might you
think
intuitively say again yeah so more light
bulbs so let me do this let me just put
grab something to put these on so I can
use a few of them at a time and let me
propose that here instead of having just
one light bulb let me give myself maybe
three in total so all of them are
initially off and if you think of this
in miniature form in your mind's eye
this is like a computer with three
transistors three switches representing
now the number you and I know as zero
why they're just all off so how does a
computer go about representing the
number one well it turns on one of these
light bulbs and how does the computer
represent the number two well you might
think if I by may you just turn on a
second light bul and if you might think
how does a computer represent three you
just turn on the third light bulb and so
as such with three bits a computer would
seem to be able to count from zero on up
to 1 two three but it turns out if I'm a
little smarter here I can actually count
higher than that why well I'm just
considering like the combination of
bulbs being on here what if I do
something like this this is still zero I
will claim but what if I propose now
that this will be how a computer
represents one on on off off this though
will be how the computer represents two
notice I didn't turn on the same two I'm
just turning on the one in the middle
this I now claim will be how a computer
represents three this is going to be in
just a second how a computer represents
the number we know as four and yet I'm
still only using three bulbs this is
going to be the number the computer
represents as five this is going to be
how the computer represents the number
six and then lastly it turns out with
three light bulbs if you're smart about
it you can count it seems as high as
seven now even if you kind of lost track
of like what I was turning on and Y I
claimed there were eight different
patterns from all of them off to all of
them on but notice that I started to
permute them I took into account which
ones were on and which ones were off why
though do these represent the numbers we
know as 0 through 7even well let me go
ahead and maybe let's let's do this
instead of just considering there to be
light bulbs let's assign some special
significance to each of them based on
where it is and maybe for this could we
get uh maybe three volunteers three
volunteer okay yeah who's you're being
volunteered okay come on up if you want
to go over to the stage there yeah you
want to come on up as well and over here
as well so there's some stairs on either
end maybe a round of applause for our
first volunteers of
term all right so you want to be you are
number one and if you want want to go
ahead and stand roughly right here how
about you want to be number two okay
come on over and right uh to the right
of here and you'll be number four it
turns out and if you want to come over
here on this end let's give you all a
moment to uh introduce yourselves uh
briefly to your classmates if you'd like
hi I'm Ellie I'm a senior nice to meet
I'm rahana and I'm a first year welcome
hi I'm Joseph and I am a first year
welcome all right so so glad to have all
three of you up here thank
you let me propose now that we'd like
you you three to represent how about the
number zero and I claim now that if each
of you now represents a switch you have
sort of fancier light bulbs now one is a
one one is a two one is a four but each
of you still just has a switch on the
bottom in fact of your plastic devices I
claim these three volunteers are
representing the number zero let me ask
you all now how might you represent the
number one how should you cooperate here
okay so so we would have on off off
which I think is matches what I did with
my three light bulbs as well if you want
to go ahead and turn yours off how might
you three represent the number
two okay so off on off now from right to
left how would you3 represent the number
three ah so that's why my two light
bulbs went on at the end how would you
three represent the number
four perfect number
five number six
and number
seven all right and give us one more how
would you represent
eight okay you can't uh how about then
one more volunteer one more volunteer
okay come on
up all right what's your name my name is
Moen if you want to say it there my name
is Moen all right Moen you're GNA be
number eight and if now you all actually
let's make this uh how would you
represent number eight all collectively
as four bits or four
switches okay eight and now lastly give
me
15 everyone's awkwardly doing arithmetic
in their head oh using
unar hey yeah is
everyone yes okay Round of Applause okay
thank you
all if you want to leave your numbers
over here we have a 650 stress ball for
you but thank you for volunteer you can
turn those numbers off and leave them
over here so thank
you so how do we go about how do we go
from there to uh creating these patterns
well even though we still had three bits
initially and three switches later four
bits and four switches ultimately we
still used it used the same approach
fundamentally to actually representing
information and now why were they those
patterns and why did I very deliberately
have our volum volunteers line up in
that way well I wanted them using base 2
AKA binary but with binary there come
certain rules and even if you're not
familiar with binary beyond that it
exists and relates somehow to computers
it's actually pretty much identical to
the system you and I use every day known
as base 10 AKA decimal so let's consider
if you will by rewinding to primary
school for just a moment like how
decimal works and you'll see that even
if you're not a computer person you
actually are you just have to tweak your
mental model ever so slightly so here is
the number that you're probably viewing
as 123 but why is that well it's not
really 123 these are just uh this is
just a pattern of three symbols on the
screen 1 2 three and your mind is sort
of rapidly assigning mathematical
meaning to them 123 but why is that well
if you're like me you probably learned
back in the day when you have a
three-digit number like this the
rightmost number is in the ones place
the middle digit is the 10 place the
leftmost digit is in the hundreds place
and why is that relevant well if you
then quickly do some mental math as you
and I just do uh instantly nowadays that
just means 100 * 1 plus 10 * 2 plus 1 *
3 of course 100 + 20 + 3 gives us the
number you and I know as
123 but beyond that how do we get to
just two digits instead of as many as
nine in the decimal system well let's
generalize this in the decimal system
you and I know if we've got three digits
represented by these hashes here yes
it's the ones place T Place hundreds
place and if we keep going thousands 10
thousands and so forth but why is that
well base terminology is now a little
more gerine that's technically the 10 to
the zero column the 10 to the 1 10 to
the two so these are powers of 10 where
10 is your base computers just simplify
things a little bit because computers at
the end of the day only have access to
electricity on or off they don't have
access to like 10 different types of
electricity just two on or off if you
will well they just use a different base
and the rightmost digit would be in the
so-called 2 to the zero then the middle
digit is 2 to the one the leftmost is 2
to the 2 AKA one's Place two's Place
Four's place and as we kept going 8 and
if we keep going 16 32 64 128 and so
forth but the idea is fundamentally the
same so why is this how the computer
represents the number you and I know is
zero well off off off from right to left
or in this case left to right is just
zero why CU that's 4 * 0 + 2 * 0 + 1
time 0 is of course 0o this is why 0 01
represents one this is why 0 1 0
represents two and three and four and
five and six and seven on up and why did
we need a fourth bit to represent eight
well we kind of needed to carry the one
so to speak using our human familiar uh
familiar human terminology but for that
we need a fourth bit another transistor
and this now represents the number eight
and that's why we ended with on from
left to right off off off so I keep
saying on and off or the light bulb is
on or off but really I just mean one or
zero and so computers and we humans
think of things digitally as just being
zeros and ones but mechanically you can
think of it indeed as these light bulbs
now a bit not very useful even three
bits four bits not that useful you can
count to seven or 15 generally speaking
bites are a more useful unit of measure
and anyone familiar how many bits is in
a bite yeah so eight bits are in a bite
can think of it as an octet equivalently
uh in some context there are nuances
there but think of a bite as just being
eight bits and that's just a more useful
measure so what does this mean in real
terms well if you've ever downloaded
like a music file or a photograph or a a
video those are measured in bytes
probably not small numbers of bytes
probably kilobytes for thousands of
bytes megabytes for millions of bytes
gigabytes for billions of bytes
especially for video that just means you
have a lot of patterns of 8 Bits some
combination of zeros and ones on your
computer's hard drive here then with a
bite of bits eight bits is how a
computer would typically represent the
number zero and if that same computer
uses all eight of its bits it's full
bite to rep uh to change it to one
anyone who's quick with math or have
seen this before how high can a computer
count with eight bits or one yeah 255
why is that well we're not going to turn
this into a constant math exercise
indeed after today we're not really
going to think about or talk about bits
at this low level but this is the ones
place 2os 4S 8 16 32 64 128 and if I do
all of that math from left to right that
indeed gives me
255 it ignores how we might represent
negative numbers but perhaps more on
those some other day but computers of
course do so much more than numbers and
math and all this lowlevel stuff we send
text messages right documents emails and
the like so how might a computer
represent something like the letter A I
claim at the end of the day your Mac
your PC your phone just has lots of
transistors lots of switches that it can
use in units of eight in units of bytes
how though if it's already using those
patterns of zeros and ones apparently to
represent numbers from zero on up how do
you go about representing letters of the
alphabet might you think yeah okay so we
could assign a number to every letter
okay so let me just conjecture well
let's just call a0 for Simplicity B1 1
C2 and now let me play Devil's Advocate
okay how do I now represent zero or one
or two well we've maybe created a
problem for oursel if now we have to
steal some numbers to represent letters
we kind of have to pick a lane but
there's a solution to that too that
we'll see and it turns out the world is
not quite as simple as a being zero a
typically is represented by computers
everywhere phones everywhere with the
number 65 the decimal number 65 using 8
Bits if we turn some of the zeros to
ones let me just stipulate you can
represent the letter A Using eight bits
by turning certain ones on and certain
ones off but we will try not to focus on
the that binary level too much so if a
is 65 it turns out that b is going to be
66 and C is going to be 67 and so forth
and so where does that get us well it
turns out there's a whole system that
Maps uh numbers to letters and here uh
as I alluded to verbally a moment ago is
the pattern of zeros and ones via which
you'd represent 65 and just quick check
here we won't constantly do math uh
one's place that's easy 2os Four's 8 16
32 64's place so 64 + 1 gives us
65 so once I do that how do I get to all
of the others well it turns out a bunch
of Americans years ago came up with this
asky the American Standard code for
information interchange now what does
that mean well it's just an acronym
describing what really you proposed a
mapping between numbers and letters not
not quite as simple as 012 starts at 65
66 67 for capital letters but here are
most of the letters in use today at
least with this system so this is just a
big chart from online and you'll see it
in the middle of this chart here here's
my 65a here's my 66 b c and let's see 72
is H 73 is I and so forth so there's a
mapping at least for English between all
of these numbers and all of these
letters and if we focus here those are
the beginning of our up case alphabet so
suppose then that today tomorrow you
receive a text message from someone and
underneath the hood now that you're a
computer person you figure out a way to
see what pattern of zeros and ones was
sent in this case it's wireless as
opposed to wired but it's still some
pattern of zeros and ones and your phone
is turning some switches of its own on
and off to represent that message from a
friend suppose that the three patterns
you received were these three btes from
left to right spelling out a
three-letter word well if if we do out
the math one's Place two's place and so
forth I'll spoil it for you suppose that
you received a text message that doesn't
literally say 72 73 33 but you've
received a pattern of 8 plus 8 plus 8 24
bits that if you do out the math
represent the decimal number 72 73 33
anyone recall what message you might
have received from the green and white
charts
yeah hi but yes hi is the message but
7273 gives H and I what's 33 any any
guesses to
33 yeah over here yeah so it's an
exclamation point how would you know
that well you really do need some kind
of cheat sheet AKA aski in this case and
if we look elsewhere let me highlight
the left of the chart you can see that
next to 33 in decimal is indeed the
exclamation point so back in the day a
bunch of humans got in a room decided
that hey when we start building PCS and
later Macs and phones we all just have
to agree on this form of representation
of letters of the the English alphabet
in this case we just need to agree on
this mapping but somewhat curiously
notice this it turns out that once you
paint yourself into this corner and
start using 65 for a 66 for B well how
do you represent 65 the number and 66
the number if you want to do math or use
Excel or something like that does anyone
kind of see the solution perhaps how do
you represent the number one in asy yeah
in the
middle yeah so this is getting a little
maybe Inception or something but you
could represent numbers with other
numbers and so if you want to represent
the number you and I know as one like
when you type it on your keyboard turns
out the computer stores that as the
decimal number 49 if you hit two on your
keyboard the computer is not storing two
per se it's storing the decimal number
50 now thankfully the the uh the uh the
the Paradox kind of stops there we just
have a mapping now of numbers to to
numbers but really at the end of the day
and you're going to learn this when we
start writing code in that other
language C next week it's just context
dependent at the end of the day inside
of your Mac PC and phone there's just
all of these permutations of bits all of
these patterns of zeros and ones and
generally speaking when you open up a
text message that you've received from
someone it's zeros and ones but
obviously if it's a text message the
whole point of text messages is to send
text and so those patterns of zeros and
ones by default will typically be
interpreted as letters of the alphabet
so you won't see zeros and ones you
won't see decimal numbers you'll see the
English message that your friend
intended by contrast if you open up
something like Excel that same pattern
of zeros and ones might indeed work out
to be 6 uh 72 73 33 you might see cells
in your spreadsheet with literally those
three numbers why because spreadsheets
are all about numbers and number
crunching and math uh in many cases if
by contrast you open up Photoshop and
try to look at that same pattern of
zeros and ones it's not going to be 727
73 33 it's not going to be zeros and
ones it's not going to be high it's
going to be some color of the rainbow
you're going to use those patterns of
zeros and ones it turns out too to
represent colors and indeed so long as
you and I just agree as humans long have
what these patterns are going to be all
of our systems many of our systems
nowadays are indeed interoperable but
I'm being very biased here and indeed
the a in ASI is very American Centric
what do you not see in this chart if you
speak any other language in English odds
are you're not seeing characters you
know and love and need every day to type
or send messages well there's a huge
character set that's not supported here
whether it's accented characters and a
lot of Asian alphabets you have many
more symbols than can fit even on this
screen here and so humans kind of
painted themselves into a corner early
on or really Americans did but on a
typical keyboard us English keyboard
yeah you have A's and B's and C's
uppercase and lowercase but you also
have accented characters here and
nowadays not sure if this is maybe
necessary but nowadays you have other
characters on your keyboard like these
and these are kind of a playful
incarnation of what's actually a
technical solution to this problem if I
claim for the moment that ASI
historically used seven bits to
represent letters and let's just round
that up to a bite eight bits to
represent letters aski can represent as
many as 255 or really
256 total characters why 256 well if you
have them all zero that's zero and the
highest number I claimed a moment AG go
was 255 so that's 256 total
possibilities that's not many letters
it's fine for English but not a lot of
human languages so what might the
intuitive solution be if you want to
represent accented characters um Asian
characters Emoji even like these which
are just keys on a keyboard
nowadays what's the intuitive solution
if a bite's too few
yeah yeah so add another digit just like
we had a fourth volunteer come on up to
give us a fourth bid let's just throw
throw Hardware at the problem and use a
few more bits so maybe instead of one
bite let's use two or heck let's use
three or four bytes even though it's
getting a little expensive we're going
from 8 to 16 to 24 or 32 bits that's how
computers do things these days and
thankfully we have so much memory inside
of our computers and phones we can
certainly spare a few to represent these
things and the solution then to aski is
what we'll call Unicode so Unicode is
also just a mapping of letters to num of
numbers to letters but in many many
different languages and indeed the
Unicode Consortium is a bunch of people
from all different companies and and uh
and a lot of different uh companies and
countries and cultures whose mission as
an organization is to capture digitally
all forms of human language in this case
and to ensure that especially smaller
demographics of humans speaking lesser
known languages are nonetheless
represented and preserve digitally using
some mapping of these zeros and ones it
turns out though if you start using 32
bits as many as 32 bits to represent
characters on a keyboard that's 4
billion possible permutations of zeros
and ones that's way more than we need
for most human languages so there's a
little bit of room in there for some of
those more playful things like those
Emoji so for instance suppose you got a
text message with this pattern of zeros
and
ones or if we do out the math suppose
you receive a text message that if you
do out the math in decimal is 4 B 36
m991 106 anyone know what emoji you're
looking
at this would be weird if you do
but what is this Well turns out that as
of this past year this is the most
popular Emoji to be sent uh by many
measures face with tears of joy so that
is the pattern that a bunch of humans in
the Unicode Consortium decided would
represent this but you'll notice some
many of you might have iPhones some of
you might have Android devices too and
sometimes these don't actually look
quite the same this happens to be the
current version of face with tears of
joy on iOS on Android it tends to look a
little something more like this and
here's kind of a curiosity even though
you and I look at these things and they
look like images they're not images
they're characters at least as we've
defined them now in Unicode and a IOS
and Android and Windows and Facebook and
other companies and uh apps nowadays
really just have different fonts if you
will so just like fonts with English and
other languages can give you different F
characters with seraps or not emoji are
themselves yes drawings that someone
made but they're really just a font and
so that same pattern of zeros and ones
might just render slightly differently
on someone's phone or another if you've
ever gotten like an icon on your phone
that's broken and you've been sent an
emoji but it's like a square or
something arbitrary and not sensical
sensible it might just mean that you
have not updated to the latest version
of iOS or Android which just updates the
font of supported Emoji because those
Folks at Unicode pretty much every year
nowadays are adding more and more Emoji
to that that particular character said
now I went down the rabbit hole figuring
out the other day just which are the
most popular Emoji these days on Twitter
specifically this past year the most
popular Emoji by contrast uh was loudly
crying face I don't know if that says
more about 20121 or about Twitter but
you'll see different Trends certainly in
how these are used but even humans
themselves didn't necessarily think two
steps ahead and now a lot of the Emoji
are the sort of default yellow color but
there's a lot of emoji that aren't sort
of these cartoon characters but they're
meant to represent humans in various
professions or gestures or the like and
nowadays too you've probably noticed on
your phone and Macs and PCs there are
different skin tones that you can assign
to certain emojis if it's supported by
the company and by Unicode you can
actually like touch and hold on a
certain emoji and then you can choose
the appropriate skin tone to represent
yourself or someone else and that then
modifies the display well let's just
think for a moment here how did Apple
and Google and Microsoft and others go
about implementing support for emoji
with different skin tones how could you
do this if you want to represent some
smiling Emoji but in five in this case
different skin tones you could come up
with what five different patterns that
are identical structurally except for
the skin tone used in places in that
image but that's a little inefficient
right to kind of just do copy paste
paste paste paste and like change the
color in Photoshop if you will that's
going to use more bits more information
than you might need to how else if you
now start to think a little bit more
like a computer scientist if at the end
of the day all you have are zeros and
ones how else could you implement skin
tones might you think
yeah okay so RGB and we'll come to that
in just a moment that stands for red
green blue that's one way in this case
though I'm seeking an alternative to
just using five different patterns of
zeros and ones to represent the same
Emoji but different skin tones so not
quite RGB
yeah okay so store one copy of the Emoji
and then store different variants of the
color that you want to assign to that
emoji yeah so this is actually an
example of do you want to
elaborate okay so you can use a loop to
actually output these things more on
that in a moment let me go down this
this road for just a moment this would
be in some sense sort of a a better
design if you will uh but why yeah
filter okay so filter if we think sort
of in the Instagram sense you can sort
of change the color of something and
that could be related here too could it
be oh interesting so maybe it could be
just a completely different font and you
have five different fonts that are
almost identical except for the various
interpretations of skin tone for those
same Emoji let me spoil I think if we go
down this one particular Road the way
the uh the Unicode folks decided to do
this some years ago were the first uh
bite or bites that you receive via text
or email just represent like the
structure of the Emoji the default
Yellow Version thereof but if it's
immediately followed by a certain
pattern of bits that these humans
standardize to represent each of these
different shades of skin tone then the
phone the Mac the PC will change that
default color yellow in most cases to
whatever the more apt human tone is so
you just use twice as many bits but you
don't use five times as many bits so
what do I mean you don't have uh five
completely distinct patterns per se uh
for each of these possible variants you
have a representation of just the Emoji
itself structurally and then uh reusable
pattern patterns for those five skin
tones un um unfortunately that wasn't
quite versatile enough for other
features that were in the pipeline and
nowadays too and there's a double
meaning now to representation emojis had
tended to focus on certain professions
and early on too were certain
professions associated with certain
genders and vice versa and you couldn't
necessarily be one gender or another in
a certain profession or another there
were these combinatorics that just
weren't possible but nowadays as you
might have seen you can have couples in
love for instance that actually look a a
little more like three emojis but just
kind of combined into one and indeed
this is just one key press on your phone
and you can combine different emoji on
the left and in the right with the Emoji
in the middle and so it turns out how
computers nowadays represent these
patterns are one set of bits for the
character on the left one set of bits
for a character on the right one set of
bits for whatever Emoji you want in the
middle and then you assemble more
complicated compositions of emoji by
just reusing those same patterns and
bits and bits Emoji doesn't the Unicode
folks don't have to come up with a whole
new representation for some very
specific Incarnation they can create one
for person for male for female for other
uh characters that you might want to
display and reuse those same patterns of
zeros and ones and so here you see sort
of the imperfection of or lack of
foresight of humans for building a
system early on that was entirely
American Centric no characters Emoji or
the like that's evolved too and so
that's an important detail in Computing
nowadays um it too is evolved in and the
languages you're about to learn in the
coming days those twoo are evolving as
well and new features are getting added
and even programming languages have
version numbers you might have a
different version of an app on your
phone programming languages too have
different versions as well questions
then thus far and how information is
represented using asy or
Unicode or anything in between yeah so
you can use a string of a good question
so to recap why can't you just um well
let me summarize that as why can't you
similarly use different patterns to
change the context of what these
patterns of bits represent whether it's
a number or a letter or a graphic in
actuality that's kind of what's
Happening underneath the hood it's not
standardized in quite the same way but
starting next week when we transition
from scratch to C you'll learn about
types data types where the onus
initially is going to be on you the
programmer to tell the program whether
or not this pattern of bit should be
interpreted as a number or as a letter
or as a color or something else nowadays
though in toward the end of the semester
you'll use languages like python where
the computer just figures it out for you
by context which makes it even easier
and faster to program as well other
questions on Unicode asky or the
like all right well how about just a few
other forms of information RGB was
called out earlier red green blue How do
images get represented in computers well
in fact it's typically an assembly of
some amount of red some amount of green
some amount of blue but there are other
representations if you're a graphic
designer you might know them but RGB is
still pretty common what does this mean
this means to represent every dot on
your phone or every dot on your TV or
your laptop or desktop there is a number
representing how much red that dot
should show a number representing how
much green and a number representing how
much blue it should show red green blue
respectively so for instance if a DOT on
your screen were using these three
numbers these three values or bytes 72
73 33 in a text message email that would
be interpreted as I claimed high but in
Photoshop or in some graphical program
that same pattern would be repres would
be interpreted as let's call it a medium
amount of red a medium amount of green
and a little bit of blue and why medium
and little turns out that each of these
are bites the smallest value you can
have in a bite we said is zero the
largest value you can have in a bite is
255 so I'm just kind of spitballing here
this is like medium medium and a low
amount of red green blue uh specifically
those three colors um like uh
wavelengths of light are combined in
such a way that you would have this dot
on the screen a sort of murky shade of
yellow or brown that is how a computer
would store precisely that color and in
fact we've seen this color when you type
in face with tears of joy generally on
your screen it looks like this typically
much smaller but let's zoom in or let's
zoom in a little more what do you
starting to see if you know the term so
pixels it's getting very pixelated a
pixel is just a DOT on the screen and if
you really zoom in on it you can
literally see all of the dots that
compose in emoji in this case on iOS in
the font that Apple's using to represent
this particular pattern of zeros and
ones so one of those yellow dots and
there's many of them all that kind of
blend together here each dot on the
screen I claim is three bytes how much
red green blue for this dot how much red
green blue for this dot how much red
green blue for this Dot and you'll
notice too that when it gets to be sort
of brownish here the dots really stand
out the three values the three bytes AKA
24 bits are just slightly different and
so underneath the hood this is why
images photographs that you take or GIFs
that you download get so darn big
potentially because you have a number
representing every dot on the screen
well if this I claim is indeed how
images are typically represented using
pattern of bits that are assigned to
some amount of red green or blue how do
you get video what is a video if at the
end of the day all we have are zeros and
ones
what's a video perhaps yeah oh let's go
here weighing back yeah pixel's really
changing values over time and do you
want to confirm or deny the hand that
went up here yeah or equivalently a
sequence of images that over time are
changing on the screen so both of those
are valid interpretations and you know
just for fun if you uh grew up with
these sort of picture books you might
remember a little something like this if
we could dim the
[Music]
lights
so that's sort of the old school analog
way to implement a video in the sense
that um that artist wrote out like
hundreds of pieces of paper with almost
identical images but where the ink from
their pencil or pen was slightly moving
and if you digitize that such that each
of those Strokes are represented with
dots instead that's really what you're
seeing as a sequence of all these images
flying across the screen and if we dive
into the the real world if you've ever
watched a film a Hollywood movie is
typically 24 FPS frames per second that
really means you're seeing 24 images per
second or on TV or in soap operas it's
often 30 frames per second that makes
things look a little more smooth so it's
not actual motion picture if you will it
sequences of pictures and your brain and
mind are kind of interpolating that oh
this is smooth movement even though
we're just seeing a lot of pictures
really fast now that gets really big and
we'll talk later in the semester how you
can compress information so that you're
not using way more bits than you
actually need to and there's fancy
algorithms that folks have developed but
at the end of the day that's really all
a video might be is a sequence of images
conversely if you want to represent the
music that accompanies that or something
else if any of you play an instrument
and can read sheet music How Could You
digitize this like how could you
represent musical notes in a computer
you and I hear them when we play files
but what's really going on underneath
the
hood any any musicians piano players
anyone yeah Val okay so Hertz value so
some frequency so sound is some
frequency and it's kind of hitting your
eardrum and that's what makes it sound
low or high or somewhere in between so
maybe we could assign just like there's
letters a through G here maybe we could
assign specific frequency values which
are just going to be numbers measured in
something called Hertz something per
second and maybe we could have a few
other numbers for each of these notes
not just the note or the frequency maybe
we could represent the loudness of it
like how hard or how softly a human
might equivalently press it maybe a
third number like duration like how long
is their finger on the keyboard so you
could imagine quantizing something like
music that in the real world is
perfectly continuous as something more
discret by representing each note over
time as just some sequence of values and
there's so many different ways to do
this midi if you've heard uh MP3s AAC I
mean almost all the file extensions you
see on your Mac or PC if you see them at
all ultimately just mean there's a
different form of representation for in
this case something like sound so let me
just stipulate there are these and many
more ways to represent inputs and
outputs and thankfully humans have
standardized a lot of this they don't
always dis agree and this is why we have
different file formats for Apple numbers
and Microsoft Excel and Google
spreadsheets and sort of stupid
incompatibilities like that but
generally speaking humans have
standardized how we represent the inputs
and outputs to and from problems but
let's now focus on this black box so to
speak in the middle this abstraction so
abstraction is technically a term that
you'll see all over the place in
computer science and really problem
solving that just refers to the
simplification of something so that you
don't focus on the lower level
implementation details you really just
focus on the high level goals or the
process itself uh Therefore your car if
youve uh if you have a license and have
driven or have been in a car a car so
far as you're concerned is probably an
abstraction most of us if you're like me
probably don't really know or care how
the engine works and all the parts that
are moving to you it's just a way of
getting from point A to point B it's an
abstraction but someone hopefully the
mechanic does know those lower level
implementation details if you had to
understand how a car works every time
you want to go to school or to the store
it's probably going to be a pretty slow
process you just want to think and
operate at this higher level of
abstraction and we're going to do this
all the time when writing code and
solving problems
so what then is in this black box this
abstraction at the moment well generally
it's what a computer scientist would
call an algorithm stepbystep
instructions for solving some problem
now let's consider the implementation
details that is to say how you might
solve certain problems and let's take a
a sort of old school example but in
modern form this icon if you have an
iPhone is of course for your contacts
application and if you've got a whole
bunch of family members or friends or
colleagues in your phone book you have
some kind of contacts pictured here here
and it's alphabetized typically by first
name and last name and odds are you and
I are in the habit if they're not
already a favorite of like clicking on
search and then using autocomplete and
what happens when you start typing
autocomplete well if you type in the
letter H you'll see only presumably
Hagrid Harry Hermione and so forth if
you type in ha that shows you only
Hagrid and Harry and it all happens
super fast so how is that happening well
typically you could just start at the
top and look to the bottom searching for
all the hes or all of the ha but for
larger data sets that's going to get
slow for the Googles of the world that's
going to get really slow and even on our
phones when you have hundreds thousands
of contacts eventually even that kind of
approach that algorithm step by step but
it might be slow so how might we go
about searching for someone in a phone
book like this uh like say uh John
Harvard well here's an old school
incarnation of this and uh odds are you
might not have had occasion to even
physically use this thing nowadays and
in fact this is a bit of a white lie cuz
this is the Yellow Pages which means
this is a book of companies not people
uh but for this is all you can find and
at that it's even hard to find this but
this is the same thing in analog form
physical form so if I wanted to search
for someone like John Harvard how could
I do that well I could start on page one
and I could start searching for page two
page three page four page five little
hard to do physically especially since
no one's used this phone book in a lot
of years but uh is this algorithm
correct Turning Page by Page
very inelegantly is this correct will I
find John Harvard if if he's in here all
right so yes I mean this is a little
stupidly tedious because if there's like
a thousand Pages he might be a few
hundred pages into this but it's correct
at some point I will find him and if
he's on the page I'll be able to call
why because presumably the names are
alphabetized in here and there's no like
cheat sheet on the edge so I have to
search for John Harvard from left to
right searching for H if it's
alphabetized by last name well what
would be marginally better well how
about two pages at a time it's hard to
do with a 20-year-old old phone book
where the pages are kind of uh grown
together but 2 4 6 8 10 12 this
algorithm is this correct all right so
no
why yeah so I'm skipping every other
page so if I don't consider that and I
find myself in like the I section or the
J section well I might accidentally
conclude nope I haven't found John
Harvard yet just because I skipped them
because it was sandwiched between two
pages now I can fix this I think if I do
hit the I section well let me just
double back one page just in case he was
in that last page so it's recoverable
but it's almost twice as fast minus that
that hiccup there but what most of us
would do and what your phones are doing
albeit digitally is they open up roughly
to the middle of the phone book and they
look down and they say oh I'm in roughly
the M section so I'm roughly halfway
through this thousand page phone book
but what do I now know about John
Harvard where is he to my left or to my
right all right so alphabetically he's
presumably to my left and so here I get
can both uh met uh metaphorically and
physically tear the problem in
half you don't need to be impressed it's
really easy down the the spine that way
but uh I know that John Harvard is to
the left here but now I can throw
unnecessarily dramatically half and page
one out of the way and what do I now
know I've gone from a thousand pages to
like 500 I can kind of repeat roughly
the same algorithm go to the half of
this and so this time I went back a
little too far I'm in now the um e
section so what do I know is John
Harvard to my left or to my
right to my right so I can again tear
the problem in half throw this half away
and now I'm really flying I'm toing it
verbally slowly but that went from a
th000 pages to 500 to now 250 and now I
can do it again 125 i' do it again
roughly like 67 and keep doing it again
and again and again until I get left
with hopefully just one single page or
in this case an ad for ironically a
mechanic okay so
what is the implication for our
performance well let's just do this sort
of in the abstract if you will if that
first algorithm were to be plotted just
quickly on a chart without even numbers
here's my x-axis size of problem on the
x-axis so the bigger the problem the
farther out that way time to solve the
problem the tire you go up on the y-
axis the uh more time you're taking to
solve it how would we draw the running
time The amount of time taken to run
that first algorithm well it's going to
be a straight line why cuz if you add
one more page next year because more
people move to Cambridge you're going to
add one more page turn potentially so
one more second one more unit of time so
it's a straight line and we'll abstract
it away as n if there's n pages in the
phone book the slope of this line is
essentially n the second algorithm
wherein I was doing two pages at a time
was twice as fast but it's still a
straight line and in fact let me just
draw some dotted lines here if the phone
book is this big with my first algorithm
it might take this many step this many
units of time this many steps this many
page turns but with that that second
algorithm notice that the intersection
is with much lower on the yellow line
than on the red so n/2 means there's
half as many pages here if n is the
number of pages so indeed that algorithm
the second one is twice as fast minus
the little hiccup that I have to double
back one page but that's not a big deal
if I'm still doing things twice as fast
but the third algorithm looks
fundamentally different it looks like
this logarithms if you recall from high
school or prior if you don't that's fine
too it's just a fundamentally different
function a different shape and notice
that the green line is going up and up
and up but a much slower rate of
increase which means crazy things are
possible if two towns in Massachusetts
like Cambridge and Austin across the
river merge next year for instance in
terms of their phone book their phone
book just got twice as big for the first
algorithm that's going to take me twice
as many steps to go through the second
algorithm almost Twi it's going to take
me 50% more steps to go through two at a
time but the third algorithm that I
ended with tearing things again and
again divid and conquering if you will
in half and in half and in half how many
more steps will my third algorithm take
if Cambridge and Austin merge into a
phone book that's twice as
big just one more step right no big deal
you just take a really big bite out of
the problem once you decide if John
Harvard is to the left or to the right
and so you've made much faster progress
and so this in essence is what your
computer your phone is probably doing
underneath the hood when searching for
Harry or Hermione or Hagrid or anyone
else because it's that much faster
especially when you have large data if
you don't have that many contacts
probably doesn't matter if you search
from top to bottom or more uh more in
the form of this divide and conquer
algorithm but if you're the Googles of
the world or you're analyzing large data
sets indeed this is going to add up
quite quickly so where do we go with
this well we're going to introduce next
something called pseudo code how can I
translate what I did verbally there sort
of intuitively to actual code well this
won't be scratch this won't be C or
python just yet it's just going to be an
english-like syntax and this is how many
programmers would start solving a
problem they don't start typing out code
in C or python or the like they use
English or whatever their human language
is to jot down an outline for their
ideas my first step really was picking
up the phone book my second step was
opening to the middle of the phone book
my third step was somewhat different
look at the page because why my fourth
step was if person I'm looking for is on
the page I then do what never happened
in my example but I call the person so
I'm done else if the person is earlier
in the book alphabetically as John
Harvard was in the case of my H then I
should search to the middle of the left
of the phone book and then I should go
back to step three step three is look at
the page thereby repeating the same
process again and again step nine though
might be else if the person is later in
the book then let's go ahead and open to
the middle of the right half of the book
and then go back to line three else
there's a fourth scenario we should
probably consider lest my search process
freeze or crash or give me one of those
spinning beach balls with a bug
yeah yeah what if John Harvard isn't in
the phone book I'd prefer that my
algorithm my phone not just reboot or
freeze I should handle that with some
kind of catchall else so to speak let's
just quit the program so there's
welldefined behavior for every possible
scenario of the four now let's call out
a few of these Salient terms it turns
out if I highlight in yellow here
there's a pattern to what I've been
doing here these are all of my English
verbs and we're in a moment we're going
to start calling those verbs functions
when you program or write code and you
want the program or the computer to do
something for you some action or verb
we're going to refer to those actions or
verbs as these things called functions
like those here by contrast I've just
highlighted instead my if my El if my
Els if and Els this is going to
represent what we're going to start
calling a conditional a proverbial fork
in the road where you can either go this
way or that way do this thing or this
other thing and you're going to decide
which of those things to do based on
what I've now highlighted here which are
going to be called Boolean Expressions
bull referring to a mathematician last
named bull a Boolean expression is just
a question with a yes no a true false a
one or a zero answer if you will and it
governs whether you do this thing or
this thing or this thing or that the
indentation in this case is important
the fact that I've indented line five
implies by convention in programming
that I should only do line five if the
answer to line four is a yes or true and
same for these other indented lines as
well and the last characteristic here is
this here uh someone called this out
earlier in fact these lines eight and 11
are now highlighted and represent
what what might we call these in code if
you've done that yeah so these are Loops
some kind of cycles that result in my
doing the same thing again and again but
there's a key detail with this algorithm
in pseudo code even though it's telling
me to go back to line three why is this
algorithm event going to stop why do I
not constantly keep looking for John
Harvard Forever by nature of these Loops
telling me to keep going back to line
three good eventually he'll be on the
page or or to your point earlier he
won't be at all and we're out of pages
and so we just quit and that's the key
about going to the left half or the
right half it doesn't matter if you do
the same thing again and again you're
not going to get stuck in a so-called
infinite Loop so long as you keep
dividing the problem and shrinking it
into something small smaller smaller
eventually there's going to be no
problem left to solve so even if you
don't think of yourself as a computer
person even if you've never written code
what you'll find in the coming days is
that these ideas that we've just kind of
harnessed from real life are at your
fingertips already and a lot of the
process of learning to code is yes it's
going to be a bumpy Ro uh some bumps in
the road because you can't quite see the
new syntax in a familiar way but you'll
find that the ideas in fact are going to
be more familiar than you might
otherwise think and so we'll see in a
bit and we'll take a break in a moment
uh to take a breather that you will see
these same ideas in a moment in the
context of scratch an actual programming
language via which we drag and drop
puzzle pieces to make actual code work
we'll see some variant of these ideas
things called arguments and return
values and variables but we'll
ultimately convert it into this somehow
anyone want to wager what this program
will do if fed to your Mac or PC or
phone here's just a massive pattern of
zeros and
ones it will indeed say rather
disappoint ly apparently just hello
world and indeed baked into all of these
zeros and ones are not just the h l l o
but also the verbs the action of
printing something to the screen and
there's other stuff too so that the
program knows how to start and how to
stop a lot of stuff that we won't have
to worry about that whoever designed the
computer or the language did but at the
end of the day you're never going to be
writing these zeros and ones yourselves
though our ancestors Once Upon a Time
did in some form we'll be using a much
higher l level language like this in C
or better yet in just a moment like in
scratch like this and indeed this is why
today we focus with focus on and begin
with scratch this graphical programming
language so we have a way of expressing
ourselves with functions conditionals
loops and more but in a way that doesn't
have stupid parentheses and curly braces
and all these visual distractions in the
way and we'll translate that thereafter
to this lower level language but for now
that was a lot that was definitely a
fire hose let's go ahead and take a
10-minute break feel free to get up or
stay here and we'll resume in a bit with
some actual
code uh so this then is scratch a
graphical programming language from a
friends down the road at mit's media lab
that indeed some of you might have used
in grade score the like for playing and
writing code and the like but you maybe
didn't necessarily think about how some
of these Primitives ultimately worked
and in fact everything you've done if
you've used scratch before and
everything you'll see today is going to
apply to all of the weeks to come as we
explore these things called functions
and loops and conditionals Boolean
expressions and more with scratch
because it's so graphical and animated
can create can you create animations
like this one interactive art and
software more generally but you'll do so
by dragging and dropping puzzle pieces
that only lock together if it makes
logical sense to do so and what you
won't have to deal with in this first
week of class is Curly braces
parentheses all of the weird symbology
that you might recall seeing when we
just wanted to say hello world now this
particular program um riging men was
written by a former cs50 teaching fellow
Andrew bar who's actually now the
general manager of the Cleveland Browns
the American football team and so these
are just some of the programs that some
of your predecessors in the class have
created and you'll see in the remainder
of class here a couple of others as well
and more in the course's first
assignment namely problem set zero so
how do we get there well first a quick
tour of what it is we're going to do
this in scratch is perhaps the simplest
program you can write and even if you've
never seen scratch or any programming
language before can probably guess that
this just says on the screen somehow
hello world but what you don't have to
do is type esoteric commands and weird
syntax those curly braces and
parentheses I keep alluding to you just
drag this yellow puzzle piece you drag
this purple puzzle piece let them
magnetically lock together so to speak
click a button and boom with those same
building blocks and several others can
you make what exactly the sorts of
things that Andrew brought to life as
well so here's what we're about to see
at scratch.mit.edu is a cloud-based
programming environment on MIT servers
you can also download it offline on your
own Mac or PC and it gives you an
interface like this on the left hand
side of the screen you'll see a blocks
pette these puzzle pieces AKA blocks
come in different colors which rather
categorize them so pictured here for
instance in blue are a whole bunch of
motion related blocks so Andrew used a
whole bunch of those to have the singer
and the men moving around on the screen
um in synchronicity with the song that
was playing in the background meanwhile
in the middle of this interface is going
to be the code area and this is where
Andrew and sunu will drag and drop some
of those puzzle pieces and other colors
as well and lock them together to get
your character soon to be invented to do
something on the screen indeed at the
bottom right here will you see
ultimately a Sprite area where a Sprite
is a technical term for like a character
in a video game or a programming
environment like this by default
historically scratch uh is the cat the
mascot if you will for this programming
environment and so here we see by
default just one Sprite selected because
on the top right of the screen is the
stage for that Sprite and you can click
in Click and zoom in to make it full
screen but this is the world in which
Scratch by default the cat will live but
you can change scratch's costume so that
it looks like a singer or a man falling
from the sky or the like or anything
else either creating the art yourself or
importing some of the things that come
with it or elsewhere online so what is
this world that scratch rather lives in
well generally speaking we won't have to
care too much about numbers because
we'll be able to ask questions like
intera active ones like is scratch the
cat or any character otherwise touching
the edge of the screen touching
something else but scratch does exist in
this
two-dimensional uh coordinate system
world so when the cat or any character
is dead center in the middle that would
be XY location 0 comma 0 if you will
meanwhile over here is 240 pixels or
dots all the way to the right so this
would be 240 comma 0 where Y is z
because it's right on that midline so
it's neither up or below
over here to the left of course would be
240 and 0 above the cat would be xal 0
cuz it's right on that vertical midline
and 180 and then down here as you might
guess would be 0 comma netive 180
generally speaking we don't have to care
about those precise pixel coordinates
but it's helpful ultimately if you do
want the cat to move up down left or
right having some sense of direction
according to the x- axis and y AIS as
well can help you express your ideas
ultimately so what might some of those
ideas be well let's do this I'm going to
go ahead and create on
scratch.mit.edu just an empty screen
like this one here and so this is the
exact same interface but now I'm in my
browser uh full screen so that I can
start writing some code and let's get
that cat to say something actually on
the screen now this takes a little bit
of practice but honestly just by
scrolling through these puzzle pieces
can you quickly get a sense of what's
possible not just categorically but
specifically and I'll jump around
because I've done this of course but I'm
going to go to events in yellow first
and I'm going to drag and drop this
first block called when green flag
clicked and I've zoomed in there just to
make it a little more legible and notice
that the shape of this green flag just
so happens to mirror this green flag
here at top next to this red stop sign
of sorts and the green flag is going to
mean go and the red stop sign's going to
mean stop to start or stop our program
next week you're going to be writing a
textual command at your keyboard to do
the exact same idea but for now it's a
button so when green flag clicked what
do I want scratch to do well how about
we have scratch just initially say
something like Hello World which indeed
historically is the first program that
most any programmer might write so
anything related to what the cat looks
like it's doing is actually going to be
under looks here in purple so I'm going
to drag over say hello and you'll notice
something curious and different about
this purple block it says of course say
in purple but then there's this white
oval and some text that by default is
hello cuz MIT just decided that by
default the placeholder will be hello
but anytime you see this white oval it's
an opportunity to provide an input into
the function called say and so here I'm
borrowing terminology from before
problem solving again is all about
inputs producing outputs and in between
there is some algorithm in a moment
we're going to start referring to
algorithms quite frequently as functions
why because it's the implementation of
some algorithm so let me override the
default with hello comma World I'll zoom
out and now if I go to the top right of
the screen and click the green flag
we'll see hopefully my very first
program in code now it wasn't a huge
lift right it only was a matter of
dragging and dropping puzzle pieces but
what has now happened well it turns out
that two things have happened when I the
human clicked on that green flag I
triggered what we're going to start
calling now an event an event is
generally something graphical or
interactive that just happens in a
computer program you and I trigger
events on our phones all day long
whenever you tap or drag or long press
or pinch or any of those gestures in
Vogue nowadays on phones you are
triggering events and people at Apple
and Google and elsewhere have written
code that listen for those events and do
something when that event happens that's
what I just did when green flag is
clicked I want something to happen
namely I want this purple function this
verb this action called say to do
something what do I want it to do I want
it to say what this input is and I'm
going to introduce another vocabulary
term the white ovals here are yes inputs
very generically but in the programmer's
terminology they're called arguments
otherwise known as parameters and that
just means an input to a function that
modifies Its Behavior in some way when I
click stop that's just another event and
that one is just built into scratch
scratch knows that when you click the
green stop sign uh everything should
just stop automatically I don't have to
write code to support that feature so
that's all fine and good hello world but
if I keep doing stop and start and stop
and start it's going to do the same
thing again and again and it's really
not that interesting at the end of the
day maybe gratifying once but it'd be
nice if this were a little more
interactive so it turns out that we can
do that too but we need a different
mental model instead so in this case
here when we think about this function
say in this input hello world this
actually Maps pretty cleanly to this
model earlier that I propose is problem
solving is computer science if you will
the input to the current problem is
going to be in white here hello world
the algorithm is the say algorithm now I
don't know how MIT got it to print out
the little pretty speech bubble on the
screen but they wrote those underlying
low-level implementation details and
they gave me and you a purple function
called say that just does that for you
you and I don't have to reinvent that
wheel the output of SE is another
technical term now called a side effect
a side effect is usually something
visual that happens like as a side
effect of you calling a function and so
the side effect here is that the cat has
this speech bubble magically appear
inside of which is hello world so we
have an input we have an output we have
an algorithm but now we're talking about
these ideas in the context of
programming so now the input is an
argument the algorithm is a function and
the output in this case is a side effect
terminology that you'll just hear more
and more and it'll eventually sink in
but not to worry if the terminology
doesn't come naturally early on so what
more might I do with this let me go back
to scratch here and make this maybe
perhaps more interactive and actually
get the cat to say something a little
more dynamically so instead of hello
world why don't I get it to say hello to
me or to you or anyone else so let me do
this let me go under say uh let me get
rid of this first and you'll notice this
neat trick as soon as you start dragging
on a block if it gets close to it it
kind of goes gray and it can be
magnetically snapped together you don't
have to do it very precisely conversely
if I want to get rid of a puzzle piece I
just drag it anywhere on the left let go
and that deletes it or you can right
click or control click in a little menu
will let you delete it as well well let
me do this instead under sensing which I
know is there because I've done this
before are a whole bunch of things
related to sensing whereby the cat can
kind of feel out its World in some sense
it can do things like ask this question
am I touching the mouse pointer like the
user's cursor am I touching a specific
color that you can override to be
anything you want is the distance to the
mouse pointer some specific value but
for now I'm going to focus this on this
this blue puzzle piece that asks a
question which itself is this white oval
that I can apparently change and then
it's going to wait for a response but
this puzzle piece is a little different
it's a little special it comes with a
freebie it comes with what we're going
to call technically a return value so
some functions don't just do something
on the screen they hand you back so to
speak a value that you can do anything
that you want with nothing happens
immediately unless you do something with
that so-called return value so let me go
ahead and drag this thing over here ask
what's your name and I'll use the
default question that seems a reasonable
place to start I'm not going to override
that default and now let me go ahead and
zoom out let me go back to looks let me
go to say and let me just form the
English sentence I want so let me zoom
in here and type in hello maybe comma
space I could do David but that's that's
obviously not right because I'm asking
for a name and then I'm like in advance
hardcoding my name that's not what I
want I just want hello comma and now let
me zoom out and grab one more say block
Let Me Maybe say here okay I don't want
to say hello hello I I don't want to
just type in my own name CU again then
what's the point of asking the user for
their name but notice this if I go back
to the sensing block this is where that
oval that's blue called answer is useful
this will be the so-called return value
of that function so I'm just going to go
ahead and do this and drag and drop even
though it's not the right size it is the
right shape and so scratch will be smart
about it and grow to fill that puzzle
piece for you let me zoom out now and
now let me click the green flag you'll
see that scratch is indeed prompting me
with the speech bubble what's your name
notice the little text box below the cat
is asking what's your name so I'm going
to type in da a v d and hit enter or I
can click the blue check
enter okay it's a little weird I wanted
him to say hello not just my name so let
me stop let me start it again all right
hello what's your name da a v
enter huh kind of rude uh why is there
this bug like I wanted to say hello
David not just David and and yet twice
it has failed to do so uh
yeah yeah the computer is processing my
directions my actions really quickly and
so it actually is doing it it's just you
and I in the room are just way too slow
to notice that it said hello David it
just seems to have just said David so
all right how can I fix this well here's
where you start to poke around and think
about how you might solve this let me go
back under looks maybe there's a smarter
way to do this maybe I could do okay I
could do this how about instead of just
say hello there's apparently another
puzzle piece where I can time it so I
can maybe slow things down a little bit
so let me do this let me throw away all
of this let me drag a say hello for two
seconds let me drag another say hello
for two seconds let me change the first
one to indeed hello comma and then let
me go back to sensing let me grab that
same answer because I threw it away a
second ago and I'll just change it I
don't even have to delete hello I can
just overwrite it like this so now I
think we'll kind of pump the brakes and
see things more slowly let me stop let
me start da ID enter
hello David okay so it's better like it
seems to be working I think your
hypothesis was right just looks kind of
stupid right like the fact that it's
saying
hello David like we can do better and
like literally every piece of software
on your phone or Mac or PC is better
than that it adds words together in the
user interfaces you and I are familiar
with so let's go a little more fishing
here let me throw away these let me go
back to look and just get the simpler
say I want this to say hello comma name
where name comes from that answer return
value so how can I do this well let me
go under operations which we haven't
been before there's a lot of stuff in
here some of it's mathematically related
adding subtracting and so forth you can
Generate random numbers which might be
useful and if I keep scrolling down
there's this join apple and banana but
that's just placeholder text you can
join one piece of text with another
piece of text by default apple and
banana but let's change it to hello and
my name name so this to wrong size but
right shape so let me let it snap into
place let me go ahead now and do hello
comma and now I think I just want to go
grab that answer return value let me
drag the same oval as before clobber
that is overwrite banana so now I'm kind
of composing functions the output of one
function join is going to be the input
of another function say so let's see
what happens now that they're kind of
stacked on top of each other or nested
so to speak click the Green Arrow a
green flag DAV ID enter hello David all
right that was pretty fast let's just
just do it once more stop start here we
go daavid enter okay right it's not the
most exciting program in the world but
it's more correct it's better design
just because that's what you would kind
of expect the software to do and not be
some kind of lame user interface that's
just inserting random delays to just
make it kind of work like that's a
workaround a hack if you will but
there's some cool things you can do with
scratch and we won't really go down the
rabbit hole of all of the fun and
familyfriendly features that it has but
there is one that's kind of cool here
let me go into the extensions button at
the bottom left of my screen and this
one's kind of cool let me go to text to
speech and you'll notice that this one
requires internet because it's
cloud-based but this just gave me some
new puzzle pieces in a new category text
to speech and these green ones do
exactly what they say so let me do this
let me zoom out again let me keep the
join block and I'm just going to
temporarily toss it over here it's not
going to delete itself cuz I didn't drag
it over to the other side but I'm going
to get rid of the say block in purple
I'm going to do the speak block here in
green and let it snap into place and
then I'm going to drag and drop this
onto the input to speak and now perhaps
a little more adorably let's try this
green flag what's your name d ID enter
and hello
David okay it's a little it's a little
robotic but at least now it has
synthesized speech and I've kind of got
my own like Siri or Google assistant or
Alexa thing going on here now where it's
now recognized whatever text it is and
it's played it well let's make this an
actual cat that doesn't talk in that
weird human voice let me go ahead and
get rid of most of this stuff and let's
get the cat to actually meow like a cat
tends to and let me go under the sounds
block now MIT gives you a few sounds for
free because it's designed around a cap
by default and I'm going to go ahead and
grab this one play sound meow until done
and now and we saw I heard a teaser for
this earlier in the
crowd
it's a little piercing admittedly we can
lower the volume a little bit there but
notice if I want the cat to meow a
second time I'll just click it
again okay and over there too I
hear okay all right so it's kind of cute
now right so it's just meow okay yes
echo echo so it's meowing now every time
I hit the green flag now that's great
but even a kid is probably going to like
would prefer that it just meow perhaps
like again and again without having to
keep hitting the button so well how
might we do this all right well if I
want it to meow multiple times why don't
I just like grab it another time and
another time alternatively you can right
click or control click a puzzle piece
and just duplicate it from a little menu
that drops down so here we go three
meows all right that's not really a
happy cat it sounds maybe hungry so can
we slow that down well maybe in fact if
I poke around let me go under control
looks like there's a weight block wait 1
second by default and notice scratch
will be pretty accommodating if you just
hover in between blocks it will grow to
fill that too so I could change it to
one or two or anything seconds I'll just
leave it at the default for now one and
now I'll go ahead and do
this okay so cuter and less hungry and
just more friendly but this isn't the
best design it is correct and let's use
that as a term of art correct means the
code does what you want it to do I want
the cat to meow three times slow slly
and it did so iager this is correct but
it's not the best design and this is
where things get more subjective right
like you could write accurate sentences
in an essay for an English class but
otherwise just it's just completely a
mess like your arguments here and there
and you don't say anything wrong but you
don't say it well in the context of code
we can do better than this and copy
paste or repeating yourself again and
again tends to be bad practice why
suppose that you want to change the
weight to two seconds instead of one
it's aditt not a big deal F I click
there I change it to two I click there I
change it to two but what if you Ma five
times 10 times now I have to change the
weight like in five 10 different places
like that's just stupid it's taking
unnecessary human time and you're going
to screw up eventually especially if
your program is getting longer you're
going to miss one of the inputs you're
going to leave the number wrong and
you're that's a bug so just based on
what you've seen already or if you've
programmed before which a few of you
have what's the term of art here that
will solve this how can we design this
better I heard it here here yeah so a
loop a loop some kind of cycle that says
do that again do that again not
infinitely many times necessarily but
some finite number well you can perhaps
see a spoiler on the screen under the
same uh orange control category is a
repeat block and by default it's
proposing 10 but we can change that so
let me do this I'm going to throw away
most of this copy paste as redundant I'm
going to detach this temporarily just to
make room for something else and I'm
going to drag a repeat block over here
and let that snap into place and I'm
going to change it for now just to be
three for consistency and this is the
correct shape even though it's too small
but scratch will accommodate that for us
and now same uh same output but arguably
better designed why because if I want to
change the number of meows I change it
in one place no copy paste messiness if
I want to change the waiting one place I
don't have to change it in multiple
places and not screw up so let me hit
the green
flag all right so nice now it would have
been nice if MIT had just given us a
meow block that just automates all of
this for us let me wager they gave us
the low-level implementation details
they gave us the play sound meow but I
had to implement like a decent number of
blocks just to get a cat to meow again
and again I feel like we should have
gotten that for free from MIT well they
don't have to be the only ones that
invent blocks for us to use you can
write your own functions your own verbs
or actions so how can we do this let's
make our own puzzle piece called now
that uses this code but creates it in
such a way that it's reusable elsewhere
so let me do this under my blocks in
pink here I'm going to go ahead and
click literally make a block now here's
an interface via which I can give the
block a name Meo W will be the name of
this block and I'm just going to go
ahead and quickly click okay that just
gives me a very generic pink puzzle
piece that starts with the word Define
because scratch is asking me to Define
that is implement or create this new
puzzle piece for me well what does it
mean to meow I'm going to claim that it
means to do these two steps to play the
sound meow and then just wait for one
second but what's powerful about this
idea is look at this up top now that
I've made a block it exists in scratch D
MIT didn't need to create this for me I
created it for myself and even you if we
end up sharing code so I can now drag
meow up in here and what's nice about
meow is that itself is yes a function
but it's also an abstraction like never
again do I or even you need to worry or
care about what it means to meow or
implement it I can sort of drag it out
of the way I didn't delete it drag it
out of the way out of sight out of mind
why because my code is now even better
designed in some sense because it's more
readable what is it doing when the green
flag is clicked repeat three times meow
it just says what it means and so it's a
lot easier to read it and it's a lot
easier to think about it especially if
you're using Meow in other uh projects
too now let me go ahead and right hit
click play same thing so it's not really
fundamentally any different but I can
make this custom puzzle piece this own
function of M meow even more powerful
let me kind of rewind a bit and go to my
meow puzzle piece and I am going to
control click or right click on my pink
puzzle piece and I'm going to edit it so
I kind of regret making meow so simple
wouldn't it be nice if meow took an
input AKA an argument that tells meow
how many times to meow then I can get
rid of that Loop and just tell meow how
many meows I actually want so I'm going
to click on another button here called
literally add an input and it's going to
have placeholder here so I'm just going
to put a placeholder there I keep using
n for number which is a go-to in
computer scientist terms um and I'm
going to add some descriptive text just
so that it's a little more
self-explanatory I'm just going to say
meow n times but there's only one oval
times is just going to be explanatory
text and now notice what has happened
now my puzzle piece takes an input AKA
an argument that will tell that function
to meow some number of times but it's
not just going to going to work
magically I need to implement that lower
level detail so let me zoom out I have
to remind myself what this function was
so I'm going to drag it higher up just
so they're on the screen at the same
time I'm going to go ahead now and
temporarily move this over here I'm
going to temporarily detach this over
here why because what I think I want to
do is move my Loop into the function
itself move the play and the weight into
the loop but I don't want to hardcode
three notice that n here is its own oval
I can drag a copy of N and just let it
go there so now I have a new version of
meow that takes an argument in that
tells meow how many times to meow and
now let me again drag this out of sight
out of mind because who cares how I
implemented it once it's implemented
it's sort of done now my program is even
better designed in some sense why
because now it really just says what it
means there's no Loop there's no repeat
no like implementation details when
green flag clicked meow three times and
so functions indeed let you implement
algorithms like they're just code that
do something for you but they're also
themselves abstractions why because once
a function exists it has a name and you
can think about it in that term and you
can use it by its name you don't have to
care or remember how the function itself
was built whether it's by you or even
MIT so again here I'll click the green
flag it's the same
thing so still correct but better and
better designed and so anytime here and
out with scratch or soon C and
eventually python when you find yourself
doing anything resembling copy paste or
again and again grabbing the same code
probably an opportunity to say wait a
minute let me refactor this so to speak
that is rip out the code that seems to
be repeated again and again and put it
in its own function so you can give it a
descriptive name and use and reuse it
any questions just yet on now saying or
these Loops or these functions that
we're using yeah
[Music]
how did I make it so it meows three
times so I originally only had a puzzle
piece called meow and I decided to
improve it so I held down control and I
right clicked or control clicked on the
pink puzzle piece at top left and I
clicked edit and that brought back the
original interface that lets me add some
arguments to the puzzle piece itself and
I clicked add an input on the left here
and then I clicked on add a label over
here so that just lets you customize it
even further all right so we've done
this let's add one of those other
Primitives too to do something
optionally so how about we make the cat
meow only if it's being petted by a
human as by moving the mouse to hover
over the cat like a human would pet a
cat well let me go ahead and throw uh
away the meowing uh for now and let me
simplify it by just using a sound I'm
going to go ahead and do this I'm going
to go ahead and have a control block
that says if because I want to implement
the idea of if the cursor is touching
the Cal
then play sound meow or I could use my
same pink puzzle piece but I'm going to
throw that away and focus only now on
the sounds and I'm going to do this uh
if uh touching Mouse pointer so I need
to sense something about the world and
we saw this earlier so if touching Mouse
pointer so notice this shape here way
too big but it is the right shape so if
I hover just right it'll snap into place
and this now in blue is my Boolean
expression a yes no question true false
uh if is a conditional and what do I
want to do well if the Cat is being uh
is touching the mouse pointer I want to
go ahead and play sound meow until done
so let's do this I'm going to hit green
flag click now nothing's happened yet
because it's a conditional right it's
only supposed to do something if I'm
touching the cat let me move the cursor
over to the cat and and and wait for
it h another bug why is the cat not
meowing even though I very explicitly
said if touch in Mouse pointer meow yeah
in the
middle yeah this is again my computers
are so darn fast like yours I click the
green flag it asked the question am I
touching the mouse pointer well no cuz
my cursor was up there not touching the
cat it's too late the cat's out of the
bag and so we have to instead solve this
some other mean by some other means how
can we fix this how do we fix that sort
of race yeah yeah so why don't we just
keep asking the question until I
eventually am I'm not actually petting
the cat so let me detach this
temporarily let me go under control let
me go under instead of repeat some
finite number of times let's just do it
forever so sometimes Loops that do work
forever are a good thing like the clock
on your phone that's in a loop forever
because you want it to always tell time
and not stop at the end of the day so
sometimes you do want code to Loop
forever as in this case so let me go
ahead and drag and drop it there let me
again click the green flag nothing's
happening yet but notice the program's
still running and so if if I move my
cursor move my cursor move my cursor
and okay so maybe we could add some
waiting but the cat does not want to be
pet in this case but it's indeed
conditional so there we have an
incarnation in scratch of doing
something conditionally now we can make
this really cool really fast if you will
let me stop this version let me go ahead
and do this uh let me go ahead and throw
all of this away let me go into my
little uh extensions Bucket over here
and let me do video sensing since most
uh laptops or phones these days have
cameras and there indeed I am with
Sanders behind me and let me do this um
when video motion and let me get out of
the way when video motion is greater
than some value so 10 is the default
this is just a number that measures how
much motion there is or isn't so small
number is like no motion big number is
lots of motion so I'm going to choose 50
somewhat arbitrarily here so 50 this is
not normal to program off to the side
but I'm now going to say this when video
motion is 50 go ahead and play sound
meow like this so the cat is still in
that world I'm going to stop the program
and rerun it so here we go green flag
and
now here come all right this is a little
creepy the way I'm petting the cat
but
and ah
okay there we go okay so 50 was too big
of a number I have to pet the cat
faster whereas this if I don't
know yeah
so okay so you can make things even more
interactive in this way by just
assembling different puzzle pieces and
honestly there are so many different
puzzle pieces in here we're not going to
even scratch the surface of a lot of
them but they generally just do what
they say and indeed when you see on the
screen here um this pallet of puzzle
pieces really a lot of programming
especially early on when learning a
language is just trying different things
and try and fail and if it doesn't work
quite look for doesn't work quite right
look for an alternative solution there
too as even I just had to do a moment
ago well let's go ahead and use actually
how about another example of something a
predecessor of yours made let me go
ahead and grab a program I opened in
advance here uh called wacka um might we
get a brave volunteer to come up who is
willing to whack a mole with their head
virtually maybe okay let's see how about
in way back you want to come on down all
right come on down and in just a sure
Round of Applause for our
volunteer all
right so here we
have come on down there what's your name
I'm Josh oh actually say it into the
microphone hi I'm Josh
okay nice welcome Josh come on
over all right so same idea here I'll
take the mic back you can you'll have to
stand in front of the camera in just a
moment you're going to have to position
your head in a box that your classmate
from yester year
created and we'll start with beginner
okay so line your head up in the Box in
a moment all right all
[Music]
[Applause]
right
[Music]
nice 12
seconds 5 Seconds notice the score is up
to 18 already pretty
good all right a round of applause for
Josh if you
can so notice how using some fairly
simple Primitives things do get
interesting pretty fast and how was that
implemented well there were probably at
least four Sprites so you're not re
confined to just one cat you can create
more and more Sprites change what they
look like so they actually look like a
mole in this case there's probably some
conditionals in there Some Loops for 30
seconds that's checking if Josh's head's
movement is exceeding some value over
this way or over this way then increment
something called a variable we'll see
those two just like in algebra you might
have X and Y and Z storing values like
numbers so can computer programs have
variables called X or Y or Z or more
descriptively called score as in this
case at top right or another variable
called countdown typically one word in
code but in this case two words that
just store some value so there's
probably some math going on in there
whereby the author of this program just
is incrementing that is adding one in
one every time it detected that uh a
mole had been whacked in this case with
movement so back in the day I myself
actually implemented my very first
program in scratch when I was at a
graduate student actually at MIT um cost
registered at MIT taking a class from
mit's media lab specifically the
lifelong kindergarten Group which is the
group that created scratch itself and
the program I wrote all those years ago
and still rather cling to is a little
something here called Oscar time that I
thought I'd play just a quick excerpt of
my myself here so in this case consider
as the music starts playing how this
program which is much more sophisticated
certainly than the earliest say hello
examples we just did might also be
implemented let me go ahead now and
click the green
flag so some trash is moving presumably
in some kind of loop from the
Top If I'm touching the mouse cursor it
follows
me if I hover over the trash can it
responds if I let
go in some kind of loop Oscar pops out
creates a variable with the current
score and it happens
again pretty easy at first
but I don't need to keep playing this up
on stage in front of everyone so my
score is already now up to some six or
so but in a moment two you'll see that
it's going to escalate so I'm taking
into account some time apparently so
now so more and more Sprites are
suddenly appearing and notice that each
time they're appearing from a different
part of the screen that's an illusion
perhaps do that pick a random number
between X and Y so you can actually pick
some range of values to have the game
constantly changing and indeed I'm going
to go ahead and click stop since i'
spent like 8 hours plus years ago making
this and I can never listen to the song
again not that I should be anyway at
this point in my life but this song is
uh synchronized in with a lot of the
actions that's happening and ultimately
there's just a lot of building blocks
but I didn't sit down and Implement
Oscar time as I called it all at once I
really did take baby steps so to speak
and I figured out well how could I
decompose this Vision I had at the time
to create this game ultimately and how
do I bite off maybe the easiest Parts
first and honestly the first thing I did
was I found this image and I just like
dragged and dropped it into scratch okay
done like lamp post is installed it
doesn't do anything it's not interactive
but I at least set the stage so to speak
for the program then what else might I
have done well let me do this let me go
ahead and open up uh in another editor
here a early incarnation of Oscar Time
by doing this let me go into Oscar time
here let me full screen this and here
you have let me hide the trash for just
a moment is what I might call the second
uh version of my program wherein at the
top right of the stage here I had the
lamp post which I just dragged and
dropped and got going but then I added
an actual Sprite and it has to be a
Sprite if you wanted to do things
interactively the lamp post not a Sprite
it's just an image a costume if you will
for the whole stage itself a backdrop
but this thing is indeed a Sprite
because it needs to respond to code and
events like dragging and dropping so
what might I have done early on with
that code well maybe the first version
would have been something like this
where by my very first version of Oscar
time might have said something like oh
this how about let me control the
program as before or rather events when
the green flag is clicked what do I want
to do well I want to go ahead and
forever do something like this uh
forever so I want the lid to open up if
I touch it so if the cursor gets near
the lid I want the lid to open up and
then if I move away I want it to close
so how can I do that I want an if but I
just don't want one question I really
want two a fork in the road that goes
left or right so to speak and let me
grab this puzzle piece here as I did
long ago so notice it grows to fill
what's the question I want to ask well
under sensing I'm going to go ahead here
and say if this trash can is touching
the mouse pointer what do I want to do
well I want to change what the trash can
looks like and this part I did in
advance of class if you go up here to
costumes this is where all the graphical
stuff happens and you'll see that I
imported a whole bunch of different
costumes that effectively much like a
video when you play them quickly creates
the illusion of movement some animation
but it's really just dot dot dot dot dot
different images showing on the screen
well some of these costumes are called
like Oscar 1 Oscar 2 Oscar 1 is closed
Oscar 2 is open so let's just deal with
those first so if I'm touching the mouse
pointer let me go under how about looks
and we didn't use this before but
there's this block switch costume to
something else I'm going to drag and
drop this inside of the if and notice
it's a little bit indented I'm going to
change it not to Oscar 8 but Oscar 2
otherwise if not touching the mouse
pointer this is the other direction in
the fork and the road let's go ahead and
switch the costume back to what I
described as Oscar 1 so let me run this
program and not much of interest is
happening yet but notice if I move the
cursor up down but how is that working
it's just changing the costume that's
being overlaid on the Sprite so it looks
like interactivity but you're really
just changing the Aesthetics and we
humans are just kind of you know
assuming oh it's opening up well no it's
just changing a costume so here's the
difference the high level abstraction
trash can opening the lower level
implementation detail
costume changing creating that illusion
and if I wanted to look prettier I could
just have many other costumes and go
boom boom boom boom boom to create more
frames per second if you will so I need
to do um one other thing maybe if I
accidentally leave the trash can open
let me make one change here let me make
sure that the very first thing I do when
the green flag is clicked is always
start with the trash can closed because
otherwise you might accidentally leave
it open so this gets me into some
default state so now it's always closed
until I manually hover over it instead
well what might I have done next well if
I wanted to introduce something like the
trash I need a second Sprite and here in
advance I grabb the image already let me
pretend that this never happened let me
drag this away here and now I have
nothing in my code area for this piece
of trash but it is a second Sprite and
all I did was I clicked on the little
cat plus icon here created a second
Sprite I named it trash I added an
costume for it sort of the aesthetic
stuff I did in advance but here I'll do
now the code how do I want to do this
well how about when the green flag is
clicked for the trash can I want the
trash can in parallel to do or I want
the trash the piece of trash to do its
own thing so what I wanted to do is
maybe let's do motion how about and
let's go to a specific coordinate now
there's a lot of options here there's
turning go to a random position go to x
comma y Glide more elegantly there's a
lot of different ways to implement
movement I just wanted to go to a very
specific location first so I'm just
going to go to x comma y first and I'm
going to say x how about will be um uh
let's not hardcode this let's just have
it be well let's do it at zero initially
and then 240 so whoops let's do 0 comma
240 so that this piece of trash always
starts at the top middle of the screen
if you think back to that coordinate
system 0 0 is in the middle 240 is
straight above it all right now after I
do that what do I want to do well how
about I control this thing by forever
falling now how do I make the trash move
we haven't seen this puzzle piece yet
but under motion the very first thing is
called move some number of steps by
default it's 10 but we'll do it more
simply let me go ahead and
move uh oh sorry move is going to move
it uh in whatever Direction it's facing
I only want it to move down so here even
I'm getting confused as to how many
different ways there are to do things
what I think I want to do is this let me
only change my y AIS as follows so
here's another puzzle piece called
change y so again Y is the vertical so
let me just change y by one pixel
downward at a time so Nega one one pixel
at a time so it's kind of slow and I
think now I think that's it let me hit
stop notice that my trash can is still
going to be interactive I haven't
changed or deleted that code I've just
added now code for my trash piece of
trash if I click the green flag notice
that after I enable it let me start that
again I had it hidden for before class
but let me enable it now green flag
notice it starts dead center at xal 0 y
= 240 and it's dropping one pixel at a
time if that seems a little boring we
can change it to negative 10 pixels at a
time and boom it's done so that's how
you might change the speed of a program
but I'm going to leave it more simply as
negative 1 and honestly it would be nice
if it doesn't always start from the top
otherwise this game is not going to be
very interactive I'm literally going to
be grabbing the trash from the same
place every time so why don't I instead
stop this let me go under operators and
let's pick our random number so let me
change the hardcoded the manually
inputed zero and let's make X be
somewhere between zero so in the middle
and all the way over to uh what was it
one oh I got my numbers wrong 240 and my
y will be 180 sorry I got my X and my my
y confused so let me play this again and
now we have a game that's more like
games you might have played growing up
or even now like there's some Randomness
to it so the CPU so to speak is doing
something more interesting let me run it
again now it's a little to the left let
me run it again now it's a little more
to the left again now it's back to the
right so Randomness just makes games
more interesting and this is why when
you play any video game if different
things are happening there's probably
just some Randomness and it's quantized
is just a simple number now I think I
just need one final flourish here if I
may let me go ahead and add this how
about uh events or rather yes events
when green flag is clicked I can do
multiple things within the same Sprite
they don't all have to be attached to
the same one let me go ahead and forever
go ahead and do something else how about
whenever the trash is how about touching
the trash can so forever if let's see I
need a sensing block so how about is
touching uh not the mouse pointer this
time but touching Oscar himself there
now let's see what happens all right so
let's go ahead and click the green flag
now I go down over here and let
go okay that's I kind of want it to go
into the trash can how do I make it go
into the trash can how can we take this
high level idea put trash into the trash
can and make it seem to
disappear logically what could we do
yeah okay so when it touches it let's
have it disappear so I could hide it or
honestly if the game's going to be
ongoing like it was letting me Mo drop
more and more trash let me just have it
go ahead and pick a new random location
so let me do this let me go ahead and
copy this puzzle piece up here and
duplicate and I don't want the whole
thing sorry let me get rid of this let
me just do this let me go back to some
random location at the top so now notice
what happens if I click and drag on it
here it goes and I let go it looks like
it's going into the trash can because it
snaps back up to some random location
now the only thing I'm not doing really
is keeping track of any kind of score
and it turns out if I full screen this
it's not going to be draggable by
default so just as a corner case so to
speak something that you might trip over
otherwise let me go ahead and under uh
let's see uh sensing it turns out I also
need this for the piece of trash there's
this way of setting and scratch a puzzle
a Sprite to be draggable or not
draggable I need to explicitly make it
draggable so that when I do full screen
this thing now it Still Remains
draggable and someone like myself can
play it again and again well how about
we supplement this with one final
flourish why don't we keep track now of
the user score so how about when the
user actually drags the piece of trash
to the trash can let me go under
variables here where in advance I've
already made myself a variable called
score I could have called it X or Y or Z
or ABC but that's not very descriptive
in programming you typically give things
a more descriptive English or some other
language name so I called this one score
so how do I want to do this in my score
well let me go ahead and initially set
this game score to zero at the very top
of one of these Scripts
or one of these programs up here and
then anytime my cursor my piece of trash
is touching Oscar let's not just jump to
the top let's change the score by one up
here so now notice if touching Oscar
change the score that is add one to the
score and then pick a new random
location and now green flag let's do
this slowly here it goes it's the trash
can opens I let go and now notice at the
top left of my program notice the score
is now two notice the score if I do this
again is about to become three and so
here we have building blocks literally
of making this program better and better
and better and so indeed that's how you
generally approach solving any large
program uh any problem with code be it
in scratch or C or python or some other
you take this Vision you might have or
some Vision you've been assigned in a
homework assignment and try to break it
down into these constituent parts and
just pluck off the easy ones first put
the lamp post there first and at least
feel like you're making some progress
then pluck off something like the trash
can and just make it do a little thing
and it doesn't have to be in some same
order here I could have done this in a
million different ways but figure out
what the small pieces are that
ultimately like a few of the problems
we've solved today assemble into a
greater solution there too uh so that
you have now a mental model for these
types of blocks and others let's return
for a moment to this we saw a moment ago
that when I started saying hello David
and nesting those puzzle pieces we had a
whole different Paradigm Al together my
input for that second version of hello
world was to now pass in for instance
what's your name into my function called
ask that gave me not a side effect but
what I called again a return value
called answer by default in scratch and
now notice and recall when I had that
same output become the input to my next
block it looked a little something like
this say so how does this type of block
and this nesting the stacking of blocks
fit into the same mental model well same
idea my input for that part of the story
is now taking in not one input but two
two arguments hello and the answer from
before the function in this case is that
new block called join the output thereof
is hello David which itself became if we
sort of animate this the input to my
final function which indeed was still
say and this is only to say no pun
intended that almost everything that
that you do with these puzzle pieces be
in the context of Oscar time or the mole
whacking or even just something simple
like hello world will ultimately fit
into that relatively simple mental model
there now I thought we'd End by taking a
look at just a couple final examples
these ones two made by some of your
predecessors and for this I thought we
would not write code together but read
it instead and so allow me to open up
one other example here that will show us
a few different versions of a program
that a predecessor made give me just a
moment here and we'll see how we might
build up to something even more
interactive and in just a moment we'll
see something they called Ivy's uh
hardest game focused here on these
particular mechanics so here is version
zero so to speak of this program where
in the goal is to create a game where
you have to like get out of some kind of
Maze and you have to get out in this
case the Harvard Crest from this maze
let me go ahead and just hit play on
this green flag so you can see what what
the first building block for this
program might have been notice that my
hand here is actually on the arrow keys
of my keyboard and it seems that by
moving up down left or right this little
Crest on the screen responds in exactly
that way now let's hypothesize for just
a moment even though we've not done
anything quite like this before how
might this code be implemented how do
you get a Sprite be it a cat or a Crest
to respond to keys on a keyboard might
you think intuitively yeah there could
be something that's sensing what key
you're pressing on yeah there could be
something sensing what key you're
pressing on and if you do it again in a
forever Loop you'll just constantly be
listening for keystrokes and this is how
like every piece of software nowadays
works it's constantly waiting for your
phone to be tapped or something to be
typed on the screen so let me go ahead
and look inside of this existing program
here and there's more going on but we'll
take a quick glance what's actually
going on well up here at top left notice
we just have go to x equals 0 and Y
equals 0 that means put the Harvard
Crest dead center in the middle of the
stage then we have forever two functions
that we made in advance as custom
functions uh listen for keyboard feel
for walls so it's doing two things at
once it's forever listening for the
keyboard up down left right and feeling
for the walls in the sense that if I get
too far to the left I don't want it to
keep moving past that black wall and if
it moves too far to the right I don't
want it to blow through that wall either
so it's going to do two things
constantly listening for keyboard and
feeling for walls so to speak and how
are those implemented well this one's a
bit long but on the left here is listen
for keyboard so this pink puzzle piece
listen for keyboard first checks if the
key up arrow is pressed question mark
Boolean expression in a conditional
change y by one that means move it up
one else if the key down arrow is
pressed then change y by negative one
and similar for left Arrow similar for
right arrow and even though there's not
a loop in this pink function there is
where I'm using it so it's constantly
being asked again and again how about
feeling for walls well over here to the
right it's a little cut off but here you
have if touching left wall change X by
one so if you hit the wall it's too late
you're kind of blowing through it
already so I want to move it wh one
pixel so it's no longer touching that
wall similarly if it's touching the
right wall I want to back it up one
pixel so it's no longer touching that
wall so it's kind of like bouncing off
ever so slightly so that it doesn't slip
through that actual wall and what are
those walls well noce down here it's
just a simple Sprite with a black line
that I've oriented hor vertically
instead of horizontally and that's just
so that I can ask questions of these
other two Sprites now that gives me that
form of interactivity what more can I
now do well what if we make things a
little more interactive here let me go
ahead and see inside version one our
second and let me propose what's going
to happen here well how might we add a
little something like Yale into the mix
well what's Yale going to do when I I
hit the green flag now based on this
code any
hunches here is the code for my Yale
Sprite yeah yeah it's kind of got to be
an adversary by blocking my path
theoretically if I keep writing more
code so why it to goes to the middle of
the screen it points in Direction 90 de
so similarly there's a whole degree
system as well and it forever asks this
if touching the left wall or notice the
green block touching the right wall then
just turn around 180 and in if you
think this through logically that just
means you're bouncing this way and this
way by just flipping yourself around
180 for just this Yale Sprite so if I
go ahead and zoom in on this and click
the green flag I can still move up and
down but Yale is just kind of doing this
all day long back and forth and back and
forth forever nothing bad happens if I
try to go through it but we could add
that certainly to the mix in fact let's
add one final feature before we play
this particular game and let me go ahead
and open up the final version of these
building blocks that adds MIT to the mix
so here's
MIT someone want to explain what this
code does and this is what we're doing
this itself is a skill reading someone
else's code and understanding it is half
of the part of programming besides
writing yeah yeah it's chasing down the
Harvard logo outline so this is
apparently the name of the costume that
this student made Harvard logo outline
outline and apparently it goes to a
random position first but then it
forever points to Har so no matter where
I'm moving it up down left or right MIT
is being a little more strategic than
Yale bouncing back and forth like this
so let's go ahead and play this one in
full screen and here we have a green
flag so if I move up
MIT rather strategically is following me
no matter where I go all right so still
nothing bad happens but and now it's
struggling right it's going up down up
down it's trying to uh follow me even
though I'm not moving so we need some
final flourishes and so I think for this
we need perhaps one final volunteer
after this cake awaits for everyone
outside as is an end of first lecture
cs50 tradition would you like to come up
and be our our vinyl of
volunteer all right and so this will be
the actual version bit written by one of
your predecessors that I'll full screen
here it's going to stitch together all
of these same Primitives in more but add
the notion of score and lives so that
there's actually a goal which in this
case is to move the Harvard Crest to
constantly pursue the character on the
right hand side so that your Sprite
touches that one would you like to
introduce yourself uh hi my name is
Muhammad all right wonderful welcome
aboard and here we come with some
instructions and final flourish if we
want to keep the lights up but perhaps
increase the
music
[Music]
e
you
[Music]
all right this is cs50 and this is week
one wherein we continue programming but
we do it in a different language because
recall last time we focused on this
graphical language called scratch but we
use scratch uh not only because it's
sort of fun and accessible but because
it allows us to explore a lot of these
Concepts here Nam functions and
conditionals Boolean Expressions Loops
variables and more and so indeed even if
today's syntax as we transition to this
new language called C feels a little bit
cryptic maybe a little intimidating at
first and you don't quite see all of the
meaning of the symbols beyond the syntax
itself realized that the ideas are
ultimately going to be the same in fact
as we transition from what was last week
a hello world program that looked a
little something like this this week of
course it's going to now look a little
more cryptic it's going to look a little
something like this and now even if you
can't quite distinguish what all of the
various symbols mean in this code turns
out that at the end of the day it's
indeed going to do what you expect it's
just going to say hello world on the
screen just like we did in scratch so
let's start to apply some terminology to
these to these uh tokens first so what
we're about to see what we're about to
write henceforth we're going to start
calling source code code that you the
human programmer write is just
henceforth called source code doesn't
matter if it's scratch doesn't matter if
it's C doesn't matter if it's python
before
source code is the general term for
really what you and I as human
programmers will ultimately write of
course computers don't understand source
code it turns out computers don't
understand scratch and puzzle pieces per
se or C code like we're about to see
they only understand this which we
called what last week yeah so this is
binary zeros and ones but really it's
just information represented in binary
and in fact the technical term now for
patterns of zeros and ones that a
computer not only understands
understands how to interpret as letters
or numbers or colors or images or more
but knows how to execute as well
henceforth is going to be called machine
code to contrast it with source code so
whereas you and I the humans write
source code it's the computer that
ultimately only understands machine code
and even though we won't get into the
details of exactly what pattern of
symbols means what you'll see that in
this kind of pattern of zeros and ones
there's going to be numbers there's
going to be letters but there's also
going to be instructions because indeed
computers are really good at doing
things addition subtraction moving
things in and out of memory and suffice
it to say that the Macs the PCS the
other computers of the world have just
decided as a society what certain
patterns of zeros and ones mean when it
comes to operations as well so not just
data but instructions but those patterns
are not something we're going to focus
on in a class like this we're going to
focus on the higher level software side
of things simply assuming that we need
to somehow output machine code so it
turns out then that this problem we have
to solve getting from source code to
machine code actually fits into the same
Paradigm as last time but the input in
this case is going to be source code on
the one hand like that's what you and I
ideally will write so that we don't have
to write zeros and ones but we need to
somehow output machine code because
that's what your Macs PCS phones are
actually going to understand well it
turns out there's special programs in
life whose purpose is to do exactly this
conversion convert the source code you
and I write to the machine code that our
phones and computers understand and that
type of program is going to be called a
compiler so indeed today we'll introduce
you to another piece of software and
these come in many forms we'll use a
popular one here that allows you to
convert source code in C to machine code
in uh zeros and ones now you didn't have
to do this with scratch in the world of
scratch it was as simple as clicking the
green flag because essentially MIT did
all of the heavy lifting there figuring
out how to convert these graphical
puzzle pieces to the underlying machine
code but now starting today as we begin
to study programming and computer
science proper now that power moves to
you and it's up to you now to do that
kind of conversion but thankfully the
fact that these compilers exist means
that you and I don't have to program in
machine code like our ancestors Once
Upon a Time did be it virtually or with
physical Punch Cards like pieces of
paper with holes in them you and I get
to focus uh on our keyboard as such but
it's not just going to be a matter today
of like writing code it's going to be a
matter ultimately today onward of good
code as well and this is the kind of
thing that you don't just learn
overnight it takes time it takes
practice just like writing an essay in
any subject might take time and practice
and iteration over time but in a
programming class like cs50 we're going
to Aspire to evaluate the quality of
code along these three axes generally is
it correct first and foremost like does
the code do what it's supposed to do
after all if it doesn't well what was
the point of writing it in the first
place so it sort of goes without saying
that you want code you write to be
correct and it's obviously not always
again anytime you're Mac or PC or phone
has crashed some human somewhere wrote
buggy that is code with mistakes but C
correctness is going to be the first and
foremost goal but then there's a more
subjective goal we'll see in time a
matter of design and we saw a little bit
of this last week when I proposed that
we could design even scratch programs
better maybe by using Loops instead of
just by copying and pasting the same
blocks again and again so design is more
subjective it's more of a a learned art
whereby two people might ultimately
disagree as to which version of a
program is better designed but we'll
give you building blocks and principles
over the coming weeks so that you can
have a better sense for yourself if your
own code is well designed and why is
that valuable well the better design
your code is often the faster it's going
to run the more maintainable it's going
to be by you or colleagues if you're
working with others in the real world so
good design is a good thing it helps you
communicate your ideas just like an
typical English essay and then lastly
we'll talk this week onward about style
and this is really just the Aesthetics
of your code it turns out that computers
often don't care how sloppy your actual
code is um where uh in the world of code
it turns out that you don't really need
to indent things in a beautiful way you
don't need to paginate things like you
might in an essay the computer generally
does not care but the human does the
teaching assistant does you will care
the next day when you're just trying to
understand what your code does so we'll
focus lastly on Style the Aesthetics of
the code that you're writing so where
are we going to write code where are we
going to compile code so for this class
not only with C but the other languages
we use later in the term we're going to
use a free text editor that is program
called Visual Studio code AKA vs code
it's super popular nowadays not just for
C but for C++ and Python and Java and
any number of other languages it's a
text editor in the sense that it lets
you edit text and that all that's all
code is going to be now strictly
speaking you could write code on paper
pencil in fact in high school if you
took a class you might have done that
one or more times as sort of an in-class
exercise you can't run it on paper of
course but you could write it certainly
you could use something like Microsoft
Word or notepad.exe or text edit on the
Mac but none of those programs are
really designed to format the code in
the best way for you nor are they
designed to let you compile and run the
code so VSS code is going to be a tool
via which you can do all that and more
write the code compile the code run the
code so that you all don't have to
wrestle with stupid technical support
headaches at the beginning of the course
by installing this software and that on
your Macs or PCS we'll use a cloud based
version of VSS code at code. cs50. and
that's going to be the exact same tool
and the goal then is by the end of the
semester to sort of uh migrate you off
of that cloud-based environment to your
own Mac and PC so that even if cs50 is
the only CS class you ever take you're
100% equipped to continue writing code
after the class using not something
that's even cs50 specific but a de facto
industry standard at least for some time
so what's this program VSS code going to
look like be it on your Mac PC or
initially in your browser and it's going
to look a little something like this and
there's going to be several different
regions to the screen and picture here
is that very same code I keep proposing
is the simplest program you can write in
C and what are these different regions
of the screen well there's essentially
these four here so first highlighted up
top is going to be one or more tabs
where you're going to actually write
code so much like in Google Docs or
Microsoft Word you can have tabs open
with files similarly in VSS code or
really any programming environment do
generally nowadays have tabs of some
sort and this is going to be a tab
containing a file it seems called
hello.c and that's going to be the very
first file we write in just a moment uh
down here though is going to be an
interface that many of you might not
know this is what's called a terminal
window and a terminal window provides
what's generally called a commandline
interface or CLI and this is in contrast
with a graphical user interface or guey
now you and I every day are using guies
on our phones on our PCS and a guy is
literally graphical so menus and buttons
and icons and you generally use your
finger or a trackpad or a mouse or
something like that to interact with it
but it turns out that many programmers
dare say most programmers at least over
time come to prefer not a guey but a CLI
a command line interface where you
actually do everything somewhat uh
somewhat arcely via keyboard alone why
well it turns out there's just more
features built in to most computers if
you can access them with a keyboard
turns out you can most of us can type
faster than you can point and click and
so that ends up being an efficient gain
over time so in time will you get
comfortable using this terminal window
to do things like compile your code or
make your program as well as run it so
you won't be in the habit initially of
just double clicking icons like we do in
our typical real world you'll do it sort
of the programmer's way but it's not to
the exclusion of adding icons and
clickability and more on the left hand
side of vs code there's going to be a
somewhat familiar file explorer some
kind of hierarchical tree like on your
Mac or PC where you can see all of the
files in your account pictured here for
instance is just hello.c which I'll
create myself in a moment and then far
away on the left is the so-called
activity bar and this is where you just
get a lot of traditional menus and
buttons so VSS code itself gives you
both a guey and a CLI but it's within
the CLI the terminal window the bottom
region of the screen that we're actually
going to type most of our commands and
in general in class I'm going to hide
all of the graphical stuff that's just
not of all that uh that much interest so
with that said let me actually change
over to a live version of vs code and
I've indeed HD in the activity bar I've
indeed hid in the file explorer so what
I have here for visibility sake is a
really big area for writing code and a
really big terminal window at the bottom
you'll see in the terminal window
there's a dollar sign and this doesn't
mean any form of currency this is just
the standard symbol that represents type
commands here so the fact that there's
just a dollar sign in a cursor means
eventually that's where I'm going to
type commands but first i'm going to
actually create some code so how might I
program using vs code be it on my Mac PC
or in this cloud-based environment that
you'll get set up for problem set one go
about writing my first file well perhaps
the easiest way is this literally run
the command code and then the name of
the file you want to create notice that
I deliberately end the file with C in
lowercase notice that I've deliberately
lowercased the whole file name and these
are just conventions you could use a
capital H you kind of could use a
Capital C but just don't do that follow
best practices so that it's consistent
with what most everyone else would do
when I hit enter I just get an empty tab
just like the screenshot a moment ago
and it's in this tab where I can now
write my very first program in C
unfortunately it's not quite as user
friendly as scratch where you drag and
drop a couple of puzzle pieces and boom
it's done so I'm going to do this for
memory but this too will become familiar
to you over time I'm going to include
something called standard io. I'm going
to type int main void and parentheses on
a new line I'm going to insert some
curly braces as we'll call them and then
I'm going to type print F and then some
parentheses and then in quotes hello
comma world then a backslash then a
lowercase n then a close quote and then
a semicolon at the very end of the line
so all I've done is recreate just from
memory that very first program in a
little bit we'll make clear what most of
this does but for now let's just
actually run this thing and just like I
click the green flag last week for the
first time let's actually compile and
run this program if it were your Mac PC
and Google or Microsoft or someone else
had made the software at this point in
the story we'd be double clicking an
icon but we can't do that yet this is
still source code so I'm going to click
back down in my terminal window notice I
have a second dollar sign below the
first which just means it's ready for a
second command and now the command via
which to make this an actual program to
compile it from source code to machine
code is going to be quite simply make
and then the name of the program I want
to make slight subtlety I'm omitting
deliberately. C because the program I
want to make I just want to call hello
so don't write make hello. C just write
make hello and this program make is
essentially our compiler technically
speaking it's a program that automates
the compilation of my program for me but
it is going to see that I've typed the
word hello it's going to automatically
look now for a file on the hard drive
called hello.c and convert it from
source code in C to machine code in
zeros and ones so if I didn't make any
typos
enter nothing seems to happen and that's
a good thing almost always if nothing
gets outputed on the screen like you did
good like you didn't make any mistakes
you didn't get yelled at there's no
error messages so this is actually a
good thing how do I now run this program
well notice I've got a third dollar sign
which just means I'm ready for a third
command and now I'm going to go ahead
and run dot slash hello and this is
admittedly a little weird that you have
to do dot slash but for now just take on
faith that this is how you run a program
called hello in your current folder in
your current directory in this
cloud-based environment all right
crossing my fingers again hitting enter
and voila my very first program in see
hello world and now let me go ahead and
reveal the file explorer that I proposed
exist earlier I'm just going to use a
keyboard shortcut to reveal that and
generally I keep it close because I
don't really need to know constantly
what files are in my account but you'll
see now in the file explorer similar
INSP to a Mac or PC but graphically a
little different here's my file hello.c
it's highlighted because I have that tab
open but now there's a second file here
called just hello that's the name of my
program so if you were on a Mac or PC
you would ideally double click that
thing you can't do that in a command
line environment you have to run it down
here but that's all we've done we've
created a file called hello.c and then
my compiler made the program from that
let me pause here and see if there's any
questions because it's a lot of magical
phrases
yeah yeah so if you're currently
following along uh playing along at home
and you're getting some kind of error
message part of today will be for me to
deliberately induce some of those error
messages for now let me just propose
that if you literally did what I did you
must have made a typo somewhere and
notice that it's indeed standard IO
stdio.h uh maybe you type
studio. okay super common mistake if I
don't if I could call you out um like it
is not studio. it is standard io. so
common but this is exactly
representative of like the kind of
stupid headaches you're going to run
into this week probably for a few weeks
probably honestly for a few years but
you start to see past these sort of
stupid mistakes over time and it just
gets easier and easier because the
computer is going to be so regimented
like you it will only do what you tell
it to do and if you say because it's
verbally sounds like studio. it's not
going to know what the file is so
actually thank you for tripping over
that so early that's super common to
happen yeah have two hello so I why do I
have two hello files so why do I have
two hello files one is the one I created
as the human called hello.c and it's
pictured right here but then when I ran
make hello that process compiled my
source code into machine code so this
second file just called hello is the
file that contains all of those zeros
and ones that the server actually
understands all right so yeah
question if you try clicking on the
Hello file you'll see in this
environment of vs code quote unquote the
file is not displayed in the editor
because it is either binary AKA zeros
and ones or uses an unsupported text
encoding in this case it's binary it's
zeros and ones now you could use
software to see those zeros and ones it
won't be intellectually enlightening to
most any human so VSS code just takes
the choice of not showing it to you at
all so that would be a common mistake
too clicking on a file you don't intend
but the source code is indeed going to
be editable by us all right all right so
I've written this program it seems to
sort of magically work at least with
some effort if you get every single
keystroke right well what is it that's
going on and how is this working well
first of all notice that even without my
highlighting things or choosing buttons
from menus notice that it's already kind
of colorcoded and yet I wasn't
highlighting along the way in sort of
Google doc style changing the color
certainly well it turns out what VSS
code and most programming environments
nowadays do for you automatically is
syntax highlighting so syntax
highlighting is just this feature of
typical text editors nowadays that
analyzes the code that you've typed and
when it notices certain types of
keystrokes things that represent
functions or conditionals or Loops or
variables a lot of the vocab from last
week it just highlights it ever so
differently for you so main for instance
which we'll soon see is in purple here
int and void and include are in red
hello world is in blue my parentheses
are in green this will totally vary by
programmer too in fact if you do want to
change these colors for problem set one
for your own environment you can poke
around vs code settings via the gear
icon you can change a different a change
to a different color theme syntax
highlighting isn't some specific color
scheme like it is in scratch it just
generally is to each human their own
preference but that's all that's
happening here is this notion of syntax
highlighting at the moment well what
more is going on in this code before I
run it but rather write it well it looks
a little something like this if I take
away all of the colors and then just for
discussion sake let me ahead and color
it a little more like scratch recall
that our very first scratch program that
just said hello world on the screen had
a when green flag clicked icon uh puzzle
piece roughly an orange and then a
purple uh sa block beneath it so whereas
this is the C version if we rewind to
last week this was the same program in
scratch but what's happening now is
exactly the same so if you think back to
last week and you've got some function
like the say function in purple that
might take one or more arguments like
inputs that influences what it says on
the screen and then functions recall can
sometimes have side effects right like
the speech bubble appears on the screen
so last week when we used the sa block
and we passed in an argument of hello
world at left we got this visual side
effect on the screen that says now hello
world in the speech bubble and that's
exactly what just happened in VSS code
but much much more textually and let's
look a little closer now at the code
itself let me wave my hand at the
equivalent of the when green flag
clicked part of my code and let's focus
only on the say block in scratch and the
corresponding function in C so if I step
through this and I wanted to convert
what we did last week with the say block
to C I would first use the print
function although that's actually a bit
of a white lie it's actually the print F
function print f means formatted and
it's just a function that allows you to
format text on the screen There Is No Sa
function in C there's a print F function
what MIT did down the road years ago go
was they took what existed historically
as print F and they simplified it for a
broader audience by just calling it
essentially say instead but notice that
now if I want to convert the scratch
code at left to C code at right it's
sort of the same shape so MIT
deliberately used this white oval if
only because it kind of conjures these
uh this idea of having parentheses too
so on the right if I want to pass an
argument or an input to the print F
function I use an open parenthesis and a
CL parenthesis in those parentheses I
then type whatever it is I want to print
on the screen in this case hello comma
world but notice I've deliberately left
some room because you need some extra
keystrokes in the world of C anytime you
type out some text otherwise known as a
string of text to use computer science
jargon you need to quote it in this case
with double quotes double quote at the
left double quote at the right and
notice to I'm going to include some
slightly cryptic symbol here too back
sln which I also typed and said verbally
earlier and then one last nuisance at
the end of this which is a semicolon so
suffice it to say this is why we start
with scratch this drag and drop you're
good to go in a language like C print F
parenthesis double quotes the text you
want backs slash and semicolon at the
end there's just so much syntactic
overhead but at the end of the day it's
just a function and you'll get used to
these sort of nuisances like the
parentheses the quotes the semicolon and
the like but things can very easily go
wrong and it's very easy to make
mistakes even with lines of code like
this so let me do this let me go back to
vs code where I have the exact same code
notice that on line five is exactly that
line of code so this is the equivalent
of the sa block and let's consider what
mistakes I may make early on or even now
20 years later after learning this that
are quite common um in general suppose I
forget the semicolon there so easy to do
you will do this eventually let's see
what happens now when I go back to my
terminal window and try to compile my
code again just to keep things tidy I'm
going to clear my screen but that's just
for lecture sake so that we can focus
only on the most recent command but I'm
going to go ahead now and rerun make
Hello this will ensure that my program
is recompiled and this is a manual
process I changed my code the zeros and
ones on the hard drive have not changed
I need to recompile it to Output the
latest machine code so here we go I'm
going to hit enter crossing my fingers
as before but again I remove the
semicolon by
accident oh my God there's like more
lines of Errors now than there are of
actual code and this too takes them
getting used to um the programs we're
using were not necessarily written with
the least comfortable audience in mind
but really professional programmers back
in the day but through practice and
through experience and through mistakes
you'll start to notice patterns here too
so here's what I typed make hello after
the dollar sign prompt now I get yelled
at with as follows hello.c colon
529 well what's that referring to I've
screwed up somewhere on line five on the
29th character on that line generally
the specific character is not that
useful unless you actually want to count
it out but line five is a good clue why
it means I screwed up somewhere on line
five here all right well what is the
error expected a semicolon after
expression and this error is actually
pretty obvious now that I see it and I
realize oh wait a minute all right
here's my line of code here in sort of
asky art so to speak textual uh text
representing Graphics it wants me to put
in green here this semicolon at the end
of that line one error generated built
in so some esoteric stuff there but my
program did not compile when you see an
error like this it means it did not work
so what's the fix well obviously the fix
is to go back up here put the semicolon
there and now if I recompile my code
with make hello I won't clear my screen
just yet just to show you the difference
now it just worked so we're back in
business as before all right let me
pause here though and ask if there's any
questions about what I just did
[Music]
these error messages will become
frequent initially
yeah really good question do you need a
semicolon after every line or just some
it turns out just some uh this is
something you'll learn through practice
through demonstrations and examples
today generally you put a semicolon
after a statement so to speak and this
is the technical term for this line of
code it's a statement and think of it is
it's kind of the code equivalent of like
an English sentence so the semi colon
and code is sort of like a period in
English when you're done with that
particular thought you don't need
semicolons for now anywhere else and
we'll see examples of where else you put
them but it usually is at the end of a
line of code that hasn't that isn't
purely syntactic like uh curly braces
instead other questions on the mistake I
just fixed and created for myself
[Music]
yeah uh correct so line five is where
the error is most likely character 29
means it's sort of 29 characters that
way and then it's actually in this case
giving me a suggestion the compiler
won't always know how to advise me
especially if I've made a real mess of
my code but often it will do its best to
give you the answer like this
yeah ah so how come I first typed code
space hello.c and now I'm typing make
hello two different processes so when I
typed code space hello.c that was
because I wanted to open vs code and
create a new new file called hello.c
it's like going to file new in in a a
Mac or PC thereafter though once the
file exists and is actually open here
and it does autosave you don't need to
hit command s or control s all the time
I can now compile it with make hello
again and again so theoretically I
should never need to type code space
hello.c again unless I want to create a
brand new file called the same thing all
right so what about this other piece of
syntax here let me clear my terminal
window here you can also hit control L
just to throw everything away just to
clean it up aesthetically suppose that I
omit whatever this sequence of symbols
is back sln since I'm not really sure at
first glance why that's even there does
anyone want to conjecture especially if
you've never programmed before what
might happen now if I recompile and
rerun this version of the program I left
the semicolon but I took away the backs
slash
n any
instincts all right well yeah
will the next dollar sign appear
straight after your it will the next
dollar sign will appear right after my
hello world but what makes you think
that back creates a line exactly back
sln is actually a special sequence of
symbols that creates a new line and so
to your point if I recompile this
program make hello enter no syntax error
so it did compile this time so you don't
need the backs slash in you do need the
semicolon but if you don't have the back
sln watch what happens when I do/ hello
this time now indeed I see hello comma
world and then a weird dollar sign and
this is still a prompt I can still type
commands at it like clear and everything
gets cleaned up but it just looks kind
of stupid if I run it again here with
hello you know it's just not very user
friendly it is convention that when
you're done running your program you
should ideally clean things up move the
cursor to the next line for the user and
so the backs slash n is simply the
special symbol otherwise known as an
escape
sequence that c knows means move the
cursor to the next line in other
languages python among them uses the
same symbology as well now if I go back
to the code here and for instance I try
to do this differently like suppose I
don't put the backs slash N I just hit
enter like a normal person would in
Google Docs or Microsoft Word let me go
ahead and try compiling this program and
this you would hope would work right you
would hope this would print out hello
world and then a blank line because I
move the cursor to the next line but no
if I run make hello now and try to
compile that c does not like this now I
get a different error still on line five
this time starting at character 12 uh
error missing terminating double quote
character and then some other esoteric
stuff and then this does not sound good
fatal error this time too many errors
admitted stopping now so I really
screwed up here so why can't I do this
just because like the humans who
designed C decided that if you have a
string of text it must stay on the same
line it can get really long it can soft
wrap that is without you hitting enter
but you can't hit enter to create a new
line if you deliberately want a new line
you have to indeed use this back slash
and Escape character so let me go ahead
and do this let me put it back let me go
back to my terminal window I'll clear
the screen again let me go ahead now and
do make Hello to recompile to that
version do/ hello and voila we're back
in business with uh hello all right so
now let's tease apart some some other
aspects of this code because there's a
lot going on just to get us to say hello
world on the screen for today we're
largely going to ignore this int main
void and these curly braces here we'll
come back to that before long as to why
it's there but for now just think of int
main void and these curly braces here as
really being the C equivalent of when
green flag clicked like why you just
need it there that's how you get your
program going and Maine is indeed going
to be some special function but more on
that another time but why do I have this
line of code here the cor spelling is
indeed standard io.
stdio.h and they're angled brackets this
time so that's a little new there's a
hash and then an include keyword you
know if you don't know what something is
you know there's not really that much
harm in just getting rid of it and see
what happens so let me delete that line
let me go back to my terminal window
clear the screen and then run make hello
again and let's try compiling this
program now without that first line why
I don't understand it so let's see what
happens all right here's yet another
error but let's see how hello. C line
five character 5 so it's pretty early on
error implicitly declaring Library
function printf with type int and then
dot dot dot so implicitly declaring
Library function print F so this is very
cryptic sounding you'll get better at
understanding phrases like these but
apparently I do need the include line
for standard
i.h but why based on this symptom what
might Your Instinct be for what that
first line of code is doing for us in
the first place why intuitively must it
be
there exactly it's like importing a
library so that you can do things like
print things out on the screen now in
scratch you didn't have to do this for
most of the puzzle pieces but you might
recall that partway in through week zero
I went to the extensions button at the
bottom left of the scratch screen and I
imported some extra puzzle pieces for
text to speech that gave us the sort of
creepy uh humanized voice that actually
came out of the cat's mouth well that
was like adding a library code that
someone else wrote in that case it was a
third party then but I gave myself
access to it same here turns out that
you don't really get printf
automatically in C you have to include a
so-called header file that declares that
function to exist now the reason for
this historically is just efficiency
back in the day when computers were
really slower and resource constrained
you don't want to just give yourself
access to the entire kitchen sync of
functionality you only want to include
only the functions you actually care
about nowadays it's sort of a sort of a
a copy paste step because you almost
always want to print something out on
the screen at least when writing
programs like these but these so-called
header files contain enough information
about all of the functions in What's
called the standard IO library and
standard IO just means standard input in
output and that's appropriate right
because printing is pretty basic output
turns out there's other functions for
getting input from the human's keyboard
more on that in a bit but anytime you
want to print something on the screen
and see you indeed need to include this
header file at the top of your code and
that's going to essentially inform the
compiler hey compiler I want to use
functionality from the standard IO
Library including printf in this case
and if you omit the header file by
accident it's just not going to work
because it doesn't know what print f is
it's sort of some unrecognized symbol in
that case all right questions then about
this line of
code this line of code here or what
these header files
are all right you might wonder well how
do you know what functions exist how do
you know what files you might indeed
want to include well it turns out that c
is a many-year old language and it has
ample documentation a caveat is that its
documentation isn't necessarily all that
userfriendly but what we have for the
course is a simplified version of the
official documentation for C at this URL
here manual. cs50. so in the world of c
and other languages too there are what
are called manual pages and these are
just like text-based documentation that
honestly is typically written in a voice
that you kind of have to be an
experienced programmer to understand
some of it so what we've done it this
version of the same documentation is
we've imported all of the original
official documentation but we've added
sort of less comfortable translations in
English for a lot of the functionality
that you might use in class just to help
onboard you so at the end of the day you
don't need this documentation long term
but just to get started we'll translate
it into terminology uh that you might
appreciate from a teaching assistant for
instance as opposed to the original
author of these documents and so for
instance if you were interested in
reading up on what functions exist in
the standard io. um header file well you
could go to a URL like this or you could
search for it at manual. cs50. that
would show you a list of all of the
available functions in that library and
print F indeed would be one of them and
then you could click further on that
reaching a URL like this that's just
going to give you all of the
documentation for how to use print def
it turns out you can do even more than
it uh than just printing out hello world
and we'll scratch the surface of that
today but it turns out that the
documentation will always be your
authoritative Source ultimately for
questions like what can I do and how can
I do it meanwhile it turns out that cs50
has its own library in A Accessible via
header file called cs50.h it turns out
in C that output is actually pretty easy
relatively speaking once you get used to
all the curly braces parentheses quote
marks and the like but input is a little
more difficult and if you have
programmed before input's not that hard
to do in Python it's not that hard to do
in Java it's more difficult to do in C
and we'll see why in a couple of weeks
but for the first couple of weeks of the
class we actually provide you with some
training wheels of sorts whereby we have
a number of functions that are declared
in this file cs50.h it lives its
documentation at a URL like this this
and in a moment we'll use a few of these
you'll see that cs50 provides you with
some functions like get Char forget a
single character from the user's
keyboard uh get int to get an integer
from the user's keyboard uh get string
to get a sequence of text from the
user's keyboard and a bunch of others as
well so let's actually use some of these
functions how about by revisiting really
the second program we wrote in scratch
last time which adds some input to the
output so first version of scratch was
just hello world said the same thing
every time you click the green flag
version two recall though did this it
asked the user what's your name and then
that somehow gave it back a a return
variable return value we called it and
we then joined hello in that name to say
something a little more interesting on
the screen so what did that model look
like same thing as before we've got a
function in the Middle where function is
like the code implementation of our
algorithm that takes in one or more
arguments like what is it you want to uh
say on the the screen ultimately and
return value in this case is going to be
actually a value that comes back so in
the case of getting input we can
consider this ask block again like last
week the input to it is whatever words
of English you want to ask the user and
then it returns a value and this was
called by default in mit's World answer
that we'll see and see you can call
these return values anything you want
ultimately in variables but this is
different from a side effect a side
effect is just something visual often
that happens on the screen like the
speech bubble or hello world a return
value is actually a value you get back
from a function that you can use or
reuse so how do we convert this scratch
block from last week to C code this week
well if you want to ask the user for
something like their name you can do
this you use a cs50 function called get
string and you use the parentheses to
represent here comes the inputs there
too you can then put the sentence you
want to ask the user quote unquote
what's your name but you do indeed need
the quotes literally in C so I'll go
ahead and add those as well well subtle
but I've deliberately included a space
after the question mark but before the
double quote just so that the cursor
moves one step over because in this case
we're not going to get a special speech
box like we did in scratch it's just
going to leave the cursor where it is so
we'll see that aesthetically this just
moves the blinking cursor one space
after the sentence on the screen all
right but the catch is with scratch we
just automatically got back the answer
from the user in a special variable
called answer in C you're going to have
to be a little more specific in C if you
want to get back a return value from a
function like get string you have to use
an equal sign and then the name of a
variable on the left the choice of
variables is up to you I could have
called this anything X YZ I'm going to
more descriptively call it answer for
parody with what MIT did with scratch
but notice that this doesn't represent
equality per se this is assignment in
this case so in C when you use a single
equal sign that means means copy the
value on the right over to the value on
the left from right to left so what does
this do for us well if get string is a
function that prompts the user with
quote unquote what's your name and it
has I claim a return value that means it
kind of hands me back some value but
it's up to me in C to do something with
that value so if I want to copy that
value into a variable that I can use and
reuse I use an equal sign and I invent
on the left hand side of that equal sign
any variable name I want there's certain
rules certain conventions but generally
if you use a single word with all
lowercase you're in good shape but C is
a little more pedantic than that and
those of you who have have programmed
before might not be used to this for
instance in Python which is a world
we'll get to in a few weeks you also
have to tell see what type of value
you're storing so if I do want a string
of text from the user so not an integer
not a single character I want a whole
string of text like a phrase a sentence
a name in this this case I have to tell
C that this variable is of type string
so it's a little wordy but you get used
to it and you just have to be precise
you're informing the computer what type
of value is going in this
variable all right it's so close to
being correct but I have omitted
something that's annoyingly important
still what's missing still yeah so
semicolon this is a statement this is
like a a a full thought if you will in
code I do need to end It ultimately with
the semicolon at the end there all right
so this was more of a mouthful but let's
try using this in now my code let me go
back to vs code where I have version
zero of my code here let me go ahead and
include one other file at the top of
hello.c namely include cs50.h so that I
have access now to get string and
anything else I might want now let me go
ahead and add a line of cod here inside
of these curly braces and let me go
ahead and do this string answer equals
get string quote unquote what's your
name question mark I'm going to add an
extra space before the double quote I'm
going to indeed end my thought with a
semicolon and now let me deliberately
make a mistake just to make a point here
let me now try changing hello world to
hello comma answer all right now perhaps
even though this is some new lines of
code you can see where I've aired
already but let me try making this
program now so far so good so no error
messages so that's a good thing let me
go ahead and run /hello and you'll see
the prompt what's your name question
mark and notice the cursor indeed one
space to the right just because I
thought it would look prettier to put a
little Blank Space there as opposed to
leaving it right after the question mark
let me type my name but even if you've
never programmed before I have screwed
up here what are we going to see on the
screen when I hit
enter yeah hello answer most likely why
cuz the computer is going to take me
literally and if I say quote unquote
hello answer that is the string of text
followed by a new line that's going to
be outputed to the screen so we need
some way of actually plugging answer
into this line of code it's not quite as
simple as scratch where you could just
grab like a second say block and drag
and drop the variable there we actually
need a new syntax and it's going to look
weird at first but it is everywhere in
software nowadays especially in the
world of c and certain other languages
so let me go ahead and propose that I
solve it as follows well back when we
did this in scratch remember that the
most elegant solution was this here we
used the say block still which is going
to be analogous to print F today but I
use the join puzzle piece in scratch to
combine hello comma space and then the
name of the human so how do we translate
this code to C well it's going to look a
little different now I'm going to start
with print f with some parth C's and a
semicolon representing the say block but
how do I now do this joining this is
where the puzzle pieces don't quite
translate perfectly this would be the
way to do this you put hello comma and
then a placeholder so this is what's
known as a format code in C specifically
for printf and it just means this is a
placeholder for a string again a string
is just text so this means hey computer
print out literally hello comma space
and then not literally percent s percent
s is uh treated specially to mean plug
in some value here all right so what
else do I still need well this is still
some text so I'm still going going to
surround the whole thing with double
quotes I'm still going to include my
back sln just to keep things tidy and
move the cursor to the next line so the
last step here in C is to somehow join
the answer with that word hello and the
way you do this is with printf passing
it not one argument which is what I keep
doing I keep passing it one string of
text quote unquote I'm going to now add
a comma and then the name of the value
that I want want printf to go back and
plug into that percent s and printf is
just smart about this if you have 1% s
and one additional argument after a
comma it just does from right to left it
plugs it in if you have two percent S's
and two variables after the comma that's
okay too if you separate them with
commas it'll plug the first into the
first percent s and the second variable
into the second percent s so it's just
left to right order of operations it's
not as pretty or as uh simple as this
but this is how it's done in C all right
let me pause because this is a lot of
symbology any questions on this
technique here
[Music]
yeah yeah really good question why did I
exclude the backslash n a moment ago
really just my sense of Aesthetics if
you will No Good Reason beyond that so
if I look back at my code you quite
rightly noticed that I didn't have a
backslash in there that's just because
for whatever sense of style that I have
I wanted the name to be typed right
after the question I totally could have
added a back sln there instead of a
space that would have just allowed me to
type down here totally fine just wanted
to show you something different good
good catch
yeah can I show an example with 2% s's
surely so let me uh in vs code do this
let me clear my terminal window to clean
things up and let me do this instead of
calling the variable answer all over the
place let me call it uh first and I'll
ask two questions what's your first name
and now let me do string last equals get
string quot whoops capitalization
matters so let me fix my capital S there
quote unquote what's your last name
question mark semicolon and now we'll
plug in one percent s and a second
percent s and now I'm going to plug in
first first and last last coincidentally
and now I'm going to go back to the
terminal window make hello crossing my
fingers
all good/ hello here's my first question
David here's my second question me and
again hello David Ma so it just inserts
them left to right all I was doing for
parody with scratch though and let me go
ahead and undo this again I'll go back
to answer like this I'll go back to just
asking for the person's name I'm going
to delete mention of last I'm going to
delete mention of the second perc s and
now if I recompile this simpler
version I did screw up didn't intend it
what did I do
wrong yeah so just newbie mistakes so I
changed my variable back to answer just
to be consistent with week zero but I
didn't change it here so I have an use
of Undeclared identifier first it's
Undeclared in the sense that I declared
answer align prior I didn't declare
first so indeed intuitively I want to
just change that to that let me now do
make hello again /hello type in just my
first name this time and there it is
hello David questions on this then
syntax with print F
yeah uh the placeholder I'll zoom in is
just a single percent and then an S so
inside of my string here is percent s
and then I have a comma outside the
quotes and then the name of the variable
whose value I want to plug in for that
percent s and now notice there's
technically two commas in side of these
parentheses on line seven and yet I
claim that printf at the moment is only
taking in two
arguments why is there then two commas
but only two arguments if there were two
commas you would think there would be
three arguments
right exactly the comma in between the
quotes is just an English thing it's
separating the hello from the name so
that's why indeed it's not only in
quotes that that's also why programs
like VSS code tend to syntax highlight
it a little differently just so that it
sort of jumps out as different to you
even though in this case it's a little
subtle a light blue versus white but
indeed it's trying its best other
questions now on this placeholder
yeah ah good question if I wanted to add
an exclamation point after the name
would I have to add another placeholder
and so forth I could actually do that
much more simply I can just put the
exclamation point right after the
percent sign I don't need an additional
placeholder per se if I zoom out now and
run make hello again/ hello and type in
just my name no exclamation point now
you'll see more excitedly hello comma
David So print f is smart it will figure
out where the percent s is and then go
and replace it now let me propose that a
common thing in programming is that as
soon as we make a decision as to how to
design something we often paint
ourselves into a corner and sort of
regret a decision can anyone think of a
problem that arises from using percent S
as a
placeholder in this string to print F
what could go wrong if we're using
percent in this special
way yeah if you literally want to say
for whatever weird reason percent s on
the screen or honestly even just a
single percent it turns out that a
percent sign is treated specially inside
of of print F strings so what's the
solution here there's different uh
patterns of solutions to problems like
these but suppose you wanted to say uh I
got 100% for instance let me let me go
ahead and change this completely so I
got 100% on your test or whatever all
right let me go ahead and run make hello
enter all right so invalid conversion
specifier I mean I have no idea what
this means but it's underlining the
percent sign is problematic well it
turns out that humans years ago decided
all right damn it we already Ed percent
well 2% signs will mean 1% literally so
now if I rerun make hello aha hello I
got 100% so there's going to be things
like that honestly that you have to ask
someone you have to Google you have to
look it up in the documentation but
there's always a solution to those kinds
of problems and thankfully they don't
come up all that often yeah oh just
poting other questions
[Music]
yeah if you have multiple variables it
is in the Left Right order so print F
will analyze the first string of text
that you pass in between quotes and
whatever the first percent is the next
the first variable that's passed in
after a comma gets plugged in there and
then the second gets plugged into the
second third and to the third and so
forth so it's just based on left to
right
yeah it's just a placeholder it's called
a format code and it just means
colloquially plug in some value here and
printf the like the humans who wrote
printf decades ago decided to treat
percent s special why just because they
needed some placeholder they decided
that eh no one's ever going to really
want to type percent s and if they do
they can just do percent percent s so
they decided to implement printf in such
a way that they have code that look
analyzes whatever text comes in looks
for percent s and then somehow plugs in
the subsequent values into that
placeholder and just this H question
[Music]
sorry ah so what if you wanted to do
single characters like initials like DM
or djm for first middle last absolutely
and that too is a perfect segue from the
two of you to what in general are going
to be called data types in C so it turns
out in C there's not only strings as
text and we'll see in more detail in
over the next couple of weeks what a
string really is underneath the hood but
strings of text are not the only thing
that programs can output they can indeed
output single characters as for initials
they can output integers as well turns
out that printf has different format
codes for all sorts of different data
types and just some of the data types
we'll see in the coming weeks will be
this list here which you'll notice it
almost perfectly lines up with the cs50
functions that I rattled off earlier
like get Char get int get string the
reason we called those functions that is
because each of them is designed to
return to you a different type of value
we've used get string already in this
example here we'll soon see get in and
we'll see opportunities to use others
but these indeed are the menu of
available data types plus others dot dot
dot that you can use when writing a
program in C the onus therefore is on
you to decide in advance do I want to
store an INT in this variable or a
string or heck when writing fancier code
an image or a sound or a video even
those can all be different data types
dot dot dot but for now we'll focus
really on just these Primitives that was
a lot let's go ahead and take a 5minute
break here no cookies yet but in 5
minutes we'll come back dive into more
detail and our second break today we'll
have
cookies all right we are back and so if
you have been playing along at home but
hitting some bumps in the road that's
totally normal and indeed the goals of
lecture generally will be to give you a
sense uh conceptually of where we'll be
going during the course of the week but
it's indeed through the Hands-On labs
and problem sets that you'll really have
an opportunity at your own pace to work
through uh some of those same bumps in
the road but for today let me give you a
few more building blocks and these two
will translate from scratch initially
namely like conditionals like how now
and see after knowing now how we can use
functions at least uh get string and
print F and we can use variables like
the string I created earlier how can I
now add to the mix things like
decisionmaking and conditionals at that
well with conditionals in scratch we had
this kind of syntax on the left here in
scratch is how you might Express if two
variables X and Y have this relationship
if x is less than y then say on the
screen X is less than y well let me
translate that to the right now in C
code so in C the corresponding code is
going to look like this assuming X and Y
already exist more on that later and
notice a pattern we're going to see
again and again there is going to be
parentheses around the X and less than y
so parentheses around the Boolean
expression recall the Boolean expression
is the true false the yes no answer that
a question that you're trying to ask in
order to decide whether or not to do
something so you use parentheses there
so similar in functions where we Ed
parentheses for printf and parentheses
for get string and this is just a weird
inconsistency stylistically when using
the keyword if you should as a matter of
better best practice put a space after
the word if when using a function like
print F or get string you shouldn't both
will work but you'll find that these are
conventions stylistically that most
people adhere to so space when using an
if here all right now inside of the
curly braces is where the actual code
goes that you want to execute
conditionally so if you want to print
out X is less than y only if x is
actually less than y in C you use this
open curly brace which up until now
you've probably rarely used on your
keyboard and the Clos curly brace down
here and those are kind of hugging if
you will the one or more lines of code
underneath the if very similar in spirit
to how the orange block here kind of
hugs the purple puzzle piece here so
there's no Graphics in C it's all text
so you can think of those curly braces
as really representing the same idea as
a side note if you only have one line of
code inside of the if condition if you
will you strictly speaking don't need
the curly braces but as a matter of good
style do include them it will make more
obvious what your intent is how about in
scratch if you wanted to express this
two ways in the road that you might go
left or right so to speak well if x is
less than y I want to say x is less than
y else I want want to say the opposite X
is not less than y in this case so I'm
making a decision based on that Boolean
expression in C it's almost the same but
you're adding to the mix the keyword Els
so MIT borrowed for scratch the same
keyword there and a second pair of curly
braces open and close respectively and
you might guess now what goes inside of
those well you print out X's less than y
or you print out X's not less than y all
right what if there's a three-way fork
in the road in scratch this actually
gets a little unwieldy graphically if
you will but notice that in scratch this
is how we could express if x is less
than y say x is less than y else if x is
greater than y say x is greater than y
else if x equals y then say x is equal
to Y now minor inconsistency here just a
little bit ago I claimed in C that a
equal sign represents what
operation assignment from right to left
left in so far as scratch is really
meant for kids and they didn't really
want to get into the weeds of this kind
of uh semantic equal sign in scratch
means equality however we're going to
need to fix this in C in just a moment
in c equal sign means assignment right
to left in scratch it literally means
what you would expect all right let's
translate this code then to C on the
right this code would correspond really
to this and you can perhaps see somewhat
goofy what the solution was not unlike
the percent percent solution earlier
when hum painted themselves into one
other corner you say if you say else if
and you say else if and how did we
resolve the use of a single equal sign
already in C when you want to repr when
you want to express equality is the
thing on the left equal to the thing on
the right you literally use two equal
signs right next to each other no space
in between them but now this code would
be correct on both the left and the
right whether you're doing this in
scratch or C respectively but now we can
kind of nitpick our code specifically
the the design thereof logically can
anyone critique the design of this code
either in scratch or C like I feel like
we could do better how about in
back perfect logically it's got to be
the case that X is less than y or X is
greater than y or by conclusion it's got
to be equal to Y so why are you wasting
my time or the computer's time asking a
third question you don't need to ask
this final else if because logically as
you knowe it should go without saying so
it's a minor tweak like you're doing
extra work potentially in cases where x
equals y so we can just refine that and
just like in scratch you could just use
an else block similarly in C could we
simplify this code to just an else a
sort of catchall logically that just
handles the reality that of course
that's going to be the final situation
instead all right so we have this
ability now to express conditionals with
Boolean expressions let's actually do
something with this next here so let me
go back to vs code I've closed hello.c
and I want to create a second file for
the sake of some demos now recall that
you can create new files by typing code
space and then the name of the file you
want to create uh for instance I might
do compare. c I want to write a program
that's going to start comparing some
values for demonstration sake but before
I do that let me just show you by
opening the file explorer at right this
is similar in spirit to a Mac or PC like
you can go up here and click on an icon
and you can click on the plus icon and
you'll get a blue box and I can type in
compare. C and I can just manually
create it that way notice that opens the
tab even without my having typed code so
again on the left you have a guey a
graphical user interface albeit a
simplistic one on the right and at the
bottom here you have a command line
interface but they're one and the same
what's nice though is that if I close
this file accidentally intentionally
whatnot I can reopen it without creating
a new one by just running that same
command code space compare. c so code is
a vs code thing it's just a userfriendly
shortcut but it's just creating a file
or opening an existing file like that
I'm going to hide the file explorer just
to make more room for code here and
let's go ahead and do this let's write a
program that compares two values that
the human inputs but not strings this
time let's use some actual integers all
right I'm going to go ahead and include
the cs-50 librar header file at top
cs50.h I'm going to also include
standard io. why one gives me
userfriendly input via get string get
int and so forth one gives me user
friendly output via printf in the case
of standard i.h now I'm just going to
kind of blindly type this line of code
which we'll come back to in future weeks
but for now that's analogous to the when
green flag clicked code in scratch and
now let's go ahead and do this let me go
ahead and get an INT from the user and
ask the user what's X question mark I'm
not going to bother with a new line I
want to keep it all in one line just for
Aesthetics sake but when I get back an
INT just like I get back a string I get
back a return value so if I want to
store the result of get int somewhere I
had better put it in a variable and I
can call the variable anything I want
previously I used answer or first or
last now I'm going to use x but there's
still two things left to do here
logically even though we haven't
technically done this yet what do I
still need to
do so I need the semicolon at the
end and the in at the beginning you the
programmer starting today kind of need
to decide what you're going to be
storing in your variables and you just
need to tell the computer that so that
it knows now as a teaser for languages
like python more modern languages turns
out humans realize well gee this is
stupid like why can't the computer just
figure out that I'm putting an INT there
why do I have to tell it proactively so
in some languages nowadays like python
we'll get rid of some of this syntax
we'll get rid of the semicolons but for
now we're looking at really the origins
of how this all worked all right so I've
done this one line ending with semicolon
let me do one other and let me get a
second int asking the user what's why
question mark so almost identical but
different responses from the user
hopefully and let me just ask simply if
x is less than y in parentheses then
some curly braces let me go ahead and
print out quote unquote X is less than y
back sln and now just as a side note I I
seem to be typing kind of fast some of
that is because vs code is helping me
let me go back to this
first line with the if hit enter and now
I'm only on my keyboard going to type
the open curly brace this is a feature
of many text editors nowadays it
finishes part of your thought why just
to save yourself a keystroke to make
sure you don't accidentally forget the
closing one so you'll notice sometimes
that things are happening that you
didn't type it's just vs code or future
programs you use trying to be helpful
for you I'll go ahead and manually type
out now printf uh X is less than y back
slend close quote semicolon so let me go
ahead now and try to run this and we'll
see let's see so make not hello but make
compare because this file is called
compare. C hitting enter okay no output
is good because it means I haven't
messed up let me do dot SL compare
instead of/ hello enter what's X how
about one what's Y how about two x is
less than y well let's try it again and
here I'll save you some keystrokes too
let me clear my screen instead of
constantly typing dot slash this and Dot
slash that you can also use your
keyboard's arrow keys in vs code to
scroll back through time so if I hit up
once there's the last command I wrote If
I write uh do it up twice there's the
second to last command I wrote so
sometimes if you see me doing things
fast it's just because I'm kind of
cheating and going through my history
like that all right let me go ahead
though and
rerun compare enter let's reverse it
this time two for x one for y and now of
course there's no no output all right
well that's logically to be expected
because we didn't have an else here so
let's add that else now let's open my
curly braces letting vs code do one of
them for me print F quote unquote X is
not less than y back sln semicolon let
me go ahead and try this again/ compare
enter again two for x one for y and we
should see
huh what did I do wrong why am I not
seeing any else output
yeah exactly you got to get into the
Habit after you change your code of
recompiling it otherwise the zeros and
ones in the server are the old ones
until you manually compile so let's fix
this make compare enter no error
messages that's good do/ compare 2 1 and
now I get back the output so X is not
less than y how about if I go and add in
the third condition well we can do this
either efficiently or inefficiently let
me go ahead head and refine this so else
if x is greater than y let's literally
say x is greater than y and now I could
do X else if x equals equals y but I
think we already claim that that's
unnecessarily inefficient so let's just
have our catchall and here I'm going to
say quote unquote X is equal 2 y back
sln close quote there so I think now
with this code we've handled all three
scenarios let me go ahead and recompile
it properly compare do/ compare and now
1 and 2 x is less than y let me run it
again 2 and One X is greater than y and
lastly one and one and X is equal to Y
so for the most part our code's getting
longer we're up to like 21 lines of code
though some of them are just single
characters on the screen almost
everything else is the same I'm using
the cs50 libraries header file for my
get int function standard i.h for my
print F function and the rest of this is
just now new syntax for conditionals as
well questions then on this C
implementation of just some basic
comparisons like
this any questions
[Music]
yeah good question do the opening
brackets need to be on a separate line
in cs50 yes what you'll see is that as
part of the submission process We
compare your code against a style guide
which is the norm in Industry a company
would have its own sense of style and
how its code should look and there's
generally automated tools within a
company that help uh give feedback on
the code or stylize it as such there are
alternative Styles than what we use in
the class we deliberately keep and ask
that you keep the curly braces on their
own line if only because it rather
resembles like the hugging nature of
scratches blocks and just makes clear
that they're balanced open and closed
however another common Paradigm in some
languages and with some programmers is
to do something like this uh on each of
them so you have the opening curly brace
on the same line as here we do not
recommend this this is invogue in the
JavaScript world and some others um but
ultimately in the real world it's up to
each individual programmer Andor the
company they're working for if
applicable to decide on those
things all right so beyond then these
conditionals what if we want to do
something that's maybe pretty common so
almost every piece of software or
website nowadays that you use has you
like agree to some terms and conditions
by typing like yes or no or just y for
yes and N for no so how could we
Implement some kind of Agreement System
well let me do this let me create a new
program a third one called agree. C so
I'm going to write code agree. C just to
give myself a new tab I'm going to start
as always now include cs50.h let's
include standard i.h and then let me do
my int main void which again for today's
purposes we'll take it face value is
just copy paste and if I just want to
get y or n for instance instead of yes
or no we can just use a simpler variable
here how about just a Char a character A
Single Character so I can use get Char
to ask the user for instance do you
agree question mark but before as before
I need to store this somewhere so I
don't want a string because it's a
single Char I don't want an INT I just
want a Char and it's literally CH h a r
and then I could call this thing
anything I want it's conventional if you
have a simple program with just a single
variable and it's of type Char call it C
if it's an INT call it I if it's a
string call it s for now I'm just going
to keep it simple and call it C and now
I'm going to ask a question so if C
equals equals how about quote unquote
y then let me go ahead and print out uh
agreed back sln as though they agreed to
my terms and conditions uh otherwise
let's see else if the character equals
equals quote unquote n
then let me go ahead and print out uh
say not agreed as though they didn't
quote unquote and let's leave it at that
I think here initially now you'll notice
one curiosity one inconsistency perhaps
does anyone want to call it out though
it's somewhat
subtle I've done something ever so
slightly differently without explaining
it yet do you see it single single yeah
so I've suddenly used single quotation
marks for my single characters and
double quotes for my actual strings of
text this is a necessity in C when
you're dealing with strings like strings
of text like someone's name a sentence a
paragraph anything really more than one
character you typically use uh double
quotes and indeed you must when dealing
with deliberately single characters like
I am here for y or n you must use single
quotes instead why because that makes
sure that the computer knows that it's
indeed a Char and not a string so double
quotes are for Strings single quotes are
for chars so with that said let me go
ahead and zoom out let me go ahead in my
terminal window run make agree enter
seems to work okay so let me go ahead
and do/ agree uh let me go ahead now and
type in y here we go
enter huh uh let me try that again rerun
do/ agree how about no
enter why is it not behaving as I would
have expected uh because you the capital
Y yeah I kind of cheated there and I hit
the caps lock key just as I started
typing in input why because I
deliberately wanted to type in uppercase
instead of lowercase which is kind of
reasonable right it's a little obnoxious
if you force the user to toggle their
caps lock key on or off when you just
need a simple answer that's not the best
user experience or ux but it would work
if I cooperated let me run this again
without caps lock on y lowercase for yes
ah that worked and uh lowercase for no
that work worked but how could I get it
to work for both well how about this let
me go ahead and just add two
possibilities so else if C equals equals
quote unquote capital Y then also do
printf agreed back sln and down here
else if C equals equals uh single quote
uh capital N then go ahead and print out
again not agreed okay this I will claim
now is correct and I'll do make agree
real fast do slash agree and I'll use
Capital it now works I'll use uh Capital
it again works but this is perhaps not
the best design let me hide the terminal
window and pull this up on the screen
all at
once why might this arguably not be the
best design even though it's
correct there's another term of art we
can toss here like something smells kind
of funky about this code this is an
actual term of art like there's code
smell here like something smells a
little off why what do you
[Music]
think yeah there's the same output again
and again I mean I manually typed it but
honestly I might as well have just
copied and pasted most of my original
code to do it again and again for the C
two capital letters so if line 10 and 14
are the same and line 18 and 22 are the
same and then the rest of these if and
Els ifs are almost the same like like
there's some code smell there like it's
not well-designed why because if I want
to change things now just like last week
in scratch I might have to change my
code in multiple places or copy paste is
never a good thing and go God forbid I
want to add support for yes and no as
full words it's really going to get long
so how can we solve this well it turns
out like we can combine some of these
thoughts so let me try to improve the
yeses first it turns out if I delete
that Clause I can actually or things
together in scratch there's a couple
puzzle pieces if you didn't discover
them that literally have the word or and
the word and on them which allow you to
combine Boolean Expressions so that
either this or this is true or this and
this is true in C you can't just say the
word or you instead use two vertical
bars and vertical bars together mean or
logically and so I can say C equals
equals quote unquote capital Y agreed
and now I can get rid of this code down
here and let me go ahead and say
vertical vertical bar twice C equals uh
quote unquote n in all caps and now my
program's like you know roughly a third
uh smaller which is good there's less
redundancy and if I reopen my terminal
window rerun make of agree SL agree now
I can type little y or Big Y and same
thing for lowercase and uppercase n any
questions then on this syntax whereby
now you can combine thoughts and just
kind of tighten things up
and there'll be other such tricks too
yeah a really good question is there not
a function to just ignore the case short
answer there is and we'll see how to do
that in actually just about a week's
time and in other languages there's even
more ways to just canonicalize the
user's input throwing away any space
characters they might have accidentally
hit forcing everything to lower case in
C it's going to be a little more work on
our part to do that but in fact as early
as next week we'll see how we can do
that but for now we're comparing indeed
just these literal values other
[Music]
questions really good question so we are
assuming with this program in all of my
last ones that the human's cooperating
when I asked for their name they typed
in David and not one two three or in
this case they typed in a single
character and not a full word so this is
one of the features often of using a
library so for instance if I run agree
again
and I say something like sure enter it
rejects it alt together why because s e
is a string of characters it's not a
single character now I could just say
something like X which is neither y nor
n of course but it tolerates that
because it's a single character but
built into cs50's library is some
built-in rejections of inputs that's not
expected so if you use get int and the
user types in not the number one or two
but cat C A it will just prompt them
again prompt them again and this is
where too if you were to do this
manually in C you end up writing this
much code just to check for all of these
errors that's why we use these training
wheels for a few weeks just to make the
code more robust but in a few weeks time
we'll take the library away and you'll
see and understand how it's doing all
it's indeed doing all that all right so
how about this let's now transition to
something a little more scratch like
literally uh by creating how about
another program here called meow so
meow. C we won't have any audio
capabilities for this one will just rely
on print and suppose that I wanted to
write a program in C that just simulates
like a cat meowing so I don't need any
user input just yet so I'm just going to
use standard i.h I'm going to do my
usual int main void up here and then I'm
just going to go ahead and do printf
meow back sln and let's have this C meow
three times like last week so I'm going
to do meow meow meow notice as an aside
whenever you highlight the lines you'll
see little dots appear this is just a
visual cue to you to let you figure out
how many spaces you've indented vs code
like a lot of editors will automatically
indent your code for you I've not been
hitting the space bar four times every
time I've not even been hitting tab
however in C the convention is indeed to
indent lines where appropriate by four
spaces so not three not five and these
dots help you see things so that they
just line up as a matter of good style
all right so this program I'm just going
to stipulate right now is indeed going
to work make meow which is kind of cute
and now meow there three times correct
it's meowing three times but of course
this is not well designed it wasn't well
designed in scratch last week why what
should I be doing
differently
yeah
yeah it's a perfect like opportunity for
a loop why because if you wanted to
change maybe the capitalization of these
words you wanted to change the sound to
like woof or a dog or something like
you'd have to change it one two three
places and that's just kind of stupid
right in code you should ideally change
things in one place so how might I do
that well we could introduce a loop yes
but we're going to need another building
block as well that we had in scratch
namely those things called variables so
we're call that a variable like in
algebra x y z whatever can store a value
for you and a variable in scratch might
have looked like this you use this
orange puzzle piece to set a variable of
any name not just X Y or Z but you could
call it something more descriptive like
counter and you can set it equal to some
value in C the way to do this is similar
to to Spirit to some of the syntax we've
seen thus far you start by saying the
name of the variable you want a single
equal sign and then the value you want
to initialize it to copying therefore
from right to left why because the equal
sign denotes again assignment from right
to left this isn't enough though you
might have the intuition already what's
missing probably from this line of code
just to create a variable so we need int
to make sure the computer knows that
this is indeed an INT and then lastly
semicolon as well and that now completes
the thought so a little more annoying
than scratch but we're starting to see
patterns here so not every piece of
syntax will be new all right if you
wanted to increment the counter by one
scratch uses the verb change and they
mean add the value to counter so if I
want to increment an existing variable
called counter this syntax is a little
more interesting it turns out the code
looks like this which almost seems like
a paradox like how can counter equal
counter plus one like that's not how
math works but again a single equal sign
is assignment from right to left so this
is saying take whatever the value of
counter is add one to it and copy that
value from right to left into counter
itself you still need the semicolon but
I claim you do not need to mention the
keyword int when updating an existing
variable so only when you create a
variable in C do you use the word string
or the word int or any of the others
will eventually see only when creating
it or initializing It For the First Time
thereafter if you want to change it it
just exists it's the word you gave it
the computer's smart enough to at least
remember what type it is so this line is
now complete turns out in code as we'll
see it's pretty common to want to add
things together increase increment
Things by One so there's actually
different Syntax for the same idea the
term of art here is syntactic sugar like
there's often in code many ways to do
the same thing even though at the end of
the day they do exactly the same
functionality so for instance if after a
few days of cs50 you find this a little
tedious to keep typing and some program
you can simplify it to just this this is
the syntactic sugar you can use plus
equals and only mention the variable
name once on the left and it just knows
that that means the previous thing it's
just slightly uh more uh more succinct
this to is such a common thing to add
one to a value and it doesn't have to be
one but in this case it is but if it is
indeed one you can further tighten the
code up to just do this counter Plus+ so
anytime in C you see plus plus it means
literally adding one to that particular
variable there's other ways to do this
in the other direction if you want to
subtract one from a variable you can use
any of the previous syntax using a minus
sign instead of Plus or you can more
succinctly do counter minus minus this
is the way a typical C programmer would
do this all right so if we have now
variables let's go and solve the meowing
with loops so in scratch we saw Loops
like this this of course had the cat
meow three times how do we do this in C
now this this is where things get a
little more uh involved codewise but if
you understand each and every line it
will follow logically what's going on so
here I claim is one way to implement a
loop that iterates three times in C and
this is kind of ridiculous right like we
went from two super simple puzzle pieces
like this to my God like it's 1 2 3 four
five six lines of code all of which are
pretty involved so like that escalated
quickly but what's each line doing and
we'll see other ways to do this more
simply so we're izing a variable called
counter to three just like before why
well what does it mean to Loop or to
repeat something three times well it's
kind of like doing something three times
and then do it and then count down and
then do it and then count down and then
do it until you're all out of counts so
this is declaring a variable called
counter setting it equal to three then
I'm inducing a loop in C which is
similar in spirit to repeat three but
you have to do more of the math yourself
so I'm asking the question in
parentheses
while counter is greater than zero what
do I want to do well Pur the indentation
inside the curly braces I want to meow
one time and then to be clear what's
this last line of code doing if counter
starts off at three this makes it two by
subtracting one from it then what
happens by nature of a loop just like in
scratch it kind of knows to go back and
forth even though there's nice pretty
arrow in scratch and there isn't here C
knows to do this again and again and
again con stantly asking this question
and then updating this value at the end
so if I highlight just a few of these
steps the variable starts off at three
and actually let me simplify two I
claimed earlier that uh when using
single variables people very often just
call it I for INT or c for Char or s for
string unless you have multiple
variables so let me tighten the code up
and this already makes it look a little
more tolerable let me actually tighten
it up further and one more step so now
this is about as tight as succinct as
you can make this code at the moment so
what's actually going to happen here
well the first line of code executes and
that initializes I to 3 then we check
the condition while I is greater than
zero is I greater than zero we'll per my
three fingers obviously so we print out
meow on the screen then we subtract one
from I at which point now we have two as
the value of I then the code goes back
to the condition and notice the
condition there is in parentheses that's
another Boolean expression so Loops can
use Boolean Expressions just like
conditionals use Boolean Expressions to
make decis ision the loop though is
deciding not whether to do this thing or
that but whether to do the same thing
again and again and again and as it
ticks through the code one line after
the other it's ultimately going to get
down to uh one and then zero and then
stop so put another way came with some
props here so suppose uh this bowl here
is your variable and you initialize it
to three with like three stress balls
you can do something three times right
if I want to give out three stress balls
here's your chance for free stress ball
without having to answer any questions
any okay there we go so here we go
subtracting one from my variable I'm
left with two uh oh my God all right uh
don't tell
Sounders oh I'm sorry oh okay that ended
poorly apologies all right but now the
educational point though is that my
variable has been uh decremented further
to just have I'm not throwing that far
again I can't do this in here we go all
right here we go and one final
subtraction and now our variable is left
so we have three stress balls there and
that's all a variable is right it's some
kind of storage it's actually of course
implemented in the computer's memory but
metaphorically it's really just like a
bow with some values and every time you
add or in this case subtract you're just
changing the value of that variable and
then the code meanwhile of course in
parenthesis is just checking is the bow
empty is the bowl empty is the bowl
empty AKA is I greater than zero or not
any questions on how we've implemented
Loops in this way
and I I'll you a stress ball after class
questions on Loops all right so it turns
out this is kind of ugly and like this
really starts to take the fun out of
programming uh when you have to like
write out this uh sequence of steps so
it turns out there's other ways to do
this but first let's see logically how
else you might Express this because it's
a little weird that we keep using zero
so the one other way to do this would be
to invert the logic you could absolutely
start with your variable call it I equal
to one and then you ask the question is
I less than or equal to three and notice
a bit of new syntax here on your uh
typical keyboard there is no less than
or equal sign or greater than or equal
sign like you would write in math class
with one over the other and so in C you
use two characters less than followed by
an equal sign or if appropriate greater
than followed by an equal sign and that
logically captures that idea so notice
that I'm kind of changing my questions
I'm initializing I to one and then I'm
going to increment It ultimately to two
and then three but because I'm doing
less than or equal to it's still going
to go from 1 to three so that works too
we could similarly do this yet another
way we could initialize I to zero and
then we could say well I is less than
three and keep incrementing it and I
showed this last form is actually the
most canonical like it might be the most
humanlike to think in terms of 1 to
three it might be the most stress ball
like to think in terms of three to zero
counting down but Ty typically the go-to
Syntax for most programmers once you get
comfortable counting from zero is to
always start counting from zero and
count up to less than the value you're
counting up to so it would be incorrect
why to change this to less than or equal
to three here what would happen if I
Chang the less than to less than or
equal to it'll me out twice yeah it'll
out an extra a fourth time in fact total
right because you'll start at zero then
one then two then three and less than or
equal to three sorry three will give you
the fourth time so we do want it indeed
to be just a single less than all right
so now that we have those options let me
just give you one other and this one
takes a little more getting used to as
well but it's probably the more common
way to write this let me go ahead and
propose that we implement this as
follows let me go back to my code here
let me go into my several printfs
getting rid of all but one of them
ultimately and let's implement this in
code so let's do in I get that's zero
how about then while I is less than
three then let's go ahead and say print
F quote unquote meow uh mellow meow back
sln and then we have to do I minus minus
or plus
plus so plus plus because we're starting
at zero and going up two but not through
three so let me go ahead now and make
meow after clearing my terminal SL meow
and it's still just as correct but it's
a little more uh it's a little better
designed why because now if I want to
change it from three to 30 times for
instance I can change it there I can
recompile my code I can do/ meow and
done I don't have to copy and paste it
27 more times to get that effect and I
can even change what the word is by
changing it in just one location but it
turns out there's other ways to do this
too and let me propose that we introduce
you to what's called a for loop as well
so if you want to repeat something three
times you can absolutely take the while
Loop approach that we just saw or you
can do this and this one's a little
takes a little more getting used to but
it kind of consolidates into one line
all of the same logic so notice we have
the keyword four here and four is just a
a preposition in this case that
generally implies here comes a loop
inside of parenthesis here is not just a
Boolean expression and this where things
get a little weird there's three things
to the left of the semicolon in the
middle of the two semicolons and to the
right of the semicolon this is really
the only other context we'll see
semicolons and it's weird normally it's
been at the end of the line now it's two
of them in the middle of the line but
this is the way humans decided years ago
to do it so what is this doing almost
the same thing it is going to initialize
a variable called I to zero it's going
to then check if it's less than three
it's then going to do what's ever in the
curly braces is and it's lastly going to
increment I and repeat so just
highlighting in turn at first I is
initialized to zero just like before
then this condition is checked this is a
Boolean expression yes or no true or
false will be its answer and if I is
less than three which it should be once
it starts at zero well then we're going
to go ahead and print out meow then I is
going to get incremented so it starts at
zero it goes now to one at that point
the Boolean expression is checked again
so you don't keep changing I back to
zero that first step happens only once
but now you repeat through those three
other highlights I check if I is less
than three it is so I print out meow it
then increments I I check if I now two
is less than three it is I print out
meow I gets incremented I now check is I
less than three no it's not because
three is not less than three and so the
whole thing stops and whatever code is
below this curly brace if any starts
executing instead just like in scratch
you break out of the loop and the the
puzzle piece being hugged questions then
about this alternative Syntax
for Loops AKA a four
Loop sorry say
again yeah can I explain again why it
doesn't reset to zero honestly just
because like this was the syntax they
chose this first part before the first
semicolon is only executed once just
because that's how it's designed
everything else Cycles again and again
and this is just an alternative syntax
to to using the slightly more lines of
code it was like six lines of code using
the while loop logically it's the same
thing programmers once they get more
comfortable tend to prefer this because
it just expresses all your same thoughts
more succinctly that's all yeah okay so
let's just work this into my meow
example let me go back to the code here
and notice indeed if I highlight all
these lines I think we can tighten this
up let me get rid of all of those and
instead do four in I equals 0 and I'm
saying equals most programmers would say
gets so in I gets zero means assignment
the word get now I'm going to do I is
less than three i+ plus now in here I'm
going to do my print F quote unquote
meow back sln and so it's indeed a
little tighter I mean two of the lines
are just curly braces there's really
only two juicy lines of code now let me
go ahead and do make
meow meow and again we're back in
business with three of them printing
only all right there's one last
structure we should explore just cuz
it's sometimes useful this was a forever
block and this would be a little weird
in scratch to just say meow Forever at
least without waiting but there is
indeed a forever Block in scratch which
means do the following forever and I
proposed I think verbally last week's at
least one example where this is useful
meowing forever little annoying but can
you think of common cases where you
might want to write code or use a
program that Loops forever
yeah yeah playing music like Spotify
playlist just repeating again and again
would be some kind of loop for
collisions checking for collisions and
scratch so seeing if something's
bouncing off the wall or another Sprite
yeah checking for input so yeah get
string is essentially just waiting there
forever for me to type in some input
until I do the time checking the time
and actually maintaining like human time
like a wall clock behind you was that
the
same okay checking the time and one more
detecting a key press too like in
scratch just waiting for some kind of
event to happen just like on a phone or
a browser and so there's so many
examples where you might want to do
something forever just so you've seen
the corresponding C building block it's
a little weird but this is probably the
most canonical way to do it in C if you
want to print meow forever which would
be a little crazy because it literally
print and take over your computer
printing forever meow you would
generally do it like this why well a
while loop expects in parentheses a
Boolean expression and a Boolean
expression is again a yes no a true
false question but if you want the
answer to that question always to be yes
or really always to be true turns out in
C in a lot of languages well then just
say true because true T R is never going
to change magically to false I mean it's
just a special word in the programming
language so by saying while true it just
means do the following forever another
common Paradigm before true and false
became common place would be to do uh
this instead change uh while one you
might see in online examples and texts
and the like while one is really the
same thing any value that is zero is
generally interpreted as false by a
computer any value that is one or any
other nonzero value is generally
interpreted as true and so this too
would have the same effect saying while
true or while one generally speaking
while true is perhaps a little clearer
these days now meowing forever is not a
good thing but suppose I did that by
intent or by accident well let's try
this so here I'll go into my code I'm
going to get rid of my for Loop and
change my while loop to uh how about
true um and in this case here well we'll
keep it let's do this make meow enter
and you'll see this use of Undeclared
identifier or true this is actually
hinting at my mention that the old way
was zero and one nowadays you could say
true or false but true and false are
themselves special words that you have
to include and it turns out if you want
to use special Boolean values like this
there's another header file we haven't
seen called standard bu that essentially
creates true and false as keywords
alternatively cs50 includes that same
file so it's more common in cs50 to see
it like this now if I clear my terminal
window and do make meow and then do/
meow and hit enter well unfortunately
this isn't the best thing to do uh
infinitely when you're in the cloud
using a browser this is indeed a a
browser full screened here um this means
I'm sending millions of meows over the
internet to my computer here uh so this
will happen to you at some point
probably not with meow but you'll lose
control over your terminal window why
because you screwed up and like you have
an infinite Loop you didn't really
intend it or maybe you did you were
curious to see what happens what do you
do like when when does the meowing stop
what recourse do we have here all right
well control c will be your friend
sometimes you have to hit it a bunch in
a cloud environment but control C for
cancel with will interrupt a program
that's running and I promise that almost
all of you will at some point
accidentally introduce an infinite Loop
because you're math is slightly off when
in doubt click in the terminal window
and hit contrl C sometimes multiple
times and that will indeed cancel
whatever is happening there in this case
I might have intended it but sometimes
it's not in fact intended all right so
we've been taking for granted this whole
graphical user interface for some time
and indeed uh the uh commands that I'm
typing and the buttons I'm clicking and
let me just give you a better sense of
what it is we are using underneath the
hood this whole time um namely an
operating system called Linux so I keep
alluding verbally of course to Macs and
PCs because almost all of us are running
Mac OS or Windows on our desktops or
laptops nowadays but there's lots of
other operating systems out there and
one of the most popular one is called
Linux and Linux is very often used on
servers nowadays companies that host
email companies that host websites or
apps more generally um certain computer
scientists or computer science students
often like to brag that they run Linux
just because that's a thing um but it is
really just an alternative to Mac OS or
windows that provides you with both a
guey if you want it but also and
especially a command line environment
now fun fact Windows and Mac OS do have
terminal windows or the equivalent
thereof and eventually you might uh use
it on your own Mac or PC to solve some
problem but Linux is really known for
along with other operating systems it's
command line environment which again I
distinguished earlier from Guy as a
command line interface or CLI and that
refers really to the terminal window so
if I go back to VSS code here and let me
in fact go ahead and close my tab and
focus entirely on the terminal window
this terminal window is really just your
command line interface to your very own
server in the cloud the term of art here
is you each will have your own container
in the cloud which is like your own
computer running somewhere on the
internet with your own username and
password to which you have access and
your own hard drive if you will your own
home folder that has all of your files
for the class and it's only accessible
to you unless you enable live sharing
thereof so when you're typing commands
here it looks like you're typing them of
course on your own Mac or PC but they're
actually being sent over the browser to
uh some server in the cloud where you
are controlling really your own account
therein so it turns out that there are
other commands that are worth knowing
and we'll give you just a few of these
today and over the coming weeks will you
have opport ities to play with others as
well but these are kind of some of the
basics and they're all incredibly
succinct because indeed for things
you're typing at the command line humans
generally have not wanted to type out
long commands so a lot of these are
abbreviations here now perhaps the most
common one I'll start with first is LS a
lowercase l and a lowercase s that
stands for succinctly list so if I go to
my terminal window now where up until
now I've only typed code which is a vs
code thing for creating and opening
files and make which triggers the compil
ation of my code what if I now type LS
this will list all of the files in my
current folder my hard drive in the
cloud if you will so if I hit enter
you'll see a whole bunch of results now
they're color-coded too the white ones
here and in. c those are the source code
files I've written during class today
agree. C compare. C hello.c and meow. C
and you can perhaps guess the green ones
here that just by convention have an
asterisk on the end to denote that
they're special represent what
what are the four others
yeah yeah the machine code so those are
my actual programs that are identically
named minus the C extension and the
asterisk means that they're executable
that is in the world of Mac OS or
Windows you would double click but in
the world of a command line environment
that means you do dot slash and then the
name without the asterisk to execute or
run the code therein so if I open up my
file explorer and I'm hitting command B
on my computer here just as a keyboard
shortcut you'll see the exact same thing
so LS is the command line interface for
listing the files in your account but
here because I'm using vs code or any
program like it I also get a graphical
user interface as well so it's just two
different places to be you're welcome to
use whatever you're comfortable with but
over time will you naturally get more
comfortable and capable with the
terminal window alone well what else is
on this this list here well during the
break I saw that at least one of you for
instance had created a file called hello
instead of hello. so you were in a
situation where you did this
accidentally and hit enter and then you
went ahead and typed in all of your code
like this and then down in your terminal
window you were trying to do make hello
enter and this now didn't actually do
anything like I can't I'm hitting um I'm
trying to run the command I got
permission denied as at least one of you
did now why is that well let's just do a
quick check if I do LS I see now hello
but hello has no asteris next to it
which means it's not executable that's
my code why well notice the top of my
tab confirms oh I screwed up I didn't
name my file hello.c which it just has
to be so what do you do well you could
very hackish like copy this create a new
file paste it in or no no no like we
know how to rename things now here
because that's one of our options let me
do this let me do MV for move hello and
then hello.c and hit enter you'll see
the tab closes cuz hello no longer
exists but if I now now type LS you'll
see ah there is hello.c and if I open
that file now there's all of my same
code and now if I do make hello make
hello now I do get an executable file
wherein the world is restored so MV is
just a command not just for renaming but
it also turns out eventually for moving
files as well you can also create
directories or folders so for instance
if I go into vs code again and suppose I
hover over here and click not on the
plus file icon but plus folder I can
create a folder called for instance like
pset one for problem set one in the
class and you'll see now that it's empty
CU all of my other files are in the
default folder of my account but I could
also go in there like this and I could
click on file and now I can create a new
file called like mario.c which is uh one
of the first problems for instance but
you'll notice now that
mario.c is inside of the pet one folder
so if I zoom out and I type LS at my
terminal window
I won't see mario. C anywhere but I do
see a pet one folder and it's in light
blue followed by a slash which you don't
have to type it just indicates that's a
folder now I can visually at top left
obviously see pet one contains mario.c
but if I try to do something like make
Mario here no rule to make Target Mario
like it just doesn't seem to exist and
that's because you're in the wrong
directory so in a command line interface
it's not quite as simple as just
clicking on a folder and voila it opens
you have to change into the directory or
folder and CD is going to be the command
there so if I want to actually change
into that directory I can do CD space
pet one enter and now you'll see my
prompt changes and this is just a common
convention but it's not the only one out
there now I still have a dollar sign
which indicates where I can type
commands but before it I see a reminder
constantly what folder I'm in and we put
that there deliberately like a lot of
Linux users do just to remind themselves
where they are cuz unlike Mac OS where
you or Windows where you have a nice big
window telling you where you are at the
command line you kind of need to be
reminded textually but now if I type LS
and hit enter what should I
see yeah mario.c and now if I want to
open it uh if I want to uh actually
compile it I can run make Mario in this
directory once I actually type out all
the code rest assured that in problem
sets in Labs we almost always certainly
in the first weeks of the class give you
exactly the commands to type odds are
because it's new to many of you view you
will accidentally type the wrong
commands no big deal just remember that
you have different ways to solve these
problems you've got like the graphical
file explorer which should feel a little
more familiar but in time you'll start
to know and honestly probably prefer
commands like these so CD for change
directory CP for copy a file uh LS for
list MK dirt to make a directory create
a new folder at the command line instead
of with the button MV for move or rename
RM
for remove so be careful with that one
RM dur remove directory and there's
dozens hundreds of other commands you
won't need many of them but we'll start
to scratch the surface all the more over
time but ultimately this command line
interface is going to be a more powerful
mechanism a more capable mechanism and
ultimately a more efficient mechanism
for writing code running commands uh
solving problems analyzing data more
generally even though no there's going
to be some uh some Growing Pains early
on just because it's probably so new for
many of you so with that said we have
some problems still to solve but we
promised cookies today so let's go ahead
and take a 10-minute break cookies are
now served in the transcept and we'll be
back here in
10 all right we are back and up until
now each of the code examples in C we've
done if been kind of designed to show
one specific topic but we thought we'd
try to take a step back and solve a more
General problem and give you a sense of
when given a problem set for instance or
just a programming problem more
generally like where you even begin and
how you go about approaching it when
it's not obvious what the point of the
exercise is so one of my favorite games
from yester year is this one here Super
Mario Brothers that has come in so many
different forms since but in this
original uh two-dimensional Sid scroller
game there was a lot of artwork like
this so for instance up here in the sky
were four question marks and we'll find
that in C in a lot of programming
languages initially it's a lot easier a
lot more accessible to focus really on
black and white type interactive
programs textually as opposed to
full-fledged graphics and the like but
more on the more Gra graphical acoustic
uh type of programs before long but for
now let me go over and propose that we
try to just Implement an asy art aski
again being the code that Maps numbers
to letters at least for English um into
a textual version of these four question
marks in the sky so for this let me go
over to vs code I'll create my own
version of mario.c that will be
different from the one you're challenged
with in problem set one indeed in
problem set one you'll be challenged to
build a little something like this
albeit with hashtags uh for asky art
instead of graphics and in mario.c I
want to just solve this simple problem
first so it's all involving output so
I'll do include standard i.h so I can
use printf I'll do my int main void more
on why we keep doing that in future
weeks and I'm just going to do something
simple initially like 1 2 3 4 back sln
this is about the simplest way I can
Implement four question marks in the sky
like these here using pure text like
this so let me go ahead and do make
Mario / Mario and voila we have those
four question marks but we've seen of
course that there are better ways to do
this and if you wanted to generalize
this to be five question marks six 60
different question marks you know Loop
was always the answer for not repeating
ourselves so maybe I should rewrite this
a little bit more flexibly and say
something like this four in I gets zero
I less than four I plus plus and then
inside of the for Loop now I can just do
a single question mark But I don't think
what I've just done is correct anyone
spot the aesthetic bug
already yeah why is this why is this
wrong if I want to print the same thing
[Music]
yeah yeah so I don't think I want to
backs slash in after every question mark
because the goal is again this like row
of question marks in the sky so if I now
recompile this make
Mario Mario okay it's almost there but
now I have that regression to where the
dollar sign's not on its own line so I
think I need a new line but I don't
think I want it here cuz that was not
going to end well where do I want it
instead any Instinct
yeah yeah so outside the for Loop so
indeed I can just go below line eight
and above line nine creating a new one
and now there's it's totally fine to
just print a new line like that you
don't have to print anything else with
it it's indeed a character unto itself
so let's do make Mario one last time/
Mario okay so now we're back in business
there well what if we wanted to do some
other scene from Mario uh such as this
one here where there's a lot of vertical
obstacles like the These Bricks here if
I wanted to print out now a column of
three bricks and I'll use hashtags for
these instead of anything graphical well
I think we're almost there right like I
think I can now it's almost maybe a
little easier I can go back here change
the question mark to something that
looks more like a brick like this hash
symbol and I think now I do want the new
line character because when I now do
make Mario Mario okay there's my wall of
four oh but wait I didn't want four I
wanted to be consistent just with this
particular scene here so I just want
three so I can still change it in one
place and here again is that Paradigm
even whether you're using four or three
if you get into the habit of starting
counting from zero you go on up to but
not through the value you want to count
up to so that's why I'm using less than
instead of less than or equals to there
so this would be the common Paradigm
though you could certainly count it like
we saw earlier in different ways but
what if things escalate one level
further and when you're in the
underground version of Super Mario
Brothers there's a lot of these
underground obstructions including like
grids of bricks like this and let me
conjecture that if you slice this up
it's roughly a 3X3 grid of bricks that
all interlock uh prettily to give us
just one big large brick like this so if
I want to print out a 3X3 grid now
things are getting a little more
interesting because up until now I
printed either one row horizontally or
one column vertically but we haven't
really seen any code where I'm sort of
printing or living in two different
dimensions like the game would imply but
let me propose that we could do this let
me go ahead and say all right suppose I
want to print a 3X3 grid of bricks it's
really that I want to print what three
rows of bricks like a grid is three rows
so if I take the highle idea and reduce
it to something a little simpler how do
I do that well let me get rid of the
print for a moment as I did and let me
just stipulate that this for Loop even
though it doesn't do anything useful yet
will do something how many times just by
Design all right three times right this
for Loop is good to go it will do
something three times by just using I to
do the counting all right well if I want
to print out now a row of three bricks
all on the same line that's pretty
similar to what we did earlier when I
just wanted to print out four question
marks in the sky so we've kind of seen a
solution there and I dare say we can
compose one into the other so if I want
to print out a row of bricks I could
just do this four in I gets zero I less
than three I ++ and then inside of this
inner loop if you will let me print out
a single brick like this and then I I
don't like where this is going yet but I
think I've taken two ideas and I've
combined them but what might be
problematic about lines five and seven
at the moment
what might be bad here uh yeah and
back yeah I'm using the same integer ey
which I feel like could get me into
trouble right if I'm sort of trying to
count three things here but then I'm
hijacking this variable and using it
inside of the loop like I feel like I
should avoid this this Collision of
names and so what's a good alternative
to I well a programmer if nesting Loops
in this way would pretty commonly go
with J you could certainly change this
to be like rows and columns if you want
more descriptive variables but I and J
is pretty canonical so I'm going to go
ahead and do this j++ instead of i++
everywhere and let me try compiling this
so make Mario
enter
Mario okay so a couple of things are
wrong here this is not a 3X3 grid but if
you count these things how many did I
indeed print at
least can probably just guess logically
yeah there's nine hashes there
unfortunately they're all on the same
line instead of on three different lines
so where logically can I fix this I'm
definitely printing all the bricks
they're just not on the right levels
yeah yeah so put a new line after the
first Loop this inner loop if you will
the nested Loop if you will so let me go
ahead and print out just a back slash n
here and what's this doing well I think
that's going to solve it by just moving
the cursor to the next line after you've
done one row so let me go ahead and do
make Mario enter SL Mario and now we're
in business so it's a very simplistic
version of the same graphic but I'm
leveraging two different ideas now the
same or the same idea twice rather now
I'm using one Loop to kind of control my
cursor going row by row by row but then
within that Loop I'm doing left to right
do do dot dot dot with printing out each
of these individual bricks like this now
there's a little sloppiness here still
like if I want this to always be a
square just because that's what it looks
like in the game well I could change it
to be a 4x4 uh Square by doing this or a
5x5 grid whoops by doing this why is
this perhaps not the best design to just
keep changing the numbers when I want to
change the
size where could this go AR
yeah yeah if it's always going to be a
square and height is going to be the
same as width I'm just inviting trouble
here right eventually I'm going to screw
up I'm going to change one but not the
other then it's going to come out to be
a rectangle instead of a proper Square
so I should probably solve this a little
differently so let me do that at the top
of my main function here let me go ahead
and give myself a variable called maybe
uh n for the number of bricks I want
horizontally and vertically and I'll
just initialize that to three initially
and instead of putting three here I'll
literally just use n but I'll do it in
both places so that now henceforth if I
ever want to change this and change it
to four or five or anything else like
I'm all done like it's better designed
because there's a lower probability of
mistakes but I could technically SK
still screw up somehow I could
technically accidentally write line of
code like n++ or you know I could just
change the value of that variable even
though I don't want it to ever change
and maybe it's because I'm a bad
programmer I copy pasted wrong I'm
working with someone who doesn't know
what n represents I can defend myself
and my code against human error like
that by going up here to line five and
instead of just declaring a simple
variable like we did in scratch I can
further Harden my code so to speak by
declaring it to be a constant using the
keyword const now this is just a feature
of c and some other languages to protect
you against Yourself by proactively
saying N is a constant specifically the
number five or previously the number
three you cannot accidentally write code
elsewhere that changes it the computer
will throw an error and catch that error
so it's just a way of programming a
little more defensively um some
languages have this some languages don't
but in general it's a good practice it
makes your code better designed because
it just is less vulnerable to Mistakes
by you colleagues or anyone else using
the code so let me change this back to
three just to be our default but now I'm
using n in both places and if I do make
mario. Mario we're back to where we
originally started but the code's a
little more better design and let me
note this too all this time I've been
mentioning that uh there's correctness
is important design is important there
was also this matter of style I've been
very deliberately writing pretty code if
you will not just the syntax
highlighting which is automatic but
notice that I keep indenting everything
nicely anytime I have curly braces like
on lines 4 and 14 everything is indented
one level when I have additional curly
braces on line 7 and 13 everything is
nicely indented uh as well technically
speaking the computer does not care
about that kind of white space so to
speak and you could really make a mess
of things like this because you have a
strange sense of style or just because
you're being a little sloppy but this
code is actually still correct if I
recompile it let me open up my terminal
window make uh Mario no errors Mario it
works perfectly fine but you can imagine
just how annoying this now is to read
like certainly for a TA U but certainly
for you the next day certainly for a
colleague who has to read your code this
is just bad style like it still works
and it's welld designed in that like
you're uh writing code defensively
you're using a constant but my God the
style is atrocious now you'll often find
that there's tools that can help you
format your code for you in a manner
consistent with a courses or a company's
uh style but this is the kind of muscle
memory you'll want to develop over time
to take vs code suggestions as it's
outputting lines of code for you because
it's trying to format your code in a
readable way and oh my God if and when
you do have bugs in your code and things
aren't even indented properly there's no
way you the human are going to be able
to wrap your mind around what's
happening and where like you're just
making the problem harder for yourself
so do get into this habit too of
manifesting good style as well all right
well let me propose that we don't only
want a 3X3 grid we want this to be a
little more Dynamic so suppose we moved
away from a constant to just using an
integer called n and let's ask the user
for the size of this grid as by
prompting them with get int as we've
done before and I'll store it in N here
and then I can go ahead and more
dynamically run make Mario to compile it
whoops oh I screwed up
accidentally what is it in suggesting I
do albeit
cryptically yeah I forgot to include the
cs50 header file up top and that's why
it doesn't know that get int is in fact
valid so that's an easy fix U I'm just
going to go up here and include
cs50.h now I'm going to clear my
terminal and rerun make Mario now we're
good Mario and now notice I'm prompted
for size so if I type in three it's the
same as before if I type in 10 it's even
bigger but it happens all now
automatically but there are some things
that we're not detecting for instance
suppose I type in cat well that's
handled by the get it function as I
claimed earlier that's one of the
features of using a library you don't
have to deal with erroneous input but we
only designed a function called get int
to get you an integer we don't know if
you want it to be positive negative zero
or some combination thereof and it's
kind of weird to allow the user to type
in like negative one for the size of the
Grid or you know ne3 for the size of the
grid and indeed your code does nothing
so at least it's not crashing but that's
kind of stupid right like it'd be nice
to force the user if they want a grid to
give us a positive value so how could we
do this well I could go up here and I
could say something like if n is less
than one so if it's zero or negative
which I don't want what could I do well
I could say well prompt the user again
for the size and now notice I'm not
declaring and again because once it
exists you don't have to mention the
data type again we said that earlier but
this is kind of stupid why because now
when You' given the user a second chance
okay now maybe I'll do all right if this
version of n is less than one well let's
just go and prompt the user a third time
I mean you can kind of see where this is
stupidly going like this can't be the
right solution to keep typing
recursively the same thing again and
again like where would it stop you'd
have to give them a finite number of
chances or just you know make a mess of
your code so what would be intuitively a
better solution
here yeah so some kind of loop we've
seen a while loop we've seen a four Loop
so maybe one of those so let me try this
let me delete this messiness and just go
back to the first question and let me do
this so while n is less than one so
while the number is not what we want
let's just prompt the user in a loop
this time for the size again now here
too this is better because it's only two
requests for information but clearly
line six and N are pretty much identical
other than the int and if I went in and
changed the size you know uh if I add
this if I change the wording here change
it to a different language like I have
to change it in two places that's bad
copy paste bad so what might be better
well it turns out there's another
Paradigm in C that you can use that gets
around this problem this duplication of
code it would be much nicer if I just
write this code once and I can do that
using a third type of loop called a do
while loop so it turns out in C you can
do this if you want to get the value of
a variable like n first just decree
create the variable without an initial
value so int n semicolon means it we
don't know what value it has yes but
that's okay we're going to add a value
to it eventually then I'm going to say
this do literally I'm going to open my
curly braces and what do I want to do I
want to assign to n the return value of
get in prompting the user for size well
when do you want to do that I want to do
that while n is less than one and this
code now achieves the exact same goal
but by never repeating myself why well
notice on these lines of code now I'm
literally saying on line six give me a
variable called n of type integer it
doesn't have a value initially but
that's fine you can do that line seven
says do the following what do you want
to do get int prompting the user with
the word size and just store that value
in N but because code runs top to bottom
left to right now it's reasonable on
line 11 to ask that question okay is the
current value of n which it definitely
got on line a less than one and if the
user didn't cooperate they typed in zero
or Nega 1 or3 what's going to happen
it's going to go back up here and repeat
repeat repeat everything in the do while
loop so a do while loop in C which is
not something some other languages have
like python if you know it does not have
a do while loop this is perhaps the
cleanest way to achieve this even though
it's a little weird that you have to
declare your variable create your
variable up top and then check it down
below but other wise it's similar to a
while loop it just flips the order in
which you're asking the question any
questions on this construct and Doh in
general is super useful when you want to
get input from the user and make sure it
meets certain requirements all right so
now that we have this building block
after that interlude how can I go about
cleaning up this code and then let's
conclude by taking a look at things that
our code can't do or can't do very well
or correctly let me propose that in a
final version of Mario let me just add
what are called now some comments so it
turns out in code in C you can Define
what are called comments which are just
notes to self some of you discovered
these in scratch there's little yellow
sticky notes you can use to add
citations or explanations in C there's a
couple of ways to write comments and in
general comments are notes for yourself
for your ta for your colleague as to
what your code is doing and why or how
it's a little explanatory note in
English or whatever your human language
might be so for instance what I might do
here in my implementation of this
version of Mario I might first ask
myself a question like I I might first
make a note to S like this on a new line
above this first block of code uh get
size of Grid it's just an explanatory
remark in any tur English that generally
explains the next six or so lines the
next chunk or block of code if you will
it would be a little excessive to
comment every single line at some point
the programmer should know what
individual lines of code do but it's
nice to be able to kind kind of glance
at this comment on line six that starts
with two slashes and it gets gray out
because of syntax highlighting it's not
logic it's just a note to self it
generally gives me a little cheat sheet
as to what the following lines of code
should be doing and or why and then down
here well there's a second block of code
that's a bunch of lines but together
this just what prints uh grid of bricks
and so it's another comment to myself
that just makes it a little more
understandable what these 20 some odd
lines of code are doing by adding some
English explanations thereof but now
that I have these you know wouldn't it
be nice if I could kind of abstract
these pieces of functionality away this
getting of the size and this printing of
the Grid in other words suppose that you
didn't know where to begin with this
problem and the problem at hand were
literally Implement a program that
prints a grid of bricks of some variable
size three or four or five or whatever
the human types in if you have really no
idea where to start comments are
actually a good way of getting started
because comments can be a approximation
of what we called last week pseudo code
pseudo code is tur English that kind of
gets your point across like for the uh
phone book searching like last time so
if you didn't really know where to begin
you could do something like this I could
for instance just say get size of grid
as my first step and then print grid of
bricks as my second step and that's it
for my program thus far this is now
implemented in pseudo code I have some
massive placeholders there like I still
have work to be done but at least I have
a highle solution to the problem in
comments and now I can even go this far
I could say well let's suppose that
there's just a function already that
exists called get size I could do
something like this I could do Inn
equals get size and now I just have to
assume for the moment that some
abstraction called get size exists it
doesn't this does not come with the
cs-50 library but I could invent it I
bet how else might I proceed well let's
just assume for the moment that there's
also a function called print grid that
just prints that a grid of that size n
so here too is an abstraction these
puzzle pieces don't exist these
functions don't yet exist but in C just
like in scratch I can create my own
functions how do I do that well let me
go down later in the file and by
convention you generally want to leave
main at the top of your code why because
it's the main function and it's just
where the human eye is going to look to
see what some file of code does and let
me do this I want to create a function
of my own called get size whose purpose
in life is to get the size that the user
wants I want this function to return an
integer and the Syntax for doing that is
this write similar to a variable the
data type that this function returns I
don't need this function to take any
inputs and so I'm going to use a new
keyword that we've actually been using
thus far more on it another time just
called void which just means this get
size function does not take any inputs
it does have an output it outputs an INT
and this is just a weird order in which
you write it you write the output format
the name of the function and then the
inputs if any inside of parentheses and
now I can Implement get size but I've
already implemented get size or at least
now at this point in the story I at
least know concretely what to do and I
could figure out eventually with some
trial and error perhaps all right if I
declare a variable and I do the
following n equals get in prompting the
user for size and I keep doing that
while n is less than one once that block
of code is done here is a new keyword in
C where you can return that value n so I
keep referring to these values that some
functions return as return values in C
there's literally a keyword called
return that will hand back to any
function that uses that function the
value in question so in a nutshell
between lines 15 and 21 now here is some
code identical to our solution earlier
that gets a value n from the user that
is positive it's one or two or higher
it's not zero or it's not less than one
and as soon as we've got that value we
hand it back as a return value notice
how I'm using this function on line
7even just like with get int just like
with get string I'm calling the function
nothing in the parenthesis in this case
but then I'm using the assignment
operator to copy whatever its return
value is into my variable n and so now I
have a function that didn't used to
exist called get size that gets me a
positive integer no matter what and now
for the grid how do I do this how do I
invent a function called print grid that
takes a single argument a number and
prints a grid of that size well let's go
down here I'm going to write the name of
this function print grid this function
just needs to print it has a side effect
as we keep saying so I'm just going to
say it has no return value it's just
void it doesn't have an output per se
it's just an aesthetic side effect but
it does take an an argument an argument
is an input and the Syntax for this in C
is to name the type of the input it
takes
and the name of the variable and I could
call this anything I want I'll call it
size I could call it n and it's okay to
use the same variable in different
functions but I'll call it size just to
be distinct and then in this function
I'm just going to copy from memory the
same code as before for in I get zero I
less than size instead of three I ++
inside of this four uh int J gets zero J
is less than size j++ and inside of that
print print out with print f a single
hash print out after that Loop a single
new line and that's it now I did this
fast admittedly but it's the same code
that I wrote earlier but now just like I
did with scratch let me just arbitrarily
hit enter a bunch of times to like move
the code out of sight out of mind now I
have abstractions I have puzzle pieces
that now exist called get size and print
grid Syntax for which takes some getting
used to but they now just exist except I
do need to do one thing because C is a
little naive if I try to do make Mario
now and hit enter implicit Declaration
of function get size is invalid and
we've seen that before when I hadn't
included a file right when I hadn't
included cs50 Library get in didn't work
but that's not the issue here because
this is not from a library I just
invented this C kind of takes you
literally and if you define these
functions at the bottom of your file
they don't exist on line seven or 10 so
I could do this I could all right fine
well let me just kind of highlight all
of this cut with to my clipboard and
paste it up here this would solve the
problem I could just move all of those
functions at the top of my file that's
kind of annoying because now main is
like the bottom of the file you're not
it's going to take longer to find it
it's just that's not a clean solution so
let me put it back where it was at the
bottom and let me do this this is the
only time in cs50 and really in C
programming where copy paste is
reasonable if you copy and paste the
first line of code from each function
and then end it with a semicolon you can
tease the compiler by giving it just
enough of a hint at the top of the file
that okay these functions don't exist
till down later but here's a hint that
they will exist this is how you can uh
convince the compiler to trust you so
those other functions can still be lower
in the file below main but now when I do
make Mario oh damn it oh I said print
instead of print F that's my
bad print f
so if I do make
Mario Mario now I can type in three and
we're back in business now this was a
very heavy-handed way and long way to
get to a much more complicated solution
but this solution in some sense is
better designed why because now
especially without the comments I mean
look how short my code is my main
function is literally two lines of code
why well I kind of factored out the
juicy stuff into its own functions and
now especially if I'm working with
colleagues or others you could imagine
splitting up up large programs into
smaller parts having different people
Implement different parts so long as you
all agree in advance on what those
inputs and those outputs actually are
all right so let's now consider what
computers can do well and not so well C
indeed supports a whole bunch of
operators mathematically via which we
can do addition and subtraction
multiplication division and even
calculate the remainder when you divide
one number by another in fact why don't
we go ahead and use these in a very
simple program and make our very own
calculator so let me go over here here
to vs code let me go ahead and create a
new file called calculator. C and in
this file let's go ahead and first
include a couple of now familiar header
files
cs50.h as well as standard i.h let's go
ahead then and declare main with int
main void and then inside of main let's
do something relatively simple let's
declare an INT and call it X and set it
equal to whatever the return value is of
get int prompting the user for a value
for x let's then give ourselves a second
variable we'll call it say y set that
equal to the return value of another
call to get int prompting the user this
time for that value Y and then let's
very simply go ahead at the very end and
just print out say the sum of X Plus y a
super simple calculator so I'll use
print F quote unquote percent I for
integer back sln to give me the new line
then I'm going to go ahead and do x + y
to indeed print out the sum let me go
down to my terminal window now let me do
make calculator in order to compile the
C no error messages so that's good let
me do/ calulator and let's do something
like 2 + 2 which of course should equal
4 and it does but it turns out that
sometimes there are going to be
limitations that we bump up against and
let me get a little more ambitious here
let me clear my terminal window and let
me go ahead and rerun calculator again
and this time let's type in
O2 billion for x and let's type in the
same for y and of course now the answer
of 2 billion plus 2 billion should have
of course be 4 billion and yet it's not
so curiously we see of all things a
negative number here which suggests that
somehow the plus operator doesn't quite
work as well as we might like now why
might this actually be well it turns out
that inside of your computer is of
course memory or Ram random access
memory and depending on the size of your
computer and the type of computer it
might very well look a little something
like this a little circuit board with
these black little modules on it that
actually contain all of the btes of your
computer's memory unfortunately you and
I only have a finite amount of this
memory inside of our computers which
means no matter how high we want to
count there's ultimately going to be a
limitation on high how we can count
because we only have a finite amount of
memory we don't have an infinite number
of zeros and ones to play with we have
to actually be bounded ultimately so
what's the implication of this well it
turns out that computers typically use
as many as 32 bits zeros or ones to
represent something like an integer or
in C an INT so for instance the smallest
number we could represent using 32 ins
of course using 32 bits of course would
be zero 32 zeros like this here and the
biggest number we could represent is by
changing all of those zeros to ones
which in this case will ideally give us
a number that equals roughly 4 billion
in total it's actually 4 billion 294 mil
967 295 maximally if you set all 32 of
those bits to ones and then do out the
actual math the catch though is that we
humans and Compu in general also
sometimes want to and need to be able to
represent negative numbers so if you
want to represent negative numbers as
well as positive numbers in zero you
can't really just start counting at zero
and go all the way up to roughly four
billion you got to kind of split the
difference and maybe allocate half of
those patterns of zeros and ones to
negative numbers and the other half
roughly to positive numbers so in fact
in practice when you're using even as
many as 32 bits the highest most
computers could count certainly in a
program like this in C using an INT
would be roughly 2 billion that is 2 b47
m
483,000 flow where you want to use more
bits than you have available and as a
result you sort of overflow the
available space what does this mean in
fact in real terms well let's suppose
that you only have three bits but I'm
going to gray out a fourth bit just to
convey where we'd like to uh put an
additional bit ultimately if this of
course is zero per week zero discussion
this is 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 now ideally in
binary if you want to add one more to
this value seven you're going to have to
carry the one mathematically and that
would ideally give you 1 0 0 0 but if
you don't have four bits and your
computer's only sophisticated enough to
have three bits not even 32 but three
the implication is that you're
effectively representing not one0 0 but
rather 0 z0 there's just no room to
store that fourth bit that I've gray out
here which is to say that your integer
might overflow and as soon as you get to
seven the next number once you add one
is actually going to be zero or worse as
we've seen here in my code a negative
value instead so what could we do to
perhaps address this kind of concern
well C does not have just integers or
ins it also has Longs which as the name
suggest or just longer integers which
means they have more bits available to
them so let me go back into my code here
I'll clear the terminal window and let
me go ahead and change my integers to
literally long here long here I'm going
to have to change my function in
uh cs50's library to be not get in but
get long and that's indeed another
function we provide in the library let
me change this get in to get long as
well I'll keep my variable names the
same but I do need to make one other
change it turns out that print F also
support supports other format codes so
not just percent I for integers or
percent s for Strings but also for
instance percent Li for a long integer
as well as percent f for floating Point
values with decimals so with that said
let's go ahead and change my print F
line to be not perc I but percent Li I
now let me go ahead and do make
calculator again enter no apparent
errors now do/ calulator and 2 + 2 still
equals 4 as before but now if I do
calculator again and let's do
two billion again as well as 2 billion
for y previously we overflowed the size
of an integer and got some weird
negative number because the pattern was
misinterpreted if you will as a negative
number instead but along instead of
using using 32 bits conventionally uses
64 bits which means we have more than
enough spare bits to go when we add 2
billion plus 2 billion and now in fact
we get the correct answer of four
billion which does fit inside of the
size of a long now along can count up
quite high and in fact it can count as
high as this nine quintilian and so that
will give us quite a bit more Runway but
of course it too is ultimately going to
be finite so if you have numbers that
need to go bigger than that you might
still very well have a problem now
there's another problem that we might
run into as well and we can see it in
the context of even this simple
calculator computers also suffer from
potentially what's called truncation
where especially when you're doing math
involving floating Point values that is
numbers with decimals you might
accidentally unknowingly truncate the
value that is lose everything after the
decimal point so in fact let me go back
to vs code here I'll clear my terminal
window and let's still use Longs but
let's go ahead and use division instead
of addition here so let me change this
plus to a divide operator let me go
ahead and recompile the code down here
with make calculator let me go ahead and
run/ calculator and let me go ahead and
do something like 14x and 3 for y and
we'll see that well wait a minute 1
divided 3 I learned should be 13 but in
a floating point value that should be
point0 it should be
0.33333 you know maybe with a little
line over in grade school but really an
infinite number of Threes And yet we
seem to have lost even one of those
threes after the decimal point because
the answer is coming back here as just
zero so why might that be well if I know
that two integers when divided one by
the other is supposed to give me a
fraction a floating point value with a
decimal point I can't continue to use
integers or even in this case Longs
which do not have support for decimal
points so let me go ahead and change
this format code here from percent Li I
to percent F which is again going to
represent a floating point value instead
of a long integer or even an integer and
let me go ahead further and Define maybe
a third variable Z as a float itself so
I'll give myself a variable Z equals x /
Y and now rather than print X ided Y
let's just go ahead and print Z so now
I'm operating in a world of floating
Point values because I know proactively
that an long or an INT divided by
another such value if it's meant to have
a fraction needs to be stored in a
floating point value something with a
decimal point well let me go down to my
terminal window here and rerun make of
calculator seems to work okay/ calulator
and let's do 1 / 3 again and still here
we see all zeros well so we do at least
see a decimal point so we've made some
progress thanks to the percent F in the
float but it seems that we've already
truncated the value 1 / 3 so how do we
actually get around this issue well if
you the program know that you're dealing
in a world that's going to give you
floating Point values with decimal
points you might very well need to use
what's called a feature known as typ
casting that is convert one data type to
another by explicitly telling the
compiler that you want to do so now how
do I do this well let's go back to my
code here and if the issue fundamentally
is that c is still treating X and Y as
integers or technically Longs with no
decimal point and dividing one by the
other therefore has no room so to speak
for any numbers after a decimal point
why don't I proactively do this let me
using a slightly new syntax with
parenthesis specify that I want to
convert X proactively from a long to a
float let me specify proactively that I
want to convert y from a long to a float
as well and now let me go ahead and
trust that in Z should be the result of
dividing not a long by a long or an INT
by an INT but rather a float by a float
Let Me Clear My terminal window run make
calculator again seems to work okay/
calulator and now 1 3 and hopefully now
we actually see that my code has
outputed
0.333 333 and I think if we kept showing
more numbers after the decimal point
we'd theoretically see as many of those
threes as we want but there is still one
more catch and especially when we're
manipulating numbers in this way in a
computer using a finite amount of memory
another challenge we might run up
against besides integer overflow besides
truncation is this known as floating
point in Precision just as we can't
represent as big of an integer as we
want using int or long alone because
there is going to be an upper bound
they're similarly going to be a boundary
on just how precise our numbers can be
and indeed let's go back to vs code here
I'll clear my terminal window yet again
and this time let me use some slightly
unley syntax to specify that I don't
want to see the default number of
numbers after the the decimal point
which percent F gives us automatically
let's go ahead and show me 20 decimal
point numbers after the decimal point
and the weird Syntax for this is to do
not percent F but percent period to zero
to indicate to see that I want to see 20
digits not the default after now the
decimal point let me rerun make
calculator let me do dot calculat again
and let's do one let's do three and now
this is even weirder right from grade
school you presumably learned that 1
divided 3 is of course 1/3 but that
should be
0.33333 infinitely many times or on
paper with a little line over it but the
computer is just doing some weird
approximation here it's a whole bunch of
Threes And then 43 267 44 079
590 well what's really happening under
the hood well again is this issue of
floating point in Precision if you only
have a finite number of bits and in turn
a finite amount of memory the computer
can really only be so precise
intuitively alter Converse or
equivalently the computer has decided on
some way of representing floating Point
values but the catch is per grade school
math there's an infinite number of
numbers out there and an infinite number
of floating Point values because you can
keep adding more and more digits if you
want so the computer given the way it's
implementing these floating Point values
is essentially giving us the closest
approximation that it can now how can we
go about improving the situation well
there is one alternative instead of
using float I can use something called a
double which as the name suggests uses
twice as many bits as a float so instead
of 32 typically it will use 64 and
that's just like the difference between
a long and an INT which gave us more
bits but in this case this will be used
for more Precision let's go ahead and
Cast X to a double let's cast y to a
double and now let's go ahead and using
the same format code percent 2f is still
okay for doubles let me do make
calculator let me do do slash calculator
and now let me do 1 / 3 and we still
have some of that in precision and we'd
see even more of it if we looked at more
than just 20 digits but now we have more
threes after the decimal point so it's
at least more more more precise but it's
not perfect but it it's at least more
precise so these kinds of issues then
are going to be necessary to keep in
mind anytime you do something
numerically scientifically at least with
a language like C where you're going to
bump up against these real world
limitations of hardware and intern
language now later in the semester we'll
transition to a language called Python
and that's actually going to solve at
least one of these problems for us but
just automatically giving us more bits
so to speak as we need them at least for
integers but even the issue of floating
point in Precision is going to remain
now just how real world are these issues
well back in the year 1999 we got a
taste of this when the world realized in
the Years leading up to that date that
it might not have been the best idea to
implement computers and software therein
by storing years using just two digits
like instead of storing 1999 to
represent the year 1999 a lot of
computers for reasons of space and cost
were in the habit of kind of cutting a
corner and just using two digits to keep
track of the year the problem with that
is that if systems were not updated by
the year 1999 to support the year 2000
2001 and so forth is that just like
before with integer overflow some
computers might add one to the year in
their memory 99 it should be the year
2000 but if they're only using two
digits to represent years they might
mistake the year as some systems may
very well have for the year 1900 instead
taking literally a big step backwards if
you will now you'd like to think that
kind of issue is behind us especially as
we understand all the more about the
limitations of code and Computing but
we're actually going to run up against
this very same type of issue again in
just a few years on January 19th in the
year
2038 we will have run out of bits in
most computers right now to keep track
of time it turns out years ago humans
decided to use a 32-bit integer to keep
track of how many seconds had elapsed
over time they chose a somewhat
arbitrary date in the past January 1st
1970 and they just started counting
seconds from there on out and so if a
computer stores some number of seconds
that tells the computer how many seconds
have passed since that particular date
January 1st 1970 unfortunately using a
32-bit integer as we've seen you can
only count so high at which point you
overflow the size of that variable and
so potentially if we don't get ahead of
this as humans as a society as computer
scientist on the date January 19th
2038 that bit might flip over there by
overflowing the size of those integers
bringing us back computationally to
December 13th
1901 so this is to say now with all of
this computational ability and code
comes a responsibility to actually write
correct code next week we'll peel back
some of these layers but for now this
was week one and best of luck on problem
set
[Music]
one
all right this is cs50 and this is this
is week two wherein we're going to take
a look at a lower level at how things
work and indeed among the goals of the
course isn't this bottom up
understanding so that in a couple of
weeks time even a few years time when
you encounter some new technology you'll
be able to think back hopefully on some
of this week's and this courses basic
building blocks and Primitives and
really just deduce how tomorrow's
Technologies work but along the way it's
going to seem it's going to be a little
hard perhaps to see the forest for the
tree so to speak and so the goal at the
end of the day still is going to be
problem solving and so we thought we'd
begin today with a look at some of the
problems we'll talk about or solve this
coming week uh and for that we have some
Brave volunteers who have already come
up if we could turn on some dramatic
lighting and meet today's
volunteers so on my left here we have hi
my name is Alex I'm a first year at the
college and I'm from Chapo North
Carolina Welcome to Alex and to Alex's
right um I'm Sarah I'm from Toronto
Canada and I'm also a first year student
at the college wonderful well welcome to
both Al and Sarah so one of the problems
you'll perhaps solve this week for
problem set two is to analyze the
reading level of a body of text whether
someone reads at a first grade level
second grade level third grade level all
the way up to 12 or 13 or Beyond but
you've perhaps never quite thought about
certainly in terms of code like how you
would analyze some text some book and
figure out what reading level is it at
and yet surely our teachers growing up
kind of knew or had an intuitive sense
of this so let's consider some sample
text for instance Alex what have you
been reading lately um
One Fish Two Fish Red F Fish Blue Fish
wonderful so given that what grade level
would you say Alex is currently reading
at feel free to just shout it
out first first so indeed you'll see
this week if you run your code on Alex's
text it actually turns out he reads
below a first grade reading level but
but why might that be what might your
intuition be for why we've
uh why we've accused Alex of reading at
this level feel free to shout
out yeah so very few syllables short
words short sentences and so there's
some puristic perhaps we can infer from
that short text that that probably means
that it's best for younger children now
Sarah by contrast what have you been
reading Mr and Miss dersley of number
four privet Drive were proud to say that
they were perfectly normal thank you
very much they were the last people
you'd expect to be involved in anything
strange or mysterious ious because they
just didn't hold with much nonsense all
right now irrespective of what grade you
were in when you might have read that
text what grade level does Sarah seem to
be reading
at so eighth grade second grade okay so
hearing a bit of everything so that at
least according to code would actually
be seventh grade and what might the
intuition there be why is that a higher
grade level even though we might
disagree exactly which grade it is comp
yeah so complicated sentences longer
sentences so indeed a lot more more
words were being spoken by Sarah because
there was so much more there on the page
so we'll translate these ideas this
coming week and problem set two if you
tackle this one to code so that you can
ultimately infer things of these
quantitatively but to do so we're going
to have to understand text so let's
first thank our volunteers and then
we'll dive in to that lower
level stress
balls sure you can keep those yeah all
right so besides that let's consider one
another body of text perhaps that you
might see this week which is namely a
little something like this what I have
here on the screen is what we'll start
calling today Cipher text it's the
result of encrypting some piece of
information and encryption or more
generally the Art and Science of
cryptography is all around us it's what
you're using on the web on your phones
with your Banks and anything that tries
to keep data secure is using encryption
but there's going to be different levels
of encryption strong encryption weak
encryption and what you see here on the
screen isn't all that strong but we'll
see later today how we might decrypt
this and actually reveal what the plain
text is that corresponds to that Cipher
text but in order to do so we have to
start taking off some training wheels so
to speak and believe it or not even
though your time with C this past week
for the first time probably might have
been rather in the weeds and much more
complicated seemingly than C it turns
out that along the way we have been
providing and will continue to provide
certain training wheels for instance the
cs50 library is one of them and even
some of the explanations give up topics
for now in these early weeks will be
somewhat simplified abstracted away if
you will but the goal ultimately is for
you to understand each and every one of
those details so that after cs50 you
really can stand on your own and
understand and wrap your mind around any
future Technologies as well so let's
consider first the very first program
with which we began last week which was
this one so hello world and C at the end
of the day it was really the print a
function that was doing the interesting
part of the work but there was a lot of
technical stuff above and below it the
the curly braces the parentheses words
like void and include and then of course
the angled brackets and more but at the
end of the day we needed to convert that
source code in C to machine code the
zeros and ones in binary that the
computer understood and to do that of
course we ran we compiled the code we
ran make and then we were able to
actually run that code there so let me
actually go over here to VSS code and
really quickly recreate that hello.c
pretty much by transcribing the same so
I have here uh include standard
i.h uh int main void and then in here I
had quite simply hello comma world with
my back slend quotes and more now last
time to compile this I indeed ran make
hello followed by enter hopefully you
see no errors and that's a good thing
and if you do do/ hello you see in fact
the results of that program but it turns
out that make is not actually a compiler
as I alluded to last week it's a program
that clearly makes your program but it
itself just automates the process of
using an actual compiler and there's
lots of different compilers out there
and the one that it's actually using
underneath the hood is a little
something called clang for C language
and clang is a pretty popular compiler
nowadays there's another one that's been
around for ages called GCC but these are
just specific names for types of
compilers that different people
different companies different groups
have actually created but if you use in
week one a compiler yourself manually
you have to know you have to understand
a little more about what's going on
because it's even more cryptic than with
just make a loan so in fact let me go
back to my terminal window here let me
go ahead and clear the screen a little
bit and just run really the raw compiler
command so what make is automating for
me let me actually do this manually for
just a moment so if I want to compile uh
hello.c into an executable program I can
run I can do this uh clang space hello
C and then enter and now there's no
output which is a good thing in this
case no errors but notice this if I go
ahead and type LS it turns out there's a
uh a file that's been created suddenly
in my current folder weirdly called
a.out that stands for assembler output
and long story short that's actually the
default name of a program that's created
when you just run C by itself now that's
a pretty uh bad name for a program
because it doesn't describe what it said
does so better would be here to perhaps
do well instead of a.out which yes still
prints hello. world but isn't really a a
clearly named program it'd be nice to
name this hello so what could I do I
could do like we learned last week well
I could rename a.out to Hello by using
linux's MV command so I'm going to move
a. out to become hello but that too
seems kind of tedious now I have three
steps like write my code compile my code
and then rename it before I can even run
it like we can do better than that and
so it turns out that certain commands
like clang support what we're going to
start today calling commandline
arguments a commandline argument unlike
an argument to a function is just an
additional word or key phrase that you
type after a command at your prompt in
your terminal window that just modifies
the behavior of that command it
configures it a little more specifically
so what you're seeing here on the screen
is a summary of a better command with
which to run clang so that now I can
specify the output of this command this-
o so what do I mean by that well let me
go ahead and clear my terminal window
again and more explicitly type clang d o
hello hello. C and then enter nothing
again appears to happen but that's a
good thing when you see no errors and
now the program I just created is indeed
called hello so it achieves really the
same exact effect as make did but what I
don't have to do with make is type and
remember something as long as this
command and this too is a bit of a white
lie it turns out we have preconfigured
vs code in the cloud for you to also use
some other features of clang that would
be even more tedious for you to write
yourselves and so really this is why we
distill this as ultimately just running
make so let me pause here to see first
if there's any questions on what I've
done by taking my very first program in
C and just now compiling it first with
make but then starting over and now
manually compiling it with clang with
what we'll call command line arguments -
o space hello and then the name of the
file
yeah yeah so a.out is a historical name
it refers to assembler output more on
that soon and it's just the default file
name that you get automatically if you
just run the compiler on any file so
that you have just a standard name for
it but it's not a very well-named
program instead of running Microsoft
Word on your Mac or PC it would like be
like double clicking on a.out so instead
with these command line arguments you
can customize the output of clang and
call it hello or anything you want other
questions on what I've done here with
clang itself the
compiler
yeah so- o and you would only know this
from reading the manual taking a class
means output so- o means change clangs
output to be a file called hello instead
of the default which is a.out and this
too is again a detail you would have to
uh look it up on a web page read the
manual hear someone like me tell you
about it and in fact there's even more
than these options but we'll just
scratch the surface here all right so if
we now know this what more is actually
happening underneath the hood well let's
take a a closer look at not just this
version of my code but my slightly more
complicated version last week which
looked a little something like this
wherein I added in some Dynamic input
from the user so I could say not Hello
World to everyone but hello David or
hello to whoever actually runs this
program so in fact let me go ahead and
change my code here in vs code just to
match that same code from last week so
no new code yet I'm just going to in a
moment compile it in a slightly
different way so I did last week string
uh I think answer equals get string
quote unquote what's your name just like
in scratch and then down here instead of
doing world I initially wrote answer but
that didn't go well what did I
ultimately do instead to print out hello
David or hello so and so yeah sorry a
little louder yeah so percent s the
so-called format code that printf just
knows how to deal with and I had to add
one other thing someone else besides
percent F
yeah the name of the variable that I
want to plug into that placeholder
percent s and in this case it's answer
now let me make one refinement only
because now we're in week two and we're
going to start writing more lines of
code even though scratch called the
return value of the ask puzzle piece
answer always and see we have full
control over what our variables are
called and now it's probably good not to
just generically always call my variable
answer if I'm using get string let's
call it what it is so this is now just a
matter of style if you will let me
change the variable to be name just so
that it's a little clear to me to you to
a TF or ta exactly what that variable
represents instead of more generically
answer all right so that said let me go
down to my terminal window and last week
again I ran make to compile this exact
same program now though let me go ahead
and just use clang so clang d o I'll
still call this version hello space
hello.c so exact same command as before
the only thing that's different is I've
added a couple of more lines of code to
get the user's input let me hit enter
and now darn it our first error so
output from clang and make is not a good
thing and here we're seeing something
particularly cryptic uh so something in
function main undefined reference to get
string and then Linker command failed
with exit code one so there's actually a
lot of jargon in there that will tease
apart today but my hint is that clearly
my problem's in Maine although that's
not surprising because there's nothing
else going on here get string is an
issue and the uh issue is that it's an
undefined reference and yet notice I was
pretty good I added the cs50 header file
and I said last week that that's enough
to teach the compiler that functions
exist but the problem is that even
though this does in fact teach clang
that get string exists it is not
sufficient information for clang to go
find on the hard drive of the computer
the zeros and ones that actually
Implement get string itself so in other
words this include line per last week is
a little bit of a hint it's a teaser to
CLA that you're about to see and use
this function somewhere but if you
actually want to use the zeros and ones
that cs50 wrote some time ago and bake
those into your program so your program
actually knows how to get input from the
user well then I'm going to have to go
ahead and run a slightly different
command so let me do this let me clear
my terminal window just to get rid of
that distraction and let me propose now
that we run this command instead almost
the same as before clang - o space hello
then hello. C but with one additional
command line argument at the end and
this is a-h L not a number one so- L
cs50 with no space in between those two
now the L is going to result in all of
those zeros and ones that actually were
written by cs50 being linked into your
code your few lines of code or mine here
but that's the second step that the
compiler requires in order to know how
to actually execute and rather compile
your code and cs50's and cs50 is not the
only one that does this if you use any
third-party library in C that doesn't
come with the language you would do- L
such and such where whoever however
they've named their own library but you
don't have to do it for built-in things
like uh like we've been using thus far
all right so let me go ahead and try
this I'll go back to vs code here and
let me go ahead now and run clang - o
hello then hello. C and now instead of
just hitting enter - L cs50 with no
space between the L and the cs50 enter
now nothing bad happens and now I can
do/ hello what's your name I'll type in
David enter and now we see hello David
now honestly this is where we're really
getting into the weeds and now this is
taking this is really just adding new to
the process of compiling and running
your code and so the reality is even
though this is indeed what is happening
this is why we used last week and we're
going to continue using this week onward
make because it just automates that
whole process for you but it's ideal to
understand what's going wrong because
any of the error messages you saw for
problem set one any of the error
messages you see for the next few weeks
probably aren't coming from make they're
coming from clang underneath the hood
because make is just automating the
process but with make you literally just
write make and then the name of the
program you don't have to worry about
any of those command line arguments
questions then on compiling with- l cs50
or anything else
yeah sorry what is the benefit
of what is the benefit of using clang
manually none really in fact all main is
doing is just sa make is doing is saving
us some keystrokes um if you prefer
though and you just like to be more in
control you can totally run clang
manually if you remember the various
command line arguments yeah
exp exactly why did I have to explain
that is provide a hint to cs50 with the
cs50.h henter file but I didn't have to
do that with standard i.h just because
standard i.h comes with C just like a
few other libraries come with C that
we'll start seeing today um cs50 though
is not built into C everywhere and so
you do have to explicitly add that one
there
yeah a command line argument is a a word
or phrase that you type at the command
line AKA your terminal in order to
influence the behavior of a
program for whatever you're doing yeah
it changes the defaults right in our
guey World graphical user interface you
and I would probably click some boxes we
would select some menu options to
configure a program to behave in the
same way at a command line interface you
have to just say everything all at once
and that's why we have command line
arguments
yeah no make is not just for cs50 it's
used globally in any project really
nowadays using C C++ even other
languages as well in fact most every
command you see in this class unless it
has 5 zero at the end of it is globally
used only those suffix with 50 are
indeed course specific and even those
will gradually take training wheels off
of so that you know exactly what those
commands are doing as well all right so
what is it that we've just done
everything we've just done of course I
keep calling compiling but let's just go
down one Rabbit Hole so that you
understand that when you compile code
there's actually a whole bunch of steps
happening and this is going to enable uh
a lot of features like companies can
write code and then convert it to run it
on Macs and PCs alike or phones or the
like so it's not just a matter of
converting source code to machine code
there's actually four steps involved in
what you and I as of last week know as
compiling and these aren't terms that
you'll have to keep in mind constantly
because again we're going to abstract a
lot of this away but just so we've gone
down the rabbit hole once let's consider
each of these four steps that have been
happening for you for a week
automatically uh the first of which is
called pre-processing so what is this
mean well let's consider that same
program as before notice that a two of
the lines of code start with a hash mark
that is a special symbol in C and it's a
so-called pre-processor directive you
don't need to memorize terms like that
but it just means that it's a little
different from every other line and
anything with a hash symbol here should
be pre-processed that is analyzed
initially before anything else happens
so let's consider these two lines up top
what exactly is happening well it turns
out with these two lines you have two
header files of course cs50.h and
standard. i.h where are those files
because they've never been in VSS code
for you seemingly if you type LS if you
open up the file explorer in the GUI you
have never seen probably cs50.h or
standard i.h they just work but that's
because there's a folder somewhere on
the uh the hard drive that you're using
on your Mac or PC or somewhere in the
cloud as in our case and inside of this
folder traditionally called sluser SL
include and user is deliberately
misspelled it's just slightly more
succinct although it's a little weird
why we drop that one letter but user SL
include is just a folder on the server
that contains cs50.h standard i.h and a
bunch of other things as well so in fact
if you type in uh VSS code in your
terminal window uh when you're using
Code spaces in the cloud and type LS
space SL user include you can can see
all of the files in that folder but
we've pre-installed all of that stuff
for you so let's consider what's
actually in those files here where if I
highlight these two lines up top that
start with hash include well I kind of
hinted last week that what's in that
first file is a hint as to what
functions cs50 wrote for you so you can
kind of think of these include lines as
being temporary placeholders for what's
going to become like a global find and
replace that is the first thing clang is
going to do it's pre-process this file
it's going to look for any line that
starts with hash include and if it sees
that it's going to essentially go into
that file like cs50.h and then just copy
and paste the contents of that file
magically there for you you don't see it
visually on the screen but it's
happening behind the scenes and so
really what's happening with this first
line is that somewhere in
cs50.h is the Declaration of get string
like we talked last week and it probably
looks a little something like this and
we didn't spend much time on this yet
this past week but we will in time more
notice that this is how the a function
is declared that is it is decreed to
exist the name of the function of course
is get string inside of the parenthesis
are its arguments in this case there's
one argument to get string I claim today
but you've known this implicitly and
it's a prompt it's the prompt that the
human sees when you use get string what
is that prompt well it's a string of
text like quote unquote what's your name
or anything else that I asked last week
mean meanwhile get string as we know
from last week has a return value it
returns something to you and that too is
a string so again this is also called a
functions prototype it's the thing
toward the end of last week that I just
copied and pasted from the bottom of my
file to the top just so that it was like
this teaser for clang as to what would
exist later so you can think then of
these include lines as just kind of uh
combining all of those function
declarations in some separate file
called cs50.h so that you yourself don't
have to type them every time you use the
library or worse so that you yourself
don't have to copy and paste those lines
this is what clang is doing for you in
its first step of pre-processing second
and last in this example what happens
when clang pre-processes this second
include line well the only other
function we care about in this story is
printf of course which comes with C so
essentially you can think of printf's
prototype or Declaration as just being
this print f is the name of the function
it takes a string that you want to
format like hello comma world or hello
comma percent s and then with dot dot
dot this actually has technical meaning
it means of course that you can plug in
zero variables one variable two or 10 so
dot dot dot means some number of
variables now we haven't talked about
this yet and we won't really in general
print F actually returns a value a
number that is an integer but more on
that perhaps another time it's generally
not something the programmer tends to
look at but that's all we mean by
pre-processing so that the the end of
this process even though there's more
lines of code in cs50.h and standard i.h
what's really just happening is that
clang in pre-processing the file copies
and pastes the contents of those files
into your code so that now your code
knows about everything get string printf
and anything else any questions then on
that first step
pre-processing
yes
good question when you include a file
does it only include what you need or
Does it include everything think of it
as including everything so if it's a big
file that's a lot of code at the very
top and that's why if you think back to
all of the zeros and ones I showed a
little bit ago as well as last week
there's a lot of zeros and ones that end
up on the screen as a result of just
writing hello world a lot of those zeros
and ones are perhaps coming from code
that you didn't actually necessarily
need but some of it is perhaps there but
there are ways to optimize that as well
all right so step two of compiling is
confusingly called compiling it's just
this is the term that most everyone uses
to describe the whole process instead of
just this one step but once a program
has been pre-processed uh behind the
scenes by the compiler for you it looks
now a little something like this and
I've put dot dot dots just to imply that
yes to your question there's more stuff
above it there's more stuff below it
it's just not interesting right now for
us so now we have just C code there's no
more pre-processor directives at this
point all of the hash symbols and those
lines of code have been pre-processed
and convert it to something else and so
now and this is where things get a
little spooky looking uh here now is
what happens when clang or any compiler
literally compiles code like this it
converts it from this in C to this in
assembly code so this is among the
scarier languages I myself don't really
have fond memories this is not language
that many people program in if you take
a subsequent class in computer science
in systems uh a higher level class you
might actually learn this or some
variant there of but there's at least a
few people out there that need to know
this stuff because this is closer to
what the computers themselves nowadays
understand like the Intel CPUs or the
AMD CPUs the brains of today's computers
and phones understand stuff that looks
more like this and less like C now it's
completely uh esoteric but let me just
highlight a few phrases there's some
stuff that's a little familiar there is
mention of Maine at the top there in
yellow there is mention of get string
toward the bottom there is mention of
prf down below so this is just another
programming language called Assembly
Language that decades ago humans myself
included in school did write code in and
absolutely some people still write this
code especially since you can write very
very efficient code but it's a lot more
uh Arcane it's a lot more uh lot less
user friendly so you'll see in Yello now
the these are the so-called instructions
that a computer's brain or CPU
understands pushing values around moving
them subtracting values uh calling
functions and move move move so really
the low-level operations that computers
understand tend to be arithmetic
operations subtraction addition and the
like moving things in and out of memory
it's just a lot more tedious for folks
like us to write code like this this is
why you and I tend to write stuff like
this and ideally still people like you
and I tend to drag and drop puzzle
pieces that sort of abstract all of that
away further but for now this is again
called Assembly Language it is what
happens when the compiler literally
compiles your code but of course this
still not zeros and ones so we got two
steps to go so when a compiler proceeds
to step three this is where things get
converted to machine code and when a
compiler assembles your code for you it
converts what we just saw on the screen
here to actual zeros and ones the
so-called machine code that your phone
or your computer understands but it's
worth noting that these are not
necessarily all of the zeros and ones of
your program yes they re uh they are the
zeros and ones that correspond to your
hello program or printf and get string
and the like but notice that here we
need one final step in those zeros and
ones are only your lines of code but
what about cs50's lines of code that we
wrote to Implement get string what about
the lines of code that humans wrote
decades ago to implement printf those
are somewhere on this hard drive like on
my Mac my PC or somewhere in the cloud
but we need to combine all of those
zeros and ones together and Link My code
with cs50's code with uh standard io's
code all together and so what happens in
the last step ultimately is that if we
have my code here in yellow and then the
code that cs50 wrote and the code that
the authors of C itself wrote what
really is happening is that somewhere we
have not only hello.c which obviously I
wrote and wrote with us live here
there's also let's assume somewhere on
the computer a cs50.c file that
coincidentally I and cs50 staff wrote
years ago and also somewhere on the
computer there's another file Let Me
oversimplify by just calling it standard
io. C in practice it's probably
specifically called print F.C but
there's somewhere these two other files
and so this last step called linking
takes my zeros and ones from the code I
just wrote namely this code on the
screen here it then grabs the zeros and
ones that cs50 wrote and it grabs the
zeros and ones that the authors of C
wrote In order to implement the standard
IO library and lastly voila links them
all together and this is the same blob
of zeros and ones that we saw earlier
it's just now the result of
pre-processing your code compiling your
code assembling your code linking your
code and my God it's at this point like
if there were any fun in programming for
you yet we've just taken it all away we
just call this whole process compiling
why because now that we know those steps
exist and smart people solve that
problem for us you and I can kind of
operate at this level of abstraction and
just assume that compiling converts
source code to machine code questions
though on any of these
intermediate steps
yeah
a good question so where are all of
these zeros in one store because you and
I we've been using a browser at code.
cs50. of course is this web-based user
interface but again recall from last
week even though you're using a web
browser to access VSS code that
web-based version of vs code is
connected to an actual server somewhere
in the cloud and on that server you have
your own account and your own file and
really your own hard drive virtually in
the cloud think of it a little like
Dropbox or box or Google drive or one
drive or something like that so you have
a hard drive somewhere out there that
we've provisioned for you and it's on
that hard drive that we have uh your
code that you just wrote or I just wrote
cs50.c standard I.C and all of the other
code that implements the math functions
and everything else that c
supports good question
yeah
c
good question that uh hash includes
cs50.h line at the top of my code if I
just replace that with the contents of
cs50.c would that work short answer yes
that would work you could copy all of
the code there however there's some
order of operations that might come into
play and so it's probably not quite as
simple as copy paste but conceptually
yes that's what what's happening now
with that said in
cs50.h are only the prototypes of the
functions the hints as to how the
functions look what their return type is
what their name is and what their
arguments are it's in the C file that
actual code tends to be written and this
is a little confusing now because you
and I have only written code in C files
but in the next few weeks you'll
actually start writing some of your own
files as well just like cs50 just like
standard iio but in essence that line of
code just makes it easier to use and
reuse code that's already been written
and that's the whole point of a
library I say that little
louder yes does linking happen when you
compile your code yes when you run make
as we have been doing the past week now
all four of these steps are happening
pre-processing converts the hash include
lines to something else compiling
technically converts it to assembly code
which the Mac the PC the server more
closely understands assembly converts
that language to Binary machine code
that this computer actually understands
and then linking combines everything
together and in fact if you think back a
few minutes ago to when I did this- L
cs50 the reason I had to add that and
the reason my code did not compile at
first was because I forgot to tell clang
to link in cs50's zeros and ones per
that last step I don't need to do- L
standard IO because it comes with c so
that would just be tedious for everyone
in the world but cs50 does not come with
C so we link that in and to be clear too
we won't always use cs50's Library
that'll be yet another pair of training
wheels we take off in the coming weeks
but for now it makes a few things
simpler
yeah short answer yes so what do the
zeros and ones the machine code
translate to yes there is a one toone
relationship between the machine code
and the assembly code assembly code it's
not really English but at least it's
symbols I recognize it's not zeros and
ones machine code of course is just
zeros and ones so back in the day before
c existed people were programming only
in assembly code before assembly code
existed people were coding in zeros and
ones and you can imagine just how
painful that was and so each of these
languages makes life for us sort of
easier and easier in a few weeks we'll
transition to python which will in turn
make C even uh simpler or coding in
general simpler to do to all right so
with that said what now can we uh what
could go wrong with this well it turns
out that besides compiling technically
speaking there's decompiling and we've
not done this and we won't do this but
it's worth considering for just a moment
uh if you were to not compile your code
but decompile it as the word suggests
this just means reversing the process
converting it ideally from machine code
zeros and ones maybe back to C now this
would be cool perhaps if all you have is
a program you can convert it and see the
actual source code what might a downside
be if if anyone on the Internet is able
to decompile code on their machine
yeah okay so it's easier to find bugs in
the code that oh to exploit so it might
be easier to uh hack into the software
by finding mistakes you and I made
because literally they're staring at you
in code worries the zeros and ones make
it way less obvious other downsides of
what I call decompiling
yeah
yeah yeah if your code your work is your
intellectual property copyrighted or
otherwise you know that's kind of
obnoxious that someone can just like run
a command and boom they can see the
original code that you wrote now it
turns out it's not quite as simple as
that and so even though yes you could
take a program like hello or even
Microsoft Word and convert it from zeros
and ones back to some form of source
code be it in C or Java or python or
something else whatever it was
originally written in odds are it's
going to be an utter mess to look look
at why because things like variable
names are not retained in the zeros and
ones typically function names might not
be retained in the zeros and ones the
code is the logic is but the computer
doesn't care what pretty variables you
chose and how nicely named your uh
functions were it just needs to know
them as Z in ones moreover if you think
about last week we introduced things
like loops and c and besides four Loops
there's what other kind of loop for
instance so a while loop and even though
they look different and you have to
write different code they achieve
exactly the same functionality which is
to say when you compile a for Loop or
you compile a while loop if they
logically do the same thing they might
end up looking identical as zeros and
ones and so therefore it's not
necessarily predictable that you'll get
back the original code why cuz because
the zeros and ones might not know so to
speak whether it was a for Loop or a
while loop so maybe decompiling will
show you one or the other and honestly
decompiling while possible and it's one
way of reverse engineering someone's
product odds are if you're good enough
to start reading code that's been
decompiled and reading through the
messiness of it odds are you have the
talent probably to just write that same
program from scratch yourself now that's
an overstatement perhaps but it's not
quite as easy or threatening um as you
might first think so in general once
codee is piled it's pretty challenging
timec consuming costly to reverse
engineer it um much like it would be in
the real world right like all of us have
some kind of phone probably nowadays in
our pocket there's nothing stopping you
from opening it up somehow poking around
recreating what's there that's a huge
amount of effort most likely and at that
point maybe you should just invent the
phone instead of trying to reverse
engineer it so same kind of idea in the
physical world any questions then on
compiling or even decompiling in these
forms
all right so odds are at this point not
only I but you have made mistakes and
you've written buggy code a bug in a
code is just a mistake a logical error
or otherwise where the code just does
not behave correctly as you intend and
up until now odds are your debugging
techniques have been to maybe look back
at what I did in class maybe ask a
question online or in person but
ultimately it'd be nice if you had some
tools of your own with which to debug
code and this honestly is a lifelong
skill you're going to emerge from cs50
and even 20 years from now you're not
going to be writing if you're writing
code at all correct code all of the time
like all of us on the staff continue to
write bugs hopefully they get a little
more sophisticated and not sort of like
oops I missed a semicolon but even those
kinds of mistakes we make too but
there's tools out there and techniques
that can make your life easier when it
comes to solving those problems now the
term bug has actually been around for
decades but a fun story to tell is that
the first documented actual bug was
actually somehow connected to Harvard in
fact this is the log book relating to
the Harvard Mark 2 computer from 1947
whereby if you read the notes here and
if I zoom in this was an actual moth
discovered inside of this big Mainframe
computer that was causing some kind of
problems and the engineers at the time
actually thought it was funny that wow
physical bug actually explains the issue
and it's been forever uh taped to the
sheet of paper which I believe now is on
display in the Smithsonian uh with that
said this is just represented two of a
logical bug and that story is actually
uh that story was often retold by a
famous mathematician then computer
scientist really uh Dr Grace Hopper who
actually worked not only on the Harvard
Mark 2 computer but its predecessor the
Harvard Mark 1 and if you ever spent
time yet in the engineering building
across the river here you can actually
see much of this computer which is along
the wall when you first walk into the
science and engineering complex and
indeed as you've probably heard growing
up this is a Mainframe computer like
this is what Macs and PCs so to speak
looked like back in the day with very
physical things that essentially
implemented the zeros and ones that you
and I take for granted now being
miniaturized in our laptops and phones
so there's a piece of history there if
you visit campus that side of Campus
sometime do take a look but let's
consider then how we solve not of course
physical bugs but logical bugs and let's
consider something like this from last
week whereby we were trying very simply
to print like this uh column of three
bricks using hashtags of sorts so let me
go over here in just a moment to VSS
code and I'm going to go ahead and open
a program I wrote in advance and I'm
bringing it to class because there's a
bug in it and I'd like to figure out how
to solve this bug so let me open up uh
buggy z.c which is version zero of my
code and let's just take a quick peek at
what's here it's pretty short it
includes only standard i.h it uses
printf it uses a for Loop and the goal
quite simply is to print out that column
of three bricks now it's short enough
that some of you if you're getting comfy
already with see you might already see
The Logical bug it's not a syntax error
like it will compile and run but there's
a bug there and suppose that I'm very
new to see I'm very uncomfortable with C
it's 2 a.m. and I just can't see the bug
what are my recourses here for actually
finding a mistake like this well first
let's look at the symptom let me go down
to my terminal window I'm going to use
make buggy zero because again the file
is called buggy zero. C I'm not going to
use clang in fact I'm never really going
to use clang manually here and out I'm
just going to use make because it makes
our lives easier it does compile no
errors so it's not syntax it's not
something silly like a missing semicolon
but when I runbuggy Z I of course see 1
2 3 4 and this of course does not match
the zero the one two three bricks that I
actually intended for that column and
yet I'm starting counting at zero as I
usually do I've got three I'm going up
to three so where is my logical error if
it hasn't obviously jumped out at you
already well how can I solve this well
first and foremost perhaps the best
technique for solving bugs at least
early on is just use printf like thus
far we've used printf to say hello and
other things on the screen but print def
is just a function for printing anything
and there's no reason you can't
temporarily use print def to like print
out the contents of variables what's
going on inside of your program just to
figure out where your mistake is and
then you can delete that line of code
later it doesn't have to stay there
forever so let me do this instead of
just printing out in vs code the hash
symbol let me do a little safety check
here and print out the value of I so let
me go ahead and say something like I is
now I want to say I is this but of
course this is not how I print out the
value of I if I want to print out the
value of I what should I put
here so percent I for integer instead of
percent s for string so they're still
placeholders but we use percent s for
integers and now if I want to print out
I I just need the comma as the second
argument and then I all right let me go
ahead and back to vs uh to my terminal
window let me recompile the program
because I've changed it that still works
fine do/ bugy Z and now let me increase
the size of my terminal window here you
just see some diagnostic information if
you will like this is not the goal this
is not what you should be submitting for
this homework problem we're at one uh
but it is helping us diagnostically know
that okay when I is zero here's a hash
when I is one here's a hash when I is
two here's a hash when I is three here's
a hash well wait a minute that's one two
three four so clearly I'm printing it
one too many times so let me look back
at the code here by shrinking my
terminal window and let me just ask the
group where is in fact the mistake or
what equivalently would be the solution
yeah in the
middle yeah instead of less than or
equal to use just less than so you got
to kind of pick a lane here like if
you're going to start counting from zero
you generally use less than and go up to
but not through the value or if you
prefer like in the human world counting
from one on up you can use great less
than or equal to but you have to be
consistent and in general as a
programmer just always start counting
from zero if you're doing something
canonical like this but the solution is
indeed just to change this by changing
the greater less than or equal to to
less than if I re compile this program
with make buggy zero and then do buggy
zero again and let me increase the size
of my terminal window now you see okay
almost the same output but indeed I
starts at zero goes up two but not
through three all right so printf in
short should be can be your first uh
diagnostic tool instead of just staring
at the screen or raising your hand I
mean use printf to see literally what's
going on inside of your program by just
printing out things of interest and then
once you've solved the problem you can
go back into your code AS I'll do here
by shrinking my terminal window I'll
delete the print F line and now I'm
ready to share this program with the
world or submit it as homework or the
like it's just meant there to be
temporary any questions on printf as a
debugging
tool no all right well that only gets us
so far and honestly as your programs
grow and grow and grow it's going to
actually get really annoying to start
going in and adding printfs then
removing them and figuring out if you've
got multiple printfs well which one
printed what like it just gets messy
eventually to rely on printf alone so
being a computer scientist computer
scientists have written software to make
it easier to debug code that software is
what we would generally call a debugger
which would be the second tool of the
trade that you can use to actually solve
problems in your code now in the world
of VSS code there's actually a debugger
built in so the graphical user interface
you're about to see in VSS code isn't
specific to cs50 it actually comes with
vs code and it supports C and C++ and
Java and Python and lots of other
languages too but it's admittedly a
little complicated to just start using
the debugger you have to like create a
configuration file and do like some
annoying steps that just get in the way
of solving real problems so we have
automated the process for you of just
starting the debugger and thereafter
it's sort of Industry standard how you
use it but we save you the headache of
having to create those configuration
files so suppose I want to do this
suppose I want to try to debug this
program step by step using special
software well how can I do that well let
me propose that if I revert this back to
the original version where I was less
than or equal to three I'm pretty sure
that I was printing to hashes so I'm
going to do this and you might have done
this accidentally or never at all but
notice if you hover over the gutter so
to speak in vs code the part of it all
the way to the left of the editor you
see this sort of grayed out uh Red Dot
if you click there it becomes a brighter
Red Dot and this represents what we're
going to call a break point and this is
just a visual indicator that you've put
like a stop sign equivalent there and
you're telling the debugger in a moment
stop running my code there why because I
prefer to step through my code at sort
of a human speed and not as computer
speed where it runs all at once so I've
set my breakpoint which is step one and
then step two is quite simply this
instead of running the program itself
run a command called debug 50 and then
do/ bugy Z and now this will start your
program but inside of the debugger which
is a special program that smart people
wrote that will Empower you to now step
through your code line by line at again
at your own Comfort Pace I'm going to
hit enter some stuff's going to happen
on the screen whoops uh notice this is a
common mistake that I made accidentally
here looks like I've changed my code I
did because I went in and changed the
less than or equal to sign so let me go
ahead and rerun make buggy zero enter
good now let me rerun debug 50 enter and
now some stuff just happened on the
screen and it takes a moment to get
started but once it's started you'll see
this you'll still see your code but
you'll see this yellow highlight which
you've probably not seen before and
notice that it's specifically
highlighted in the same line that I set
a breakpoint on why that just means the
program has EXE the debugger has
executed all of these lines except for
line seven it has broken at not in a bad
way but it has paused execution on line
seven so it hasn't yet printed any
hashes and you can see that no hashes in
the terminal window yet it's paused
execution but what's interesting with
the debugger is the stuff over here on
the left hand side in the debugger here
you'll see under variables all of your
so-called local variables and we haven't
really made a distinction between local
and something called Global but for now
local variables just means all of the
variables that exist in your function so
I currently has a value of zero okay and
that makes sense so now how do I step
through my code and see what it's doing
well at the top of the screen here
you'll see some playback icons kind of
like a video player but they have
special meaning this first one will just
play the rest of your program all the
way to the end so you only click that if
you sort of solved a problem and you
just want to run run it to completion
like before but the next three or next
two really are really the juiciest the
second one here if you hover over it
eventually you'll see that it's called
step over step over means that the
debugger will run this currently
highlighted line of code but it's not
going to dive into it so if it's a
function like print F it's not going to
start stepping through print F line by
line why because I can pretty much
assume print F written decades ago is
correct problems probably with me but
this next line if I did really want to
step in into the printf code to figure
out how it works or find some problem in
it all these years later you can step
into printf and then the screen would
change and you'd see each of the lines
for print F line by line at least if you
have the source code for print F
installed all right I'm going to use the
first one step over and watch as the
yellow highlight moves and watch as in
the terminal window there's a hash
symbol here we go there's one hash now
notice line five is highlighted that
means it has paused on line five line
five has not yet been exec executed so
what does that mean the value of I per
the top left hand corner is still zero
but as soon as I click step over again
Watch What Happens at the top left where
I is a variable on the
screen now I and it flashed briefly has
a value of one and now if I step over
again watch the terminal window there's
my second hash now let me click step
over on the for Loop watch the variable
at top left now one goes to two now let
me click it again third hash and Here's
Where The Logical error is perhaps
revealed let me go ahead and step over
the loop now I is three wait a minute
I'm still going to print out a hash
there it is there's the fourth hash and
at this point hopefully the light bulb
proverbially has gone off I realize oh I
screwed up I can either stop the program
Al together with the red square or I can
just let it run all the way to the end
which just terminates everything at this
point I just want to get back into my
code and start fixing things and you can
close for instance as I will here the
file explorer just to hide the panel
that open so that's debug 50 but it's
not a cs50 thing that just starts the
debugger for you which is something
you'd find in most any programming
environment nowadays questions on
debugging questions
yeah good question where does it tell
you where it went wrong so sadly it does
not tell you any of that the onus is
still on you the human to use this tool
productively to walk through your code
at a a saner pace but your brain is is
the one that still needs to solve it and
I don't doubt down the line with
artificial intelligence and more
programs like this will get all the more
helpful and start answering questions
like that for us and there are other
tools we'll introduce you this semester
that are even more powerful than this
but for now it's just a tool really to
slow things down and not have to change
your code the fact that I had that panel
on the left that just showed me eyes
changing value is just an alternative to
print F and I can step through it a
little more slowly other questions on
debugging now let me show you one final
example with this debugger here and this
one too I wrote in advance let me close
buggy z.c and let me open up buggy1.c my
second version thereof let me close my
terminal window for a second and give
you a quick tour of this program which
similarly has a mistake now at the top
of this program some familiar includes
cs50.h and standard i.h this is not
something we've seen before it's
specific to this example a function
called get Negative int takes no
arguments and it returns an integer what
does it do it literally gets a negative
integer ideally from the user fun fact
though it doesn't correctly that's the
bug get Negative int is broken at the
moment so what does Maine do well main
just calls this function passing in
nothing in parenthesis no inputs and it
stores the return value in I and then it
just prints out I on the screen so
honestly just by eyeballing this you
know I feel comfortable enough with
programming and see I think main is
correct let me just stipulate main is
correct but there is going to be a bug
down here now what's the bug down here
here well let me look at get Negative in
implementation notice this first line 12
is identical to the Prototype up here
the Prototype is sort of stupidly
required up here because C reads things
top to bottom left to right the compiler
technically does so if you reference get
Negative in here but you don't implement
it until down here and you haven't told
C in advance that it will exist again
you get the error we saw last week all
right so how does get Negative int work
we declare a variable called n
we've got a do while loop that does what
it uses get int which comes with the
cs50 library per last week it prompts
the user for negative integer quote
unquote and stores the value in n i then
do all of this while n is less than zero
right remember we used a do while loop
last week to make sure the human
cooperates and doesn't give us the wrong
type of value be it positive or negative
or something else and then we return n
and there's some subtleties anyone
recall or have an intuition for why I've
declared clared in on line 14 instead of
on line 17 this is a c specific
thing exactly there's this notion of
scope in see and we'll continue to see
this over time whereby a variable only
exists inside of the most recent curly
braces that you've opened so if I've
declared and here on line 14 I can use
it anywhere between lines 13 and 21
because those are the nearest curly
Braes if by contrast as you note if I
instead said this int n equals get int
and so forth and didn't have the current
line 14 well n would exist inside of
these curly braces but not here which is
too late and definitely not here so you
just have to declare it first and then
use and reuse it as such now let me just
show you how I can debug this but let me
show you the symptoms first let me open
my terminal window let me run make buggy
one compiles okay so it's not something
silly like a semicolon dots SL buggy one
and I'm asked for a negative integer all
right let me give it negative one
enter well the main function supposed to
print out what I typed but it clearly
didn't it's prompting me again all right
so maybe it'll like -2 no maybe
-3 50 okay so it's definitely broken
right it kind of seems logically to be
doing the opposite now you can perhaps
see why this is happening already these
are deliberately simple programs by uh
for demonstration sake but let's do this
let me go ahead and set a break point in
main even though I'm pretty sure main is
correct but it just helps me start my
thought process start with Main and then
take it from there let me run now uh
debug
50 bugy one enter and let's see with
that breakpoint now the the goey is
going to reconfigure itself it's going
to pause on line eight because that's
the first interesting line inside of
Maine so I could have just put the
breakpoint on line eight too it's smart
enough to know that if I set it on six
eh you really mean line eight because
that's the first actual line of code and
watch when now what happens if I step
over this line notice that I which at
the moment seems to have a default value
of zero more on that another time but if
I click step over like before I'm
prompted for a negative integer let me
type negative 1 enter and now
notice there's no additional yellow
highlight why where am I currently stuck
logically yeah just logically I must be
in that D while Loop and even if you
don't understand it like that's the only
explanation if you keep getting prompted
surely there's a loop going on there's
only one Loop in my code so there's
probably a problem there so okay I can't
just set a breakpoint in Main and then
wait for this to work so let me just uh
let me stop this with the red square and
let me think all right instead of I can
still set my break point in main but let
me rerun the debugger instead and this
time not step over that line of code let
me step into that line of code so Watch
What Happens now instead of clicking the
second icon here let me click the third
whose name is indeed step into and watch
as the yellow highlight does not move to
line n it dives into line8 the function
on line eight thereby bringing me whoosh
down to line 17 it's kind of going down
into that next function now it didn't
bother pausing on line 12 or 13 or 14
because there's nothing intellectually
interesting there happening yet the
juicy part really starts it would seem
in line 17 so now notice n is my
variable at the top left if I click I
don't want to click step into now
though what what would go wrong if I
click on step into or what would it do
that I don't think I want to
do
yeah yeah it would step into get int but
I'd like to think that the staff's
version of get in is correct and that's
not our problem today so I want to step
over it and watch now at top left that
nothing happens yet to the value of n
until I go to the terminal window now
and type in something like Nega 1 now
notice it jumps to line 19 which is the
next interesting line top left n indeed
is1 and here's where I can now pause as
a human and think all right so while n
is less than zero all right n per the
top left corner is negative 1 so all
right while negative 1 is less than zero
well obviously that's true
mathematically so what's going to happen
it's a do while loop so when I click on
step over again it's going to go to this
line cuz it's at the end of the inside
of that Loop and now here it's looping
through again and again all right let me
do this once more I'm going to step over
all right I'm going to type in -2 and
it's the exact same thing now is my
chance on the yellow line okay wait a
minute -2 is obviously less than zero
let me try this one more time click it
once here and now all right let me give
it 50 and now okay while 50 is less than
zero that's not true so the loop is over
because it's not going to do it while 50
is less than zero that's not true so now
watch when I click step over once more
it then finishes the loop even though
there's nothing more to do it's now
about to return n it jumps back up to
main where I left off on line nine it
now prints in my terminal window the
number 50 and hopefully at this point to
your question earlier my human brain has
realized oh I'm an idiot like I flipped
my my sign there so I probably let me
stop this I probably want to do
something like this if the goal is to
get a negative integer I probably want
to say well n is for instance greater
than or equal to zero would work so
while n is greater than or equal to zero
keep doing this and that's the logic I
wanted to express so the debugger just
saves me from staring at the screen
raising a hand sort of asking someone
else at least in this case it allows me
to go through it at a healthier Pace
questions now on debug 50 which should
be your new friend even if it's not your
first instinct after
printf any questions on debug 50 no all
right all right well there's one last
Technique we can equip you with here um
and that is in addition to printf and a
debugger no joke um a rubber duck is
actually a reasonably recommended uh
solution to finding bugs in your code to
your question earlier the duck two is
not going to solve the problem for you
but if you've wondered why this little
guy has been here for so long um there's
this technique has its own Wikipedia
article of called rubber duck debugging
the idea of which is that if you're home
in your dorm room wrestling with some
bug in your code printf didn't quite
reveal the source to you debugger isn't
really helping honestly maybe it would
help to just sound out what problem
you're having similar to going to office
hours talking to a a TA or a professor
just walking through your problems
because in sort of talking to the duck
about you know the fact that you're
doing this while uh n is less than zero
and then if it is I wait a minute I'm an
idiot not just for talking to the rubber
duck you realize hopefully in expressing
yourself literally verbally you probably
will hear with non-zero probability like
some illogic in your statement and just
by sounding things out you'll realize
like oh that's my problem and so frankly
if you have roommates you can also use a
roommate for this but the rubber duck is
just sort of a go-to when your roommates
have no interest in your you know C
problem set talking something through
that um as follow as such and this is an
invaluable technique I admittedly tend
not to do it so much with a rubber duck
but ideally with colleagues human
colleagues but just talking through
things often will help you just realize
oh I said something logical now I can go
back to the code so don't solve problems
by staring at your screen endlessly for
minutes for hours at that point it's
time for a break time to walk away time
to talk to the duck if you've already
exhausted some of those other tools um
as an aside on your way out today at the
end of class we have H clearly plenty of
rubber ducks uh for you um and uh it's
become a thing over the years at least
among some uh to bring the duck with
them when they travel and send us photos
here for instance is uh cs50's rubber
duck debugger AKA ddb for duck debugger
which is a pun on a geekier program
called GDB the ganu debugger which is an
actual piece of software for debugging
this is cs50's debugger uh in the hills
of Puerto Rico uh also here on the sea
uh he made its way to San Francisco here
uh also down by Fisherman's dwarf by the
sea lions if familiar uh here at
Stanford where there's a William Gates
computer science building for computer
science uh down the road in SF at Google
uh and this is the Tre fountain in Rome
and lastly uh the Coliseum so we'll be
curious to see in the coming years where
your duck two travels so that then was
quite a bit why don't we go ahead here
and take a short five minute break no
snacks yet you're welcome to get up or
sit down we'll return in about five all
right so we are back and if the goal
ultimately today is to have a better
understanding of things like strings so
that we can solve problems with text
let's consider some simpler types of
data first how we might represent those
and then see if that doesn't lead us to
a discovery as to like how strings in
just today's modern software is using
things like that so when we talked on
week zero about representation of data
we had different ways of doing it in
terms of binary and decimal and uh unary
even when we started talking about the
same last week in code we started
talking about uh data types instead and
these data types were a way of telling
the computer like do you want an integer
do you want a character do you want a
floating point value like a real number
or even a string as we've seen but it
turns out that computers of course only
have finite amounts of resources your
computer only has a fixed amount of
memory or RAM and that actually has very
real world implications so for instance
here are some of the data types we've
seen thus far and it turns out that each
of these in C has a specific number of
bits allocated to it now admittedly this
can vary by System it's not so much the
case nowaday days but for many years for
decades computers were getting better
and better the earliest computers might
have used fewer bits for some of these
data types more modern computers might
use more bits so the numbers you're
about to see are pretty much where we
are present day so when it comes to
these data types A bu which is true or
false somewhat curiously uses a whole
bite even though that's way Overkill
because for a bull true or false you of
course only need one bit but it turns
out even though it's wasteful to use
eight bits or one bite just to represent
true or false it's just easier for
computers so a bull tends to be one bite
an INT which we've been using a lot uses
four bytes typically or 32 bits and if I
do some quick math from week zero with
32 bits you have four billion possible
values roughly but if you want to
represent positive and negative that
means you can represent roughly -2
billion all the way up to positive2
billion so that's the range typically
within if that's to few numbers for you
turns out there's things called Longs
and longs use 64 bits which allow you to
have like a quintilian number of
possibilities which is a lot certainly a
lot more than 4 billion so sometimes you
might use a long but even that's finite
and so uh as we discussed at the end of
last week bad things can happen if you
make certain assumptions as the data
because of things like Inger overflow or
the like where things wrap around then
there's a float which is a real number
something with a decimal point by
convention it's four bytes or 32 bits
which gives you in short only a specific
amount of precision it doesn't
necessarily dictate how many numbers to
the left or to the right in the
aggregate ultimately you have though uh
three uh 4 billion possible permutations
still if you need more Precision for
scientific for medical for financial
applications you might use eight bytes
AKA a double which just gives you more
digits of precision they eventually get
imprecise per the example we looked at
last week but it at least gets you
further down the line as an aside in
really really important applications in
finance and medicine and Military
operations and the like where you really
can't have rounding errors long story
short humans have developed libraries in
C and other languages that use more even
than 8 bytes so there are solutions to
these problems but they're always finite
you have to pick uh an upper bound then
there's Char which we saw briefly last
week when I asked the user for y or n
for yes or no and then there's string
which I'm going to propose as a question
mark because a string totally depends
like high h i exclamation point would
seem to be three bytes d a ID would seem
to be five so strings clearly are
variable based on what you or the human
type in so we'll see what this means
though in just a bit this though is the
thing inside of your Mac your PC your
phone might not look exactly like this
but this is a a memory module for a
modern computer and let's go ahead and
use this really as just representative
of the finite amount of memory that any
computer indeed has let's zoom in on one
of these little black chips on the uh uh
circuit board here zoom in and let me
propose that this rectangle really
represents some number of bytes like
tucked inside of this little black uh
circuit on the board is maybe I don't
know a gigabyte a billion bytes maybe
it's a 100 btes some number of bytes it
totally depends on the computer and how
much you paid for the Stick of memory
but if there's a finite number of bytes
physically implemented somehow digitally
inside of this Hardware well then it
stands to reason that we could number
those bytes we can just arbitrarily
decide that the top left corner is bite
number one or really bite number zero
the one next to it is number one then
number two number three dot dot dot
number two billion or whatever it is
however big this this memory is so if
you are use a variable in a c program
that's only one bite like a Char it
might literally be stored in that top
left hand corner of the memory like in
practice you don't care where physically
it is but really the artist rendition
would be this a Char might use one of
those single btes somewhere in the
computer's memory if you use an INT
which is four bytes it would give you
four bytes contiguous that is left to
right top to bottom but all 32 bits
would be next to each other so the
computer knows that those indeed all
belong to the same int if you need a
long or a double for that matter then
you might use a full eight bytes in this
case and you just keep using and using
this memory kind of like a a canvas you
know almost in Photoshop or a
spreadsheet where you can just move uh
pixels or you can move data around
that's really what your computer's
memory is a canvas for storing uh
information in units of bytes or 8 Bits
now we don't need to keep looking at
these circuit boards can abstract it
away as we often do and let's go ahead
and zoom in on this grid just to
consider some very specific variables so
let me zoom in and now I see fewer but
larger uh boxes on the screen Each of
which again represents a bite and now
let me propose that we play with some
actual code so here in C albeit without
a full program or three ins score one
score two score three I have
coincidentally given myself two uh uh
two scores at around 72 and 73 and then
a pretty low score at 33 of course
course last week or two weeks ago this
would have been high but now we're
dealing with actual integers so these
are three so so scores on my quizzes or
tests or the like so let me go to vs
code here and let's make a program
called scores. C so I'm going to write
code scores. C that's going to give me
my new file and let me go ahead and
Implement something like this include
standard i.h int main void and then
inside of here let me do int score one
will be 72 uh int score two be 73 and
int score three will be 33 and then let
me just do something like write a
program to average my three test scores
together something like that so let me
do print F quote unquote my average is
and I'm going to go ahead and do say
percent I back sln and now let me plug
in the results and this is kind of grade
school math now how do I compute the
average of three values well just like
in on paper I can do score one plus
score two plus score three in
parentheses because of order of
operations divided by three since
there's three total scores all right so
I think this checks out and indeed you
can use parentheses and operators like
plus and your code like this in C let me
go ahead now and do make scores no
syntax error so that's good nothing
missing there and now let me do dot
scores and see what my test average is
all right you know it's not great but I
I I think I still passed and indeed my
average here is is 59 is it precisely 59
though well let's see let's let's
actually instead of using an INT how
about we go ahead and use something like
a floating point value here and let me
go ahead and do this so let me recompile
my code make scores huh all right I've
got an issue let me zoom in on my
terminal window we've not seen this one
necessarily before but error on line
nine format specifies type double which
is a lot of precision but the argument
has Type in so what does this mean well
it's showing me with these green
squigglies that something's bad between
the percent F and this thing over here
well on the left I'm implying a float or
a double for that matter on the right
though what data type are score one
score two score three all right so
they're ins so Cent does not like this
the compiler just doesn't like that I'm
using ins on the right but I want floats
on the left so there's going to be
different ways of solving this one way
would be to just ignore the problem like
I originally did and just go back to
percent I or as an aside percent D is
often an alternative to percent I for a
decimal number but we use perc I cuz it
sounds like int so percent I is fine
here too but I don't want to just avoid
the problem I want to actually display a
floating point value so how can I fix
this well it turns out I can solve this
in a few different ways the simplest is
just to make sure that at least one
number on the right is a floating point
value like
3.0 instead of just three now I think
clang will be happier let me do make
scores enter and indeed it's okay why as
soon as you have at least one more
precise data data type on the right it
just treats everything at that point as
floating point value so that the math
works out so/ scores enter and now there
we go right you know uh some of us might
really want that third of a point our
average was not 59 it's 59 and a third
as in this case here all right so we've
solved that there as an aside though
there's one other technique to uh to
show here if you didn't want to change
it to 3.0 because that's a little weird
because I there were literally three
scores it's not like that needs to have
a decimal point you could also
explicitly convert the three to a float
by saying in parentheses float this is
what's called type casting and this will
just convert the thing right after it to
that data type if it's possible so if I
do this again make scores no errors now
do/ scores and I get in fact the same
result there's a bit of a rounding issue
here but we know the rounding relates to
the imprecision from last week for now
let me just be happy with my 59.3
something I'll take that for now but
this is you know is close to um a good
enough correct answer for me now but how
do I think about now what's going on
inside of the computer's memory well
let's consider here's that same grid of
memory each box represents a bite where
are score one score two and score three
in my memory well score one let me just
propose is at the top left but it's
taking up four boxes for four bytes
score two probably ends up right next to
it in memory though this isn't always
going to be the case but I've chosen
simple examples 73 is next to it also
taking up four bytes and then lastly 33
is in score three uh down there
underneath now if we don't if we really
look at the computer's memory look at it
with some kind of microscope or the like
there's actually 32 bits 32 bits 32 bits
in each of those four uh groups of four
bytes representing those values but
again for today's purposes onwards we
don't really need to think again and
again in binary it's just indeed these
decimal numbers being stored there but I
claim now this isn't the best design
even if if you have never programmed
before cs50 what you're looking at here
on the screen as an excerpt in what
sense is this perhaps bad design even
though it's a correct way of storing
three test
scores what's kind of bad here
yeah yeah always do exactly what you did
extrapolate to four scores five scores
50 scores this can't be that welld
designed because now you're going to
have four lines of code five lines of
code 50 lines of code that are almost
identical except for this like arbitrary
number that we're updating at the end of
the variable so indeed there's probably
going to be a better way even though at
least in C we haven't yet seen that
technique but the solution today onward
is going to be something called an array
an array is a uh way of storing your
data back to back to back in the
computer's memory in such a way that you
can access each individual member easily
put another way with an array you can
instead do something like this instead
of saying int score one int score 2 in
score three giving each a value you can
first tell the computer please give me a
variable called scores plural that you
can call it anything you want of size
three Each of which will be an integer
that is to say this is how you declare
an array in C that will have enough room
to store three integers put another way
this is the technical way of telling the
computer please give me uh 12 bytes in
total
3 * 4 each for an inch so give me 12
bytes in total and what the computer
will do is guarantee that they're back
to back to back in the computer's memory
and that'll be useful in just a moment
so let me go ahead and do something
useful with this let me store three
actual scores here's how I could now
store those same numeric scores in this
array syntax is a little different but
there's one variable called scores but
if you want to go to its first location
starting today you use square brackets
and go to location zero first which
because things in C are zero indexed uh
so to speak you start counting at zero
the first int is at bracket zero second
int is at bracket 1 third int is at
bracket two so it's not 1 two three it's
literally 0 one2 and this is not
something you have control over you must
start at zero so these lines now create
an array of size three and then insert
one two three values into that array but
the upside now is that you only have one
name of the variable to remember it's
just called scores yes you need to go
into the array to get individual values
you need to index into it using those
square brackets but at least you don't
have this hackish approach of declaring
a separate variable for each and every
one of these values so let me go back to
scores do c here and let me propose that
I do this let me just kind of use that
same idea to do the following let me get
rid of these three separate integers let
me give myself an INT scores array of
size three and then scores bracket Z
will as before be 72 scores bracket 1
will be 73 and scores bracket 2 will be
33 and let me get rid of the Little Dot
there all right so now if I go ahead and
run this again with make uh scores
enter huh what did I do wrong here I
think I got a little too ahead of myself
let me increase my terminal
window let's focus on line 10 here first
error use of Undeclared identifier score
one what did I do here that was dumb
yeah right so I didn't declare score one
I've got old code right so I just kind
of honestly got ahead of myself here not
even intentionally so let me go ahead
and Shrink my terminal window again I
need to finish my thought here so let me
clear my terminal and let me change this
now to be scores brackets zero plus
scores bracket 1 plus scores bracket two
so it's a little more verbose because
I've got these these um square brackets
so to speak but I think now my code is
consistent so let me make scores now now
compiles do/ scores gives me indeed the
same rough average with those same
values all right so let me go ahead and
maybe um tidy enhance this a little bit
it's a little silly to have to write a
special program just to check your
average of three test scores like 72 73
33 why don't I actually make the program
Dynamic and ask the human for that
average uh for those scores so instead
let me do do this how about we get rid
of the 72 and change this to get int and
I'll just prompt the user for a score
let me get rid of the 33 and change 73
and get this to be get int score quote
unquote and then lastly get rid of the
33 and replace it with get int quote
unquote score get int is a cs50 thing
for now so I need to include cs50.h as
always but I think now it's sort of a
better program because now I can compile
it once I can even share it with my
friends and now any of us can average
three scores on some classes test they
don't need to know the code or rewrite
the code just to T type in their scores
so make scores worked scores now I can
type anything I want maybe it's a 72 73
33 still get the same answer or maybe
I'm having a better semester 100 100
maybe 99 and now we get still a pretty
high score there but now it's Dynamic
now you don't need the source code you
don't need to recompile the program it's
just going to work work again and again
but this too let me propose that this
code is correct if I want to get three
scores from the user but these
highlighted lines now 6 through n are
they welld designed would you
say
yeah yeah right this is we can use a
loop is the spoiler here why I mean my
God it's like the same code again and
again and again the only thing that's
changing is the number and you it should
have kind of had some code smell again
because if I keep typing the same thing
again again and again like that's
clearly an opportunity to better design
something so let me do this let me go
ahead and still create my ver my array
of size three and but let me use our old
friend the for Loop for in I equals z i
Less Than 3 I ++ and then in here let me
do scores bracket we haven't seen this
before but any
intuition scores bracket I because that
will use whatever I is be it Z or one or
two in iteration and then I can get an
INT asking the user for score without
having to repeat myself again and again
so hopefully if I didn't make any typos
make scores all good do/ score 72 73 33
and we're back in business but the code
is arguably now better designed because
now I haven't actually uh I haven't
actually hardcoded the scores and I
haven't actually copied and pasted any
of that code well if we consider now
what's going on inside of the computer's
memory it's pretty much the same in
terms of the values but instead of the
variables being literally score one
score two score three there's just one
variable it's an array called scores but
you can index into its three locations
by using scores bracket Z to get the
first scores bracket one to get the
second scores bracket two to get the
third but this is key the memory is
contiguous it's only the screen is only
so large so it wraps around but
physically digitally the memory is
contiguous top to bottom left to right
and that's important why because the
brackets indicate 0 1 2 that each of
these integers is just one integer away
from the next it can't be randomly down
here all of a sudden it's got to be back
to back to back all right now equipped
with that Paradigm what more could we
actually do here well it turns out it's
worth knowing that it's possible in code
to even pass arrays around as arguments
and let me just whip this program up
somewhat quickly just so you've seen it
before long but let me go ahead and do
this let me propose that I create a
function that does this averaging for me
so I'm going to create a function called
average that returns a float uh and the
arguments this thing is going to take uh
let's see it's going to be the array so
it turns out if you want to take in an
array of numbers you can call it
anything you want this is how you tell C
that a function takes not an integer but
in Array of integers and you don't have
to call it array I'm doing that just for
the sake of discussion it can be called
X it can be numbers it can be anything
else I'm just calling an array to be
super explicit as to what it is there
now how do I change my code down here
what I think I'm going to do for the
moment is just this I'm going to get rid
of this code here where I manually
computed the average and let me just
call the average function here by
passing in the whole array of scores so
this is just an example of abstraction
like now I have a fun function called
average I don't care I don't have to
remember how it works once I implement
it it just kind of tightens up my main
code a little bit but I do still have to
implement this so later in my file let
me repeat myself before the only time
it's okay and see to repeat yourself
again and again by typing out again
average and then int array Open Bracket
but now not a semicolon now I have to
implement this thing and I can implement
this in a bunch of different ways uh but
I don't know huh in advance I can't just
do this I can't just do array bracket 0
plus array bracket 1 plus array bracket
2 unless unless this program is only
ever going to work on three numbers so
huh let me let me go ahead and do this
let me first propose that there's a poor
design here in my main function what
value have I repeated
twice among the highlighted lines what
jumps out at use twice L of the array
yeah the length of the array is just
three now it's not a huge deal that I
type the number three on line eight on
line nine but this is exactly the kind
of like shortcut that's going to get you
in trouble eventually why because
eventually you or someone else is going
to go in make the array bigger or
smaller and you're not going to realize
that magically that same number is in
two places and indeed this is what a
programmer would often call a magic
number a magic number is one that just
kind of appears magically and you're on
the honor System to change it here if
you change it here and then you change
it over here like that's not going to
end well if it the onus is on the
programmer to remember where they
hardcoded that is rote out three
explicitly so anytime you reuse a value
like this you know what we should
probably do what we did last week which
was to declare a variable uh perhaps at
the very top of my program so it's super
obvious what it is called maybe n and
set that equal to three better yet what
did I do last week to make sure that I
Can't Screw Up and accidentally change
that value yeah constant and the keyword
there was just const for short and now I
have a global variable Global in the
sense that I can access it anywhere that
is called n it's an INT and it's always
going to be three and now I can improve
my main function a little bit by just
changing the threes to n so now if I if
a colleague realize oh wait a minute
there's four tests this year you change
n to four recompile the code and it just
works everywhere else except in my
average function let me change it back
to three just for consistency this is
not going to fly now to just uh sum up
things like this for instance and then
return this divided three why will this
not work
now as I've defined
it
yeah okay I might be in returning an
integer value when I intend to return a
float per this but I think I'm okay CU I
Ed that little trick where I made sure
that at least one of the numbers in my
my arithmetic expression is in fact a
floating point value and just by adding
the point zero make sure that everything
gets treated as a float so I think
that's
okay sorry a little
ladder exactly so left hand's not
talking to the right hand here and that
my current implementation of average is
still assuming that there's only going
to be three tests or whatever but wait a
minute I just went through the trouble
of modifying this to be n generically
and if I change this to four I'm not
going to be happy perhaps with my
average because now I'm going to ignore
one of my test scores Al together so let
me change this back to three and
unfortunately if it's a variable now n
and therefore I have literally a
variable number of scores how do I take
the average of a variable number of
things I mean what's my building block
there
yeah
yeah why don't I use a loop that goes
through the array and adds things up as
you go I mean kind of like grade school
as you take the average on your
calculator or paper pencil you just keep
adding the numbers together and then you
divide at the End by the total number of
things so how can I do this well let me
change my implementation of average to
First declare a a variable called sum or
whatever set it equal to zero so this is
like me on my piece of paper getting
ready to count or my calculator of
course when you turn it on typically
defaults to zero and now let me do four
in I equals z i is less than a VAR I no
I didn't do that n i is less than n
i++ and now in here let me go ahead and
add to the current sum uh whatever is in
the arrays location I and then down here
I think I can just return sum divided by
3 nope not 3.0 n perhaps here and
actually I think I'm going to get let's
make sure it's a float let's use the the
type casting trick just to make sure I
don't accidentally Short change someone
and uh throw away everything after the
decimal point so it just escalated
quickly right like average just got a
lot more involved it's just not just a
single one line of code but now it's
Dynamic I initialize a variable called
sum to zero in this loop I go through
and just keep adding to sum which is
initially zero whatever is in Array
bracket I or specifically array bracket
zero array bracket one array bracket two
that gives me a total sum that I return
divided by the total number of things
now this I can tighten slightly recall
that this is syntactic sugar for just
adding things I can't use plus plus
because that only literally adds one but
I can use here plus
equals questions on this implementation
here really the only takeaway or the
most important takeaway is that this is
the Syntax for how you tell a function
that to it expects a whole array not a
single variable like an INT or the like
you literally use square brackets but
you don't specify the length inside
there
yeah what about the variable at the
top good question what do I have it
defined as at the top this variable n it
must be an integer if you're going to uh
use it inside of in arrays square
brackets here so this line 10 notice no
longer says three it says n and so
whatever n is three or four or something
else that's how many integers I will get
in that array and it must be by
definition of an array an integer that
goes in those square brackets and here's
a common source of confusion when you
create the array that is declare it you
use square brackets like this where you
put the total number of elements you
want when you subsequently use the array
like I'm doing here you don't mention
int again just like you don't mention in
again and again once a variable exists
you use the square bracket still but you
don't use n you use zero or one or two
or generically here I so when C was
designed they sometimes use the same
Syntax for two different ideas or
contexts
yeah good question do I have to include
line six short answer yes because of the
reason we ran into last week C or clang
really reads your code top to bottom
left to right and so if the compiler
sees some mention of this function
average on line 16 but you haven't told
the compiler that average exists you're
going to get an error on the screen so
the conventional way to do that is you
just copy paste the one first line of
code from the function it's so-called
prototype or Declaration
yeah really good question uh in a
perfect segue is there a library you can
use if you don't know the size of the
array no and so if any of you have
programmed in uh in uh Java or python or
other Lang languages you can actually
just ask the array like how big is it in
C you and I the programmers have to
remember it and so short answer no
there's no function that will just
automatically do this for us and in fact
let me make a more subtle claim that
it's fine to use Global variables like
this if they're really for configuration
options why it's just convenient to put
them at the very top of the file because
everyone you your colleagues your Tas
are going to see them at the top of the
code but you really shouldn't be using
them everywhere throughout your code
it'd be better if the average function
itself we're independent of that special
variable so by that I mean this you know
what I should really do if I really want
to be welld designed I should pass in
the length of the array to the average
function I should give the average
function a second argument I'll call it
length for instance but I could call it
anything I want and so rather than
putting n all the way down here at the
bottom of my file let me just
dynamically say length instead and this
is a subtlety and no need need to get
too tripped up over this but this now is
just an example of how the same function
can take not one but two arguments but
indeed in C you must remember yourself
what the length of an array is you can't
just ask the array via some syntax like
you can those of you who've programmed
before in Java or python
yeah good question would it be better to
write a function that computes the size
short answer can't do that in C as soon
as you pass an array into a function in
C you cannot figure out its size if it's
a generic array like that of integers
there are special cases that uh you can
do that but in general no it's just not
possible in see and if that's some
frustration honestly this is why more
modern languages add that feature why
because it was really annoying um as I'm
alluding here to not having that
information now just to make sure I
didn't screw up anywhere let me compile
this final version of
scores
suspense all good/ scores 72 73 33 and
we're still back in business so this
version is more complicated and as
always we'll have this version on the
course's website for reference but the
point really is that arrays not only can
be used as containers to store multiple
values three or more in this case um you
can also even pass them around as
arguments as such all right now besides
that let's let's simplify for just a
moment and consider now the world of
chars if we've just got single bites
where uh where does this lead us and how
does this get us ultimately to strings
to solve problems like readability and
cryptography and the like well here for
instance are three lines of code out of
context that simply store three chars
and you can already see where this is
going having three variables called C1
C2 C3 is clearly going to end up being
bad design because of all the silly
redundancy here but notice I'm using
single quotes like last week because
these are single chars what does this
look like in the computer's memory well
it looks a little something like this if
we clear out the old memory C1 C2 C3
probably will end up here maybe not
literally in the top leftand Corner this
is just an artist rendition but C1 C2 C3
will probably end up like that now
what's really there it's really those
same three numbers 72 73 33 but how many
bits does a bite
have just eight so if we were to look at
the binary representation of these
characters it would only be eight bits
each that's enough to store small
numbers like 72 73 33 we're not dealing
with Unicode and emoji and the like but
the point is the same you don't have to
use four bytes to store these numbers
you can use a different data type like
chars and underneath the hood it's
indeed going to use just single bytes
for each but this is sort of like a this
isn't really how we Implement strings
right when you wanted to say hi last
week or this we use double quotes and we
wrote all of the things together and
used one variable not three right when I
typed in David I didn't have a variable
for d a v i d i had one variable called
name that stored the whole thing so in C
we keep talking about these things
called strings we'll see eventually that
strings are not necessarily what they
seem to be but for now the key thing
about strings is that they're variable
length uh so to speak right they might
be three characters high or five
characters David or anything uh smaller
or larger so how do we go about
implementing strings if all we have at
the end of the day is my memory well
here is an example of just creating uh
declaring and defining a string called s
s because it's just a simple string and
quote unquote high in double quotes what
does this look like in the computer's
memory well let's clear it again and
here now because it's technically stored
in one variable s here is how I might
draw it as an artist it's three bytes in
total H exclamation point but there's no
C1 C2 C3 it's just the whole thing is uh
s but it turns out that a string fun
fact is really just what underneath the
hood kind of leading up to this what is
a string if this is how it's laid out in
memory literally it's just an array of
characters and we didn't have to know
about arrays last week to use strings
this is where again the training wheels
are starting to come off but a string is
just an array of characters Hi
exclamation point for instance so
technically an array a string called s
is really a variable called s that
allows you to get at the first character
with s bracket zero if you want s
bracket 1 s bracket2 you can literally
get individual characters just by
treating S as though it's an array which
it really is underneath the hood in this
case but there's a catch how do you know
where strings end in the past when I
drew some integers on the screen I know
I claim they always take up four bytes
if I had drawn a long it always takes up
eight bytes if I drawn a a character it
always takes up one bite but how many
bites does a string take up yeah I mean
that's kind of the right answer in this
case three it would seem but if it's
David that's a good five characters but
where do we put the number three where
do you put the number five right this is
literally all that's into your computer
this is all our building blocks in front
of us so how can we where does the three
go where does the five go well it turns
out you can solve this in a couple of
different ways but the way humans
decided to implement strings years ago
is indeed an array but they added one
extra bite at the end of every such
string array just to make clear with a
so-called Sentinel value that the string
ends here why so that if you have two
strings in the computer's memory like hi
and by you know where the barrier is
between like the exclamation point of
one and the letter B in the next right
you need some kind of delimiter and so
what really is underneath the hood is
this when you store a string in memory
when you type in a string as the user if
you type in three characters it's it's
going to use 3 + 1 = 4 bytes in total if
you type in David it's going to use 5 +
1al 6 bytes in total why because C
automatically adds this special zero at
the end of the string I've drawn it with
back SL Zer because this is how you
represent zero as a Char as a character
but this is literally just zero as we'll
soon see so anytime there's a string in
memory it always takes up one more bite
than you yourself as the programmer or
human typed in in fact if we convert
this again just for discussion sake to
those integers what's literally stored
in the computer's memory is going to be
72 73 33 and now a zero and the computer
because of c and how it was invented
it's just smart enough to know that when
you print out a string it prints out
every character until it sees a zero and
then it just stops printing in
particular printf knows how this works
and this is why print F knows when to
stop printing decimal numbers are not
that enlightening we'll generally write
the characters like this and again back
back sl0 is just special symbology like
it's what the programmer types to make
clear that you're not saying hi zero
you're saying hi and then it's a special
zero specifically it is eight zero bits
that indicate that it's the end of the
string technically that back sl0 if you
want to be fancy it's called null
NL and it turns out you've seen this
before that we didn't call it out here's
that same asky chart from the past
couple of weeks if I highlight this what
is decimal number zero mapping to n
which is just programmer speak for the
special null character all zero bits
that means the string ends here this all
happens automatically for you you do not
need to create these null characters or
these
zeros any questions
then on this implementation thus
far any questions here no well let me do
this let me go back to vs code in a
second and let's actually corroborate
this with some code let me go ahead and
create a small program called high. C
and how about we do this let me include
standard i.h let me include uh let me
type out int main void as always and now
let me do something simple and kind of
bad but Char C1 equals quote unquote H
in single quotes Char C2 equals quote
unquote I in single quotes and lastly
Char C3 equals exclamation point in
single quotes and now let me just print
this out I can't use percent s cuz that
is not a string that's literally three
chars cuz that's the design decision I
made but I could do this percent C
percent C percent C which we haven't
seen before but percent s is string
percent I is int percent C is indeed uh
Char so let me put a back sln at the end
for cleanliness and now do C1 C2 C3 so
this is like a Char based version of
printing string so let me make high and
then let me do/ high and it looks like I
use print f with percent s but I did
things very manually by printing out
each individual character what's cool
now though is that once you know that
characters are just numbers and strings
are just characters you can kind of poke
around let me change all three
placeholders to percent i instead and
this is totally fine too let me rerun
this make
High um actually let me make one change
just so we can see this let me add
spaces just for Aesthetics sake let me
do make high do SL High enter and voila
like now you can actually see the
numbers that I claimed back in week zero
were in fact happening underneath the
hood well this is not how you would make
strings it'd be incredibly tedious to
have three variables for threel Words
five variables for five letter words
we've been using of course strings since
last week so let's do that instead uh
string uh s equals quote unquote double
quotes high for this no because of these
training wheels I need to include the
cs50 library but we'll come back to that
in the coming week but for now I'm going
to go ahead and create a string s called
quote unquote high and now I'm going to
change this to be my familiar percent s
and now just print out s itself this of
course is the same thing as last week
high gives me the exact same thing but
now we're dealing of course with strings
but how can we see a little beyond that
well how about this let's poke around
further with today's Primitives even
though s is a string I could technically
print out its first character with
percent C by doing s bracket z i could
technically print out its second
character with percent C by doing s
bracket one I could print out its third
character with percent C and printing
out s bracket 2 so again this just
derives logically from my understanding
now of that strings or arrays as you
note let me do make let me do make high
SL high and no visual change but I'm
just kind of now tinkering around and in
fact if you're really curious let me do
this let me change these back to I back
to I I oops back to I and let me add a
fourth one because if I'm really curious
now let's see it what's S braet 3 this