memory but I think this is going to get
me in trouble pointer equals list just
gives me a temporary pointer that points
at the three and then eventually the two
and then the one how well while pointer
not equal null I'm freeing the pointer
so this is like saying to Malo free that
node free that node free that node but
what's the problem with what I've just
done
here this code is technically Bugg
[Music]
yeah exactly after you call free on
pointer You Are by social contract with
c not allowed to touch pointer anymore
it is invalid now it's still going to be
a number it's still going to be a
pattern of bits but it's invalid and
you'll very often get a segmentation
fault if you tempt fate in that way so I
can't free the pointer and then use it
literally the next line the solution
here kind of like our swapping of the
liquids last time was to maybe just have
a temporary variable so I can do a
Switcheroo and so a common way to solve
this problem to get the order of
operations right would be to do
something like this give yourself a
temporary pointer like node star next
set it equal to the place you want to go
next so one step ahead now you can free
pointer and then you can update pointer
to be that next value so essentially you
need need like two hands now you create
on line 41 another pointer that if this
is pointing at the first Noe the three
your new pointer is pointing at the two
temporarily so now you can tell malok
via free release this memory but I
haven't forgotten where I want to go
next and so I can now continue on so a
common Paradigm for just iterating over
these nodes and then freeing them a
couple of observations strictly speaking
I could have Consolidated this I don't
need two Loops to print the nodes and
then free the nodes I could do that all
at once but let's assume that there's
other stuff of interest in my program
and I don't want to just immediately
free it there's one other bug that I
should probably address here there is
still a potential memory leak up here
and this one is super subtle the valind
would help you find it notice that in
this Loop here when I'm calling malok
this line of code is fine if the first
line of malok fails and returns null
because I immediately return and I'm
done but what if the second call but not
the first or the third call but not the
first or second fail this line of code
has me returning immediately you really
need to to do some garbage collection so
to speak whereby you really need to go
in and free any nodes that you did
allocate successfully earlier honestly
that's going to be a pin in the neck we
won't do that here but probably what I'd
want to do is write a function called
free list or something like that and
call that function to free any nodes I
had previously created so it's not quite
at the finish line but the building
blocks are indeed here questions on this
code and I think it's safe for me to
promise that it won't escalate further
from
that questions on
[Music]
this no well let me show you one
alternative that you might prefer and
I'm pretty sure this isn't an escalation
it's just an alternative formulation
another way you can iterate over nodes
in a list could be this instead of a
while loop for instance let me actually
show you one other piece of syntax here
you could technically use a for Loop you
could give yourself a node pointer here
that initialized is initialized to the
list you can then check in your for Loop
that it's not equal to null and then you
can do your update as usual like this
either of these are equivalent even
though this one I suspect looks scarier
it's doing the exact same thing in one
line instead of two but there's no
reason we can't use four Loops instead
of while Loops to achieve the same idea
but I'll leave these two as
demonstrations of one approach or the
other but that's just like in week one
four Loops while Loops whatever looks
simpler to you even though admittedly
neither of these probably looks super
clean all right so let's take the back
to things more conceptual here up until
now we've been inserting elements into
this link list by prepending them let's
consider what the running time then is
of these operations so if I've got a
link list of size three or size N More
generally time has passed and I've added
a lot of things to it what's going to be
the running time for instance of
searching a linked list for some value
and I'll tell you already it's not login
because again binary search is off the
table as per before break so what might
the running time be of searching a
linked list for some value like two or
three or 1 or
50 what might the running time
be o of I heard it over here o of n and
y who was that oh in the middle here why
o of
[Music]
n exactly you're going to have to go
through every item in the list starting
from the left from the beginning which
is how we've been drawing things and
connecting the dots and in the worst
case the element might very well be at
the very end so it's going to be Big O
of n what about insertion how many steps
in terms of Big O notation has it been
taking me to insert elements into the
link list using this prepended
design yeah so it's technically constant
time Big O of one and again one is just
representative of any constant it could
technically be two steps or three steps
or even 10 steps or 100 steps but if
it's always finite and fixed then indeed
you can say it's in Big O of one now why
is that well over again no matter how
long this list gets so long as there's
memory available for me I can just kind
of uh create a little splice at the
beginning of the list to put in the new
node update the original list and I'm on
my way and it keeps getting longer even
though it might not be spread out in
memory so big O of one is possible with
these link lists if I indeed Preen
things of course if I Preen things
everything's going to get out of order
potentially and we're going to have
maybe the stack property instead of a q
property so we might want to do things
slightly differently so instead of doing
this
whereby we kept prepending prepending
prepending suppose we append to the end
of the list instead so if we now insert
the one the two and the three as we
might want to for a q to maintain that
fairness property we might start with an
empty list we might add the one we might
append the two append the three and so
it just is sort of laid out differently
in memory and again if I can come to you
in the middle what's the running time of
search again when the link list uses
this append
implementation yeah still Big O of n
because in the worst case you're going
to have to go through the whole list
just to find it and notice it doesn't
matter if you have an intuition now that
the bigger numbers might very well be at
the end you have no way to jump to the
end you have no way to jump to the
middle or do anything resembling binary
search every search has to start from
the left and follow the arrows again and
again all right so I don't think we've
done any better there and in fact what
is insertions running time now in Big O
when we're appending to the list in this
way as we might to implement a Q instead
of a stack what's the running time of
inserting a new
value Big O
of so not Big O of one in this case but
Big O of n because if I'm appending by
definition I have to start here and
Traverse the whole thing looking for the
end now this is a bit of an
overstatement right you could obviously
optimize this slightly by maybe adding
another variable that always points to
the last element sort of a cheat sheet a
shortcut that gets you all the way to to
the end that's totally fine it's not
doesn't really fit the traditional
definition of a singly linked list but
there's absolutely smart engineering
solutions to these kinds of problems but
as designed it would indeed be Big O of
end to insert to if you've got to go all
the way to the end and you're not using
a little extra memory to get yourself
there quickly well what if we want to
take things one last step and not just a
pen blindly because even though I
inserted one two three if I inserted
them in random order they would end up
in random order what if you want to
maintain a sorted list from smallest to
largest well then you might want to
insert numbers like this starting from
an empty list we might have a two then
we might try inserting a one but we want
to keep it sorted so now we're going to
prepend in our code but then you might
want to insert a four so you would
append the four because you're probably
going to look for the right spot to
insert it then we're going to insert a
three and this one's getting a little
annoying because now you have to like
iterate over the list look for the right
spot and then do a little smarter of a
splice but it's possible but you don't
want to Orphan the four for instance and
then ultimately we get back to this
question what would the performance be
of your linked list if you're trying to
maintain sorted order well search I
think is going to be Big O of n for the
same reasons as before what about
insertion big go of what for inserting
into a sorted linked
list yeah in the worst
case yeah it's still Big O ofen so it's
no worse than but it's not really any
better than a pending but we gain the
additional property of maintaining a
sorted list which might very well be
useful if you're sorting your contacts
in your phone or something like that
where it just maintain makes sense to
maintain sorted order now in the code
for online today if you take a look at
some of the final versions of code like
list 6. C and list 5.c as we'll post on
the website you can actually see code
that will solve all three of these
problems the Preen version that we wrote
live the appen version which we talk
through as well as this sorted order one
but I think I'll avoid showing it live
just because I do think that starts to
escalate quickly but I think we have
enough of a building block if we're
comfortable with prepending to at least
solve some real world problems with
these link
lists questions then on link list which
we'll now leave behind on their own but
now use this technique to solve fancier
problems but much less
code questions on linked list all right
so to C recap we've kind of taken a s
side step with link list like we have
this dynamism now where we can grow and
Shrink our chunks of memory without over
allocating or accidentally
underallocation as in the world of an
array we don't have to worry about
copying values endlessly because once
you allocate the node it can just stay
wherever it is in memory and you can
just maintain uh you can just Stitch it
together somehow but unfortunately we've
sacrificed what we started the class
with in week zero which was like binary
search divide and conquer which was like
gave us that log and running time which
was really compelling if you think back
to the demonstrations and the the
visuals can we get the best of both
worlds can we get the sort of uh speed
of binary search something logarithmic
but the dynamism of something like a
link list well we can actually I think
if we start to think not in a single
Dimension just the x-axis if you will
but two Dimensions such that our data
structures can maybe now have width and
height if you will and so a tree is
perhaps the right term here much like a
family tree if you have sort of your
elders up here in the tree and then the
branches below them for their children
and grandchildren and the like that's
actually what a computer scientist means
when they talk about trees not a tree
that grows up like this but really one
that typically is depicted growing down
although this is just an artist's
depiction no matter what but there are
certain types of trees in the world
called binary search trees that are
structured on paper and in visually like
a uh family tree but they have a special
property that lends themselves to
exactly that feature binary search so
for instance here is an array back from
week two and I've sorted a whole bunch
of numbers here in from 1 to seven we
know we can do binary search on this
structure if it's implemented as an
array but what feature do arrays to be
clear not have that link lists
do today's kind of a seesaw like what
did we just gain by adding link list
that arrays do not
allow
yeah
yeah you can insert more elements
without having to copy or moving
everything else around like right now in
this single Dimension if these values to
the left and or right are already used
then you have to move everything and
that's where we started today's story so
arrays kind of paint you into a corner
because you have to by definition decide
in advance how big they are well
couldn't we have some kind of array that
can still grow but still is contiguous
so we can do binary search in some way
well yes if we sort of rethink how we
Implement binary search Let Me propose
that this I've chosen these seven
elements in the array much like the
lockers from uh week two to be ordered
from smallest to largest I've
highlighted now in yellow the middle
elements here and if we were telling the
story of week two going left or going
right let me highlight in red the middle
elements of the left half and the right
half and then let me further highlight
in green the other elements in between
those and there's a pattern here as you
might notice whereby there's one yellow
in the middle and then there's the two
red and the four green there's kind of
an implicit structure there if you will
and what if I do start to think in two
dimensions and instead of laying out an
array of lockers like this on the x-axis
only what if I kind of like Slide the
four up and pull the uh the the one the
three the five down and kind of draw
this in two Dimensions instead well let
me do that as by separating these things
like this such that now let me propose
that each of these squares maybe it
doesn't have to be contiguous it can be
anywhere in the computer's memory but I
can't have these crazy gaps among them
how could I perhaps keep these things
connected conceptually what should I add
to the picture if you
will yeah branches say again so branches
metaphorically here and more technically
in the language of C maybe just some
arrows some pointers so I won't bother
drawing things as rectangles constantly
let me propose that we're now just
abstracting away what a node is but let
me claim that each of these squares now
is a node and a node might have a number
but it might also have a pointer heck
maybe even two or more pointers and let
me draw those now I don't care about
addresses like ox1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 n
anymore let's just draw our pointers
with arrows but now let me propose that
we could very well think about this as a
tree storing what was previous
previously array data but now each of
these nodes can be anywhere in memory
and moreover even though I've kind of
painted myself into a corner visually on
the screen so long as there's more
memory in the computer I could put the
number zero over here I could put the
number eight over here and I'm if I'm
smart I could probably if I want to
insert other numbers like 2.5 or 1.5 or
values in between you know I bet we
could kind of make room by swiveling
things around and just kind of hanging
things off of these branches slightly
differently and so what does this gain
me well if I instead start to model my
data not single dimensionally but in two
dimensions and I connect those nodes
with these pointers what can I now do I
think I just gave myself back binary
search why suppose I'm searching for the
number five how do I find it Well just
like in a family tree where you might
visually start reading from top to
bottom I'm always going to start from
the so-called root of a binary search
tree this is just like the list pointer
that kicks off the whole link list
process
this is the so-called route all right
here I am at the number four I want to
find the number five what decision can I
make when I see that I'm currently at
the number four just like the phone book
from week zero where is five
not it's not to the left and if I were
had you know built a little mobile here
or something we could very dramatically
snip off this Branch this is this is
like very lowbudget animation these
nodes could like fall to the ground and
we're left with half of essentially a
tree but what do I now know it's
obviously the five to the right so let
me go to the right six is obviously not
the one I'm looking for but what do I
now know about the five well five is
less than the sixth so I can sort of
snip this off here because I know it's
not going to be down there and I can
follow the remaining Arrow here and
voila I just found it and now without
getting into the weeds of the math I've
got here what Seven Elements that's
roughly eight if I round up and if I do
some log base two I actually 1 two three
is the key detail here the height of
this tree
is three because I took a list of size
seven and IED it and IED it in order to
let it dangle in these two Dimensions
plus or minus one for rounding sake so
what do I get back I now have binary
search but it's not like H the middle of
the middle of the middle I now follow
these arrows in one of two directions so
each of these nodes now has an INT and
maybe a left pointer and a right pointer
but you can call them anything you want
and so I've gotten back binary search
and dynamism because if you want to add
zero or eight or 9 or 10 we can just
dangle them at the bottom of the binary
search tree so what would this look like
in code but we won't actually implement
it line by line well here was previously
our definition of a node for a link list
which was onedimensional if you will
even though it might bounce up and down
on the screen it was still just a line
if you will well let me get rid of the
single pointer in the linked list let me
make a little bit of room here in this
type death and let me propose that we
just add two pointers each of which is a
struct node star one will be called left
by convention one will be called right
by convention and so long as someone not
me not today not in class writes the
code that stitches together this data
structure too handling both the left
child and the right child so to speak I
think we can indeed stitch together that
two-dimensional structure and moreover
once you have this in memory you can
translate pretty elegantly to code
binary search itself using a principle
we talked about recently too here is for
instance a function that I'll write by
just clicking through steps called
search whose purpose in life is to
return a Boolean true or false the
number I'm looking for is in the tree
this search function therefore takes two
arguments the number I'm looking for
called number and then a pointer to the
tree the so-called root of the tree now
how can I Implement binary search in
code will recall our brief discussion of
recursion it turns out recursion is a
beautiful technique and honestly more
obvious technique when you have two
dimensional structures which finally
after five plus weeks we now do here's
maybe my first line of code here if the
tree is null then obviously return false
you've handed me an empty tree there's
nothing going on obviously the number
you're looking for is not going to be
here so that's my like safe base case to
make sure I don't screw up and recurse
infinitely well what else might be the
case well if the number I'm looking for
is less than the tree's own number and
now recall that trees a node star so
even though I'm calling it a tree it's
really the current node that's been
passed in so if the number I'm looking
for is less than the current nodes
number then I must know that the number
I'm looking for is to the left so to
speak so how can I solve that well this
is where the magic of recursion just
return whatever the answer is to calling
search again but on a sub tree if you
will this is the sort of equivalent of
snipping off half of the tree pass in
the left sub tree if you will with the
same number else if the number you're
looking for isn't less than the current
nodes number but greater than snip off
the other subtree instead and just
return whatever search says it finds in
the right subtree here and then there's
a fourth and final case what else could
be true
logically
[Music]
yeah perfect if the number you're
looking for equals equals the number in
this node then I'm just going to return
true and you might recall from our
recurring discussions of design I don't
strictly need to ask that explicitly
either there's no node it's to the left
it's to the right or you found it so I
can just Whittle that down as usual to
an else and this now returns my true so
here too this is where recursion once
you get comfy with it sort of gets
pretty elegant and cool in the sense
that wow even though there's a lot of
lines here I mean there's only a few
interesting lines a lot of it's like
Curly braces at that which strictly
speaking I could get rid of and so
recurs lends itself to Elegance when it
comes to traversing these
two-dimensional data structures as well
so that is in code how you might
Implement something like
search questions then on these
trees we have dynamism we can insert
more nodes to them they're faster
because we get B search back but but but
there's got to be a price paid any
downsides or question or
downside okay let me come back to that
in just one sec downside though what
price of we paid for this dynamism and
for this binary
searchability even though I've
abstracted it away in the
picture say
again we're using a lot of memory right
I'm kind of misleading you now because
I'm just drawing these little squares
with the simple numbers but there's
actually three things in there a four
byte integer an 8 by left pointer a 8 by
right pointer so we're already up to 16
20 bytes now to store individual ins
that's probably okay though if memory is
relatively cheap and voluminous as it
nowadays is but these are the kinds of
trade-offs and here too you see a hint
of why some people still do like and use
C and in fact it's so omnipresent
because when you have C you can really
fine-tune how much memory is being used
for Better or For Worse under the hood
as we transition soon to python these
decisions get made for you and you have
much much less control about how many me
how much memory is being used by your
program because someone else made those
designed decisions for you
question
is it bad if we don't know the parent
node uh not necessarily there's no
reason why you need to have pointers in
both directions however that can lend
itself to efficiency by spending more
space and having arrows go up too you
can actually save more time when
searching the tree in other context this
though would be the canonical way the
typical way to implement it um but
absolutely just like a doubly link list
that could help you solve other problems
too all right so turns out I'm kind of
overselling binary search trees there
are perversions of them so to speak
whereby they won't actually behave as
advertised for instance here's a a good
situation suppose you've got an empty
tree initially and you insert the number
two well it's got to go somewhere so it
might as well become the root of this
binary search tree and let's assume that
someone wrote the code to do this now
you want to insert the number one and
you want to maintain the searchability
of this tree well it's important to note
that binary search tree is different
from tree if you just got a tree in
memory there is no social contract with
where the numbers need to go they can be
completely random all over the place
binary search tree means that you can do
binary search means that any node here
is going to be greater than every node
here and less than every node here and
that's a definition it's a recursive
structural definition that must be true
to be a binary search tree or BST so if
we maintain that property ourselves let
me insert two let me insert one one
belongs there by that definition let me
insert three three belongs there by that
definition but I kind of got lucky in
that I in the story inserted two and
then one and then three let me propose a
sort of perversion of the algorithm
whereby we just get unlucky let me
propose that we insert in uh insert one
first and then we insert two well where
does two go well logically it goes to
the right because it's larger all right
now the user inserts three where does it
go okay it goes there logically and how
does this story un fold the user inserts
four five six it's wonderfully sorted in
advance by luck but this is a perversion
of the structure in what
sense it's still technically a binary
search tree but what does it look more
like it really is devolving if you will
into a linked list and so if you the
programmer don't Implement a binary
search tree with some kind of repairs
going on such that as soon as something
gets whoa a little too long in stringy I
think I can fix this it's going to be an
annoying line number of lines of code
which we're not going to write here or
or in a pet but we could kind of pivot
this thing right and we could just
rejigger things so that the two becomes
the new root the one becomes the left
child the three becomes the right child
but that's what like two three plus
lines of code it's possible it's doable
but it's it's extra work it's extra code
so unless you write that code though and
maintain balance of these trees just
because it's a binary search tree does
not mean its height is going to be log
base 2 of n the height could be log it
could be n in which case you don't get
those properties so when it comes to
looking up in a balanced binary search
tree yes it's log in but if it's
unbalanced if you don't add that
additional logic and those repairs so to
speak you could it could devolve into
Big O of N and this is a whole category
of algorithms and fanciness that you
would explore in a higher level course
on algorithms and data structures
there's lots of way to do that sort of
fixing that I'm alluding to in the
picture there on the screen
screen all right a few other data
structures if you will toward an end of
a sort of computer science Holy Grail so
log in is repeatedly a really good place
to end up we started in week zero when
we got log in we lost it this earlier
today by introducing link list but we
just got it back albeit at the price of
spending more space but the Holy Grail
so to speak when it comes to algorithms
would not be Big O of n certainly
definitely not n squar like our mer like
our bubble sorts and selection sorts and
not even Big O of Logan what's better
than all of
those big O of one constant time right
that's the Holy Grail because if we
could store huge amounts of data but
find it instantly in one step or two
steps or heck even 10 or 20 steps but
independent of the size of the data
structure that's pretty powerful I mean
that's the secret sauce of the Googles
and the twitters of the world trying to
get back results really really fast well
it turns out another abstract data type
or abstract data structure might be
something called a dictionary just like
the maram Webster Oxford English
dictionaries that you might know which
associate say words with definitions
well you can think of a dictionary
really abstractly as this like two
columns maybe on a spreadsheet of sorts
where the left column represents
something and the right column
represents something else like the word
is on the left and its definition is on
the right and that's almost literally
what a dictionary is on paper you've got
all the words and all the definitions
right next to it but more generally in
Computing a dictionary really just has
not words and definitions per se but key
value pairs this is a term of Art and
we're going to see this again and again
especially as we transition to web
programming keys and values key is what
you use to look for something the value
is what you find ultimately via that key
so that's the generic term there we've
seen key value pairs really in the past
in week zero we talked about your
contacts in your iPhone or Android phone
uh being an app that has a whole bunch
of contexts presumably alphabetized by
first name or last name or the like well
one one of those contact cards
ultimately has someone's number for
instance like John Harvard in this case
so in that type of application the keys
is the name like John Harvard that you
use to find information and the value is
the number that you find there or if
there's more information like where he
lives and uh email address and the like
the whole contact card could be the
value thereof the key is what you use to
look up John Harvard now back in week
zero oh and rather the corresponding
table then if we draw this in two
columns wouldn't be word and definition
or key value generically it would be
name and number for instance so we're
just slapping some new terminology on
this old contact problem well this is
the picture we drew way back in week
zero whereby I claimed that log of n was
really really good and indeed it was and
has been since but the Holy Grail would
indeed be something more like this in
this dashed Green Line constant time and
maybe not literally one step but a fixed
number of steps that even as the problem
gets huge and you go way way out on the
right of the X AIS the problem does not
depend on the side the uh the uh the
time to solve the problem does not
depend at all on the size of the problem
itself you can have a thousand contacts
or 100,000 contacts constant time means
it takes the same number of steps no
matter what well how can we get to that
point well there's a couple of final
building blocks today and there's one
called hashing and this is something
that will recur a few times but for now
hashing is all about taking as input
some value
and outputting a simpler version thereof
so for instance here's a a gratuitously
large deck of cards which are all the
more visible as a result and in a deck
of cards typically you've got like what
52 cards plus maybe the Jokers and
whatnot and each of those cards has a
number of sorts and a suit on it and
here are literally four buckets on the
stage and how might I go about sorting
these cards not just by number but also
by suit well you could certainly like
spread them all out and sort of make a
mess of things and just kind of reason
your way through it and get everything
in order according to suit and corded by
number but most of us even if you don't
have four buckets at home probably are
going to do something a little more
intuitive feels like an optimization
where if I find like the nine of Hearts
I'm going to put that into the hearts
bucket the King of Spades I'm going to
put that into the Spades bucket the jack
of diamonds over here and I'll do this
with the Queen of Diamonds and uh the
Ace of clubs here and the three here and
the 10 here and even though it's still
going to be 52 steps why am I and maybe
at home like why would you perhaps do
this step
first what's the value of bucketization
reduces the probability of errors or the
like and what I'm doing here to give it
a technical term is that I'm hashing the
values I'm taking as input a card like
this and I'm reducing it more simply
from a larger domain to a much smaller
range if you will so here's a domain of
like 52 possibilities I want to map that
to a range of four possible outcomes the
Diamonds the clubs the carts or the
Spades here and by doing that I'm just
shrinking the size of the problem so
hashing does that it's like literally an
F ofx type Arrangement whereby you pass
something in and you get back a simpler
known value well a hash function more
technically is the algorithm or even the
math or even the code that implements
that idea converting something bigger to
something smaller to this indeed finite
range of values and it turns out that
hash tables are a wonderful application
of arrays and length lists to try to
Leverage The Best of Both Worlds the
goal being theoretically to achieve that
Holy Grail of constant time and that's
going to be a bit of an overstatement
because you're not always going to
achieve it exactly but at least we can
get a little closer there too so with
hash tables you have something that
looks like this this is just an array
this is an artist rendition of drawing
it vertically instead of horizontally
but that's just a a detail graphically
and this array for instance maybe uh is
of size 26 and where am I going with
this well how does Apple how does Google
Store your contexts alphabetically in
your phone and search for things quickly
well they might they probably
alphabetize at least in English
according to a through z or if we
convert that to numbers it's like what
65 through whatever or really 0 through
25 suffices if we're using an array of
size 26 we start counting at zero and we
count up to 25 but let's abstract that
away as just letters of the alphabet so
maybe what Google and apple are doing in
your phone is storing all of the A's up
there all of the Z's down there and
everything else in between and so this
works pretty well if you start adding
your friends and your family so for
instance and I'll get rid of the letter
so it's to not distract uh alvus might
go in that first spot because a you
subtract the 65 maps to zero so we put
him in the first bucket the a bucket uh
maybe Zacharias ends up all the way at
the end there and then in the middle
might here be Hermione and if we do this
dot dot dot you keep adding all of your
classmates you might get a uh contact
database that has all of this data here
in now each of these nodes they're drawn
differently because this is just another
artist rendition these rectangles these
long rectangles represent a contact card
like John Harvard's that's got the name
maybe email definitely phone number and
things like that so this seems great why
how can I find Albus well I go to the a
bucket how do I find Zacharias I go to
the Z bucket how do I find Hermione I go
to the H bucket but but but I've done
this very deliberately what problem will
arise eventually assuming you have
enough classmates
yeah there'll be too many people too
many contacts for all of the available
spaces in the array there's still some
room here but I'm pretty sure if I think
back to this particular class uh we've
got not hermy but also Harry who's also
an H Hagrid who's also an H so where do
I put them I could just put them
arbitrarily in any of the open spots but
then you lose the immediacy of jumping
right to the H right to the a right to
the Z but now that we have link lists we
can kind of combine these ideas right
use an array to get to the first letter
of the name you care about and then if
you have a collision so to speak whereby
someone's already there you don't do
something stupid like put Harry down
here just because it's available or
maybe Hagrid down here just because it's
available because then you're losing the
immediacy of the lookup why don't you
just kind of stitch them together in a
linked list now what does this mean this
means for most of the characters here
you have constant time lookup you look
up alvas boom you're done Zacharias boom
you're done okay Harry Hermione Hagrid
it might be one two or three steps so
that's actually devolving into something
linear but here we make a distinction
today between theoretical running times
which we keep talking about and honestly
a clock on the wall running times that
actual humans care about this is way
faster than a linked list because you
don't have to search every name it's
even faster than a an array because you
don't need to do binary search
you can literally for most of the names
find them in constant time one step and
again it's not theoretically constant
because these if you only befriend
people who have H names it's going to be
a crazy long link list anyway so again
it really kind of depends on what the
nature of the data is here but this is
pretty close to constant time and in
fact how could we get even closer how
could we reduce the probability of
collisions for the H's or any other
letters how could we avoid putting too
many H names together
say a little
L okay yeah so we could add another
dimension if you will but let's not add
a third dimension per se but let's
indeed look at not just the first letter
of everyone's name but the first and the
second and in fact let's see if that
gets us a little uh further along so let
me go ahead and propose if you go
through the whole Harry Potter Universe
there's actually a lot of collisions if
we keep going and so we've got the L's
here the RS the S's and so forth well
let's clean this up here Hermione
originally went to the H location but
let's decrease the probability of
collisions there and everywhere else
instead of putting hermion Harry and
Hagrid Al together let's go ahead and do
this instead instead of labeling these
buckets A through Z let's just give
ourselves more buckets so in fact this
might be H well instead of H maybe this
should be ha and then this should be HB
HC HD h e HF now some of those are a
little nonsensical cuz I can't think of
names that match most of those but it's
deterministic at least we know the
bucket will be there which is important
even if it's empty and now we can put
Hermione here we can put Harry here but
uhoh we didn't do this perfectly well
Hagrid still Collide so let me come back
to you how can we reduce the probability
of Harry and Hagrid
colliding yeah so we could look at the
third letter okay so let me try that
instead of ha let's look at haa ha ha C
dot dot dot haq dot dot dot h h e q h e
r hes and so forth and now I think those
names and probably all the others we saw
are now much more cleanly distributed
there's much lower probability of
collisions unless two people have like
almost the same names or one is like a
prefix of the other but but but even
though we're now closer than ever to
constant time because the odds that we
hit a collision and have to devolve to a
link list or much lower what's the
downside that's not completely obvious
from how I've depicted this on
screen what's the price I'm paying here
yeah this is a huge amount of memory the
number of cells here in the array is now
what 26 * 26 * 26 for the first the
second and the third possible characters
all combinatorically combined here
that's a lot I didn't even draw them I
have the dot dot dot to evoke that
instead that's a huge amount of memory
this is a very sparse data set now and
odds are you're going to waste so much
memory even for the names like Hae ha
like HQ like I can't even think of names
so many of those buckets are going to be
empty not to mention the AAA and the zzz
and everything else in between so it's a
trade-off and it might be too expensive
a trade-off and so you might have to
tolerate something like the collisions
we had earlier whereby even though they
might very well happen at least you uh
are decreasing the probability by
perhaps having more buckets like this
and in fact if I rewind now to where we
might have gone with this here here's
how we might represent these nodes in
the tree previously in the past we've
had a person who had a string name and a
string number AKA now Char star and so
here now might be how in this hash table
we represent someone's name and number
as well as a pointer to the next element
in the list we let me rewind just to the
picture here we keep drawing different
shapes because again these are
abstractions who really cares if they're
to scale now we've got enough room for
the person's name not pictured on the
screen is herm's number that's somewhere
in this rectangle but yes pictured here
in this little square is a pointer to
the next node in the list so by storing
name and number maybe her address maybe
her mailing address whatever in addition
to a pointer allows each of these nodes
to be connectable just like the nodes in
a linked list but where they're starting
is in an array so the array gets us like
126 of or gets us um Narrows the problem
from size 26 to one gets us to the link
list in question hopefully it's a single
person or perhaps it has more than that
meanwhile what is the hash table itself
the hash table the whole thing is
literally just an array I've hardcoded
the simplest version of size 26 but what
do each of those boxes in the vertical
array represent just a pointer to
potentially a node a node in a length
list and if there's no one there if
there's no one in location y or X or the
like in that Universe well it's just a
null pointer signifying there's no uh
one there but if there is it's going to
be a pointer to a valid node from which
we can get to any of the others as well
and that so-called hash function just
like the one I did with the greeting
cards well it's just an a black box if
you will but implemented somewhere in
code like in C and so if you pass in
Albus what is the hash value of Albus
well in the first version of the story
with 26 buckets it should be a zero if
you pass in Zacharias it should be 25
and so just as my cards were being
hashed to one of 1 2 3 four values now
these names are being hashed to one of
26 possibilities or 26 time 26 or 26 to
the 3 power if you have more and more
granularity than
that questions on this implementation
now of this idea of a hash
[Music]
table if uh if you say that again with
the
[Music]
null oh a good question so if there's so
much spareness there's all of these
empty cells in the array couldn't you
just go in and free them or delete them
or just kind of shrink the array and not
have a a AA and aab and a a only have
the prefixes two or three characters
that you need you absolutely could do
that but now what you you lose is the
arithmetic benefit of being able to map
each letter to a number if you start uh
freeing up unused space you don't know
that Zacharias is necessarily at
location 25 Albus is still going to be
at location zero but if you've deleted
some of the elements in the middle
Zacharias could be at 24 if you've
deleted one 23 if you've deleted another
and so you don't have that arithmetic
immediacy that you need in order to
index into the array with constant time
and the same is going to be true if it's
uh two letters or three letters you need
to be able to trust that you can do some
quick math and jump to the right index
in constant time and that's again the
appeal of these arrays so when it comes
to the running time of a hash table
inserting values into it searching for
values therein at the end of the day it
technically is Big O of n because in the
craziest case you might have a huge
fancy hash table but everyone in the
universe has a name starting with h and
then it just evolves into a really long
link list just like a binary search tree
could do the same but if you choose a
smarter hash function maybe you mitigate
that and you don't rely only on the
first letter but on the second or the
third as well or some other combination
of that input and make your hash
function smarter odds are if you get a
good hash function you want it get it to
be more of like order of n divided by K
where K means constant mathematically
and so K is the number of buckets so
ideally you want like a uniform
distribution you want like this many
people here this many people here you
don't want there to be some or no people
you want a uniform statistical
distribution and maybe you get that from
Human names maybe you don't but that's
kind of the challenge of a hash function
of course Big O of n over K is not a
thing because we always throw away
constants like K so it's still Big O of
n but again the distinction today is
that okay yes academically you learned
in cs50 that sure it's Big O ofin but my
God it's 26 times faster if you do the
hash function well and you spread
everyone out over the hash table and
that's the appeal of these kinds of
structures
and we've got one more for you if I may
something now known as a try so it turns
out that a try is even cooler if you
like this kind of thing in that it does
not devolve into Big O of n it is truly
constant time but there's going to be a
price there's going to be a gotcha a try
is sort of a fancier tree and it's short
for retrieval but pronounced try for
weird historical reasons but a try is a
tree each of whose nodes is an array
right so this is all like crazy mashups
now people started inventing data
structures just by combining different
ones unfortunately a lot of the good
ideas are taken but you just have
benefits from certain aspects of those
data structures and combining them
ideally gives you the best of both
worlds so to speak so here might be the
root of a try it's literally a big node
a big rectangle but it's actually an
array so there's like 26 locations in
this picture here and here's how you use
a try for instance to store names just
like the hash table it you treat each of
the elements of that array in that node
as like a letter of the alphabet so a
through z or 0 through 25 and if you
want to store someone's name in here you
do so as follows if you want to store
like uh an H you index into the H
location and if you want to store the
second letter of someone's name like an
a well you add another node below it and
such one is connected to the other and
you then identify the a in that array
and then you go on and maybe put a g if
the goal is to store spoiler now Hagrid
in this data structure and then the r
and the I and then the D but when you
get to the D the end of the name you
have to somehow flag that this is the
end of a name that we've embedded into
this data structure so whereas all of
these are called out in white just to
make obvious what we're connecting to
what green has to be like a bull that's
true that just indicates like the buck
stops here like d is the last letter in
someone's actual name and what's kind of
cool now about a try is that we can
repeat this for other names as well so
for instance here is where we might put
Harry as well and notice they share a
common prefix ha for Hagrid ha for Harry
so we're reusing some of these nodes
some of these arrays we can even slip
Hermione in here too borrowing only the
H but she gets the H then the E then r r
m i o n e and so forth and we Mark at
the end of her name too that she's in
there now what's the takeaway here well
what is the running time of a try how
many steps does it take to find someone
in this data structure and let me zoom
out so that it sort of suddenly becomes
a massive data structure with even more
in it uh maybe it looks sorry no I'll
keep it on this one maybe it looks a
little something like this with just
these three names but how many steps
does it take to find Hagrid or Harry or
Hermione no matter how many names are in
this data structure there's three at the
moment but it takes what h a g r i d so
six steps to find Hagrid uh h a r r y
five steps to find Harry h e r m i o n e
eight steps to find Hermione but notice
that those steps are only dependent on
what the lengths of the human's names
and let's assume that no one's going to
have a infinitely long name it's going
to max out at what like eight no maybe
eight 18 maybe 20 30 there's actually
some pretty long human names out there
but it's going to be finite you know
it's abounded whereas most contexts n
could grow forever so what's compelling
here is if you assume that the longest
name is I don't know 50 for the sake of
a theme here then you know that finding
anyone in this data structure will take
you no more than 50 steps 50 is thus a
constant which means you have big O of
one running time it doesn't matter if
there's a million people in this phone
book or a billion people in this phone
book that's going to definitely add more
nodes to it but it's still going to take
you h a r uh sorry h a g r i d six steps
to find Hagrid h a r r y five steps to
find Harry even if there's a billion
other people in that data structure so
now we actually do seem to have constant
time if you assume that there's going to
be a bound on the length of the name why
don't we use tries for everything then
what's the price we're paying for this
data structure even though we've
represented just three characters here
yeah it's a lot of memory yeah and you
can see it even with these three names
most of the squares on the screen are
empty like bites and bits that are there
and are allocated and they need to be
there because you need to be able to do
that arithmetic thing of this being zero
this being 25 so you can jump from boom
boom boom boom based on each of the
letters but it's a hugely sparse data
structure which means it takes up a
crazy amount of memory now maybe that's
tolerable especially for short names but
that's going to be the trade-off as well
and this is such a tension in Computing
almost any time you want to improve time
you want to speed up the efficiency the
speed of your algorithm you're going to
spend space if by contrast you want to
decrease the amount of space you might
very well have to increase the running
time it is indeed this seesaw back and
forth and you your colleagues your
company need to decide what resource is
the most precious heck it might be much
harder to code one of these data
structures than another you're a human
your time is valuable do you really want
to spend hours implementing a try when
you know hey in 30 minutes I can bang
out an array nowadays or a linked list
even there too development time is going
to be yet another resource and why
sometimes there's good code or bad code
it depends on what you're prioritizing
so what do each of these nodes look like
in a try well we can keep calling it a
node this is a very generic term for
just a container in these data
structures in this story though let me
claim that everyone has a number like a
phone number a string akhr star every
every node has 26 children or
technically an array of size 26 that can
point to more of these nodes notice that
I don't need to store the name of
someone in a try because it's implicit
in the path that you take to find them
so that's a minor optimization but it
saves us some space but this would be
just a different data structure we could
use to actually solve this problem as
well albeit at a very expensive cost and
what do we need our variable to be that
stores the try just like four we just
need a single pointer that hangs on to
the root of this structure that's null
if it's empty or non-null if it's
actually pointing at
something any questions then on
tries and if it's feeling like a lot the
fire the the fire hydrant it is we
started with arrays then link list then
tries but questions on how we've just
assembled from these basic building
blocks
[Music]
yeah a good question why is this not uh
size 26 uh it's just like with the try
just like with the link list before it
just tends to be en code convenient to
have a separate additional pointer
that's small that just points to the
beginning of the data structure because
that way it can be null thereby clearly
indicating there are no nodes the whole
structure is empty if you allocated one
of those nodes you absolutely could but
then you'd be just wasting space even if
it's empty and it creates an ambiguity
so just having a single pointer linked
to the beginnings of all of these things
is a good thing other questions now on
tries or trees or hash tables or
arrays so what problems might arise well
here's a counter example what names are
manifest in this try
here feel free to just call it
out what do you
see Danielle and Danielle so presumably
if these are two uh names here one of
which is a prefix of another notice that
the data structure still works and I
chose you know a friend's name and then
appended a couple of more characters to
it that's also a name because we have
here d a n i e l and the green
technically is implemented as a bull or
something like that that indicates a
word stops here but we don't want to
preclude storing Danielle as well who's
a super string if you will of Daniel and
so that's okay too so long as the
structure allows for the pointers to
keep going so even that works out okay
whereas it might not have otherwise and
in terms of the running time just to be
clear at the end of the day tries do
give you actual constant time for
insertions lookups deletions and the
like because it's dependent only on the
length of the input the key if you will
and not on how many other people are in
your phone or a dress book and now
thought we'd conclude with a visual if
you've gotten out into the square anyone
recognize this okay okay sweet green a
local salad place what are we looking at
here and what's its connection to today
um you're about to become all the
geekier in the real world cuz you will
start to see data structures
everywhere what is this or how does this
work maybe in salad form who's been to
Sweet
green okay either of you so how does
this
[Music]
work okay good so if you order a salad
for someone named L when it's ready they
put it in the l section here and so this
is kind of a set of key value pairs
right if L is the first letter of
someone's name the value hopefully is
the salad and so what you kind of have
here is a dictionary key value pairs
where it's not words and definitions
it's names and salads and you can think
of this too as kind of a hash table why
even though it actually doesn't fit on
one long shelf cu the store is only so
big this is really an array and
apparently a is missing or maybe it's
around around the corner but this array
just happens to wrap onto multiple lines
but it's still conceptually a single
Dimension but suppose two people have
the name L what do they do
typically yeah so maybe they they well
if they run put that much effort into it
they might look at the second letter and
then the third letter odds are this is
not that interesting a problem to solve
optimally in that way but they probably
do start stacking the salads on top of
each other maybe scooching it over just
a little bit and so what do you have
there well now you start to view the
lens through like cs50 glasses like okay
you have an array and then you have like
these link lists that are sort of
growing here but even then you run into
a problem why because it's not really a
link list because at some point you're
going to hit the boundary here so it's
kind of like an array of arrays because
you can only fit what like three or four
salads here and so long story short we
started today deliberately talking about
real world things like stacks and cues
and even though it did escalate quickly
into binary search trees and hash tables
and tries even those things are
everywhere even though they don't call
them as such these are just solutions to
problems and now with this final week of
SE under your belt you have all the more
of a technical toolkit via which to
implement these things and code next
week we'll be able to trust that someone
else solved all these problems we'll
introduce Python and lines of code like
this will finally become lines of code
like that so that's the promise ahead
and we'll see you next
[Applause]
[Music]
time
yeah
[Applause]
[Music]
yeah
all right this is cs50 and this is week
six wherein we finally transitioned from
scratch to see to now Python and indeed
this is going to be somewhat of a unique
experience in that just like a few weeks
past perhaps for the first time and now
uh today you're going to learn a new
language but the goal isn't just to
throw another fire hose of content and
syntax and whatnot at you but rather to
really equip you all to actually teach
yourself new languages in the future and
so indeed what we'll do today what we'll
do this coming week is sort of prepare
you to stand on your own and once python
is p a and the world has moved on to
some other language in some number of
years you'll be well equipped to figure
out how to wrap your mind around some
new syntax some new language and solve
problems as well now you recall in week
zero this is where we started just
saying hello to the world and that
quickly escalated just a week later in C
to see be something much much more
cryptic and if you've still sort of
struggled with some of the syntax find
yourself checking your notes or your
previous code like that's totally normal
and that's one of the reasons why there
are languages besides C out there among
them this language called python humans
over the decades have realized gee that
wasn't necessarily the best designed
decision or humans have realized wow you
know what now that computers have gotten
faster with more memory and more faster
CPUs we can actually do more with our
programming languages so just as human
languages evolve so do actual
programming languages and even within a
programming language there's typically
different versions We for instance have
been using version C11 of C which was
updated in 2011 um but python itself
continues to evolve and it's now up to
version three plus and so there too
these things will evolve in the coming
days thankfully what you're about to see
is hello world for the third time but
it's going to be literally this none of
the crazy syntax above or below fewer
semicolons if any fewer curly braces and
really a lot of the distractions get out
of the way so to get there let's
consider exactly how we've been
programming up until now so you write a
program in C and you've got hopefully no
syntax error so you're ready to build it
that is compil it and so you've run make
and then you've run the program like/
hello or if you think back to week two
where we took a peak underneath the hood
of what make is doing it's really
running the actual compiler something
called clang maybe with some command
line arguments creating a program called
hello and then you could do do/ hello so
today you're going to start doing
something similar in spirit but fewer
steps no longer will you have to compile
your code and then run it and then maybe
fix or change it and then compile your
code and run it and then repeat repeat
the process of running your code is
going to be distilled into just a single
step and the way to think of this for
now is that where a c is frequently used
as indeed a compiled language whereby
you convert it first to zeros and ones
Python's going to let you speed things
up whereby you the human programmer
don't have to compile it you're just
going to run what's called an
interpreter which by Design is named the
exact same thing as the language itself
and by running this program installed in
VSS code or eventually on your own Max
or PCS this is just going to tell your
computer to interpret this code and
figure out how to get down to that lower
level of zeros and ones but you don't
have to compile the code yourself
anymore so with that said let's consider
what the code is going to look like side
by side in fact let's look back at some
scratch blocks just like we did with C
in week one and do some side by sides
because even though some of the syntax
this week and Beyond's going to be
different like the ideas are truly going
to be the same there's not all that much
intellectually new just yet so whereas
in week zero we might have said hello to
the world with this purple puzzle piece
today of course uh or rather in week one
it looked like this in C but today
moving forward it's going to quite
simply look like this instead and if we
go back and forth for just a moment here
again is the version in C noticing the
very seike characteristics and just at a
glance here in Python I claim it's now
this what do you apparently need not
worry about
anymore what's gone so semicolon is gone
and indeed you don't need those to
finish most of your thoughts anymore
anything else so the back sln is absent
and that's kind of curious because we're
still going to get a new line but we'll
see that it's become the default and
this one's a little more subtle but now
the function is called print instead of
print F so it's a little more familiar
in that sense all right so when it comes
to using libraries that is code that
other people have written in the past
we've done things like hash include
cs50.h to use cs50's own header file or
standard IO or standard lib or string or
any number of other header files you
have all used well moving forward we're
going to give you for this first week a
similar cs-50 Library just very
short-term uh training wheels that will
quickly take off because in reality it's
a lot easier to do things in python as
we'll see but the Syntax for this now is
going to be to import the cs50 library
in this way and when we have now this
ability we can actually start writing
some code right away in fact let me
switch over to vs code here and just as
in the past I'll create a new file but
instead of creating something called C
I'm going to go ahead and create my
first program called hello.py using Code
space hello.py that of course gives me
this new tab and let me actually quite
simply do what I proposed print quote
unquote hello world without the back
slash without the semicolon without the
F in print and now let me go down to my
terminal window and I don't have to
compile it I don't have to do dot slash
i instead run a program called python
whose purpose in life is now to
interpret my code top to bottom left to
right and if I run python of hello.py
crossing my fingers as always voila now
I have printed out hello world so we
seem to have gotten the new line for
free in this sense where it's
automatically happening the dollar sign
isn't weirdly on the same line like it
want was in week one but that's just a a
minor detail here if we switch back to
now some other capabilities well indeed
with the cs50 library you can also not
just import the library itself but
specific functions and you'll see that
temporarily we're going to give you a
helper function called get string just
like in C that just makes it work
exactly the same way as in C and we'll
see a couple of other functions that
will just make life easier initially but
quickly will we take those training
wheels off so that nothing is indeed
cs50 specific all right well how about
functions more generally in Python let's
do a whirlwind tour if you will much
like we did in that first week of C
comparing one to the other so back in
our world of scratch one of the first
programs we wrote was this one here
whereby we asked the human their name we
then used the return value that was sort
of automatically stored in this answer
variable as a second argument to join so
that we could say hello David or hello
Carter so this was back in week one uh
week zero in week one we converted it to
this and here's a perfect example of
things like escalating quickly and again
this is why we start in scratch there's
just so much distraction here to achieve
the same idea but even today we're going
to chip away at some of that syntax so
in C we had to declare the argument as a
we had to declare the variable as a
string here we of course had the
semicolon and more well in Python the
comparable code now is going to look
more simply like this so semicolon is
again gone on both lines for that matter
so that's good what else appears to have
changed or disappeared yeah type of
variable yeah so I didn't have to
specifically say that answer is now a
string and indeed python is is
dynamically typed and in fact it will
infer from Context exactly what it is
you are storing in that variable other
details that seem a little bit
different little bit different what else
jumps out at you here I'll go back this
was the C version and maybe Focus now on
the second line because we've rather
exhausted the first here's now the
python version what's different here
yeah yeah there's no percent s anymore
there's no second argument at the moment
per se to print now it is still a little
weird it's as though I've like deployed
some addition here arithmetically but
that's not the case some of you have
programmed before and plus some of you
might know means what in this
context so to combine or more
technically anyone know the buzz word
yeah
to concatenate so to concatenate is like
the fancy way of what scratch calls
joining which is to take one string on
the left one string on the right and to
join them together to glue them together
if you will so this is not addition it
would be if it were numbers involved
instead but because we've got a string
hello comma and another string
implicitly in this variable based on
what the human typed in in response to
this get string function that's going to
concatenate hello comma space and then
David or Carter or whatever the human
has typed in but turns out there's going
to be different ways to do this in
Python and we'll show you a few
different ones and here too try not to
get too hung up on or frustrated by like
all of the different ways you can solve
problems odds are you're going to be
picking up tips and techniques for years
to come if you continue programming so
let's just give you a few of the
possible ways so here's a second way you
could print out hello comma David or
hello comma Carter but what has changed
in the previous version I used
concatenation explicitly and the space
here is important grammatically just so
we get that in the final phrase
now I'm proposing to get rid of that
space to add a comma outside of the
double quotes as well but if you think
back to C this probably just means that
print similar in spirit to print F can
take not just one argument but even two
and in fact because of this comma in the
middle that's outside of the double
quotes it's hello comma and then it will
be automatically concatenated with even
without using the plus to whatever the
value of answer is and by default just
for grammatical prettiness the print fun
function always gives you a space for
free in between each of the multiple
arguments you pass in we'll see how you
can override that down the line but for
now that's just another way to do it now
perhaps the better if slightly cryptic
way to do this or just the increasingly
common way is probably this third
version which looks a little weird too
and probably the weirdness jumps out
we've automatic we've suddenly
introduced these like Curly braces which
I promised were mostly gone and they are
but inside of this string here I've done
a curly brace which might mean what just
intuitively and here is sort of an
example of how you learn a new language
just kind of infer from Context how
python probably
works what might this mean yeah able to
tell that this is not one of the actual
stat
inside yeah so this is an indication
because the curly braces because this is
the way python was designed that we want
to plug in the value of answer not
literally a ANS w r and the fancy word
here is that the answer variable will be
interpolated that is substituted with
its actual value but but but and this is
actually weird looking and this was
introduced a few years ago to python
what else did I have to change to make
these curly braces work
apparently
yeah yeah there's this weird F and so
it's sort of like part of print F but
now it's inside the curly it's inside
the parenthesis there this is just the
way python designed this so a few years
ago when they introduced what are called
format strings or F strings you
literally prefix your quoted string with
the uh letter F and then you can use
trickery like this like putting curly
braces so that the value will be
substituted automatically if you forget
the F you're going to literally see
hello comma curly brace answer close
curly brace if you add the F it's indeed
interpolated the value is plugged in all
right questions on how we can just say
hello to the world via python in this
case
yeah if you do this without the without
the F if you omit the F you will
literally see c h e l l o comma curly
brace a NS w r close curly brace so in
fact let's do this let me go back to vs
code here quickly I've still got my file
called hello.py open and let me go ahead
and change this ever so slightly so I'm
going to go ahead and uh let's say from
cs50 import get string and that's just
the new syntax I propose using to import
a function from someone else's Library
I'm going to now go ahead and ask the
question uh let's go ahead and use get
string storing the result and answer so
get string quote unquote what's your
name question mark and then on this line
I'm going to deliberately make a mistake
here exactly to your question let me
just say hello comma answer and just
this now even though answer is a
variable Python's not going to be so
presumptuous as to just plug in the
value of a variable called answer what
it's going to do of course is if I type
in my name whoops I typed too fast let
me go ahead and rerun that again if I
run python of hello.py type in my name
and hit enter I get hello comma answer
well let me do one better let me apply
these curly braces as before let me
rerun python of hello.py What's Your
Name daav ID and here's again the answer
to your question now we get literally
the curly braces so the fix here
ultimately is just going to be to add
the F there rerun my program again with
daav ID and now hello comma David so
this is admittedly a little more cryptic
than the ones with the Plus the comma
but this is just increasingly common why
because you can read it left to right
it's nice and convenient it's less
cryptic than the percent s's so it's
sort of a new and improved version if
you will of printf in C based on Decades
of experience of programmers doing
things like this questions on printing
in this
way we're now on our way to programming
in
Python anything all right well what more
can we do with this language here well
let me propose that we consider that we
have for
instance a few other features that we
can add to the mix as well
namely let's say some data types as well
so let me flip over here to um back to
the slides and there's different data
types in python as we'll soon see but
they're not as explicit as we already
saw by using a string from get string
you don't have to explicitly State what
it is but you solve recall and see all
of these various data types and then in
python kind of nicely enough this list
is about to get shorter and so here is
our list in C here is an abbreviated
list in Python so we're still going to
have strings but they're going to be
more succinctly called stirs now St Str
we're still going to have in for
integers we're still going to have
floats for floating Point values we're
even going to have bulls for true and
false but what's missing now from the
list is long and floats and why is that
or rather long and double well recall
that in C those used more bits well in
Python the smaller data types previously
int and Float themselves just use more
bits for you and so you don't need to
distinguish between small and large you
just use one data type and the language
gives you a bigger range than before it
turns out though there's going to be
some other features as well of python
these data types one of which will be
called range another of which will be
list So Gone will be arrays we'll
actually use something literally called
a list tle sort of like XY pairs for
coordinates and things like that uh dict
for dictionaries so we have built-in
capabilities for storing keys and values
we'll see and even a set sort of
mathematically a set is like a
collection of values but it
automatically gets rid of duplicates for
you so all of these things we could
absolutely Implement in C if we wanted
and indeed in problem set five you've
been implementing your very own spell
checker using some form of hashtable
well it turns out that in Python you can
solve those same problems but perhaps a
little more readily in fact let me go
back over here to vs code and let me
propose that I do the following let me
go ahead and create a file called
dictionary. let me propose that I try to
implement say problem set five our spell
checker in Python instead of c and
Achieve ultimately the same kind of
behavior uh whereby I'll be able to
spell check a whole bunch of words so
this is jumping the gun a little bit
because you're about to see syntax will
revisit over the course of today but for
now I've got a new file called
dictionary. py and let me begin to
create uh some placehold ERS for
functions we'll see in just a bit that
in Python you can define a function
called check and that check function can
take a word as it's input and I'll come
back to this in just a moment in Python
I can define a second function like load
which itself will take a whole
dictionary just like in problem set five
and I'll go ahead and come back to the
implementation of this meanwhile we
might similarly Implement a function
called size which takes no arguments but
ultimately is going to return the size
of my dictionary of words and then last
lastly for consistency with problem set
five we might Define an unload function
whose purpose in life is to free any
memory that you've been using just to
give it back to the computer now odds
are whether you're still working on
speller or half finished speller like
you wrote a decent amount of lines of
code and indeed it's been by design a
challenge but one of the reasons for
these higher level languages like python
is that you can stand on the shoulders
of programmers before you and solve very
common problems much more quickly so
that you can f us on building your new
app or your web application or your own
project to solve problems of interest to
you so at the risk of crushing some
Spirits let me propose that in Python if
you want a dictionary for something like
a spell checker well that's fine go
ahead and give yourself a variable like
words to store all of those words and
just assign it equal to a dictionary or
dict for short in Python that will give
you a hashtable now it turns out in
speller recall you don't need to worry
about words and definition conditions
it's just about spellchecking the words
so strictly speaking we don't need keys
and values we just need keys so I'm
going to save myself a few more key
strokes by just saying that technically
in Python using a set suffices again a
set is just a collection of values with
no duplicates but they don't necessarily
have uh keys and values it's just one or
the other but now that I have on line
one I claim the equivalent in Python of
a hash table I can actually do something
like this here's how I might implement
the check function in Python if the word
passed into this function is in my
variable called words well return true
else go ahead and return false done wait
you're thinking if anything at all maybe
we want to handle lowercase instead of
just uppercase and lowercase well you
know what in Python if you want to force
a whole word to lowercase you don't have
to iterate over it with a loop you don't
have to use any of that ctype functions
or anything just say word. lower and
that will convert the whole thing to
lowercase for parody with the dictionary
all right how about something like the
load function in Python well in Python
you can open files just like in C for
instance in Python I might do open the
dictionary argument in read mode just
like fopen in Python I might do
something like this for each line in
that file let me go ahead and add to my
words variable that line and then let me
go ahead and close that file and I think
I'm done I'm just going to go ahead and
return true just because I think think
I'm already done now here too I could
nitpick a little bit technically if I'm
reading in every line from the file
every line in the dictionary ends with
technically a back sln but there's an
easy way to get rid of that uh just like
you might in see with an alternative
syntax what I'm actually going to do is
this let me grab from the current line
the current word by stripping off with
reverse strip R strip a function will
again see that just gets rid of the
trailing new line the back sln at the
end of that line and what I really want
to do then is add this word to that
dictionary meanwhile if I want to figure
out what the size is of my dictionary
well and see you're probably writing
code to iterate over all of those lines
and you're just going to uh count them
up using a variable not so in Python you
can just return the length of those
words and better still in Python you
don't have to manage your own memory no
more Malo no more free no more manual
thinking about memory the language just
deals with all of that for you so you
know what it suffices for me to just
return true and claim that unloading is
done for me and that's it again whether
you're in the middle of or already
finished this might perhaps suggest some
frustration but also Enlightenment in
this in that this is why higher level
languages exist you can build on top of
the same principles the same ideas with
which you've been dealing struggling
even this past week but you can now
express yourself all the more succinctly
like this one line implements a hash
table for you and all of this now now
just uses that hash table in a simpler
way any questions now on this keeping in
mind that the point nonetheless of
speller and P said 5 is to understand
what's really going on underneath the
hood and better still to notice this
this might seem all rather amazing but
let me go ahead and do this I've
actually got a couple of versions of
speller written here and I've got a
version written in C that I won't show
the source code for but I'm going to go
ahead and make that version of speller
in C and I'm going to go ahead here and
let's say split my window here for just
a moment and I'm going to go into a
python version of spell really that I
just wrote and on the left hand side
here let me go ahead and run speller the
version I compiled in C using a big text
like uh the Sherlock Holmes text which
is a whole lot of words in it and on the
right hand side let me run python of
spell. Pi which is a separate file I
wrote in advance just like we give you
speller.c and I'll similarly run this on
the Sherlock Holmes text and I'm going
to do my best to hit enter on the left
and the right of my screen at the same
time but we should see hopefully the
same list of misspelled words and the
timings thereof so here we go on the
right here we go on the
left all right sort of a race to see
which one wins here C is on the left
python is on the right okay
interesting hopefully Python's close
behind note that some of the is internet
delay and so it might not necessarily be
a crazy number of seconds but the system
is indeed using if we measure at a low
level how much time the CPU spent
executing my code C took a total of 1.64
seconds that was pretty fast even though
it took a moment more for all of the
btes to come over the Internet the
python version though took what 2.44
seconds so what might an inference be I
mean one maybe I'm just better at
programming in c than I am in Python
which is probably not true
but what else might you infer from this
example should we maybe give up on
python stick with
C no so where what might be going on
here like why is the python version that
I claim is correct and I think the
numbers all line up just not the
times where's the trade-off here well
here again is sort of this design
tradeoff
yeah yeah exactly in order to save the
human programmer time there's a lot more
features built into python more
functions more automatic management of
memory and so forth and you have to pay
a price like someone else's code is
doing all of that work for you but if
they've written some number of lines of
code those are just more lines of code
that need to be executed for you whereas
here the computer is at the risk of
oversimplifying only running my lines of
code so there's just less overhead and
so this is a Perpetual trade-off
typically when using a more userfriendly
and more modern language one of the
prices you might pay is performance now
there's a lot of smart computer
scientists in the world though trying to
push back on those same tradeoffs and so
these interpreters like the command I
wrote python technically can especially
if you run a program again and again
they can actually sort of secretly
behind the scenes compile your code for
you down to zeros and ones and then the
second the third the fourth time you run
that program it might very well be
faster so this is a bit of a head fake
here in that I'm running them once and
only once but we could get benefit over
time if we kept running the python
version again and again and perhaps
fine-tune the performance but in general
there's going to be this trade-off now
would you rather spend the 60 seconds I
wrote implementing a spell checker or
the 6 hours 16 hours you might be or
have spent implementing the same and C
you know probably not for productivity
sake this is why we have these
additional languages just for fun let me
flip over to another screen here and
open up a version of python that's
actually on on my in just a second on my
own uh Mac instead of the cloud so that
I can actually do something with
Graphics so here I just have a black and
white terminal window on my very own Mac
and I've pre-installed python just like
we've done so for VSS code in the cloud
for you uh notice that I've got this uh
photo of uh perhaps one of your favorite
TV shows here with the cast of The
Office notice all of the faces in this
image here and let me propose that we
try to find one face in the crowd sort
of CSI style whereby we want to find
perhaps the stranton Strangler so to
speak and so here is an example of this
this guy's face now how do we go about
finding this specific face in the crowd
well our human eyes obviously can pluck
him out especially if you're familiar
with the show but let me go ahead and do
this instead let me go ahead and propose
that we run code that I already wrote in
advance here this is a Python program
with more lines of code that we won't
dwell on for today but it's meant to
motivate what we can do from a a pillow
uh Library implying a python image
Library I want to import some type of
information called some type of some
feature called image so that I can
manipulate images not unlike our own
problem set 4 and this is kind of
powerful you in Python you can just
import face recognition as a library
that someone else wrote from there I'm
going to create a variable called image
I'm going to use this face recognitions
libraries load image file function it's
a little verbose but it's similar in
Spirit to F open and I'm going to open
office. jpeg I'm going to then declare a
second variable called face locations
plural because what I'm expecting to get
back per the documentation for this
library is a list of all of the faces
locations that are detected all right
then I'm going to iterate over each of
those uh faces using a for Loop that
we'll see in more detail I'm going to
then infer what the top right bottom and
left Corners are of that face and then
what I'm going to do here is show that
face alone if I've detected the face in
question so let me go ahead here and run
detect. and we'll see not just the one
face we're looking for but if I run
python of detect. piy it's going to do
all of the analysis I'll see a big
opening here now of all of the faces
that were detected in this here program
okay some better than others I guess if
you zoom in on catching someone typical
Angela if you now want to Now find that
one face I think we need to train the
software a bit more so let me actually
open up a second program called
recognize that's got more going on but
let me with a wave of a hand point out
that I'm now loading not only the
office. JPEG but also toby. JPEG to sort
of train the algorithm to find that
specific face and so now if I run this
second version recognize. with python of
recognize. py hold my breath for just a
moment it's an analyzing presumably all
of the faces you see the same original
photo but do you see one such face
highlighted here this adversion of the
code found Toby highlighted him with
this green and voila we have face
recognition so for better for worse this
is what's happening increasingly
societally nowadays and honestly even
though I didn't write the code live
because it's a good dozen or more lines
of code it's not terribly many and
literally all the authorities all we
have to do is import face recognition
and voila you have access like these
techn IES are here already but let's
consider for just a moment how did we
find Toby like how might that Library
even though we're not going to look at
its implementation details how does it
find Toby and distinguish him from all
of these other faces in the crowd what
might it be doing
intuitively think back even to pet 4
like what you yourselves have access to
data wise
yeah you know pixels in one area area
and a lot
of
that it's a lot of a lot of
simar yeah exactly and to summarize for
for camera here we have trained the
software if you will by giving it a
photo of Toby's face by so by looking
for the same or really similar pixels
especially if it's a slightly different
image of Toby we can perhaps identify
him in the crowd and what really is a
human face well at the end of the day
the computer only knows it as a pattern
of bits or really at a higher level a
pattern of pixels so maybe a human face
is perhaps best defined in general as
like two eyes and a nose and a mouth
that even though all of us look similar
structurally odds are the measurement
between the eyes and the nose and the
width of the mouth the skin tone and all
of these other physical characteristics
are patterns that software could perhaps
detect and then look sort of
statistically through the image looking
for the closest possible match to these
various measurement shapes colors and
sizes and the like and indeed that might
might be the intuition but what's
powerful here again is just how easy and
readily available this technology now is
all right so with that said let's
propose to consider what more we can do
with python itself get back to the
fundamentals so that you yourselves can
start to implement something along those
same lines so besides having access to
things like a get string function um the
cs50 library provides a few other things
as well namely in C we had these but in
Python we're going to have fewer in
Python our library short term is going
to give you not only get string but also
get in and get float why it's actually
just kind of annoying as we'll student
see to get back an integer or a float
from a user and just make sure that it's
an INT and a float and not like a word
like cat or dog or some string that's
not actually a number well we can import
not just the specific function get
string but we can actually import all of
these functions one at a time like this
as we'll soon see or you can even in
Python import specific functions from a
file one of you asked a while back when
you import when you include something
like cs50.h or standard i.h you're
actually getting all of the code in that
file which potentially can add bulk to
your own program or time in this case
when you import specific functions from
python you can be a little more narrowly
uh precise as to what it is you want to
have access to all right so with that
said let's go ahead and see what
conditionals look like in Python so in
the left hand side again here we'll see
scrp
and here for instance was just kind of a
contrived example asking if x is less
than y then say x is less than y in C it
looked like this in Python now it's
going to look like this instead and
here's before in C and here's after and
just to call out a few of the obvious
differences what has changed in Python
for conditionals it would
seem sort of what's the difference
yeah yeah so there's no more curly
braces and indeed you don't use those
what appears to be taking their place if
you might
infer what seems to have taken their
place what do you think so the colon at
the start of this line here but also
even more important now is this
indentation below it so some of you and
we know this from Office hours have a
habit of like uh indenting everything on
the left right and it's just kind of
this crazy mess to look at frustrating
for you surely but C and clang is pretty
tolerant when it comes to things like
Whit space in a program python uh-uh
they realized years ago that let's help
humans help themselves and just require
standard indentation so four spaces
would be the norm here but because it's
indented below that colon that indeed
indicates that this now is part of that
condition something else has gone
missing versus C in this conditional
what else is a little
simplified yeah so no more parentheses
you can still use them especially when
you need to logically to do order of
operations like in math but in this case
if you just want to ask a simple
question like if x less than y you can
just do it like that how about when you
have an if else well this is almost the
same here with these same changes in C
this looked like this and it's starting
to get a bit bulky at least if we use
our curly braces in this way in Python
we can tighten things up further even
though strictly speaking in C you don't
always need the curly braces but here
gone are the parentheses again gone are
the curly braces indentation is
consistent and we've just added another
keyword else with a colon but no more
semicolons as well how about something
larger like this and if else if else
this one's a little curious but in C it
looked like this if else if else in
Python it now looks like this and
there's perhaps one curiosity here that
honestly all these years later I still
can't remember how to spell it half the
time what's weird about
this what do you spot as
different uh yeah over
here yeah instead of else if it's l if
why apparently El space if was just too
many keystrokes for humans to type so
they condensed it into this way probably
means it's a little more distinguishable
too for the computer between the if and
the else to but just something to
remember now it's indeed L if and not
else if all right so what about
variables in Python I've used a couple
of them already but let's let's um
distill exactly how you define uh and
declare these things as well so in
scratch if we wanted to create a
variable called counter and set it equal
initially to zero we would do something
like this specify that it's an INT use
the assignment op operator and the
thought with a semicolon in Python it's
just simpler you name the variable you
use the assignment operator as before
you set it equal to some value and
that's it you don't mention the type you
don't mention the semicolon or anything
more what if you want to change a
variable like the counter by one that is
incremented by one you have a few
different ways here in C we saw syntax
like this where you can say counter
equals counter plus one which again
feels like illogical how can counter
equal counter plus one but again we read
this code really right to left updating
its value by one um in Python it's
almost the same you just get rid of the
semicolon so that logic is there but
recall in C we could do something
slightly different that we can also do
in Python in Python you can also more
succinctly do this plus equals and then
whatever number you want to add or you
can even change it to subtract if you
prefer sadly gone is something you've
probably typed a whole lot what was the
other way you can add
one Plus+ is no more sadly in Python
just too many ways to do the same thing
so they got rid of it in favor of just
this syntax here so keep that in mind as
well what about loops when you want to
do something in Python again and again
well in scratch in week zero here's how
we meowed three times specifically in C
we had a couple of ways of doing this
this was like the more mechanical
approach where you create a variable
called I you set it equal to zero you
then do while I is less than three the
following and then you yourself
increment I again and again mechanical
in the sense that like you have to
implement all of these gears and make
them turn yourself but this was a
correct way to do that in Python we can
still achieve the same idea but we don't
need the int keyword we don't need any
of the semicolons we don't need the
parentheses we don't need the curly
braces we can't use the Plus+ so maybe
that's a minor step backwards if you're
a fan but otherwise the code the logic
is exactly the same but there's other
ways to achieve this same idea recall
that in C we could also do this you
could use a for Loop which it does
exactly the same thing both are correct
both are arguably welld designed it's
kind of to each their own when it comes
to choosing between these in Python
though we're going to have to think
through how to do this so you don't do
the same for loop as in C the closest I
could come up with is this where you say
four I or whatever variable you want to
do the counting in literally the
preposition and then you use square
brackets here and we've used square
brackets before in the context of like
arrays and things like that and the 012
looks like an array in some sense even
though we've also seen arrays with curly
braces but these square brackets for now
denote a list python does not have
arrays an array is that contiguous chunk
of memory back to back to back that you
have to resize somehow by moving things
around in memory as per two weeks ago in
Python though you can just create a list
like this using square brackets and
better still as we'll see you can add or
even remove things from that list down
the road um this though is not going to
be very welld designed this will work
this will iterate in Python three
times but what might rub you the wrong
way about this design even if you've
never seen python before how does this
example not end well
yeah yeah like if you're making a large
list you have to type out each one of
these numbers like comma three comma
four comma 5 comma dot dot do 50 comma
dot dot dot 500 like surely that's not
the best solution to have all of these
numbers on the code on the screen
wrapping endlessly on the screen so in
Python another way to do this would be
to use a function called range which
technically is a data type unto itself
and this returns to you as many values
as you ask for it range takes some other
arguments as well but the simplest use
case here is if you want back the
numbers 0 1 and two a total of three
values you say hey python please give me
a range of three values and by default
they start at zero on up but this is
more efficient than it would be to
hardcode the entire list at once and the
best metaphor I could up with is
something like this like here for
instance is a deck of cards this is sort
of normal human size and there's
presumably 52 cards here so writing out
0 through 51 on code would be a little
ridiculous for the reasons you know it
would just be very unwieldy and ugly and
wrapping and all of that it would be the
phys it would be the virtual equivalent
of me like handing you all of these
cards at once to just deal with and
right you know they're not that big but
like it's a lot of cards to hold on to
it requires a lot of memory or physical
storage if you will what range does
metaphorically is if you ask me for
three cards I hand you them one at a
time like this so that at any point in
time you only have one number in the
computer's memory until you're handed
the next the alternative the previous
version would be to hand me all three
cards at once or all 52 cards at once
but in this case range is just way more
efficient you can do range of a thousand
that's not going to give you a list of a
thousand values all at once it's going
to give you a thousand values one at a
time reducing memory sign signicantly in
the computer itself all right so besides
this what about doing something forever
in scratch well we could do this
literally with a forever block which
didn't quite exist in C in C we had had
to hack it together by saying while true
because true is by definition TR always
true so this just in uh deliberately
induces an infinite Loop for us in
Python the logic's going to be almost
the same and infinite Loops in Python
tend to actually be even more common
because you can always break out of them
as you couldn't see in Python it looks
like this and this is slightly more
subtle but gone are the curly braces
gone or the parentheses but ever so
slight difference
toal capital T for true and it's going
to be a capital f for false stupid
little differences eventually you're
going to mistype one or the other but
these are the kinds of things to keep an
eye out and to start recognizing in your
mind's eye when you read code questions
now on any of these building
blocks
yeah
I in the for Loop was I re uh it was set
to zero on the first iteration then one
on the next then two on the third and
the same thing for range it just doesn't
use up as much memory all at once other
questions now on any of these building
blocks of
python no all right well let's go ahead
and build something a little more than
hello let me propose that over here we
Implement maybe the the simplest of
calculators here so let me go back to vs
code here open my terminal uh window and
open up say a file called
calculator. and in calculator. we'll
have an opportunity to explore some of
these building blocks but we'll allow
things to escalate pretty quickly to
more interesting examples so that we can
do the same thing ultimately as well and
in fact let me go ahead and do this
moreover I've brought some code with me
in advance uh for instance something
called calculator 0. C from the first
week of C
and let me go ahead and split my window
here in fact so that I can now do
something like uh this let me move this
over here here calculator. Pi so now I
have on the left of my screen
calculator. C or calculator z.c because
that's the first version I made and
calculator. Pi on the right let me go
ahead and Implement really the same idea
here so on the right hand side the
analog of including cs50.h would be from
cs50 import get int if I want to indeed
use this function now I'm going to go
ahead and give myself a variable X
without defining its type I'm going to
use this get int function and I'm going
to prompt the user for X just like in C
I'm then going to go ahead and prompt
the user for another int like y here
just like in C and at the very end I'm
going to go ahead and do print X Plus Y
and that's it now granted I have some
comments in my C version of the code
just to remind you of what each line is
doing but I've still distilled this into
like six lines or really four if I get
rid of the blank line so it's already
perhaps a bit tighter here here but
there's also it's tighter because
something really important historically
is missing what did I seem to Omit
altogether that we haven't really
highlighted yet
yeah yeah the main function is gone and
in fact maybe you took for granted that
it just worked a moment ago when I wrote
hello but I didn't have a main function
in hello either and this too is a
feature of python and a lot of other
languages as well instead of having to
adhere to these long-standing Traditions
if you just want to write code and get
something done fine just write code and
get something done without necessarily
all of the same boiler plate so whatever
is in your python file left indented if
you will by default is just going to be
the code that The Interpreter runs top
to bottom left to right well let me go
ahead now and run code like this let me
go ahead and open that back up my
terminal window run python of
calculator. piy and I'll do X is one y
is 2 and as you might expect it gives me
three slight aesthetic bug I put my
space in the wrong place here so that's
a new mistake let me fix that
aesthetically let me rerun python of
calculator. Pi type in one type in two
and voila there is now my same version
again but let me propose now that we get
rid of this training wheel we don't want
to keep taking one step forward and then
two steps back by adding these training
wheels so let me instead do this in my
version of calculator. suppose that we
take away already the training wheel
that is the cs50 library here and let me
instead then use just Python's built-in
function called input which literally
does just that it gets input from the
user and it stores it as before in X and
Y so this is not cs50 specific this is
real world Python Programming well let
me go ahead and run again python of
calculator. Pi and of course if x is one
and Y is 2 X + Y should of course still
be three
hm it's apparently 12 according to
python until cs50's Library gets
involved but does anyone want to
infer what's just went wrong
yeah exactly the input function by
Design always returns a string of text
after all that's what the human typed in
and even though yes I type the number
keys on the keyboard it's still coming
back is all text now maybe we should use
like a get in function well that doesn't
exist in Python all you can do is get
textual input a string from the user but
we can convert one to the other and so a
fix for this so that we don't accident
Al concatenate that is join X+ y
together would be to do something like
this let me go back to my python code
here and whereas in C we could
previously do type casting we could
convert one type to another that
generally wasn't the case when you were
doing something complex like a string to
an INT you could do a Char to an INT and
vice versa but for a string recall there
was a special function in the ctype
library called a to I like ask e to
integer that's uh that closest analog
here and in fact the way to do this in
Python would be to use a function called
int which indeed is the name of the data
type 2 even though I have not yet had to
type it and I can convert the output of
the input function automatically from a
string immediately to an INT and now if
I go back to my terminal window rerun
python of calculator. piy with one and
two for X and Y now I'm back in business
so that then is for instance what the
cs50 library does if temporarily this
week is it just deals with the
conversion for you and in fact bad
things could happen if I type the wrong
thing like dog or cat instead of a
number but we'll cross that bridge in
just a moment as well all right what if
we do something slightly different now
with our calculator instead of just
addition let me go ahead and do how
about uh div instead of addition let's
do division instead so Z equals x / y
thereby giving me a third variable Z let
me go ahead and run python of
calculator. piy again I'll type in one
I'll type in three this time and what
prog what problem do you think we're
about to
see or is it gone what happened when I
did this in C albeit with some slightly
more cryptic syntax when I divided one
number like one one divided by
three anyone recall
yeah yeah so it would round down to the
nearest integer whereby you experience
trunc so if you take an integer like one
you divide it by another integer like
three that technically should be
0.33333 infinitely long but in uh C
recall you truncate the value if you
divide an INT by an INT you get back an
INT which means you get only the integer
part which was the zero now python
actually handles this for us and avoids
the truncation but it leaves us still
with one other problem here which is
going to be for instance not necessarily
visible at a GL
this looks correct this has solved the
problem in C so truncation does not
happen the integers are automatically
converted to a float a floating point
value but what other problem did we trip
over back
in week uh
one what else got a little dicey when
dealing with simple
arithmetic anyone recall well the syntax
in Python's a little different but let
me go ahead and do this it turns out in
Python if you want to see more
significant digits than what I'm seeing
here by the default which is a dozen or
so let me go ahead and print out Z as
follows let me first print out a format
string because I want to format Z in an
interesting way and notice this would
have no effect on the difference this is
just a format string that for no
compelling reason at the moment is
interpolating z in those curly braces
using an F string or format string if I
run this again with one and three we'll
see indeed the exact same thing but when
you use an F string you indeed have the
ability to format that string more
precisely just like with percent F in
Python you could start to fine-tune how
many significant digits you see in uh p
in C rather in Python you can do the
same but the syntax is a little
different if you want the computer to
interpolate Z and show you 50
significant digits that is 50 numbers
after the decimal point syntax is
similar to C but it's a little different
you literally put a colon after the
variable's name 50 means show me the
decimal point and then 50 digits to the
right and the F just indicates please
treat this as a floating point value so
now if I rerun python of calculator. Pi
divide 1 by 3 unfortunately python has
not solved all of the world's problems
for us this again was an example of
floating point in Precision so that
problem is still latent so just because
the world has advanced doesn't
necessarily mean that all of our
problems from C have gone away there are
solutions using third-party libraries
for scientific calculations and the like
but out of the box floating point in
Precision is still an issue meanwhile
there was one other problem in C that we
ran into involving numbers and that was
this integer overflow recall that an
integer in C only took up what like 32
bits typically which meant you could
count as high as four billion or maybe
if you're doing positive and negatives
as high as two billion after which weird
things would happen the number would go
to zero or negative or just it would
overflow or wrap back around well
wonderfully in Python they did it at
least address this whereby you can count
as high as you want and python will just
use more and more and more and more bits
and bites to store really big numbers so
integer overflow is not a thing with
that said python is limited to how many
digits it will show you on the screen at
once as a string but mathematically your
math will be correct now so we've taken
a couple steps forward One Step sideways
but indeed we've solved some of our
problems here all right questions now
now on any of these examples thus
far
question all right well how about uh how
about another problem that we
encountered in C let's revisit it here
in python as well so let me go ahead and
on the left hand side here let me open
up a file called say compare let's see
uh how about a file called compare 3. C
on the left and let me go ahead and
create a new file on the right called
compare. Pi because recall that bad
things happened when we needed to
compare two values in C so on the left
here is a reminder of what we once did
in C whereby if we want to compare
values we can get an INT in C stored in
x a get int in C stored in y we then
have our familiar conditional logic here
just printing out if x is less than y or
not well we can certainly do the same
thing ultimately in Python by using some
fairly familiar syntax and let's just
demonstrate this one quickly let me go
over here too I'll do from cs50 import
uh get int even though I could do this
instead with the input function itself x
equals get int and I'll prompt the user
for that y equals get int and I'll
prompt the user for that after that
recall that I can say without
parentheses if x is less than y then
print out without the F uh X is less
than y then I can go ahead and say else
if x is greater than y i can print out
uh quote unquote X is greater than y if
you'd like to interject now what did I
screw
up anyone yeah L if right so L if L if x
is greater than y else this part's the
same print X is equal to Y so there's
not all that much new there's no New
Logic going on here but at least
syntactically it's a little cleaner
indeed this program is only 11 lines
long albeit without any comments let me
go ahead and run python of compare. Pi
let's see is 1 less than two indeed
let's run it again is 2 less than 1 no
it's greater than and let's lastly type
in one and one twice X is equal to Y so
we've got a pretty side by side onetoone
conversion here let's do something a
little more interesting then and see how
about I open instead something where we
actually compared for a purpose so if I
open up from last uh from earlier in the
course how about uh agree do C which
prompt the user to agree to something or
not and let me code up a new version
here called agree. pi and I'll do this
on the right hand side with agree. pi
but on gree do c on the left notice that
this is how we did this sort of yes no
thing in C we compared c a character
equal to single quotes y or equal to
single quotes little Y and then the same
thing for n now in Python this one's
actually going to be a little bit
different here let me go ahead and in
the python version of this let me do
something like this uh we'll use get
string uh actually no we'll just use
input in this case so let's do uh s
equals input and we'll ask the user the
same thing do you agree question mark
then let's go ahead and say if s equals
equals how about uh
y huh how do I do this well a few things
turns out I'm going to do this s equals
equals little y then I'm going to go
ahead and print out a agreed and L if s
equals equals capital N or S equals
equals lowercase n I'm going to go ahead
and print out not agreed and I claimed
for the moment that this is identical
now to the program on the right the
program on the left in C but what's
different so we're still doing the same
kind of logic these equal equals for
comparing for equality but notice that
nicely enough python got rid of the two
vertical bars and it's just literally
the word or if you recall seeing
Ampersand Ampersand to express a logical
and in C you can just write literally
the word and and so here's a hint of why
python tends to be pretty popular people
just like that it's a little closer to
English there's a little less of the
cryptic syntax here now this is correct
as this code will now work but I've also
used double quotes instead of single
quotes and I also omitted a few minutes
ago for my list of data types in Python
the word Char in Python there are no
chars there are no individual characters
if you want to manipulate individual
character you use a string that is to
say a stir of size one now in Python you
can use single quotes or double quotes
I'm deliberately using double quotes
everywhere just for consistency with how
we treat strings in C it's pretty common
though to use single quotes instead if
only because on most keyboards you don't
have to hold the shift key anymore I
mean humans have really started to
optimize just how quickly they want to
be able to code so using a single quote
tends to be pretty popular in Python and
other languages as well they are
fundamentally the same uh single or
double unlike in C where they have
meaning so this is correct I claim and
in fact let me run this real quick I'll
open up my terminal window here let me
get rid of the version and see run
python of agree. piy and I'll type in y
okay I'll run it again and type in
little Y and I'll stipulate it's going
to work for no as well but this isn't
necessarily the only way we can do this
there are other ways to implement the
same idea and in fact I can go about
doing this this instead let me go back
up to my code here and we saw a hint of
this earlier we know that lists exist in
Python and you can create them just by
using square brackets so what if I
simplify the code a little bit and just
say if s is in the following list of
values capital y or lowercase y it's not
all that different logically but it's a
little tighter it's a little more
compact so L ifs is in capital N or
lowercase n i can express that same idea
too so here again it's just getting a
little more pleasant to write code
there's less like hitting of the
keyboard you can express yourself a
little more succinctly and using the
keyword in Python will figure out how to
search the entire list for whatever the
value of s is and if it finds it it will
return true automatically else it will
return false so if I run agree. Pi again
and type in capital y or lowercase y
that still now works well I can typen
tighten this up further if I want to add
more features well what if I want to
support not just why Big Y and little y
but how about yes or yes or in case the
user's yelling or you know someone who
doesn't really isn't good with caps lock
types in yes wait a minute but it could
be weird like do we want to support this
or this I mean this this just gets
really tedious quickly combinatorically
if you consider all of these possible
permutations what would be smarter than
doing something like this if you want to
just be able to tolerate yes in any form
of capitalization like logically what
would be nice maybe whatever theut is
you justf over to all lower and then
exactly super common Paradigm why don't
we just force the users's input to all
lowercase or all uppercase doesn't
matter so long as we're self-consistent
and just compare against all uppercase
or all lowercase and that will get rid
of all of the possible permutations
otherwise now in C we might have done
something like this we might have
simplified this whole list and just said
let's say uh we'll do how about
lowercase so y or yes and we'll just
leave it at that but we need to force
now s to lowercase well in C we would
have used the ctype library we would
have done like two lower and called that
function passing it in although not
really cuz in C type those operate on
individual characters or chars not whole
strings we have actually didn't see a
function that could convert the whole
string in C to lowercase but in Python
we're going to benefit from some other
feature as well it turns out that python
supports what's called objectoriented
programming and we're only going to
scratch the surface of this in cs50 but
if you take a higher level course in
programming or CS you explore this as a
different Paradigm up until now in C
we've been focusing on what's called
really procedural programming you write
procedures you write functions top to
bottom uh left to right and when you
want to change some value we were in the
habit of using a procedure that is a
function you would pass something like a
variable into a function like to Upper
or to lower and it would do its thing
and hand you back a value well it turns
out that it would be nicer programming
wise if some data types just had
built-in functionality like why do we
have our variables over here and all of
our helper functions like two upper and
two lower over here such that we
constantly have to pass one into the
other it would be nice to sort of bake
into our data types buil-in
functionality so that you can change
variables using their own default be uh
buil-in functionality and so
object-oriented programming otherwise
known as oop is a technique whereby
certain types of values like a string
AKA stir not only have properties inside
of them attributes just like a struct in
C your data can also have functions
built into them as well so whereas in C
which is not objectoriented you have
strs and strs can only store data like a
name and a number when implementing a
person in Python you can for instance
have not just a structure otherwise
known as a class storing a name and a
number you can have a function like call
that person or email that person or
actual verbs or actions associated with
that piece of data now in the context of
strings it turns out that strings come
with a lot of useful functionality and
in fact this URL here which is in docs.
python.org which is the official
documentation for python you'll see a
whole list of methods that is functions
that come with strings that you can
actually use to modify their values and
what I mean by this is the following if
we go through the documentation poke
around it turns out that strings come
with a function called Lower and if you
want to use that function you just have
to use slightly different syntax than in
C you do not do to lower and you do not
say as I just did lower because this
function is built into s itself and just
like in C when you want to go inside of
a variable like a structure and access a
piece of data inside of it like name or
number when you also have functions
built into data types AKA methods a
method is just a function that is built
into a piece of data you can do s do
lower open pen closed pen in this case
and I can do this down here as well if
if s do lower in quote unquote uh n or
no the whole thing I can force this
whole thing to lowercase so the only
difference here now is in
object-oriented programming instead of
constantly passing a value into a
function you just access a function
that's inside of the value it just works
because of how the language itself is
defined and the only way you know that
these functions exist is the
documentation a Class A book a website
or the like questions now on this
technique all right I claim this is
correct now even though you've never
programmed most of you in Python before
not super well-designed there's an
subtle inefficiency now on lines three
and five together what's dumb about how
I've used lower might you
think
yeah yeah if you're going to use the
same function twice and ask the same
question expecting the same answer why
are you calling the function itself
twice maybe we should just store the
result in a variable so we could do this
in a couple of different ways we for
instance could go up here and create
another variable called T and set that
equal to s. lower and then we could just
change this to be T here but honestly I
don't think we technically need another
variable Al together here I could just
do something like this let's change the
value of s to be the lowercase version
thereof and so now I can quite simply
refer to S again and again like this
this reusing that same value now to be
sure I have now just lost the user's
original input and if I care about that
if they typed in all caps I have no idea
anymore so maybe I do want to use a
separate variable altogether but a
takeaway here too is that strings in
Python are technically what we'll call
immutable that is they cannot be changed
this was not true in C once we gave you
arrays in week two or memory in week
four you could go to town on a string
and change any of the characters you
want upper casing lower casing changing
it shortening it and so forth but in
this case uh this returns a copy of s
forced to lowercase it doesn't change
the original string that is the memory
the bytes in the computer's memory when
you assign it back to S you're
essentially forgetting about the old
version of s but because python does
memory management for you there's no
maloc there's no free python
automatically frees up the original
bytes like yees and hands them back to
the operating system for you all right
questions now on this
technique questions on
this in general I'll call out the python
documentation will start to be your
friend because in class we'll only
scratch the surface with some of these
things but in docs. python.org for
instance there's a whole reference of
all of the built-in functions that come
with the language as well as for
instance those with the string all right
well let me go ahead and before we take
a break let's go ahead and create
something a little familiar to based on
our week here in C let me propose that
we revisit those examples in involving
some meow so for instance when we had
our cat meow back in the first week and
then second in C we did something that
was a little stupid at first whereby we
created a file as I'll do here this time
called meow. p and if I want a cat to
meow three times I could run it once
like this little copy paste and now
python of meow. py and I'm done now
we've visited this example like two
times at least now in scratch it and see
it's correct I'll stipulate but what's
obviously poorly
designed what's the fault here
yeah it should just be a loop right like
why type it three times literally
copying and pasting is almost always a
bad thing except in C when you have the
function prototypes that you need to
borrow but in this case this is just
inefficient so what could we do better
here in Python well in Python we could
probably change this in a few different
ways we could borrow some of the syntax
we proposed in slide form earlier like
give me a variable called I set it to
zero no semicolon while I is less than
three if I want to do this three times I
can go ahead and print out meow and then
I can do i+ equals one and I think this
would do the trick python of meow. and
we're back in business already well if I
wanted to change this to a for Loop well
in Python it would be a little tighter
but this would not be the best approach
so for I in uh
012 I could just do print meow like this
and that too would get the job done but
to my to our discussion earlier this
would get stupid pretty quickly if you
had to keep enumerating all of these
values like what did we introduce
instead the the range function exactly
so that hands me back way more
efficiently just the values I want
indeed one at a time so even this if I
run it a third a third or fourth time
we've got the same result but now let's
transition to where we went with this
back in the day how can we start to
modularize this like just like it would
be nice I claimed if MIT had given us a
meow function wouldn't it be nice if
like python had given us a meow function
maybe less compelling in Python but how
can I build my own function well I did
this briefly with the spell checker
earlier but let me go ahead and propose
that we could Implement now our own
version of this in python as follows let
me go ahead and start fresh here and use
the keyword defa so this did not exist
in C you had the return value the
function name the arguments in Python
you literally say defa to define a
function you give it a name like meow
and now now I'm going to go ahead and in
this function just print out meow and
this lets me change it to anything else
I want in the future but for now it's an
abstraction and in fact I can uh move it
out of sight out of mind just going to
hit enter a bunch of times to pretend
like now it exists but I don't care how
it is implemented and up here now I can
do something like this 4 I in range of
three let me go ahead and not print meow
anymore let me just call meow and
tightening up my code further but I
think let's see python of meow. py this
is I think going to be the first time it
does not work
correctly okay so here we have sadly our
first python error and let's see the
syntax is going to be different from C
or clangs output traceback is like the
term of art here this is like a trace
back of all of the lines of code that
were just executed or really functions
you called the file name is
uninteresting this is like my codes
space specifically but the file name is
important here meow. py uh line two is
is the issue okay I didn't get very far
before I screwed up and then there's a
name error and you'll see in Python
there's typically these capitalized uh
keywords that hint at what the issue is
it's something related to names of
variables meow is not defined all right
you're programming python for the first
time you've screwed up you're following
some online tutorial you're seeing this
reason through it like why might meow
not be defined what can weer infer about
python how to troubleshoot
logically is it me ised after maybe is
it because meow is defined after you
know as smart as python seems to be Visa
VC they have some similar design
characteristics so let's try that so let
me scroll all the way back down to where
I move this earlier let me uh get rid of
it way down there I'll copy it to my
clipboard and let me just kind of hack
something together let me just put it up
here and let's see if this works so now
let me clear my terminal run python of
meow. okay we're back in business so
that was actually really good intuition
good debugging technique to sort of
reason through it now this is kind of
contradicting what I claimed back in
week one which was that you know the
main part of your program ideally should
just be at the top of the file like
don't make me look for it it's not a
huge deal with like a four-line program
but if you've got 40 lines 400 lines you
don't want like the juice juicy part of
your program to be way down here and all
of these functions way up here so it
would be nice maybe if we actually have
a main function and so it actually turns
out to be a convention in Python to
define a main function it's not a
special function that's automatically
called like in C but humans realized you
know what that was a pretty useful
feature let me Define a function called
main let me indent these lines
underneath it let me practice what I'm
preaching which is put the main code at
the top of the file and wonderfully in
Python now you do not need prototypes
there's none of that hackish copying and
pasting of the return type the name and
the arguments to a function like we
needed in C this is now
okay instead except for one Minor Detail
let me go ahead and run python of
meow. hopefully now I've solve this
problem by having a main function but
now nothing has happened all right even
if you've never programmed in Python
before What might explain this
behavior and how do I
fix again when you're off in the real
world learning some new language all you
have is deductive logic to debug yeah I
remember
right so the solution to be clear in C
was that we had to put the Prototype up
here otherwise we'd get an error message
in this case I'm actually not getting an
error message and indeed I'll claim that
you don't need the prototypes in Python
just not necessary because that was
annoying if nothing
else but what else might explain yeah
I'm
back yeah maybe you have to call Main
itself if main is not some some special
status in Python maybe just because it
exists isn't enough and indeed if you
want to call Maine the new convention is
actually going to be as the very last
line of your program typically to
literally call Main it's a little stupid
stupid looking but you know they made a
design decision and this is how now we
work around it python of meowy now we're
back in business but now logically why
does this work the way it does well in
this case top to bottom line one is
telling python to define a fun fun
called Main and then Define it as
follows lines two and three but it's not
calling main yet line six is telling
python how to define a function called
meow but it's not calling these lines
yet now line 10 you're telling python
call Main and at that point python has
been trained if you will to know what
main is on line one to know what meow is
on line six and so it's now perfectly
okay for Maine to be above meow because
you never called them yet you defined
defined and then you called and that's
the logic behind this any questions now
on the structure of this technique
here now let's do one more then recall
that the last thing we did in scratch
and in Python uh scratch and in C was to
actually
parameterize uh these same function so
suppose that you don't want Maine to be
responsible for the loop here you
instead want to very simply do something
like meow three times and be done with
it well in Python it's going to be
similar in spirit toy but again we don't
need to keep mentioning data types if
you want me now to take some argument
like a number n you can just specify n
as the name of that argument or you
could call it anything else of course
that you want you don't have to specify
int or anything else in your code now
inside of meow you can do something like
for I in let's say I definitely now
can't do this because like that would be
weird to start the list and end it with
n so if I can come back over here what's
the solution how can I do something n
times yeah using range so range is nice
cuz I can pass in now this variable n
and now I can meow whoops now I can
print out quote unquote meow so it's
almost the same as in scratch almost the
same as in C but it's a little simpler
and if now I run meow. P I'll have the
ability now to do this here as well all
right questions on any of this right now
we're sort of like taking the stroll
through week one we're going to
momentarily escalate things to look not
only at some of these basic but also
other features like we saw with face
recognition with the speller or the like
um because of how many of us are here we
have a huge amount of candy out in the
lobby so why don't we go ahead and take
a 10-minute break and we come back we'll
do even fancier more powerful things
with python in 10 all right so we are
back among our goals now are to
introduce a few more building blocks so
that we can solve more interesting
problems at the end much like those that
we began with you recall from a few
weeks ago we played with this sort of
two-dimensional Super Mario World and we
tried to print a vertical column of like
three or more bricks well let me propose
that we use this as an opportunity to
now Tinker with some of Python's more uh
useful more userfriendly functionality
as well so let me code a file called
mario. py and let's just print out like
that the equivalent of that vertical
column so it's of height three each one
is a hash so let's do for I in range of
three initially and let's just print out
a single hash and I think now python of
mario. py voila we're in business
printing out just that same pyramid
there or just that same column there
what if though we want to print a column
of like some variable height where the
user tells us how tall they want it to
be well let me go up here for instance
and instead how about we'll use um let's
do this how about uh from cs50
import how about the get in function as
before so it will deal with making sure
the user gives us an integer and now in
the past whenever we wanted to get a
number from a user we've actually
followed a certain Paradigm in fact if I
open up here for instance uh how about
Mario in how about Mario 1. C from a
while back you might recall that we had
code like this and we specifically use
the do while loop and see whenever we
want to like get something from the user
maybe again and again and again until
they cooperate at which point we finally
break out of the loop so it turns out
python does have while Loops does have
four Loops does not have do while loops
and yet pretty much anytime you've
gotten user input you've probably used
this Paradigm so it turns out that the
python equivalent of this is to do
similar in spirit but using only a while
loop and a common Paradigm in python as
I alluded earlier is to actually
deliberately induce an infinite Loop
while true capital T and then do what
you want to do like get an INT from the
user and prompt them for the height for
instance in question and then if you're
sure that the user has given you what
you want like n is greater than zero
which is what I want in this case cuz I
want a positive integer otherwise
there's nothing to print you literally
just break out of the loop and so we
could actually use this technique in C
it's just not really done in C you could
absolutely in C have done a while true
loop with the parentheses lowercase true
you could break out of it and so forth
but in Python this is like the python
way and this is actually a term of art
this way in Python is pythonic like this
is the way everyone does it quote
unquote doesn't mean you have to but
that's sort of the way like the cool
python programmers would Implement an
idea like this trying to do something
again and again and again until the user
actually cooperates but all we've done
is take away the do while loop but still
logically we can implement the same idea
now below this let me go ahead and just
print out for I in range of n this time
because I want it to be variable and not
three I can go ahead and print out the
hash let me go ahead and get rid of the
C version here open my terminal window
and I'll run again python of mario. py
I'll type in three and I get back those
three hashes but if I instead type in
four I now get four hashes instead so
the takeaway here is quite simply that
this would be the way for instance to
actually get back a value in Python that
is consistent with some parameter like
greater than zero how about this let's
actually uh practice what we preached a
moment ago with our meowing examples and
kind of factoring all this out let me go
ahead and Define a main function as
before let me go ahead and assume for
the moment that a get height function
exists which is not a thing in Python
I'm going to invent it in just a moment
and now I'm going to go ahead and do
something like this for I in the range
of that height well let's go ahead and
print out those hashes so I'm assuming
that get height exists let me go ahead
and Implement that abstraction so Define
a function now called get height it's
not going to take any arguments in this
design while true I can go ahead and do
the same thing as before assign a
variable n the return value of get int
prompting the user for that height and
then if n is greater than zero I can go
ahead and break but if I break here I
logically just like can see end up
executing below the loop in question but
there's nothing there but if I want get
height to return the height what should
I type here on line 14
logically what do I want to return to be
clear yeah so I actually want to return
n and here's another curiosity of python
Visa BC there doesn't seem to be an
issue of scope anymore right in C it was
super important to not only declare your
variables with the data types you also
had to be mindful of like where they
exist inside of those curly braces in
Python it turns out you can be a little
looser with things for better for worse
and so on line 11 if I create a variable
called n it exists on line 11 12 and
even 13
outside of the while loop so to be clear
in C with a while loop we would have
ordinarily had not the colon we would
have had the curly brace like here and
over here and a week ago I would have
claimed that in C N does not exist
outside of the while loop by nature of
those curly braces even though the curly
braces are gone python actually allows
you to use a variable anytime after you
have assigned it a value so slightly
more powerful as such how however I can
tighten this up a little bit logically
and this is true in C I don't really
need to break out of the loop by using
break recall that or know that I can
actually once I'm ready to go I can just
return the value I care about even
inside of the loop and that will have
the side effect of breaking me out of
the loop and also breaking me out of and
returning from the entire function so
nothing too new here in terms of C
versus python except for this issue of
scope and I indeed returned n at the
bottom there just to make clear that n
would still exist so either of those are
correct now I just have a Python program
that I think is going to allow me to
implement this same Mario idea so let's
run python of mario. and okay so nothing
happened uh python of mario.
py what did I do wrong yeah I have to
call Main so at the bottom of my code I
have to call Main here and this is a
stylistic detail that's been subtle um
generally speaking when when you are
writing in Python um there's not a cs50
style guide per se there's actually a
python style guide that most people
adhere to um it's and in this case
double blank lines between functions is
the norm I'm doing that deliberately
although uh it might otherwise not be
obvious but now that I've called main on
line 16 let's run mario. once more aha
now we get there now we see it type in
three and I'm back in business printing
out the values there
yeah
sure why do I need the if condition at
all why can't I just return n here as by
doing return n or if I really want to be
succinct I could technically just do
this the only reason I added the if
condition is because if the user types
in negative 1 -2 I wanted to prompt them
again and again that's all but that
would be totally acceptable too if you
were okay with that result instead well
let me do one other thing here to point
out why we are using get in so
frequently this new training wheel all
be it temporarily so let me go back to
the way it was a moment ago and let me
propose now to take away get int I
claimed earlier that if you're not using
get int you can just use the input
function itself from
python but that always returns a string
or a stir and so recall that you have to
pass the output of the input function to
an INT either on the same line or if you
prefer on another line instead but it
turns out what I didn't do was show you
what happens if you uh don't cooperate
with the user uh with the program so if
I run python of mario. now works great
even without the get int function and I
can do it with four still works great
but let me clear my terminal and be
difficult now as the user and type in C
for the height instead enter now we see
one of those tracebacks again this one
is different this isn't a name error but
apparently a value error and if I kind
of ignore the stuff I don't understand I
can see invalid literal for INT with
base 10 cat that's a super cryptic way
of saying that c a is not a number in
decimal notation and so I would seem to
have to somehow handle this case and if
you want to be more Curious you'll see
that this is indeed a trace back and um
C tends to do this too or the debugger
would do this for you too you can see
all of the functions that have been
called to get you to this point so
apparently my problem is initially in
line 14 but line 14 if I keep scrolling
is uninteresting it's main but line 14
leads me to execute line two which is
indeed in main that leads me to execute
line nine which is in get height and
okay here's the issue so the closest
line number to the error message is the
one that probably reveals the most line
nine is where my issue is so I can't
just blindly ask the user for input and
then convert it to an INT if they're not
going to give me an INT now how do we
deal with this well back in problem set
two you might recall validating that the
user typed in a number and using a for
Loop and the like well it turns out
there's a better way to do this in
Python and the are kind of there if you
want to try to convert something for a
number to a number that might not
actually be a number turns out Python
and certain other languages literally
have a keyword called try and if only
this existed for the past few weeks I
know but like you can try to do the
following with your code what do I want
to try to do well I want to try to
execute those few lines except if
there's an error so I can say except if
there's a value error specifically the
one I screwed up and created a moment
ago and if there is a value error I can
print out an informative message to the
user like not an integer or anything
else and what's happening here now is
literally this operative word try the
pro python is going to try to get input
and try to convert it to an in and it's
going to try to check if it's greater
than zero and then try to return it all
why all of three of those lines are
inside of indented underneath the tri
block except if something goes wrong
specifically a value error happens then
it prints this but it doesn't return
anything and because I'm in a loop that
means it's going to do it again and
again and again until the human actually
cooperates and gives me an actual number
and so this too is what the world would
call pythonic in Python you don't
necessarily rigorously try to validate
the users's input make sure they haven't
screwed up you honestly take a more
laxidasical approach and just try to do
something but catch an error if it
happens so catch is also a term of art
even though it's not a keyword here
except if something happens you handle
it so you try and you handle it it's
sort of best effort programming if you
will but this is baked into the mindset
of the Python uh programming community
so now if I do python of mario. py and I
cooperate works great as before try and
succeed three Works four works if though
I try and fail by typing in cat it
doesn't crash per se it doesn't show me
an error it shows me something more user
friendly like not an integer and then I
can try again with dog not an integer I
can try again with five and now it works
so we won't generally have you write
much in the way of these try except
blocks only because they get a little
sophisticated quickly but that is to
reveal what the get int function is
doing this is why we give you the
training wheels so that when you want to
get an INT you don't have to jump
through all these annoying Hoops to do
so but that's all the library is really
doing for you is just try and accept you
won't be left with any training wheels
ultimately questions now on getting
inputs and trying in this way
anything at all
yeah Tri block it say that oh you could
you put the condition outside of the tri
block short answer yes and in fact I
struggled with this last night when
tweaking this example to show the
simplest version I will disclaim that
really I should only be trying literally
to do the The Fragile part and then down
here I should be really doing what
you're proposing which is do the
condition out here the problem is though
that logically this gets messy quickly
right because except if there's a value
error I want to print out not an integer
I can't compare n against zero then
because n doesn't exist because there
was an error so it turns out and I'll
show you this this is now the advanced
version of python there's actually an
else keyword you can use in Python that
does not accompany if or L if it
accompanies try and accept which I think
is weirdly confusing a different word
would have been better but if you really
prefer I could have done this instead
dead and this is one of these design
things where like reasonable people will
disagree generally speaking you should
only try to do the one line that might
very well fail but honestly this looks
kind of stupid now it's just
unnecessarily complicated and so my own
preference was actually the original
which was yeah I'm trying a few extra
lines that really aren't going to fail
mathematically but it's just tighter
it's cleaner this way and here's again
the sort of like you know arguments
you'll start to make yourself as you get
more comfortable with programming you'll
have an opinion you'll disagree with
someone and so long as you can back your
argument up pretty
probably all right so how about we now
take away some piece of magic that's
been here for a while let me go ahead
and uh Delete all of this here and let
me propose that we revisit uh not that
vertical column and the exceptions that
might result from getting input but
these like horizontal question marks
that we saw a while ago so I want all of
those question marks on the same line
and yet I worry we're about to see a
challenge here because print up until
now has been putting new lines
everywhere automatically even without
those backslash NS well let me propose
that we do this for I in the range of
four if I want four question marks let
me just print four question marks
unfortunately I don't think this is
correct yet let me run python of mario.
and of course this gives me a column
instead of the row of question marks
that I want so how do we do this well it
turns out if you read the documentation
for the print function it turns out that
print not surprisingly perhaps takes a
lot of different arguments as well and
in fact if you go to the documentation
for it you'll see that it takes not just
positional arguments that is from left
to right separated by commas turns out
python has supports a fancier feature
with arguments where you can pass the
names of arguments to functions too so
what do I mean by this if I go back to
vs code here and I've read the
documentation it turns out that yes as
before you can pass multiple arguments
to python like this like hello comma
David comma me that will just
automatically concatenate all three of
those positional arguments together
they're positional in the sense that
they literally flow from left to right
separated by commas but if you don't
want to just pass in values like that
you want to actually print out as I did
before a question mark but you want to
override the default behavior of print
by changing the line ending you can
actually do this you can use the name of
an argument that you know exists from
the documentation set it equal to some
alternative value and in fact even
though this looks cryptic this is how I
would override the end of each line to
be quote unquote that is nothing because
if you read the documentation the
default value for this end argument does
someone want to guess is is back sln so
if you read the documentation you'll see
that back sln is the implied default for
this end argument and so if you want to
change it you just say end equals
something else and so here I can change
change it to nothing and now rerun
python of mario. and now they're all on
the same line now looks a little stupid
cuz I made that sort of week one mistake
where I still need to move the cursor to
the next line that's just a different
problem I'm just going to go over here
and print nothing I don't even need to
print back sln because if print
automatically gives you a backslash n
just call print with nothing and you'll
get that for free so let me rerun python
of mario. Pi and now it looks a little
prettier at the prompt and to be super
clear as to what's going on suppose I
want to sort of make an exclamation here
I could change the back sln default to
like an exclamation point Just for kicks
and if I run python of mario. py again
now I get this sort of you know
exclamation with question marks and
exclamation points as well so that's all
that's going on here and this is what's
called a named argument it literally has
a name that you can specify when calling
it in and it's different from positional
in that you're literally using the
name let me propose something else
though and this is why people kind of
like python there's just kind of cool
ways to do things that's kind of a you
know ver it's a three line verbose way
of printing out four question marks you
know I could certainly take the you know
shortcut and just do this but that's not
really that interesting for anyone
especially if I want to do it a variable
number of times but python does let you
do this if you want to uh multiply a
character some number of times not only
can you use Plus for concatenation you
can use star or an asterisk for
multiplication if you will that is
concatenation again and again and again
so if I just print out quote unquote
question mark Time 4 that's actually
going to be the tightest way the most
distinct way I can print four question
marks instead and if I don't use four I
use n where I get n from the user bang
like now I've gotten rid of the four
Loop entirely and I'm using the the star
operator to manipulate it instead and to
be super clear here in so far as python
does not have milock or free or memory
management that you have to do guess
what python also doesn't
have anything on your minds the past
couple of
weeks doesn't have pointers yes so
python does not have pointers which just
means that all of that happens for you
automatically underneath the hood Again
by way of code that someone else wrote
how about one more throwback with Mario
we've talked about in week one this sort
of two-dimensional structure where it's
like I claim like 3x3 a grid of bricks
if you will well how can we do this in
Python we can do this in a couple of
ways now let me go back to my mario. py
and let me do something like for I in
range of we'll just do three even though
I know now I could use get int or I
could use input and int and if I want to
do something two-dimensionally just like
in C you can Nest your for Loop so maybe
I could do 4J in range of three and then
in here I could print out a uh hash
symbol and then let's see if that gives
me nine total so if I've got a nested
Loop like this python of mario.
hopefully gives me a grid no it gave me
a column of
nine why
logically even though I've got my row
and my
columns
yeah yeah the line ending so in my row I
can't let print just keep adding new
line adding new lines so I just have to
override this here and let me not screw
up like before let me print one at the
end of the whole row just to move the
cursor down and I think now together now
we've got our 3x3 of course we could
tighten this up further like if I don't
like the nested loop I probably could go
in here and just print out for instance
a uh a brick times three or I could
change the three to a variable if I've
gotten it from the user so I can tighten
this up further so again just different
ways to solve the same problem and again
sort of evidence of why a lot of people
like python there's just some more
pleasant ways to solve problems without
getting into the weeds constantly of
doing things like like with um uh for
loops and wild Loops endlessly all right
well how about some other building
blocks lists are going to be so
incredibly useful in Python just as
arrays were in C but arrays are annoying
because you have to manage the memory
yourself you have to know in advance how
big they are or you have to use pointers
and malok or realloc to resize them like
oh my God like the past two weeks have
been painful in that sense but python
does this all for free for you in fact
there's a whole bunch of functions that
come with python that involve lists and
they'll ow us ultimately um to do things
again and again and again uh with uh
within the same data structure and for
instance we'll be able to get the length
of a list you don't have to remember it
yourself in a variable you can just ask
python how many elements are in this
list and with this I think we can solve
some some old problems too so let me go
back here to vs code let me close Mario
and give us a new program called scores.
piy and rather than show the C and the
python now let's just focus on Python
and in scores. C way back when we just
averaged like three test scores or
something like that 72 73 and 33 a few
weeks ago so if I want to create a list
in this python version of 72 73 33 I
just use my square bracket notation C
let you use curly braces if you know the
values in advance but Python's just this
and now if I want to compute the average
in pi in C recall I did something with a
loop I added all the values together I
then divided by the total number values
just like you would in grade school and
that gave me the average well python
comes with a lot of super handy
functions not just length but others as
well and so in fact if you want to
compute the average you can take the sum
of all of those scores and divide it by
the length of all of those scores so
python comes with length comes with sum
you can just pass in a whole list of any
size and let it deal with that problem
for you so if I want to now print out
this average I can print out average
colon and then I'll plug in my average
uh string for variable for interpolation
let me make this an F string so that it
gets formatted and let me just run
python of scores. Pi and there's my
average it's sort of rounding weird
because we're still vulnerable to some
floating point in Precision but at least
I didn't need loops and I didn't have to
write all this darn code just to do
something that you know Excel and Google
spreadsheets can just do like that well
python is closer to those kinds of tools
but more powerful and that you can
manipulate the data yourself how about
though if I want to um get a bunch of
scores manually from the user and then
sum them together well let's combine a
few ideas here how about this first let
me go ahead and uh import um the cs50 LI
get in function from the cs50 library
just so we don't have to deal with try
and accept or all of that and let me go
ahead and give myself an empty list and
this is powerful in py in C there's
really there's no point to an empty
array because if you create an empty
array with square bracket notation like
it's not useful for anything but in
Python you can create it empty because
python will grow and shrink the list for
you automatically as you add things to
it so if I want to get three scores from
the user I could do something like this
for I in range of three and then I can
grab a variable called score or anything
I could call get int prompt the human
for the score that they want to type in
and then once they do I can do this
thinking back to our objectoriented
programming capability now I could do
scores dot a pen
and I Canen that score to it and you
would only know this from having read
the documentation heard it in class in a
book or whatnot but it turns out that
just like strings have functions like
lower built into them lists have
functions like append built into them
that just literally appends to the end
of the list for you and python will grow
or Shrink it as needed no more Malo or C
or Realo or the like so this just
appends to the scores array the scores
list that score and then again and again
and again so the array starts at
sorry the list starts at size zero then
grows to one then two then three without
you having to do anything else and so
now down here I can compute an average
with the sum of those scores divided by
the length of the total number of scores
and to be clear length is the total
number of elements in the list doesn't
matter how big the values themselves are
now I can go ahead and print out an FST
string uh with something like average
colon average and curly braces and and
if I run python of scores. piy I'll type
in just for the sake of discussion the
three values I still get the same answer
but that would have been painful to do
in see unless you committ it in advance
to a fixed size array which we already
decided weeks ago was annoying or uh you
uh grew it dynamically using malok or
realloc or the like all right what else
can I do well there's some nice things
you might as well know exist um instead
of scores. aen you can do slight
fanciness like this like if you want to
append something to a list you can
actually do plus equals and then put
that thing in a a temporary list of its
own and just use what is essentially
concatenation but not concatenation of
strings but concatination of lists so
this new line six appends to the scores
list this tiny little list I'm
temporarily creating with just the
current new score so just another piece
of syntax that's worth seeing that
allows you to do something like that as
well all right well how about we go back
to strings for a moment and all these
examples as always are on the course's
website afterward suppose we want to do
something like converting characters to
uppercase well to be clear I could do
something like this let me create a
program called uppercase dop let me
prompt the user for a before string as
by using the input function or get
string which is almost the same and I'll
prompt the user for a string
beforeand then let me go ahead and print
out uh how about the keyword after
and then end the new line with nothing
just so that I can see before on one
line and after on the next line and then
let me do this and here's where python
gets pleasant too with loops for C in
before print c. uper n equals quote
unquote and then I'll print this here
all right that was fast but let's try to
infer what's going on so line one just
gets input from the user stores it in a
variable called before line two
literally just prints after but doesn't
move the new line to uh the cursor to
the next line what it then does is this
and in C this was a little more annoying
you needed a for loop with I you needed
array in uh notation with the square
brackets but python if you say four
variable in string so for c for
character in string Python's going to
automatically assign C to the first word
letter that the user types in then on
the next iteration the second letter the
third letter and the fourth so you don't
need any square bracket notation you
just you see and python will do it for
you and just hand you back one at a time
each of the letters that the user has
typed in so if I go back over here and I
run for instance python of uppercase
dopy and I'll type in how about uh David
in all lowercase and hit enter you'll
now see that it's all uppercase instead
by iterating over it indeed one
character at a time but we already know
thanks to object-oriented programming
strings themselves have the
functionality built in to not just
uppercase Single Character
but the whole string so honestly this
was a bit of a silly exercise I don't
need to use a loop anymore like in see
and so some of the habits you've only
just developed in recent weeks it's time
to start breaking them when they're not
necessary I can create a variable called
after set it equal to before do uper
which indeed exists just like lower
exists and then what I can go ahead and
print out is for instance uh let's get
rid of this print line here and do it at
the end after and print the value of
that variable so now if I rerun
uppercase Pi type in David and all
lowercase I can just uppercase the whole
thing all at once because again in C in
Python you don't have to operate on
characters individually questions on any
of these tricks up until
now now all right how about a few other
techniques that we saw and C that we'll
bring back now in Python so it turns out
in Python there are other librar you can
use two that unlock even more
functionality so in C if you wanted
command line arguments you just change
the proo the signature for main to be
void instead of void to be int argc
comma string argv Open brackets for an
array or Char star eventually well it
turns out in Python that if you want to
access command line arguments it's a
little simpler but they're tucked away
in a library otherwise known as a module
called CIS the CIS or system module now
this is similar in spirit to the cs50
library and that it's got a bunch of
functionality built in but this one
comes with python itself so if I want to
create a program like greet py in VSS
code here let me go ahead and do this
from the CIS Library let's import argv
and that's just a thing that exists it's
not built into main because there is no
main per se anymore so it's tucked away
in that library and now I can do
something like this if the length of
argv equals equals 2 well let's go ahead
and print out something friendly like
hello comma AR V bracket 1 and then
close quotes else if the length of RV is
not equal to two let's just go ahead and
print out hello world now at a glance
this might look a little cryptic but
it's identical to what we did a few
weeks ago when I run this python of
greet with no arguments it just says
hello world but if I instead add a
command line argument like my first name
and hit enter now the length of arv is
no longer one it's going to be two and
so it prints out hello David instead so
the takeaway here is that whereas in C
argv technically contained the name of
your program like hello or dog greet and
then everything the human typed Python's
a little different in that because we're
using The Interpreter in this way
Technically when you run python of greet
py the length of arv is only one it
contains only greet so the name of the
file it does not unnecessarily contain
python itself because what's the point
of that being there omnes it does
contain the number of words that the
human typed after python itself so argv
is length one here argv is length two
here and that's why when it did equal to
I saw hello David instead of the default
hello world so same ability to access
command line arguments add these kinds
of inputs to your functions but you have
to unlock it by way of using Arvy uh
instead in this way if you want to see
all of the words you could do something
like this uh just as if we combine ideas
here for I in range of how about length
of
arv then I can do this print argv
bracket I all right a little cryptic but
line three is just a for Loop iterating
over the range of length of argv so if
the human types in two words the length
of argv will be two so this is just a
way of saying iterate over all of the
words in arv printing them one at a time
so python of greet dopy enter just
prints out the name of the program
python of greet dopy with David prints
out greet dopy and then David I can keep
running it though with more words and
they'll each get printed one at a time
but what's nice too about Python and
this is the point of this exercise
honestly this looks pretty cryptic this
is not very pleasant to look at if you
just want to iterate over every word in
a list which argv is watch what I can do
I can do for ARG or any variable name in
ARG V let me just now print out that
argument I could keep calling it I but I
seems weird when it's not a number so
I'm changing to AR as a word instead if
I now do python of greet py it does this
if I do python of greet David it does
that again David ma it does that again
so this is again why Python's just very
appealing you want to do something this
many times iterate over a list just say
it and it reads a little more like
English and there's even other fanciness
too if I may it's a little stupid that I
keep seeing the name of the program
greet dopy so I it'd be nice if I could
remove that python also supports what
are called slices of arrays sorry slices
of lists even though I get the
terminology confused if Arvy is a list
then it's going to print out everything
in it but if I want a slice of it that
starts at location one all the way to
the end you can use this funky syntax in
between the square brackets which we've
not seen yet that's going to start at
item one and go all the way to the end
and so this is a nice clever way of
slicing off if you will the very first
element because now when I run greet doy
David men I should only see David and
men if I only want one element I could
do one to two if I want all of them I
could do zero onward I could give myself
just two of one of them in this way so
you can play with the start value and
the end value in this way to sort of
slice and dice these lists in different
ways that would have been a pain in see
just because we didn't really have the
built-in support for manipulating arrays
as cleanly as this all right just so
you've seen it too though this one is
less uh exciting to see live if I go
ahead and create a quick program here it
turns out there's something else in the
CIS Library the ability to exit programs
either exiting with status code one or
zero as we've been doing anytime
something goes right or wrong so for
instance Let Me Whip up a quick program
that just says if the length of cy.
argv uh does not equal two then let's y
at the user and say you're missing a
command line argument otherwise command
line argument and let's then return cy.
exit one else let's go ahead and
logically just say print a formatted
string that says hello as before cy.
arv1 now things look different all of a
sudden but I'm doing something
deliberately first let's see what this
does so on line one I'm importing not
argv specifically I'm importing the
whole CIS library and we'll see why in
second well it turns out that this Arvy
the CIS library has not only the Arvy
list it also has a function called exit
which I'd like to be able to use as well
so it turns out that if you import a
whole library in this way that's fine
but you have to refer to the things
inside of it by using that same
library's name and a DOT to sort of
namespace it so to speak so here I'm
just saying if the user types in does
not type in two words yell at them with
missing command line argument and then
exit with one just like in C when you do
exit one just means something went wrong
otherwise print out hello to this and
this is starting to look cryptic but
it's just a combination of ideas the
curly braces means interpolate this
value plug it in here cy. Arvy is just
the verbose way of saying go into the
CIS library and get the argv variable
therein and bracket one of course just
like arrays and C is just the second
element at the prompt so when I run this
version now python of exit. py with no
arguments I get yelled at in this way if
however I type in two arguments total
the name of the file and my own name now
I get greeted with hello David and it's
the same idea before this was a very
low-level technique but same thing here
if you do Echo dollar sign question mark
enter you'll see the exit code of your
program so if I do this incorrectly
again let me rerun it without my name
enter I get yelled at but if I do Echo
dollar sign question mark there's the
secret one that's returned again just to
show You parody with C in this case
questions now on any of these techniques
here all right how about something
that's a little more powerful too we
spent so much time in week zero and one
doing searching and then eventually
sorting in week three well it turns out
python can help with some of this too
let me go ahead and create a program
called names. py that's just going to be
an opportunity to maybe search over a
whole bunch of names let me go ahead and
import CIS and then just so I have
access to exit and let me go ahead and
create a variable called names that's
going to be a list with a whole bunch of
names uh how about Here Charlie and Fred
and George and Jenny and Percy and
lastly Ron so a whole bunch of names
here and you know it'd be a little
Annoying to implement code that iterates
over that from left to right and see
searching for one of those names in fact
what name well let's go ahead and ask
the user to input the name that they
want to search for so that we can tell
them if the name is there or not and we
could do this similar to C in Python
doing something like this so for n in
names where n is just a variable to
iterate over each name if how about the
name I'm looking for equals the current
name in the list AKA n let's print out
something friendly like found and then
let's do cy. Exit 0 to indicate that we
found whoever that is otherwise if we
get all the way to the bottom here
outside of this Loop let's just print
not found because if we haven't exited
yet and then let's just exit with one
just to be clear I can continue
importing all of CIS or I could do from
CIS import exit and then I could get rid
of CIS dot everywhere else but you know
sometimes it's helpful to know exactly
where functions came from so this two is
just a matter of style in this case all
right so let's go ahead and run this
python of names. piy and let's look for
like Ron all the way at the end you know
all right he's found and let's search
for someone outside of the family here
like herion not found okay so it seems
to be working in this way but I've
essentially implemented what
algorithm what algorithm would this seem
to be per lines seven and eight and nine
and
10 yeah so it's just linear search it's
a loop even though the syntax is a
little more succinct today and it's just
iterating over the whole thing well
honestly we've seen an even more tur way
to do this in Python and this again is
what makes it a more pleasant language
sometimes why don't I just do this
instead in of iterating one at a time
why don't I just say this let me go
ahead and change my condition to just be
How about if the name we're looking for
is in the names list we're done we found
it use the in preposition that we've
seen a couple of times now that itself
asks the question is something in
something else and python will take care
of linear search for us and it's going
to work exactly the same if I do python
of names. search for run it's still
going to find him and it's still going
to do it linearly in this case but I
don't have to write all of the lower
level code myself in this
case questions now on any of this the
code's just getting shorter and
shorter now what about uh let's see what
else might we have here how about this
it turns out let's go ahead and
Implement that phone book that we
started metaphorically with in the
beginning of the course let's code up a
program called phonebook dopy and in
this case let's go ahead and let's
create a dictionary this time recall
that a dictionary is a little something
that implements something like this like
a two column table that's got keys and
values words and definitions names and
numbers and let's focus on the last of
those names and numbers in this case
well I claimed earlier that python has
built-in support for dictionaries dict
objects that you can create with one
line I didn't need it for speller
because a set is sufficient when you
only want one of the keys or the values
not both but now I want some names and
numbers so it turns out in pyth python
you can create an empty dictionary by
saying dict open parenthesis close and
that just gives you essentially a chart
that looks like this with nothing in it
or there's more succinct syntax you can
alternatively do uh this with two curly
braces instead and in fact I've been
using a shortcut all this time when I
had a list earlier where my
variable uh was called scores and I did
this that was actually the shorthand
version of this hey python give me an
empty list so there's different Syntax
for achieving the same goal in this case
if I want a dictionary for people I can
either do this or more commonly just two
curly braces like that all right well
what do I want to put in this well let
me actually put some things in this and
I'm going to just move my Clos curly
brace to a new line if I want to
implement this idea of keys and values
the way you do this in Python is key
colon value comma key colon value so
you'd implement it more in code so for
instance if I want Carter to be the
first key in my phone book and I want
his number to be+ one 617495 1000 I can
put that as the corresponding value the
colon is in between both are strings or
stirs so I've quoted both deliberately
if I want to add myself I can put a
comma and then just to keep things
pretty I'm moving the cursor to the next
line but that's not strictly required
aesthetically it's just good style and
here I might do+ 1 949 468 uh
2750 and now I have a dictionary that
essentially has two rows here David uh
Carter and his number and David and his
number as well and if I kept adding to
this this call this chart would just get
longer and longer suppose I want to
search for one of our numbers well let's
prompt the user for the name for whose
number you want to search by getting
string or you know what we don't need
the cs50 library let's just use input
and prompt the user for a name and now
we can use this super syntax and just
say if name in people print the format
added string number colon and here we
can do this people bracket name okay so
this is getting kind of cool kind of
quickly kind of confusingly so let me
run this python of phone
book. let's type in Carter and indeed I
see his number let's run it again with
David and I see my number here so what's
going on well it turns out that a
dictionary is very similar in spirit to
a list it's actually very similar in
spirit to an array in C but instead of
being limited to keys that are numbers
like bracket 0o bracket 1 bracket two
you can actually use words and that's
all I'm doing here on line eight if I
want to check for the name Carter which
is currently in this variable called
name I can index into my people
dictionary using not a number but using
literally a string the name Carter or
David or anything else to make this
clear too notice that I'm at the moment
you using this format string which is
adding some undue complexity but I could
clarify this perhaps further as this I
could give myself another variable
called number set it equal to the people
dictionary indexing into it using the
current name and now I can shorten this
to make it clear that all I'm doing is
printing the value of that and in fact I
can do this even more cryptically if I
this would be weird to do but if I only
ever want to show David's phone number
and never Carter's I can literally quote
unquote index into the people dictionary
because now when I run this even if I
type Carter I'm going to get back my
number instead but that's all that's
happening if I undo that because that's
now a bug but I index into it using the
value of name dictionaries are just so
wonderfully convenient because now you
can associate anything with anything
else but not using numbers but entire
keywords instead so here's how if in
spell we gave you not just words but
hundreds of thousands of definitions as
well you could essentially store them as
this and then when the human wants to
look up a definition in a proper
dictionary not just for spellchecking
you could index into the dictionary
using square brackets and get back the
definition in English as well
questions on this
yeah
location a really good question so how
to summarize how is python finding that
name within that dictionary this is
where honestly speller in pet 5 is what
Python's all about so you have struggled
are struggling with implementing your
own spell checker and implementing your
own hash table and recall that per last
week the goal of a hash table is to
ideally get constant time access not
something linear which is slow and even
better than something uh uh logarithmic
like log base 2 of n so Python and the
really smart people who invented it they
have written the code that does its best
to give you constant time searches of
dictionaries and they're not always
going to succeed just as you and your
own problem set probably going to have
some collisions once in a while and
start to have chains of length lists of
words but this is where again you defer
to someone else someone smarter than you
someone with more time than you to solve
these problems for you and if you read
Python's documentation you'll see that
it doesn't guarantee constant time but
it's going to ideally optimize the data
structure for you to get as fast as
possible and of all of the data
structures um like a dictionary a
hashtable is really like the Swiss army
knife of computing because it just lets
you associate something with something
else and even though we keep focusing on
names and numbers that's a really
powerful thing because it's more
powerful than lists and arrays which are
only numbers and something else now you
can have any sorts of relationships
instead all right let me show a few
other examples before we culminate with
some more powerful techniques in pythons
thanks to libraries how about this
problem we encountered in week four
which was this let me code up a program
called again compare. Pi here but this
time compare to Strings and not numbers
so let me for instance do uh get one
string from the user called s just for
the sake of discussion let me get
another string from the user uh called T
so that we can actually do some
comparison here and if s equals equals T
let's go ahead and print out that
they're the same else let's go ahead and
print out that they're different so this
is very similar to what we did in week
four but in week four recall we did this
spef specifically because we had
encountered a problem for instance if I
run whoops
uh if I
run what's going on uh input
T come
on oh the okay wow okay long day all
right if I run the proper command python
of compare. py then let's go ahead and
type in something like cat in all
lowercase cats in all lowercase and
they're the same uh if though I do this
again with dog and dog they're the same
and of course cat and dog they're
different but does anyone recall from
two weeks ago when I typed in my name
twice both identically capitalized what
did it say that they were in
fact different and why was that like why
were two strings in C different even
though I typed literally the same
thing two different places in memory so
each string might look the same
aesthetically but of course was stored
elsewhere in memory and yet python
appears to be using the equality
operator equals equals like you and I
would expect as humans actually
comparing for us Char by Char in each of
those strings for actual equality so
this is a feature of python in that it's
just easier to do and why well this
derives from the reality that in Python
there are no pointers anymore there's no
underlying memory management it's not up
to you now to worry about those lower
level details the language itself takes
care of that for you and so similarly if
I do this and don't ask the user for two
strings but just one and then I do
something like this how about give
myself a second variable T set it equal
to s.
capitalize which note is not the same as
upper capitalize by Design per Python's
documentation will only capitalize the
first letter for you I can now print out
say two F strings here what the value of
s is and then let me print out with
another F string what the value of t is
and recall that in C this was a problem
because if you capitalize s and store it
in t we accidentally capitalized both s
and t but in this case in Python when I
actually run this and type in cat in all
lowercase the original s is unchanged
because when I use capitalize on line
three this is indeed capitalizing s but
it's returning a copy of the result it
cannot change S itself because again for
that technical term s is IM mutable
strings once they exist cannot be
changed themselves but you can return
copies and modified mutated copies of
those same strings so in short all of
those headaches we encountered in week
four are now solved really in the way
you might expect and here's another one
that we dwell on in week four with the
colored uh liquid in glasses let me code
up a program called swap. pi and in
swap. pi let me set x equal to 1 y equal
to 2 and then let me just print out an F
string here so how about X X is this
comma Y is that and then let me do that
twice just for the sake of demonstration
and in here recall that we had to create
a swap function but then we had to pass
it in by reference with the Amper sand
and like oh my God like that was kind of
peak complexity and see well if you want
to swap X and Y in Python you could do X
comma yal y comma X and now python of
swap whoops python of
swap. and there we go all of that's
handled for you sort of like a shell
game without even a temporary variable
in mind so what more can we do here how
about a few final building blocks and
these related now to files from that
week four suppose that I want to save
some names and numbers in like a a CSV
file comma separated values which is
like a very lightweight spreadsheet well
first let me create a uh phonebook CSV
file that just has name comma number as
like the first row there but after after
that I'm going to go ahead now and code
up a phonebook dopy program that
actually allows me to add things to this
phone book so let me split my screen
here so that we can see the old and the
new and down here in my code for phone
book. in this new and improved version
I'm going to actually import a whole
other Library this one called CSV and
here too especially for people in data
science and the like really like being
in a manipulate files and data that
might very well be stored in
spreadsheets or csvs comma separated
values which we we saw briefly in week
four in phonebook then it suffices to
just import CSV after reading the
documentation therefore because this is
going to give me functionality in code
related to CSV files so here's how I
might open a file in Python I literally
call open it's not fop now it's just
open and I open this file called
phonebook.com
going to open it in a pend mode not
right where it would change the whole
thing I want to append new line at a
time uh after this I want to get maybe
how about a name from the user so let's
prompt the user for some input for their
name and then let's prompt the user for
a number as well using input prompting
for number all right and now this is a
little cryptic and you'd only know this
from the documentation but if you want
to write line rows to a CSV file that
you can then view in Excel or the like
you can do this give me a variable
called writer but I could call it
anything I want let me use a CSV do
writer function that comes with this CSV
Library passing in the file this is like
saying hey python treat this open file
as a CSV file so that things are
separated with commas and nicely
formatted in rows and columns now I'm
going to do this use that writer to
write a row well what do I want to write
I want to write a short list namely the
current name and the current number to
that file but I don't want to use FR
printf and percent s and all of that
stuff that we might have had in the past
and now I just want to close the file
let me reopen my ter teral let me run
python of phone book. and let me type in
how about David and then +1
949468 2750 and hold crossing my fingers
watching the actual CSV at top left my
code has just added me to the file and
if I were to run it again for instance
with Carter in plus1 617495 1000
crossing my fingers again we've updated
the file and it turns out there's code
now via which I can even read that file
but I can first tighten this up just so
you've seen it it turns out into python
it's so common to open files and close
them you know humans make mistakes and
they often forget to close files which
might then end up using more memory than
you intend so you can alternatively do
this in Python so that you don't have to
worry about closing files you can use
this keyword instead you can say with
the opening of this file as a variable
called file do all of the following
underneath so I'm indenting most of my
code I'm using this new python specific
keyword called wi and this is just a
matter of saying with the following
opening of the file do those next four
lines of code and then automatically
close it for me at the end of the
indentation it's a minor optimization
but this again is sort of the pythonic
way to do things instead how else might
I do this too well it turns out that the
code I've written here on line n
especially is a little fragile right if
any human opens the spreadsheet the CSV
file in Excel Google spreadsheets Apple
numbers and maybe like moves the columns
around just because maybe they're
fussing they SA it and they don't
realize they've now changed my
assumptions I don't want to necessarily
write name and number always in that
order CU what if someone screws up and
flips those two columns by literally
dragging and dropping so it turns out
that instead of using a list here we can
use another feature of this Library as
follows instead of using a writer
there's something called a dictionary
writer or dict writer that takes the
same argument as input the file that's
opened but now the one difference here
is that you need to tell this dictionary
writer
that your field names are name and
number and let me close the CSV here
name and number are the names of the
fields The Columns in this CSV file and
when it comes time to write a new row
the syntax here is going to be a little
uglier but it's just a dictionary the
name I want to write to the dictionary
is going to be whatever name the human
typed in the number that I want to write
to the the CSV file is going to be
whatever the number the human typed in
but what's different next about this
code is by simply using a dictionary
writer here instead of the generic
writer now the columns can be in this
order or this order or any order and the
dictionary writer is going to figure out
based on the first line of text in that
CSV where to put name where to put
number so if you flip them no big deal
it's going to notice oh wait the columns
changed and it's going to insert the
columns correctly so just again another
more powerful feature that lets you
focus
on lets you focus on real work as
opposed to actually uh getting tied up
in the weeds of writing code like this
otherwise questions on this one as well
but what we will do now is come full
circle to some of the more uh
sophisticated examples with which we
began and I'm going to go back over to
my own Mac laptop here where I've got my
own terminal window up and running and I
was just going to introduce a couple of
final libraries that really speak to
just how powerful python can can be and
how quickly you can get up and running
to be fair can't necessarily do all of
these things in the cloud like in code
spaces because you need access to your
own speakers or microphone or the like
so that's why I'm doing it on my own Mac
here but let me go ahead and open up a
program called
speech. and I'm not using VSS code here
I'm using a program called VI that's
entirely terminal window based but it's
going to allow me for instance to import
the python text to speech version three
Library I'm going to give myself a
variable called engine that's going to
be set equal to the python text to
speech 3 libraries init method which is
just going to initialize this library
that relates to text to speech I'm going
to then use the engines say function to
say something like how about hello comma
world and then as my last line I'm going
to say engine. runand wait capitalized
as such to tell my program now to run
that speech and wait until it's done all
right I'm going to save this file I'm
going to run python of speech. py and
I'm going to cross my fingers as always
and hello world all right so now I have
a program that's actually synthesizing
speech using a library like this how can
I now modify this to be a little more
interesting well how about this let me
go ahead and prompt the user for their
name like we've done several times here
using Python's built-in name function
and now let me go ahead and use a format
string in conjunction with this Library
interpolating the value of name there
and at least if my name is somewhat
phonetically pronounceable let's go
ahead and run python ofp
speech. type in my name and hello David
okay it's a sort of weird choice of
inflection but we're starting to
synthesize voice not unlike Siri or
Google assistant or Alexa or the like
now we can maybe do something a little
more advanced too in addition to
synthesizing speech in this way we could
synthesize for instance uh an actual
graphic let me go ahead now and do
something like this let me create a
program called
qr. I'm going to go ahead and import a
library called OS which gives you access
to operating system related
functionality in Python I'm going to
import a library I've pre-installed
called QR code which is a
two-dimensional barcode that you might
have seen in the real world I'm going to
go ahead and create an image variable
using this QR code library's make
function which per its documentation
takes a URL like one of cs50's own
videos so we'll do this with YouTube uh
/xv f
zj5
p g g0 so hopefully that's the right
lecture and now we've got image. saave
which is going to allow me to create a
file called qr. ping think back now on
problem set 4 and how painful it was to
save files we'll just use the save
function now in Python and save this as
a ping file portable Network graphic and
then lastly let's just go ahead and open
uh the with the command open qr. ping on
my Mac so that hopefully this just
automatically opens all right I'm going
to go ahead and just double check my
syntax here so that I haven't made any
mistakes I'm going to go ahead and run
python of qr. enter that opens up this
let me go ahead and zoom in if you've
got a phone handy and you'd like to scan
this code
here whether in person or
online I apologize you won't appreciate
it amazing okay and lastly let me go
back into our speech example here uh
create a final ending here on our final
moments and how about we just say
something like this was cs50 like this
let's go ahead here fix my
capitalization just for tidiness get rid
of the name and now with our final
flourish and your introduction to python
equipped here we go this was cs50 all
right we'll see you next
[Applause]
time
[Music]
all right this is cs50 and this is
already week seven and this is the week
where we'll continue where we left off
with python introducing you to a bit
more syntax and capabilities of the
language so you can solve like
interesting problems but a lot of those
problems increasingly are now going to
involve data in some form after all if
you think of most any website or mobile
app uh or uh process nowadays that
involves solving problems it almost
always involves some amount of data and
often data at scale lots and lots of
data and so what we're going to see
first today is that yes you can use
Python to solve all the problems past
that we've seen and also some data
specific ones but sometimes it's just
going to be annoying it's going to be a
little painful it's just going to be
more work than you might like to just
get to some answer and so today we'll
too introduce you to a new language
called SQL structured query language and
this is a language that wur is actually
much smaller relatively speaking than C
and python it sort of does less but it
does it really well and it's a language
for querying databases storing data in
it updating it inserting it deleting it
and so much more and it's the kind of
Technology that's used nowadays in
indeed web apps and mobile apps data
science analytics and and so much more
it's really good at storing lots and
lots of data now this is yet another
language and believe it or not next week
we'll introduce you to three more
languages HTML and CSS which are not
technically programming languages
they're all about Aesthetics and markup
of information but also JavaScript which
is in fact a programming language but
the goals here in cs50 really are going
to be to empower you to program more
generally and indeed when you're out
there in the real world some years from
now invariably there's going to be some
new other popular language out there and
hopefully in this week and next week and
Beyond among the goals is not just to
teach you these languages specifically
but again like how to teach yourself the
future languages that we've not even
heard about just yet so with that said
let's begin with a survey of sorts if
you go to this URL on your phone or
laptop cs50. l/f favorites a very simple
Google form awaits you that's just going
to ask you a couple of multiple choice
questions so go to cs50.
l/f favorites and that should lead you
to a Google form that looks a little
something like this asking you first as
of now in week seven what is your
favorite language among those options
here and then further down one more
question if you think back on problem
sets 0 through six what was if any your
favorite uh problem set problem be it in
scratch or C or python so answer those
two
questions and in a moment I'll flip over
to my screen here where you'll see and
anyone who's used Google forms knows the
spreadsheet that's collecting now this
data um Microsoft Office 365 can do the
same if you use one of those forms and
what you see here now is a spreadsheet
in Google Sheets enumerating all of the
audience's questions language is in
column B problem is in column C and each
row represents one student who has
responded uh a few of you were super
eager for class today at 8:33 a.m.
eastern time 10:32 11:10 okay so now
we're getting into the actual class time
here and if I scroll down we'll probably
see few dozen couple hundred Answers by
now and yeah so we're getting a whole
lot of answers here and I'm seeing some
patterns emerge but but it's not
necessarily obvious to the human eyes
what those patterns are now of course
you can use Google spreadsheets you can
like highlight the data and you can
create charts magically out of it but
you can only do what Google lets you do
with the data and same thing for
Microsoft Excel or apple numbers but
wouldn't it be nice to just be able to
manipulate the raw data relatively
simple though it is to just answer
questions about the data Maybe long-term
create your own charts customize it just
the way you want rather than be holding
to like software that's off the shelf
like this well how could we go about
doing this well let me propose that we
treat this data set now as what we're
going to call for now a flat file
database we'll see today that there's
fancier databases but the simplest
database in the world is really just
like a CSV file and we saw that a couple
of weeks ago in C we wrote a bit of C
code that used F printf to write data to
a file using commas as the separator we
didn't really do much more with csvs at
the time though because it's really
annoying painful timec consuming not fun
to use see for something like that
because of malok and memory and all that
stuff but with python it's going to be
much easier and so anytime you have
access to some data set where you can
just like download it to your own Mac or
PC or your Cloud environment it's sort
of a candidate for now writing code to
do something with the data Maybe analyze
it right away if it's been human inputed
manually maybe you have to clean it up
by doing a lot of find and replace but
not with your keyboard but rather with
code and so let me go ahead and do this
let me go back to my uh Google sheet
here that has all of the data that's
come in now and let me go ahead and
download this via uh the file menu
here and let's see download and you can
see a whole bunch of options of most
formats might be familiar but today
we'll focus just on this one comma
separated values or CSV that's going to
go ahead and download it on my Mac here
into my own downloads folder and now I'm
going to go ahead and do this let me go
ahead and pull up VSS code in the cloud
here and if you've never done this
before there's a couple of ways to do it
but the simplest way to upload a file to
your codes space so to speak is just a
sort of drag and drop that's going to
magically upload it to the server there
and we'll see that one it has a very
long file name which I'm I'm actually
going to clean this up because that's
going to be very tedious to type in my
code so I could either rightclick of of
course up here but I'm going to use my
Linux command so let's move this file
called cs50 2022 something or other and
let's just name it more simply
favorites. CSV so all lowercase no
spaces sort of good Basics and let me go
ahead now and open up this file with
code favorites. CSV I'll close my file
explorer and we'll see exactly the same
data as before but not quite as pretty
as Google Sheets makes it be rather we
see here that I still have three columns
timestamp language problem and then all
of the values down below including the
timestamps and the answers therefore but
it doesn't have proper columns it just
has commas separating them now we could
very easily write python code just like
we wrote code to manipulate files like
this either to write or read but in
instead let's do something that's a
little more pleasant which is indeed in
the form of python so python actually
comes with Native support for csvs it
has indeed a package called CSV that
just lets you read and write and do a
whole bunch of useful stuff when it
comes to CSV files so let's go ahead and
do something with this file let me go
back here to VSS code I'm going to close
favorites. CSV for now but just remember
in your mind that timestamp was the
first column language was the second
column and problem was the third and
notice because we're using commas they
don't again line up perfectly but that's
not a problem there are two commas in
every line presumably and I'm going to
go ahead and now create a file called
how about uh favorites. piy so that I
can start writing some code to
manipulate this data and let's do
something simple let's just write a
simple program in Python that opens this
file reads it and prints something out
just as like a safety check that I know
what I'm doing even though it's not
going to be useful so in Python if you
want CSV support you import CSV and that
gives you access to all the magical
capabilities thereof let me now go ahead
and use this technique to open a file in
Python which is similar in C but with
python I'm going to do this the keyword
with I'm going to open a file called
favorites. CSV which was the shorter
name I gave it this is optional but just
for explicitness I'm going to open it in
read mode explicitly just like f open
took a second argument as well and I'm
going to name this file once open quite
simply file though I could call it
anything I want and now it's just an
open file so far as python knows at this
moment it's just text or better yet it's
just zeros and ones if you want this
python package called CSV to actually do
something useful with it you have to
load this file now into the library and
the simplest way to do this is to give
myself like a variable called reader
because I want to read this file though
this too I could call anything else I'm
going to then set that equal to the
return value of a function called CSV do
reader and I pass to that per the
documentation the open file so step one
I open the file and this just gives me
me access to the bytes there in step two
now with csvreader tells the python
package called CSV to do something
useful with it and start analyzing the
commas and uh allow me to uh parse it
further so let's go ahead and do this
let me go ahead now and within this Loop
let's say this with sorry within this
open file let's do this for every row if
you will or line in the file AKA reader
let's go ahead and print out now just
how about Row Bracket one now what's
going on here well it turns out if you
read the documentation for the CSV
reader function what it hands you back
is essentially this special object so to
speak that allows you to treat it as
though it's just a really big list of
lines from the file AKA reader so by
saying for Row in reader this is a way
more succinct way of saying uh give me
the first line in the file plus plus
give me the second line in the file Plus
plus and so forth that we would have
done what much more mechanically in C
this is just much more pythonic and
English friendly if you will so in every
iteration of this Loop row is going to
contain all of the data from the current
row but better yet what the reader
function does for me is it hands me each
row not just as a big string or Stir of
text in Python it gives me what
apparently based on the syntax on line
six any Instinct yeah it's giving me
back indeed a list and I'm I presume the
visual clue for you was the fact that
we're using square brackets here and
indeed Row Bracket one is going to be
not the first but the second element in
that list and so just take a guess when
I run this code in a moment What's going
to get printed the timestamp the
language or the
problem the yeah oh the language the
language because it's the second column
that is in the file delimited by those
those commas so let me go ahead and do
this let me clear my terminal down here
here let me run python of favorites.i
and enter and there's everything it was
super fast but there's a really long
list here and in fact if I increase the
size of my terminal and start scrolling
up you'll just see all of the raw data
now this isn't that useful yet I could
have just glanced at the CSV but clearly
now I have the ability to open the file
parse it so to speak that is break it up
into its constituent parts and do
something with specific Parts therein
all right so if I want to do this a
little more pleasantly though let me at
least least make this semantically a
little cleaner and you know what just
for clarity let me just give myself a
variable it's not strictly necessary but
I know that this is the favorite uh for
instance uh language so let's just call
it favorite set it equal to Row Bracket
1 and now just to be more explicit in my
code even though again we don't need the
variable per se this codee's of course
going to do the same thing it's just
using an additional variable called
favorite if I go down here scroll up run
the program again I get back the exact
same data but this is a stepping stone
to something that's even more powerful
about python support for CSV files is
that you don't have to just treat the
return value as a list with zero and one
and two so just thinking intuitively
here why is this maybe not the best
design to hand you the programmer back
the data in a list that's numerically
indexed with
012 it clearly works but critique this
what could go wrong what's a little
poorly designed yeah you have to always
remember what
are
yeah exactly so if yeah so it's up to
you to repeat it's up to you to remember
like what column the data is actually in
and you know God forbid you're you're
collaborating with someone else on the
spreadsheet you know you've if you've
used Google spreadsheets you can move
columns around maybe just because you
want to visually reorganize things and
if you do this and then someone else
downloads that same data all of their
code is going to break so that's just
really bad design it's fragile just
because it's you're sort of on the honor
System that one means the data that you
want so wouldn't it be nice if we could
be a little more explicit well recall
that the very first line in this file is
actually this and I paused the output
this time so that we can see more
optionally I just reran favorites St pi
and notice one of these things is not
like the other every output was either
scratch or C or python except for this
first one why am I seeing the word
language
here where did language come from you
didn't have the ability to manual input
oh no where did it come from
yeah yeah the header the very first row
in the file which by human convention
generally just defines what the columns
represent so that there's some human
useful information there now that's not
really intended to be part of my output
at the moment so there is a way to skip
this if you want to skip the first row
you can actually do something like this
you can say next row and that will just
ignore that row so that I'm starting
really with the every row thereafter but
there's a better way to handle this than
that that will get rid of the row in the
output but let me go ahead and use a
different feature of the CSV package
that's just going to make this a little
cleaner Al together so let me clear my
terminal window here let me undo this
next thing that I just added and instead
of using a reader let me go ahead and
use a dictionary reader abbreviated dict
reader that's going to now return me the
equivalent of all of the rows one at a
time so I can still call it Reader just
as before but as the name implies what
this reader is going to return is not a
list after list after list but a
dictionary a dictionary a dictionary and
remember a dictionary is just a
collection of key value pairs so what
does that mean what are the keys what
are the values well now that I'm using a
dictionary reader I can actually do this
instead of sort of on the honor System
remembering that I want column one I can
treat row now not as a list but as a
dictionary and that means I can go in
here and say quote unquote language and
we saw that back in week six python
allows you to index into dictionaries
using square bracket notation in strings
or stirs on the inside just like lists
allow for numbers but this now I think
is going to be a little more robust if I
run this again python of favorites. py
all of that worked out fine and let me
pause the output to by using this
program called more now I don't even see
the header so now whoever works it uh
with python wrote the code for this
package to just analyze that first line
of code use the header as you just
called it as the keys and then every
time you iterate through this Loop it
updates the values the values the values
but the keys stay the same any questions
then on this
technique spiced to say this would be
painful in C
yes
Associated exactly so the keys are
always going to be quote unquote
timestamp uh Pro language and problem
but on each iteration of this Loop here
uh the row is going to contain a
different row of values different row
values different row values so you're
going to get back one dictionary for
every student who submitted the Google
form if you will while iterating through
it there all right so once we have this
ability here why don't we go ahead and
transition
into how about not just using that
dictionary reader which makes the code a
little more robust because now if you
move the columns around no big deal it
doesn't matter if the numeric indices
change you can still use those keywords
instead well let's actually analyze the
data now I'm just spitting it out which
is not solving any problems for anyone
so let's go ahead and and count the
popularity of scratch C and Python and
see what everyone's uh been thinking
here all right so how might I do this
well let me go ahead and do this up here
before I start iterating let me give
myself let's say three variables and to
keep things simple I'll say one variable
called scratch set it equal to zero for
zero students so far C is going to equal
zero and python is going to equal zero
there's a slightly prettier way of doing
this just because this is like three
lines of code to do something very
simple you could alternatively in Python
but not C do scratch comma C comma
python equals 0 comma 0 so kind of
slightly more elegant just to fit it all
into one line but now let's just do
something more interesting on line seven
I'm still going to figure out what the
current favorite language is and now I'm
just going to do some conditional checks
How about if that favorite equals equals
quote unquote scratch let's go ahead and
increment Scratch by one we can't do
plus plus in Python but we can do plus
equals 1 how about L if favorite equals
equals c then let's do C+ equal 1 L and
not we could do else this is actually a
good design question should I do else
should I do L if any instincts here
yeah yeah really good instincts just in
case someone goes and adds another
language to the form next week because
we're obviously going to introduce
another language today you don't want
your code to now artificially inflate
the scores for python just because
you're conflating multiple languages
together so the more defensive sort of
better way to write this code I agree
would be L if favorite equals equals
python then let's go ahead and increment
python plus equals 1 and if there's a
new language next week we're obviously
going to have to update the code but at
least we're not miscounting we're just
missing the new language so I think
that's slightly more robust all right
now at the very bottom of this program
and outside of the loop when I'm all
done counting let me go ahead and print
out using some f strings how about the
total number of people who uh whose
favorite is scratch so this is just uh
week six F string syntax let me go ahead
and print out another F string for C and
I'm of course putting the variables in
curly braces all lowercase but the
English words I'm doing capitalization
for Let's do an final one with f uh
python colon and then in curly braces
python close quote and I think I'm done
so let me just hide my terminal for a
second here's the total program same
stuff as before open favorites. CSV open
it further with the dictionary reader to
do that processing for us initialize
three variables to zero just so we have
something to count with and then iterate
over the file row by row and this is
just some sort of week one style
conditional logic albe it in Python
counting things all right so how can we
now execute this let me go back to my
terminal python of favorites.i and here
we go uh as of today everyone who's
reporting in live via the Google form
their favorite languages are
interesting that's pretty interesting
too after just one week of python no
less so but scratch is a healthy
Contender there a lot of C so a pretty
good mix here so is this going to be the
best way to write this program long term
well as you noted if there's a new
language next week this week we're going
to have to constantly update this and
here's where you should let your mind
wander to like the future like if we
have a fourth language fifth language
6th sth eth which aspect here might kind
of have some code smell to it like this
probably isn't the best design to set us
up for the
future what might be better than this
yeah add language line yeah we have to
keep adding a language to line five and
okay not a big deal we could add like
SQL today and maybe JavaScript next week
but you know anytime a a line of code a
line of logic is just going to kind of
grow out of control and we've had this
chat a couple of times with different
syntax there's probably a better way
than that so let's do that instead of
using these individual variables we
could make maybe use a list but a list
would be a little confusing because like
what does braet zero mean what is
bracket 1 bracket two but a dictionary
recall is like this Swiss army knife of
data structures whereby you can
associate anything with anything else
keys with values so I dare say a cleaner
way to solve this problem that sets us
up for Less work or confusion later
would be to create like a new variable
called counts if that's what we're doing
counting things up and just set it equal
to an empty dictionary and you can
literally say adct with the open
parenthesis closed parenthesis nothing
or the more pythonic just use open and
Clos curly braces with nothing inside
that gives me an empty dictionary just
like square brackets gives me a list now
my logic down here has to change a
little bit but what's nice is I don't
need one conditional for every language
because again if we have a fourth a
fifth a sixth that chunk of code is also
going to grow a bit out of control too
so I can get rid of this here and what I
think I'm going to do is say this
whatever the current favorite is from
the current Row in the file why don't we
go into our counts variable at that key
and again favorite is a variable it's
not quote unquote favorite it's going to
be scratch or C or Python and then why
don't we go ahead and just increment
whatever the value of that count is at
that key now this is technically bugy
we're really close but there is a
bug does anyone want to conjecture what
the bug is
yeah a good question that answers my
question in uh nonetheless so no like
the magic you describe will not happen
and to repeat the the hypothesis will
this automatically create a key for
every uh language that we try plugging
into those square brackets short answer
no odds are this is going to create a
key error one of those traceback error
messages that you've probably seen by
now either in class or in problem sets
whereby if scratch hasn't appeared in
the dictionary before or C or python
like then the dictionary has no clue
what you're talking about so I think we
actually still need some conditional
logic but not that's going to grow
longer and longer with each language
what I think we probably want to do is
this if the current favorite is in the
counts dictionary and this is the
pythonic way of just saying is this key
in this dictionary then go ahead and
safely do count favorite plus equals 1
else to your conjecture now else what do
I want to do counts
favorite
equals yeah one so initialize a brand
new key to a brand new value of one
because I'm obviously just seen this
language otherwise increment again and
again and now down here I just need to
tweak my syntax a little bit I don't
need to print out all of these things
one at a time manually I can actually
get away I think with another loop at
the very bottom here so how about I do
this for each favorite in those counts
and this is again the pythonic way to
iterate over all of the keys in a
dictionary go ahead and print out using
an F string whatever the current
favorite is scratch or C or Python and
then a colon and then figure out what
its count is and you can do that by
going into the counts dictionary looking
at the favorite key and get back its
value so close my curly braces I close
my quotes and even though this looks
ugly at the moment now this is much more
dynamic because if we go and add SQL to
the CSV file tomorrow where we add
JavaScript next week this will just work
it will keep working now automatically
all I change is the Google form not my
actual code all right let's try python
of favorites.i cross my fingers as
always and there now is the data as of
now questions on this code here
yeah really good good question what if
you wanted to print it in a particular
order uh well I could give you a couple
of solutions like if you want to print
it out in it's already coincidentally in
alphabetical order so you got that for
free although that's just by chance here
but there is a way to do this and let me
propose that we go down here to my Loop
and I explicitly use a function you
might not have seen in Python yet but
it's literally called sorted which is
going to take either a list or in this
case a dictionary and by default sort it
by key alphabetically now if my
intuition is correct this is not going
to change the output because it's
already alphabetical but if you read the
documentation for the sorted function it
takes multiple parameters potentially
some of which are named parameters and
so you can actually do this if you want
to sort the counts but you want to
reverse the order for whatever reason
here so that it's reverse alphabetical
order now let me go ahead and rerun this
and I'll keep the previous output on the
screen enter and now it's backwards uh
alphabetically if you will other
questions on this here
here no how about then how about then we
transition
to changing sorting by value and let me
this is going to escalate a little
quickly briefly but then we'll we'll
tone it down again notice that right now
this is indeed sorting by key what if
especially if I have lots of data it'd
be nice to make like a top 10 list or in
this case a top three list and actually
see in order of the counts the values uh
what these popular ones are so it's not
C python scratch it should ideally be
python then C then scratch because of
the values and the magnitude thereof so
how can I do this well it turns out
there's another key another uh parameter
that you can pass to the sorted function
that is typically implemented as a
function itself and so I'm going to go
ahead and do this I'm going to
temporarily Define a function called get
value just to make my life easier and
this get value function is going to take
I'll say a language par parameter and
then all I'm going to do is return
whatever the count is of that language
so out of context this is just a super
simple function that you hand it a
language like scratch or C or python
it's just going to tell you what the
count is thereof in that uh in that
dictionary called counts but what I can
do now down here in my newly introduced
call to sorted is I can tell it what to
use as its key instead of using
literally the key scratch C python I can
sort of override that behavior and say
you know what to figure out what to sort
by go ahead and call this function
called get value notice that I have not
put parentheses after get value because
I don't want to call get value right
then and there I want to pass the get
value function as itself in argument to
the sorted function so that the sorted
function written years ago by the people
at python can call my version of get
value again and again and again when
they try to sort sort this actual data
so now if I add that and I leave reverse
equals true let's see what happens
python of favorites. py enter and now I
get my top 10 or in this case top three
list and if I had more sophisticated
data with like more columns Al together
that I actually care about I could even
sort this more uh powerfully as well but
let me clean this up a little bit just
so you've seen it even though we won't
use these that often in cs50 until the
end of the class will they come up again
technically this is a little bit H this
isn't necessarily the best design to
spend all this time implementing a
function and then only use it in one
place in general we've argued that H you
don't necessarily need a variable if
you're only going to use it in one place
you don't really need a function if
and here we kind of have a good
candidate for that and so it turns out
in Python if you don't want to bother
creating a function just to use it once
you can create what's called an
anonymous function AKA a Lambda function
like the lamb Lambda symbol familiar and
a Lambda function the syntax is a little
strange looking but you say this you
literally say Lambda you literally then
say the name of the argument that you
want this Anonymous function with no
name to take then you have a colon and
then quite simply you write what you
want the return value of this function
to be you don't even say return
literally these Lambda functions are
meant to be used super turly so that you
can in one line Express something like
this and I admit this looks more cryptic
I think than the previous version but as
you get more comfortable with python or
other languages that support this
feature it allows you to not bother with
lines of code like that and just tighten
up your code a little bit so this line
here lamba language colon counts
language is the oneline version of this
and you don't even need to bother
picking a name for it Lambda tells
python I didn't waste any time thinking
of a name for this
function so questions then on this
technique technique of using python to
analyze data like
this any
questions we're almost done with python
questions no okay so why don't we make
things a little more interesting because
we had a much juicier data set with the
problems that we've assigned over the
past several weeks why don't we go ahead
and quite simply you know I think we
wrote pretty darn good code here so I
think we can pretty much just change a
bit of it to say let's see if I don't
want language I want problem and if I
want to sort by not language but problem
I think that's it I think if I didn't
Overlook something here just by changing
what column I'm reading the data from
and then just to be consistent renaming
my variables just so I know what I'm
looking at what will this program now do
after those minor
changes what will I see when I run
this
what would be the first thing I see when
I run
this tough crowd today yes problem yeah
the problem this the top problem so the
most popular problem which I'm a little
worried it might be hello or just
scratch but let's go ahead and see so
let me go ahead and open my terminal
window I'll even maximize my terminal
window so we can see a lot let me go
ahead and run python of favorites. py
I'm going to go ahead now and cross my
fingers that I didn't mess up and hit
enter and okay great we peaked early so
scratch was the most popular program
according to the data at the time I
downloaded it I'm sure other votes have
come in since filter uh in week four was
tied then with tan as well Mario is a
close third there and so forth so this
is helpful for us on staff that uh not
so much love down here at the bottom of
the list so it was a bunch of code to
write but now that we've written it in
this very versatile Dynamic way it's
pretty good for just like crunching data
and doing some analytics but it's still
a decent number of lines to have had to
write manually and this is where
sometimes it isn't necessarily the right
tool for the job but rather the job that
uh but rather a candidate for using some
other language alog together especially
when it's not just a one-time program
that you run and you want to see the
answer what if you want to take input
from the user and ask uh answer
questions dynamically like a mobile app
would like a website would like
Microsoft Excel or apple numbers or
Google Sheets would for for you well
let's make one final change for now to
this version of the program and actually
take in some user input so besides just
loading all of the data into memory
let's go ahead and down below here not
just print out the top 10 list if you
will but prompt the user for their
favorite so I'm going to use Python's
input function and I'm just going to
prompt them with favorite quote unquote
like tell me what your favorite problem
what problem uh rather uh you interested
in and now let me go ahead and say if
that favorite is in the counts variable
so you didn't type in something random
that we didn't actually assign as a
problem then let me go ahead and print
with a format string whatever that
favorite is of yours and show you the
actual popularity thereof by indexing
into counts using that favorite as the
key and printing this so now it's a
dynamic program it doesn't dump all of
the data and all of the summations
rather it's going to allow me to see
what my choice of favorite is and I'm
going to go ahead and say uh let's see
I'm a fan of Mario here so enter and
indeed we see the same value we saw a
moment ago but just for Mario but the
point now is that one all of this is
possible two it's way easier and more
pleasant than this would have been in C
this is still only 15 lines of code and
in C again there's the memory management
there's the iterating over the strings
trying to find the commas there's just a
lot more work but honestly even when you
just want to answer a question like this
in Excel in Apple Numbers Google sheets
you know generally you can just
highlight things you can click a button
and boom you get your answer for
summation or Max or Min or any of those
sort of Basics wouldn't it be nice if we
weren't taking a step backwards as
programmers and being sort of more
powerful and yet we now have to do more
of the work so maybe sometimes Python's
not or any language is not the best tool
for the job and that's going to now
allow us to introduce more generally
something called a relational database
graduating from Mere flat file databases
like text files or binary files in which
all of your data is stored to something
more proper but first
questions really good question to
reiterate if I were to is this case
sensitive so if I were to type in Mario
in all lowercase and hit enter I
actually get no such response now that
might be acceptable because the problem
technically what is a capital M but
that's a little uh ridiculous to be that
pedantic about the input so how could we
solve
this any tips for how we can make this a
little more robust
yeah okay
yeah yeah so we could use a few
different functions one of which is
called title which will change it to
title case where it capitalizes like in
most English sentences the first letter
of that sentence we could use capitalize
we could use upper we could use lower
but indeed we could just decide how we
want to standardize the capitalization
either uppercase lowercase or some
combination thereof and just make sure
that you change the counts themselves
make sure that you do the same to
favorite and make sure that maybe you
keep a backup of the data if you want to
show the original version that came from
the CSV without presuming to just
capitalize everything for the user but
indeed that would be the most common
scenario you just make things case
insensitive when doing those matches
other questions now on python before we
leave it behind for the coming
week all right well then let's introduce
these relational databases so relational
database is what like every is a super
popular way of storing lots of data like
this is what the Twitter's of the world
the Googles of the world the metas of
the world use to store some of their
data at scale there are alternatives to
relational databases um indeed today
we'll talk about a language called SQL
there's so a movement if you will or an
alternative generally called No SQL
which is just the opposite you don't use
SQL there are things called
objectoriented databases and the like
but if you've ever heard of MySQL or
postgress SQL or uh Microsoft SQL server
or Oracle or Maria DB or a bunch of
other products both free and Commercial
this is what they're talking about
databases that are designed to store
lots of data and what's nice about
relational databases is that they're
really similar to the spreadsheets with
which you were presumably familiar long
before today's class so a relational
database is going to store as you'll see
all of the data in rows and columns now
the terminology will thereafter be a
little different instead of having
sheets you're going to have tables but
those tables are still going to have
rows and columns and you're going to
have even more control over the
performance of your data when you start
to access it using this structured query
language or SQL this is a language you
can use for web apps mobile apps uh a
lot of analysts would sit down and their
Mac or PC and actually ask questions of
data to get back the answer and
wonderfully even though there will be
some new syntax today SQL really just
does four basic things crud is the sort
of crude acronym here crud is a way of
remembering that a relational database
supports ultimately creating data
reading data updating data and deleting
data so even if you're feeling like wow
this is a lot of new syntax which it
isn't relative to our past languages the
only things you're doing really are
creating dat data reading data updating
and deleting the same now a little
confusingly in SQL the corresponding
functions or commands that exist that
map to crud are actually this so it's
still create but there's another one
called insert uh it's not read which is
more of the computer scientist way of
saying it but select which is a little
more explicit like select data you care
about update is still update delete is
still delete but there's another command
called drop which lets you drop that is
delete entire tables as well so you can
create tables using syntax that's
generally going to look like this you'll
say create table you'll give the name of
the table uh which you can call almost
anything you want but generally all
lowercase no spaces is best then in
parentheses you can specify a comma
separated list of the columns that you
might want in this table so this is the
code equivalent in the SQL language of
like manually opening Google Sheets or
Excel or numbers and like clicking in
the top left cell and like typing
timestamp and then in the next typing
language and then in the third typing
problem this is the way to sort of
Define what your headers are if you will
in a spreadsheet but now it's called a
table now we won't use this command
manually first let's do something a
little simpler we're going to start off
by just importing this data ourselves
and I'm going to go ahead and do this
let me go back to vs code here I'm going
to leave behind favorites. py for now
because now we're going to transition to
this other language called SQL and to do
this I am going to create a new database
file and I'm going to do so using a
command called SQL light 3 which is just
the third version thereof and I'm going
to give the database a name of
favorites. DB there's different
conventions but this is one of the most
common when I hit enter this is going to
create for me a new empty database just
like opening an Untitled spreadsheet in
Excel Google Sheets or Apple Numbers I'm
being prompted do I want to create
favorites. DB I'll hit y for yes okay
we're up and running now you're going to
notice a different prompt I'm not in my
Linux prompt per se which is always the
dollar sign I'm now inside of the
program called SQL light and we're going
to use SQL light SQL light 3 as just an
interactive way for now of playing with
SQL code at the end of today we'll show
you how you can use SQL in Python code
so that you still write python code to
do whatever you want but you can talk to
databases using Python and this is
exactly how web apps mobile apps work
for instance on iOS uh and an i phone an
iPad or the like if you want to store
data it's very often stored in a SQL
database as we're about to do um but you
might use a language called Swift or
objective c and same exists in the world
of Android using Java or cotlin or
something else to query the database so
we're going to see SQL in isolation for
now like an analyst might just use at
their Mac or PC but we're going to tie
it together by Day end so at this
terminal uh SQL light let me go ahead
and execute uh this command first I'm
going to first put SQL light into CSV
mode because I'm going to cut some
Corners initially and I'm just going to
automatically import all of the data
that was submitted via that Google form
which I exported as a CSV and uploaded
to my code space and I'm just going to
automatically say turn this CSV file
into a SQL database for me just so I
don't have to figure out what those
create table commands are so to do this
I'm going to say mode CSV so that SQL
light knows that this is the command uh
knows that this is a CSV file it's
literally mode so the dot comes before
the keyword there and now I'm going to
say do import and then the name of the
file I want to import which is
favorites. CSV and now the name of the
table that I want to create with that
data and just for consistency I'm going
to call it favorites I could change
these things to be anything I want but
I'm going to do that and voila nothing
seems to have happened but just like in
C and in Python in Linux when nothing
seems to happen that's usually a good
thing it means I didn't mess up so if I
want to see what just happened there's
this other command and these commands
that start with dots these are SQL light
specific which is indeed a lightweight
version of SQL they're not SQL per se so
if you're using Oracle or something else
like that you're not going to use these
exact commands you'll see the ones we
use in just a moment and here's the
first when I type schema the schema of a
database is the design of the database
what are the tables what are the columns
and all of that so when I type schema
this actually in this case shows me that
create table command that was
automatically run for me by just doing
this import line once I get more
comfortable with SQL I could literally
type this out myself or use some program
to generate that as well but what it's
creating for me is this create table if
it doesn't exist even though it's more
tur than that I want to create a table
called favorites and then the columns
for that table are going to be timestamp
which is going to be text comma language
which is also going to be text comma
problem which is also going to be text
that was just inferred very trivially by
the do import command to just figure out
that yes just give me a three column
database table based on the Google
form okay questions on this these are
commands you run once to get up and
running you don't run these commands
frequently but we have them on the slide
just for reference all right so now
let's do something a little more
interesting I'm going to clear my SQL
light terminal here but I'm still in SQL
light I'm going to now use some of my
first SQL commands which recall were uh
were among them uh select so crud c r UD
D the r was select this is maybe the
most common the most useful the most
powerful thing to use with a SQL
database selecting data to answer
questions akin to the ones we were
trying to answer with python this is the
general syntax anytime you want to
select data from a SQL database you
literally say select you then specify
the column or columns that you want to
select data from you literally write the
word from and then you specify the name
of the table you want to get that data
from semicolon in this case everything
that's in capitals here is a sequel
keyword strictly speaking you don't have
to capitalize things but we would
encourage you to do so stylistically and
especially as you're learning and even
as you're writing it it just helps to
distinguish SQL from like words you
chose like the names of the columns and
the data there're in so uh do adopt
early on this convention so let me go
back now to my code space here I'm
running my terminal window with SQL
light 3 inside of it suppose that I just
want to get all of the data from the
favorites table which was automatically
imported let's do this select I want
everything well I can do timestamp comma
language comma problem but you know what
here's a uh convenience already if you
want everything there's what's called a
wild card character in SQL which is just
a star in asterisk which means give me
every column without my knowing even
what they're called let me go ahead now
and say from favorite it's semicolon and
this is the SQL way of opening the
database iterating over every row
they're in printing out every row
therein done so those three steps which
was like nine lines of python code give
or take earlier is now one line of SQL I
hit enter there is all of the data so I
see now all of the data just outputed as
a CSV here but it's not the CSV file
it's now actually the table and in fact
just for good measure let me do this CU
you'll see the behavior a little
different the next time we open the file
I've just exited out of SQL light 3 I'm
going to rerun it but I'm not going to
reimport the data or do anything like
that because my file now exists in fact
let me take one step back if I type LS
at my Linux prompt there's my favorites.
py from before there's my favorites. CSV
from before and here's a third file that
I did create a moment ago when I first
ran SQL light 3 so the data is
persistent it's not using Ram or memory
anything I do now is save there so let's
go ahead and rerun SQL light 3 with the
same file but I'm not going to I don't
have to reort everything because the
file already exists let me now do that
same thing again select star from
favorites to get all of the data and
what you'll see now is the same data but
it's a little prettier now because I
reran it I effectively disabled CSV mode
this time and what I'm now seeing is the
entire contents of this database table
called favorit now there's nothing new
here but you're just seeing now like an
asky or Unicode version of all of the
same data from that database well
suppose I want to get a subset of the
data well let me clear my screen and
just like in Linux I can hit contrl L
just to clean things up aesthetically
suppose I want to get just the languages
so I could do select language from
favorites and this will now select not
all three columns AKA star this will
only select the language column and all
of the data they're in if I hit enter
voila now I just see those there no time
Stamps no problems it's just a slice of
the table if you will all right not that
interesting still still because it's
just a big column of data but now things
get more interesting it turns out in SQL
that there are functions that come with
this language just like C just like
python in SQL some of the more useful
ones some of the simpler ones are these
here average count distinct lower Max
Min upper which pretty much uh do what
they say and count is a particularly
useful one let's start with that you
know it's a reasonable question to be
asked uh how many people submitted the
Google form by the time I actually
downloaded the CSV well why don't we go
ahead and do this let me go back to VSS
code here in my terminal window let me
select not star but the count of star so
give me the count of the rows that are
being returned from the database called
uh the database table called favorites
now when I hit enter I'm not going to
get all the data I'm just going to get
simply a number 430 rows came back so
that's pretty good I now know how much
data is in there well what languages
were in there well I could do select
language from favorit just as before but
that's not that useful especially if I'm
inheriting the data like I'm the analyst
who's been handed a data set by my boss
and they want me to like crunch some
numbers okay I could like load this into
Excel I could sort it but you can use
SQL now to answer pretty basic questions
too if you want to select the distinct
languages in the data set because you
didn't you weren't privy to the Google
form let me go ahead and select only the
distinct languages from the favorites
table and now I hit enter and I get back
a much more succinct answer just the
three languages in question not really
that useful since I created the Google
form but certainly if you're inheriting
data from someone else you've just
downloaded a data set at least now I'm
arguably wrapping my mind around what's
going on now this is not necessary for
such a small data set but I can combine
these things select the count of the
distinct languages in this data set
called favorites and now I should get
back what
answer so hopefully indeed an answer
called three and what you're getting
back notice aesthetically too is like a
mini temporary table when I asked for uh
just the distinct languages what SQL
hands me back is this temporary table in
memory that has one column called
language and then two row uh three rows
now this is not saved anywhere it's just
executed ephemerally like this but
that's why it's depicted in this way
what you're getting is subsets of your
data smaller tables containing some of
your data and same thing down here this
is like a crazy long
uh column name you can rename it if you
really want uh but uh that's all we're
seeing there and in fact if that's a
little ugly we can actually Alias These
Things N is a common uh name for a
variable a number in any programming
language so I can actually alas this to
be a column called n hit enter and now
I'm getting a tiny tiny table whose
column is called n that just has the one
value
there all right questions on
these application of these functions
here no questions
yeah say a little louder as oh as as
literally in English so name this column
rename this column as this technically
it creates an alias for the column so
that's all
yeah exactly distinct will operate on
whatever you handed in parentheses and
get rid of all of the duplicates giving
you back just the unique
correct other questions here
yeah good question when you define an
alias like n which I just did does it
become like a variable you can reuse
short answer no in this case but you can
reuse it within your same query even
though these these queries are getting a
little longer admittedly statements that
they are uh you can actually reuse n in
even longer queries so later in your
query and we'll see a few that are start
to going to start to grow in length so
it's a a nice way of nicknaming things
just to be a little more tur in your
query so we can transition to some of
these more sophisticated queries because
it turns out there's some other uh
techniques we can introduce as well here
are some other keywords in SQL and again
even though like this is another list of
things there's only four things
fundamentally we're doing creating
reading updating and deleting data these
are just allowing us to like fine-tune
how we do it exactly so where is going
to allow us to filter data as we'll do
in just a moment like select data where
this conditional is true uh like is
going to be an alternative to an equal
sign so instead of looking for exactly
scratch or exactly python or exactly C
you can look for something like dot dot
dot and it can be a little bit of a
fuzzier match if you will uh with other
characters as well order by is going to
deal with sorting limit is going to just
let me limit the total number of rows
that come back to one or 10 or finite if
I don't want to see all 400 plus rows
all at once because I'm just trying to
wrap my mind around it and group by is
best shown by example so let's play with
just a couple of these as well let me go
back to vs code here I'll clear my
screen I'm still in the same SQL light
instance and let's count how many of you
likeed C without writing python code as
before so let me go ahead and select the
count of the rows from favorites where
the language in each row equals c and
the convention in SQL light is to use
single quotes anytime you're surrounding
a string that's meant to represent a
literal piece of text uh as opposed to C
which was double quotes or python which
was either so this is selecting the
count of rows from favorites table where
the language in question is C enter and
this gives me 98 notice though if I omit
that predicate like we did before you'll
get back the total number of rows that
were in the table so where is what's
called a predicate that just allows me
to filter things just like an if
condition or the like in a language that
we've seen before you can be a little
more specific like how many people
really liked C and the Mario program uh
problem specifically well let's do this
uh let's go ahead and do select the
number of rows from the favorites table
where the language is C and so it's uh
still literally the word ands and or
just like in Python but not like in C uh
and
equals Mario so let's see if there's any
fans of both C and the Mario problem and
three of us really like those two things
together in this case all right what
else can we do well more compelling
might be to see kind of like in Python
for each language what was the
popularity thereof and at the moment we
don't really have a way of doing that
except in Python where we had the loop
and we had those variables with the
dictionary that did all that counting
for us you know totally doable but
tedious especially if your job is to
analyze data my God like even writing 15
lines of code to answer simple questions
is kind of ridiculous SQL can do better
for us so let me go ahead and do this
let me go ahead and select every
language and the count thereof from the
favorites table but this time Group by
language so this was another one of the
keywords that we can use in this
abbreviated list of extra features of
SQL and this one's a little takes a
moment to wrap your mind around but this
is going to give me a two column
temporary table where the First Column
is a language and the second column is
the count thereof from this data set and
group by language just means that only
show me scratch once only show me c once
only show me python once that is group
all of the identical values together but
keep track of how many of them there are
and so now if I go over to SQL light and
I hit enter now I have in SQL version
the exact same output that I had from
python that took me what 15 plus lines
before now we're down to just one
because SQL structured query language is
all about constructing queries like this
to answer questions and get back answers
quickly if we want to clean this up a
little bit you asked earlier about
sorting order well we can do that too
there's another uh key phrase we can use
here we can order by the count of those
rows and then run that query here so now
unfortunately they're from smallest to
biggest but we can reverse that it turns
out and my query is starting to wrap
here I'll I'll zoom out for a moment if
you want to order by count the default
is in ascending order abbreviated ASC if
you want to reverse the sort in SQL
instead of using reverse equals true
like we did in Python you say DC for
descending order and now we get almost
the same output but flipped in Reverse
so it's just a lot faster to answer
questions once of course you get some
muscle memory and some comfort with it
well what else can I do you know what if
I just care about the most popular
language I don't care about the second
place or the third place languages or
anything else well let me add one more
Clause here limit the answer to one and
no matter how many rows should come back
now I just get the number one language
as of the data set we collected with 27
uh 270 votes for
it
questions on
this any questions
here no well what if uh you know we're
starting to introduce SQL and it was
kind of too late to make it into the
this the Google form so it turns out
there Syntax for this too you can create
data of course not just the tables but
the data they're in and here's like the
typical Syntax for inserting data into a
SQL database you literally say insert
into the name of the table and then in
parentheses you specify one or more
columns for which you have values that
you want to insert this is to say you
don't have to give values for every
column in the given row if you only have
answers to some of those questions you
can enumerate them here like this but
the values you insert are going to be
these so you literally say after the
closed parenthesis values and then in a
second set of parentheses with the same
length comma separated list you specify
what values do you want to insert so
it's a little verbose and frankly longer
term you're going to use like python
code to automatically do these kinds of
insertions but let's go ahead and try
this right now if I do select
distinct uh language from favorites
again we see this just these three
candidates but we've now taught you a
bit of sequel so let's do insert into
favorites the column called
language uh and you know what let's I'm
going to give a problem here the values
for which and let me Zoom back out are
going to be quote unquote SQL and quote
unquote 50v you'll see soon see what
that's all about semicolon nothing seems
to happen but that's usually a good
thing and now if I scroll back up in my
my queries in SQL light three you can
scroll back and forth in time and uh to
avoid retyping things now I should see
indeed four candidate languages here now
suppose that you were never really a fan
of c and maybe you uh programmed a
little bit in high school or in the real
world and you liked C++ well there's a
whole lot of answers for C so select
star from favorites where language
equals quote unquote C so here's
everyone who submitted the answer for C
let's presume that no they didn't really
want C they wanted C++ which is not a
language we teach in the class but I
could also now do this you can use the
update command to set a column or
columns to different values where some
condition is met so if I do update table
name set column name equal to some value
filtering it perhaps by where some
condition is true so suppose I've
changed my mind or you know what let's
go ahead and do
update uh favorites set language equal
to maybe C++ where language equals c now
this is destructive so you generally
don't want to do this unless you have a
backup of your data too overriding what
people's answers are this seems to have
been successful because no error
messages and if I rerun the previous
select that gives me all of the
favorites where language equals c now
indeed I get none but if I search for
C++ now I get a lot and if I get rid of
that wear Clause altogether and just
look at the contents of my database now
you see that indeed C++ is comingled
with all the other data this is not what
you all intended of course so I can undo
this let me go ahead and undo what I
just did let me set my favorite language
to C where language equals C plus plus
but the predicate is important this I'm
not going to do what if I accidentally
omitted this predicate the wear Clause
how would that screw things up might you
think uh yeah I'm
back it would set Every Rose language to
indeed see and this is dangerous and if
you start googling around for like
sequel mistakes or the like people in
the real world have accidentally run
commands like this and without naming
names a former member of our teaching
staff at one point accidentally re ran a
command like this and changed every
student's name in our database to Bobby
I think it was the same name for every
row because they simply forgot a
predicate so here to two like there's
dangers in code and you should adopt The
Habit quite quickly of always one
backing up your data like with CP for
instance in Linux or any other technique
or just making sure before you hit enter
that yes this is indeed the query I want
to execute and generally speaking in the
real world there should be process
controls in place like the intern should
not have access to the datab the
production database the live database
and the like but you have a lot of power
now with these queries so just be all
the more careful cuz very easily can you
do bad things so let me undo this where
language equals quote unquote C++ and
I'll Zoom back out enter and now I think
we're back in business C is among the
answers
yeah is essentially doing what at the
end replace it's essentially find and
replace yes in like lay person's terms
this is find and replace implemented
with SQL and in fact the authors of
Microsoft Word or Google Docs might very
well be using language like this sequel
when you go to the nice graphical
userfriendly find and replace box this
may very well be what they're doing
underneath the hood or of course they
could be using some other language
altogether there's one last uh syntax
that's worth knowing delete which for
better for worse is even more
destructive whereby it allows you to
delete rows from tables it's distinct
from drop which lets you delete tables
themselves this focuses on rows so
suppose that you really really didn't
like let's say uh tedin was a little
challenging if you adopt if you tackle
that more comfortable problem so if you
really don't want to even think about t
in anymore so why don't we do uh delete
from favorites where problem equals and
I won't execute it for real tiamin this
would have the effect of deleting every
row including the language therein and
the time stamp where the student
answered tiamin worse than this would be
this why might this be bad
okay chuckling because like there's no
predicate there's no filter which means
literally this would delete all of the
data so again with great power here
comes great responsibility now this has
just been a data set of what 430 rows by
us dynamically created there's of course
some really juicy data sets in the real
world and one website you might have
heard or an app you might have used is
IMDb the internet movie database which
wonderfully makes some of their data
available for download as CSV files or
technically tsv files tab separated
values but what we did in advance of
class was download some of that data for
both TV shows in the real world and
movies in the real world and what's
wonderful about this data set is it's
not just dozens or hundreds or even
thousands of lines there are millions of
rows of Juicy data TV shows and movies
with which most folks are probably
familiar at least with the subset and
we'll see in just a little bit that this
data comes in the form of now six
different tables that we've given you
and the tables and question for today
are going to be the people in the TV
business the Stars they in the shows
that people are producing and the like
this is a picture we'll revisit to let
enable you to wrap your minds around
what the actual data is this feels like
a good opportunity though for a snack in
fact in just a moment we have a whole
lot of Rice Krispie treats out in the
lobby but if folks could perhaps
acknowledge uh this mini wedding cake
here cs50 own Carter zeni is getting
married this week so congratulations to
Carter
as
well
congrats all right there's
only okay there's only one piece of cake
in that box but a lot of Rice Krispy
Treats in the transip let's take 10
minutes and we'll be back with Internet
Movie Database in 10 all right we are
back so if you've never been like you
can actually go to I imdb.com right now
and play around or download the mobile
app and it's just big database of a lot
of TV show and movies and actors and the
like but what indeed is nice is you can
download some of that data and that's in
what I've done in advance and what we've
done is we wrote some python code to
convert some of the uh flat file
databases that they let you download and
we converted it into a SQL database with
six tables so not just one but six that
ultimately are these here and let me
just help you wrap your minds around
what this picture is which is a entity
relationship diagram which is just to
say each of these boxes on the screen
represents a table and each of the
arrows or edges represents some kind of
relationship across the tables because
up until now the only data we had were
those three columns in the favorites
table but what's gets really useful
about SQL databases just like a Google
spreadsheet or an Excel file is you can
have multiple sheets or in a database
multiple tables and so what we're about
to see is that in this IMDb database for
TV shows there's going to be a dedicated
table for all the people in the TV
business there's going to be a dedicated
table for all of the TV shows that are
in their database as of right now
there's going to be a dedicated table
for writers in that industry for the
ratings of uh shows for the genres to
which shows belong comedy and the like
and then lastly there's going to be this
table which somehow
Associates people with the TV shows that
they star in and vice versa and so let's
consider first what this looks like in
code and we'll see that it's going to
overwhelm intentionally at first but I'm
going to do this I'm going to go back to
my terminal window and during the break
I downloaded from the course's website a
file called shows. DB which we made in
advance for you and if I type LS I'll
see all of my favorites files from
before the CSV the DB and the python
file but now there's shows. DB so I'm
going to go ahead in my full screen
terminal window here I'm not using
actual tabs or code files now I'm going
to run SQL light3 on the file called
shows. DB and I'm just going to see this
version information here let me clear my
screen and run the one command I ran
earlier to show us the schema of the
favorites database now we'll see the
schema for the shows database and
there's a lot going on here but let me
scroll back up to the very top the
beginning and we see this here so when I
run. schema we see a dump really of all
of the SQL create table commands that
were run in order to create this
database for you and one of those tables
is called genres and another people
ratings shows stars and so forth and the
columns therein even though it's
formatted a little more prettily than
the automatically generated create table
statement for favorites whereby we have
one column per line of output here uh in
the for instance people table there's
going to be an ID column like unique
identifier like a Harvard ID a Yale ID
or the like uh a name column a birth
year and then some other stuff if I
scroll down to shows every show in the
world is going to have a unique ID as
well a title of course the year in which
it debuted and the total number of
episodes as of the time we downloaded
the data and then what else is there
some of these are a little less obvious
like ratings here so ratings don't have
an ID column but they have a show ID
column and a rating like a fivepoint
scale or 10o scale or the like and then
the total number of votes that were
collected to contribute to that rating
IMDb allows people to like up vote and
down vote uh shows and movies and the
like and then similarly is genre
structured there's a show ID and then
there's a genre which is going to be
like an English word like comedy or
drama or something else and then what
else let's go a little further at the
bottom here for stars and writers if we
go to the very bottom here stars and
writers are similarly structured too
they have a show ID and a person ID so
show and person and then this writer's
table has a show ID and a person ID and
there's a whole lot of other words that
we'll come to in just a moment but what
are the what is this code hinting at
well if I go back to the picture from
earlier here you'll see that this
picture captures the relationships among
these various tables so for instance if
we focus on shows for just a moment a
show again has a unique ID a title a
year in which it debuted and a total
number of episodes if you want to figure
out what genre or genr a show belongs to
cuz some shows are just comedies some
shows are just just dramas but you know
some shows are arguably comedies and
dramas depending on the episode or the
like so you can imagine wanting to
associate two or three or even more
genres with a show this line here in
this second table allows us to do that
every Row in the genres table we'll see
has uh two items a show ID which relates
to the ID of a show and that's why these
lines literally line up with that
specific column name and genre which is
going to be like quote unquote comedy
quote unquote drama or something else
now with that said design question why
have we deliberately not just gotten rid
of this genre's table and made our lives
simpler by just adding a genre column to
this shows table and again a table is
just like a sheet with rows and columns
at the moment shows only have four
columns ID title year episodes why not
just add a fifth column called genre and
put the show genre
there any intuition
here why not just keep things simple
like yeah and
back exactly if you add a fifth column
here and call it genre then you have to
pick a genre specifically you have to
put in that cell presumably comedy or
drama or music or something else now you
could write multiple words in the cell
but generally speaking that would be
sloppy bad design like every cell just
like in a spreadsheet should really have
one value it might have multiple words
but it shouldn't be like a weirdly comma
separated list of multiple things it
should just be in a different cell in
that case so if you instead were to
design this with just a single column
called genre you're imposing what a
computer scientist would call a on toone
relationship every show has one genre
and that's not necessarily a good thing
or strictly speaking it would be a many
to one because the same genre could
belong to multiple shows but each show
could only have one genre in that case
what a relational database allows you to
do and relational is indeed the
operative word it allows you to factor
out some of your information and then
have maybe one show here in one row but
then in this genres table you could have
one row for that one show genre or you
could have two rows in the genres table
for comedy and for drama or if it has a
third genre you could just add another
row here so you still have one row for
the show itself with all the juiciest
details but a variable number of rows by
having this relationship with another
table meanwhile ratings work the same
way at least in this case a show has ID
title year and episodes but if you want
to figure out its rating you have to
kind of Follow the arrow here so to
speak and look up the corresponding show
ID in this table find the rating of that
show and the total number of ratings so
that's been factored out Two For Better
or For Worse um now let's consider
people people have just three columns ID
name and birth but there's no mention of
the TV show in which people have starred
or the TV shows that a person has
written well why is that well if you
just had a fourth column here called
show well you would have to decide what
show is that person in and no one could
ever act again in another show because
there's no room to store the data but if
someone of course a popular actor can St
star in multiple shows well we could
have one ID for that person one name one
birth year obviously like there's only
one Steve Carell as an actor in the
world of people but Steve Carell in this
example could have his person ID
whatever his Harvard ID equivalent Yale
ID equivalent is appear in multiple rows
in this table so that it can be
associated with multiple shows and this
allows you to create what's called a one
to many relationship or technically it's
bidirectional it's a many to many
relationship why well one show can
certain certainly have multiple people
in it and multiple people writing for it
just in the real world but conversely
one uh person could certainly act in
multiple shows or write multiple shows
so this is what you get with relational
databases you put your sort of canonical
data for people in one place for for
shows in another place and then you use
these additional tables to relate one
thing to another so we won't dwell on
the pictures that's just if you sort of
uh can wrap your mind around the data
set better that way that's one way of
thinking about it but recall that the
code we just saw for the schema again
escalated quickly like there's a lot of
keywords I haven't mentioned yet but
some of these are perhaps familiar
they're capitalized differently here but
integer is on the list here null is on
the list albeit technically not null so
let's tease apart some of these key
words and consider what they're actually
doing for your database because now
we're in exploring features that do not
exist in the world of spreadsheets alone
so it turns out in a SQL database
specifically SQL light which is the
version of SQL we use in cs50 and which
is commonly used for things like mobile
applications nowadays it's like a
lightweight version of SQL it's when you
aren't trying to run Twitter and have
billions and billions of rows
necessarily you've got hundreds
thousands tens of thousands maybe even a
few million but not crazy uh numbers uh
crazy amounts of data in the world of
SQL light specifically there's these
five data types so just like in C we had
int and Char and the like in SQL we have
these uh BL which is kind of funny but
it just means binary large object so
it's like a binary data type zeros and
ones that aren't necessarily uh fitting
into the other categories integer which
of course is an integer as we know it
numeric which is kind of a catchall for
numbers that are formatted specially so
like a date uh would be like year year
year year-month month Dash day day um
and this is actually a wonderful thing
depending on the country you're from you
might think your date system in your
country is great or it's horrible the US
system is horrible because we have month
day and then year which is impossible to
sort it is the wrong way objectively to
store data and yet here we are using
this at scale other countries have
gotten this better numeric and SQL
itself standardizes that stuff so it
doesn't matter what country you're from
you're storing your data in this
particular way for instance times are
standardized and other types of numeric
data as well real is synonymous with
float so something with a decimal point
and some number of uh digits thereafter
and then text is just uh for strings and
the like with other even fancier
databases like MySQL postgress SQL
Oracle and other products you might have
heard of there's even more data types
where you have to make even finer grain
decisions but for SQL light it's indeed
pretty lightweight and you or we just
have to decide the data types for each
column in a table but there's these
additional constraints in the world of
SQL you can additionally say that cells
in this column may or may not be null so
if you want to protect yourself from
yourself so you don't screw up and
insert a null that is a blank value you
can explicitly design a table to have a
column that cannot be null and so in
fact someone came up during the break to
ask me about my having manually inserted
SQL quote unquote SQL into our favorites
database you might recall that I kind of
cheated I just inserted uh SQL quote
unquote and 50v the name of a new
problem quote unquote but what did I not
insert into the
database a Tim stamp and I could have I
could have put like the current day in
time a few minutes ago but I didn't and
that's fine if it's uh if it's
acceptable to you and the product you're
building but I could have prevented that
if we had defined the table to have a
timestamp column that isn't just text
but it's text that's not null SQL would
have complained and would not have let
me complete that insertion so there's
these kinds of built-in defenses that
you don't necessarily get with a
spreadsheet alone and unique means
exactly that if you want to make sure
that every Row in that column is unique
maybe for email addresses or in the US
Social Security numbers or anything that
you want to make sure you don't have two
versions of you can specify that the
column is unique and there's other such
constraints as well but again this is
just a list of features that you get
from a proper relational database but
perhaps the most intellectually
interesting one and the most powerful
one is what's called here a primary key
and a foreign key and let me go back now
to this output if we look at shows
you'll see that a show again has an ID a
title a year and a number of episodes
and now the data types might make sense
the ID it turns out just like a Harvard
ID a Yale ID is going to be an integer
so a simple number the title of course
is going to be text but not null like it
would be weird if a TV show had no name
like that can't be like every the whole
world would break or your TV gu and
whatnot so that makes sense there to say
not null uh year is numeric so it's a
standardized form episodes is an integer
like how many episodes have been
produced and then lastly notice this the
primary key of the show's table is
apparently the column called ID
mentioned a few lines earlier this just
means that the database will use the ID
column as the unique identifier so it's
similar to the unique keyword but
primary key just means the database is
going to treat it as special too and
make sure that it is uniquely
identifying your data but what's
interesting is this notice if I scroll
back up to people people were sort of
similarly structured but with different
attributes like up here we had a person
has an ID a name a birth year and a
primary key of ID so a ID is again
integer name is text but not null
because it'd be weird to have a human
with absolutely no name textually birth
is going to be numeric but the primary
key of people is ID as well so those are
the unique columns that the database
will just treat special why well we just
looked at shows we just looked at people
let's focus now on this one down here
Stars how do you determine who star in a
TV show well we had two columns the show
ID and the person ID this is the ex the
Incarnation of a many to- many
relationship one person could be in many
shows one show could certainly have many
people in it or writing for it but
notice this within this table of two
columns show ID and person ID there's
what's going to be called a foreign key
called show ID that references the shows
tables ID column and then another
foreign key called person ID though I
could call these things in parentheses
anything I want that references the
people tables ID column now you're not
going to often have to type commands
like this again you set the database up
once in the beginning typically maybe
with some help from a TF maybe with help
of Google or the like but once your
database is designed it's back to the
crud like create read update delete the
selects the inserts the deletions and
the like but what's this implying these
keywords like primary key and foreign
key are what are doing in code what this
picture was painting a moment ago these
lines here are drawn literally to line
up with the corresponding things
people's ID lines up with person ID
Show's ID lines up with show ID and so
you're just seeing graphical version
code version graphical code that creates
these relationships now given that let's
actually see what these things look like
so let me go back to vs code here let me
clear my screen I'm still within SQL
light with shows. DB let me go ahead and
do what I do with like any new database
if I ever download something or I'm
trying to wrap my mind around a problem
you know usually it doesn't come with a
pretty picture or uh you know a
three-hour lecture to explain what the
data set is rather you just have the
data set in your own knowledge of SQL so
let me play around so schema shows me
all the tables that might be a starting
point okay this is interesting I know PE
what people are let's go ahead and show
me all the people so select star from
people I'm just trying to wrap my mind
around what this data set looks like in
a more userfriendly way okay okay that's
already a lot of people as you see the
years flying by there's been a lot of
people in the TV
business so this was maybe not the best
query to run but this is indicative of
just how large this data set is from
IMDb okay when in doubt and when
whenever you lose control over your
computer control C is your friend to
interrupt what would have been better
because I don't think I need to know all
the million people in the world I could
do like limit me to 10 people all right
and that's enough now to get us sense of
like Fred a stair has an IDE of one
first person ever um birth year of 1899
Lauren ball and all of these other uh
people from yesterday year you see that
they are the first 10 people in the
database so there's an example of some
of the data now if I want to rep my mind
around what a show is you know I know it
technically I know it from the picture
but let's just look at some raw data so
instead of saying select star from
people let me go ahead and select star
from shows limit 10 and okay I've only
heard heard of or seen a couple of these
but these are older shows at that but I
see that every show has an ID a title a
year in which it debuted and a number of
episodes but perhaps most opaque is
going to be this select star from
Stars where this is the table that
Associates people with shows am I going
to see any names or show titles here not
according to the definition we saw
earlier oh I should have done my limit
let me interrupt that let me do that
again limit 10
no and this is where now you're
definitely in the programmer world
because like this would be the most
annoying spreadsheet to use on your Mac
or PC ever if you just had like a sheet
with all of these numbers that
Associates one thing with the other like
my God how do you figure out who this is
or what this is you have to like
manually control F or command F looking
for the data but a database doesn't care
once you know SQL you can sort of Stitch
these things back together so what
you're seeing here are foreign Keys
foreign Keys why because show ID
corresponds to the same numbers from
that other table called shows that has
an proper primary key called ID person
ID is a foreign key in this context
because it refers to numbers that belong
to really the people table and its ID
column so this is just a way of somehow
linking them and so if you think of I
always like think of um this in my
mind's eye is this if this is like the
people table this is the shows table and
there's this middle table in between the
Stars table there's some way of like
stitching those two together by lining
up the idas of one with the other and
getting back some more data so let's
actually play with some of this data how
about we start where we emphasized
earlier genres so let me go ahead and
take a quick look at all of the genres
in this database so select star from
genres star is usually going to be a
little overwhelming but it just gives me
a sense of what the data is but let's
actually look at um uh let's go look at
all of them there okay that's a lot
these are all official genres from IMDb
let me oh okay it went okay it wasn't
terribly long let me filter that down so
from genres where genre equals comedy uh
Capital C just based on the data I'm
seeing okay so what am I seeing now and
in fact let me limit this arbitrarily to
10 though I could limit it to anything I
want here are 10 comedies what are they
well who the heck knows like all I know
are the 10 show IDs now I could do
something like this as we've seen before
with SQL I could do all right well let's
figure out what this show idea is Select
star from shows where the IDE of the
show I'm looking for equals what 62 614
semicolon so I could like manually look
it up by cross referencing the other
table okay so that was the show in
question there the first comedy in the
data set let me look up the second one
so instead of that let's do 6 3881 enter
okay so that's that show and let's do
one more and suffice it to say this is
just getting tedious and vulnerable to
mistakes quickly this is not this surely
can't be the way to do this and indeed
SQL is going to let us do this a little
more powerfully instead let's do this
instead of getting this table
temporarily with all these show IDs and
all these genres let's refine the query
so let's just select the show ID from
the genres table where the genre equals
quote unquote comedy now I have a big b
list of show IDs all of which are comedy
how many well I can combine ideas from
earlier I can just count all of those
show IDs and or Star if I want to just
do that too but I can count all those
show IDs
4876 comedies and IMDB's database for TV
shows so feels like a lot but how can I
now use that information and get back
the titles of comedies in the database
without doing it manually well let's do
this I have a moment ago this query
select the show ID from genres where the
current genre is quote unquote
comedy um what if I kind of Nest these
queries kind of like grade school math
in parenthesis what if I combine this
whole thing in parenthesis and now let
me select what I really want let me go
ahead and select how about uh the title
of all shows where the idea of the show
is in this list of show
IDs so if you agree that the shows table
has an ID column which is its otherwise
known as its primary key the unique ID
that identifies it just like our Harvard
IDs our Yale IDs and you agree that per
a moment ago this shorter query will
give me back just the show IDs of all of
the comedies in the database you can
actually combine or Nest these queries
together uh it's going to respect SQL
light order of operations with
parentheses just like grade school math
so the thing in parentheses will be
executed first that gives it back a list
of IDs like what 48,000 IDs and then
this query the outer query is going to
get the title from all of the shows
where the ID of the show is in that big
list of 48,000 so if I now execute these
together I think the list is still going
to be a little long but let me execute
it together now I see this long list of
outputs a little overwhelming let's go
ahead and maybe limit it to just 10 as
before for discussion sake and now I see
10 comedies ordered arbitrarily from
however they're in the database that
happen to indeed be have comedy as their
genre if I want to do this a little more
cleanly I could do this let's see uh why
don't I order by title ascending order
which is alphabetically or the default
is also uh ascending limit 10 now I see
the top 10 I mean weirdly named things
with hash symbols presumably to get
their titles up to the beginning or
maybe these are hashtags uh here now we
have alphabetically the top first 10
shows that are
comedies any questions on these kinds of
queries it's kind of a lot but at the
same time it's just like composing the
smaller ideas from before into slightly
more useful
queries
yeah do for Keys have to set the
relationship when you create the table
the programmer or the database
administrator would create that
relationship by using those keywords
primary key and foreign key that create
that teaches the database what is
related to what per the picture so you
do that once and now I being the sort of
programmer who's familiar with the
database I am just using these foreign
keys in a way in a manner consistent
with their design but and this is where
it's useful at some point even if you no
one hands you a picture to make sure you
understand the database because that's
going to inform literally what you type
in SQL to get the data you care about
about well let's do something a little
more precise how about very reasonable
question and honestly this is exactly
what imdb.com in the app are for what if
you want to find all of the shows that
Steve Carell is in like kind of a
reasonable query like literally
something someone might type into Google
or more specifically IMDb it's not
really obvious at first glance how to do
that though because right like from my
database if these are my six tables well
I can pretty easily get Steve Carell
from here but I can really only get his
ID number whatever that is his name
which I know already and his birth year
okay interesting but has nothing to do
with the shows that he's in I can look
at shows over here but there's no
mention of Steve Carell right because
there's no person ID here where is that
relationship implemented well it's
implemented down here so how do we do
this well here's the perfect example of
a a lesson we've trying been trying to
emphasize for weeks of taking these baby
steps like break larger problems down
into smaller ones and let's do something
like this let's just get everything I
know about Steve Carell from the
database let's select star from people
where the name of the person is quote
unquote Steve Carell I just want to see
what data we've got and here's what we
have okay there's only one Steve Carell
born in 1962 and his unique ID is 136
797 according to IMDb this isn't some
like Global uh actor identifier per se
all right well how do I get now all of
the shows that Steve Carell is in well I
could do this
select star from Stars not to confuse
the two one's the symbol one's the table
name uh where person ID equals 13
6797 so I think this will now give me
everything from the Stars table that
relates to Steve Carell okay and you'll
see person ID is the same because I'm
literally searching for just Steve
Carell but there are what like 20 or so
shows that he's been in all right well
here's where things would get tedious
what are those shows well I could do
Select Title from shows where the ID of
the show equals and here's you know
whenever you copy paste you're probably
doing something wrong okay he's was in
The Dana Carvey Show familiar with that
let's do another one we'll copy paste
this uh where ID equals this over the
top another and if we keep digging we'll
probably find the office but my God like
that's going to take forever to do 20
queries manually it's not very Dynamic
but what if we just Nest these queries a
little more dynamically so let me start
from the beginning again what if we go
ahead and select everything we want we
know about uh people whose name
equals
Steve Carell that gave us earlier this
data I don't need all of that data I
know his name I don't care about his
birth year so let's change this to just
be give me the ID of Steve Carell and
that gives me back now this smaller
temporary data set all right can I now
use
this uh inside of another query well let
me wrap the whole thing with parentheses
and now let me say select star from the
Stars table where the person ID equals
this so I'm Del liely not using in
because I'm assuming there's indeed only
one Steve Carell in the world so I'm not
getting back a list of Steve Carell I'm
getting back the one and only in this
case so equal is fine in is when you
have multiple equal is when you have one
let me go ahead and hit enter now okay
that's more data than I need I don't
need like 20 copies of Steve Carell's
person ID so let me hit up let me go
back and let me just get show ID from
Steve Carell and now I have a list of
just the 20 or so show IDs that he has
been in all right how can I now use this
well let me hit up let me put the whole
thing in parentheses and now let me
select what I really want Select Title
from shows where and here's the final
flourish the shows table has an ID has a
title has a year and has an episode and
what I really want though is to check
which
shows have ID that is what anyone want
to finish the thought
I just want to
yeah exactly ID in this and this is
getting ugly and when you actually write
your queries in like a text file you can
format them nicely and indent them my
font is just getting I don't want to
make it too small to fit everything but
now we have three queries one is in
doubly nested parenthesis then there's
the middle one then there's the outer
one so this last query is going to get
me the title from shows where the ID of
the show is in this big list of 20 or so
show IDs that Steve Carell is in and I
knew that because I looked up his name
here and notice what I did not do this
time is I didn't manually hardcode his
ID number there's no need that would be
kind of a bad way to implement a website
uh if you're using a database underneath
the hood you want the IMDb for real to
search for whatever the human typed in
and no one's going to know Steve
Carell's person ID or anything else so
here we've done this all dynamically and
now if I hit enter I think I get all of
his shows let's go ahead and order this
by title just to make it tidy and you
probably will see at least one or more
shows that you know and probably the
most popular is dot dot dot the office
so this is literally the kind of query
that's being executed underneath the
hood when you go to uh websites or apps
like IMDb your textual query is probably
being plugged into a longer SQL query
like this where some programmer at IMDb
probably wrote this whole query in
advance weeks months years ago and
they're just somehow plugging in the
value that you the human type into the
search box or the like questions
now on finding this data or any
other no okay so where else could we go
with this well let's
consider how else we might combine data
suppose that the next question actually
perhaps appropriately would be focusing
in on not just like people and shows and
these stars but how do we kind of like
gather more information about the shows
themselves like the genres the ratings
or the like so indeed let's focus on
just these two tables here recall that
every show has an ID a title a year and
episodes but it also might have one or
more relationships with rose and this
other table is called genres and this is
so that a show can be a comedy can be a
drama can be any number of other things
one row per so you would see the same
show ID again and again and again with a
different genre written in English like
comma comedy drama or the like well how
do I kind of Recon subtitute that data
Well turns out there's a few different
ways to do this and let me propose that
we introduce this keyword here join and
this is really the most powerful of the
keywords in SQL itself it doesn't have
to be used we've seen with uh nested
queries that you can still select data
across multiple tables but here is
another way so let me do this let me go
back to my SQL light database and let me
select sort of in one uh breath exactly
the data I want select star from shows
and let's just limit this initially to
10 to see what it looks like all right
that's again the shows data select star
from genres let's limit that to 102 just
to wrap our minds around it and now this
is not that useful however the data in
the leftmost column here is the primary
key in the shows table these are just
unique IDs the data here in the genres
table recall show ID is the foreign key
so it's the same numbers but just copied
into another table so that we can have
this relationship across them how do I
kind of line up these numbers with these
numbers to get back like a wider table
that has title and year and episodes and
genre and heck ratings and all of that
too if we want well you can join these
Tables by just telling the database what
to join on what so let me do this select
star from shows join that table though
on the genres table well how do you want
to join those two tables and again the
two tables from the picture looked like
this how do you tell SQL
programmatically to sort of you know put
one of them right next to the other line
up all of the ID so that you just get
one larger data set well we can use
indeed this this query this uh syntax
called join so back to VSS code here and
let me join these two
tables sorry typo here join genres on
the shows tables ID column AKA it's
primary key equaling the genres tables
show ID column aka the foreign key so in
other words it looks a little cryptic
but I'm just telling SQL how to line up
these two tables and what column to
match with the other so that the numbers
line up and I get essentially a wider
table let me go ahead and hit uh
semicolon and enter and this is now
going to give me a lot of data we might
have to interrupt it but notice even at
a glance we're getting the ID the title
the year the number of episodes the ID
again redundantly but that's to be
expected if I'm joining them and the
genre all the way on the right let me
hit contrl C to interrupt let me just
limit this to the office so where title
equals quote unquote the office so we
can focus on just one sample uh datum
and here fun fact there's been more than
one office the one that you all probably
like is this one that started in 2005
with 188 episodes its ID in the shows
table is 3866 76 that's confirmed over
here too so again we've just joined the
two tables how by lining up those fields
but now that we can see that almost all
of the offices produced over the decades
are comedies except for this one there
was a version of the office produced in
2001 that was considered more of uh a
drama no unsure if it's related to the
other how can we Link in other data well
let's go ahead and Link in ratings too
or instead so instead of joining this
with genres let me go ahead and Rewind
here and join shows on ratings on shows.
ID equals ratings. show ID and let's
limit it to the office 2 for discussion
sake where uh title equals quote unquote
the office semicolon and now you can see
that among the various offices it looks
like the one that most of us probably
know and love is the highest rated also
with a 9.0 with like 585,000 people
having cast votes for whereas these
other shows seem to have been less
popular perhaps that's why indeed you
see fewer episodes for them as well so
even though we've put the data in
multiple places you can still kind of
reconstitute it by lining things up in
this way and rejoining the tables
questions now on
this like this is the heart of what SQL
does and what relational databases do
for
you
questions all right a few final features
like there's not all that much that uh
you know SQL takes practice like
anything else but in terms of syntax and
capabilities let's just introduce you to
a couple of final features here and how
and problems that arise and how we might
solve them let's do this uh as well so
let me go back into VSS code here and
let's just find out um Steve Carell's
information again last time we did it
with this nested nested query by getting
his ID and then the show IDs and then
the titles for those show IDs with join
you can do it a little differently and
any of these ways are fine one might
become EAS easier to you mentally than
another let's go ahead and select the
titles from what let's select the title
from uh the people table but and I'm
going to hit enter and when you're using
SQL light 3 interactively if you ever
find yourself with a prompt that says
dot dot dot angle bracket it means
you're continuing your thought onto the
next line if you didn't intend that you
can sometimes hit uh semicolon to just
end the thought and hit enter and just
even if it triggers an error but this is
one way of formatting my queries now a
little more nicely I'm just going to add
some wh space so that it's a little
easier to read what do I want to select
well I want to select the title of shows
from the people table joined with the
Stars table on the people tables ID
column equaling the Stars tables person
ID column so in other words if you think
back to what people are and what stars
are one has an ID one has a person ID
I'm just now connecting those two tables
I'm joining those two but I want to do
this as well with with another table let
me additionally join in so now I only
have two hands but now I'm putting a
third table joined in together here join
shows on stars. show ID equals shows. ID
so this is now linking three tables
together but I only care about this for
one person so where the name of the
person equals quote unquote Steve Carell
so more cryptic to be to be sure but
what we're doing with this query is just
taking all three tables that we care
about and we're joining them them all
together at once using this new join
syntax literally telling the database
what columns to line up with what and
then we filter at the very end just like
before to get back if I hit enter the
answer we want which in this case is a
little slower at the moment but that
same list of uh 20 or so shows that he's
been in there's one other way to do this
and again uh these are all in the slides
online so you can repeat them without
having to jot down everything and we'll
put them in the notes too but there's
another way to do this I could also use
an implicit join so that was an explicit
join because I literally typed the word
join multiple times at that but let me
go ahead and select the title from these
three tables people stars and shows and
this might just be nicer because if you
know what tables you want to select data
from just enumerate them separated by
commas which you might prefer in your
mind where the people ID equals the
Stars person
ID and the Stars show ID equals the
shows ID and the name of the person
equals Steve Carell so this is an
implicit joint and honestly I constantly
reference my notes for some of this
stuff too it's not the kind of thing
that's going to come like this to you
after just one day but it's just a
different way of expressing the same
thing I want to select data from three
different tables and hey SQL here is how
I want you to line those tables up so
that I can get like related data for
Steve Carell and this now will achieve
the same results ultimately let me hit
enter
H and there we go so a little slower and
performance might vary based on computer
based on uh implementation of SQL but I
think I still have the same answers now
suppose as I'm often do and I had to
look it up again last time suppose you
forget what uh how to spell Steve
Carell's name is it two RS two L's or
the like well I could also do something
like this select well let's just keep
this simple select star from people
where name equals I've been deliberately
getting it right so as to not embarrass
myself that's the Steve Carell I keep
querying if you forget well you could
try searching for just Steves but there
interestingly there's a bunch of Steves
we don't know when they were born uh but
that's probably not the Steve Carell we
want if we don't have his last name so I
could alternatively do well it's Steve
and then it's starts with a C I think
well it turns out there's another wild
card you can use in SQL we used the
asterisk to select all of the columns
you can in quotes use a percent sign to
say see something so there's some zero
or more characters after the letter c
and now this doesn't work cuz now I
would be literally looking for Steve
space c something but recall earlier I
mentioned that one other keyword which
is for fuzzier matching so to speak
where it's like not exactly what you're
looking for but it's like what you're
looking for if you instead say where his
name is like Steve space c something now
we'll get back a whole bunch of Steves
but I think now I could probably find
the one I'm actually looking for if I
don't remember his name you can use
multiple percent signs if you forget
what his first name is you could reverse
the order but that too is a uh very
powerful sequel feature at that
questions on these queries here
yeah
sorry what about
it oh yeah sure so the query I used here
there's a lot of Steves whose last name
starts with C oops too far uh the last
query I executed was this one here so
where the name is like quote unquote
Steve C percent sign so that's just
another tool for your toolkit here but
you'll you'll perhaps have noticed that
those two the prior to that query the
joins I did were sort of slow and
honestly this database isn't even that
big like yes it has tens of thousands of
rows in it but like in the real world
and most of the apps you and I use a lot
every day or websites like there's
Millions even billions of rows of data
and like if I had to wait on like my
computer here or my code space like a
second or two to get the data like
that's not going to work for millions of
users or customers certainly so how can
we actually improve things well it turns
out another upside of a proper
relational database is that it's not
just a spreadsheet where the onus is on
like you to like find the data you're
looking for you can also tell the
database to index the data for you an
index is an an efficient uh cheat sheet
for Finding data fast like books in the
real world often have indices at the end
of the at the end of the book where you
can look things up alphabetically and
then you can cross reference it for the
pages that that topic appears on same
idea in a database if you tell the
database in advance that you want to
search on a certain column frequently
you can tell it to build a fancy index
that will just allow you to search that
column Faster by default these columns
are going to be searched most likely via
linear search like not even binary
search because the data might not be
sorted because it came in in any order
but if you create an index you're
probably going to get something closer
to logar rmic than linear and that's
going to be a big plus overall so let me
do something simple here first let me
turn on a SQL light specific feature
that just is going to time all of my
queries by writing do timer on I just
want to keep track of uh how long each
of these commands takes this one is not
a slow command so this is just going to
be relative but let's just select
everything from the shows table where
the title thereof is the office let's
see how long this relatively simple
query takes all right not very long at
all in real terms like less than a
second .035 seconds so not slow by any
means but if you've got hundreds
thousands millions of users like every
one of those milliseconds could very
well add up so can we do better well we
can if I do this if I use syntax like
this once in the beginning of the design
of my database I create not a table but
an index with some name on a specific
table on one or more columns I can give
a clue a hint to the database in advance
saying please optimize with some Secret
Sauce searching or selecting on this
column in this table so that my searches
are faster so let me do this let me go
back to vs code here let me create an
index called how about title index I
could call it anything I want but I want
to search faster on titles so I'm going
to call this a title index where uh
rather uh title index on the table
called shows and then in parentheses is
the syntax the column called title so
again I've just borrowed this canonical
syntax and I've just translated into
something that's TV show specific all
right what is this going to do for me
once I hit enter this is going to create
in the computer's memory the database's
memory something called a b tree it's
not a binary tree a b tree is actually a
potentially more efficient data
structure that we didn't talk about a
few weeks back in week five but it looks
a little something like this which looks
similar to a binary tree but does anyone
notice what makes this not a binary tree
exactly binary tree by implying two has
no more than two children per node but
here's a perfect example one two three
and there could be four children five
children or more but the effect of that
if you have a very wide tree the upside
is that it's like very short like it
pulls the data higher up closer to the
node to the root node and recall that
the root node is where we began our
searches in the past whether it was a
BST a binary search tree even a try or
data structures we always began at the
top so the higher up you can pull the
data even if it makes the data structure
very wide you're going to be able to do
boom boom boom look up queries look up
data probably much faster certainly than
if it's just a very long list like a
column by default so with that said let
me go back to vs code I didn't create
the index yet let me go ahead and hit
enter and create it all right it took a
minute a moment it took like half a
second which obviously is not that slow
but with more data that could have been
even slower but it's a onetime operation
as of now and now let me hit up and let
me select the same data from shows where
title equals the office last time just a
moment ago it took 0.035 seconds no not
slow but also that's going to add up if
I have lots of users of IMDb let's go
ahead now and execute the same query
again how long did that
take
0.01 seconds now I mean practically
nothing and so that's the sort of
opportunity now when you've got lots of
data and you want to really speed up
these searches these indexes these
indices that just create for you these
magical data structures in the databases
memory it allows you to search on
columns that you are pretty sure you
want to search on more effectively Now
by contrast if you've ever used like
Google or Bing or some search engine
that has advanced search some of those
text boxes that you can search more
precisely in might very well be slower
why well probably you don't want to go
crazy and just index every column on
every table why well what might be the
intuition like if logically indexes
speed things up why not index everything
there's always going to be a tradeoff
here what might that
be
yeah yeah it's going to take a lot of
storage right this is just a slide on
the screen but like this has to go
somewhere like this needs space in the
computer's memory or on the hard drive
or the like and that's fine if you have
unlimited space but odds are like you
don't and that's going to get expensive
for different reasons so maybe you only
want to index certain columns and
certain tables and not all of them
because you know what even if a user
really wants to search maybe VI advanced
search on some other column or table
altogether fine if once in a while a
query is slow like we're probably
getting the bigger bang for our buck by
optimizing the common cases the more
popular queries that people actually
care about
too all right so let's come full circle
and bring this now back to uh how how we
actually began which was with some uh
python code so it turns out these are
not either or decisions it turns out in
the real world developers are constantly
using one two three languages at once in
fact next week I rattled off HTML CSS
and JavaScript one of which is a proper
programming language but those languages
are often used together totally normal
and common to use Python and SQL or Java
in SQL or Swift in SQL or any number of
different combinations with a database
language you might use use your
preferred programming language Java
python C++ to create the user interface
and the logic that builds the uh the
that implements the program itself but
for your data like SQL is a really good
candidates and indeed we've seen already
that SQL can just speed up certain
operations you can change you can uh
collapse 15 lines of code into just one
and you can use these things together so
let me come back to I'm going to quit
out of SQL light I'm going to minimize
my terminal window and here's where we
left off before with favorite .p with
favorites. everything was being stored
in uh favorites. CSV and recall that we
eventually imported that CSV file into
favorites. DB automatically with import
just so we could start playing around
with SQL but we can now tie these two
together and a way to do that is as
follows um cs50 has a library for python
you might recall having available uh get
string get int get float you don't
strictly need to use them in Python
because it's much easier to just use the
input function and then try accept and
convert things to int or float or the
like but it's a lot more work to use SQL
in Python without a third-party Library
a lot of the commercial options or
popular open source options are actually
just complicated to use so cs50 does
have a very useful function inside of
its library for python that you should
use and must use for the problem set
that just makes it easy to execute
python uh execute SQL inside of your
python code but it's built on top of a
very popular open source alternative so
you can use that too in the real world
so the documentation for that at this
URL here but I'll show you what we need
to know here by focusing back on
favorites.i so what I'm going to do here
as follows is this let me delete
everything from favorites. py except for
let's say uh this from cs50 import SQL
in all caps so that's importing a SQL
feature from cs50's library that's going
to allow me to open a DB file in code
how do I do that well let me create a
variable called DB for database though I
could call it anything I want let me
call this SQL function and pass in using
special syntax that's not cs50 specific
it's an industry thing SQL light colon
slash slash slash unlike every other URL
you type this one literally has three in
this context here and then the name of
the database which in this case is
favorites. DB so this is just a way of
telling this SQL library that we wrote
but that works exactly like third party
Alternatives openen favorites. DB using
the SQL light technology if you will all
right let's just ask the user a question
give me your favorite um uh problem so
we're going to use input instead of get
string but we could use get string but
they're pretty much the same for our
purposes let's ask the user for their
favorite and now in Python code let us
select from favorites. DB all of the
rows where students specify that problem
as their favorite so in SQL alone it
would be this select uh star from
favorites where problem equals and I'll
do um well whatever my favorite's going
to be like problem equals Mario for
instance so if I were just using SQL I
would literally write something like
that but I'm in a piy file now like I
have to use Python syntax but python
supports strings SQL is just text it's
just a string so I could certainly just
put my SQL code in a string perhaps and
then pass it to a python function and
here's the bridge between the two if you
just treat SQL as any old text we can
put it in a string and execute it so let
me actually do this let me go ahead and
create a variable called rows which is
eventually going to contain all the rows
from the database let me go ahead and uh
select db. execute this is the one
function you need to know about inside
of cs50's library and it literally
executes a SQL statement and then in
quotes you pass it literally what you
want to execute and let me go ahead and
close the parenthesis at the end there
and now let me just try this so for Row
in rows let's iterate over all of the
rows let me go ahead and print out how
about uh row quote unquote and what do I
want here uh let's print out the Tim
stamp of that person for kicks all right
let me open open my terminal window
python of favorites. Pi crossing my
fingers here for
sure
enter uh uh there we go favorit so I'll
type in
Mario okay so I got back it's not very
interesting but I got back all of the
timestamps of students who typed in
Mario that we imported into this
database well what I really care about
is how popular Mario is so let me change
this a little bit let me change this to
count the number of rows and let me keep
it simple let me give an alias like I
proposed earlier like as n where N is a
number so that now down here I can
actually just do this print out the
value of n all right let me go back to
my terminal window run python to
favorites. py let me type in Mario enter
okay 39 now technically I'm cheating
like honestly if I'm executing select
count we've seen before it only ever
returns one row not multiple so there's
really nothing to iterate over but it's
working fine it's just just iterating
once but I'm getting lucky so
technically what I should probably just
do is this I should probably give myself
like a variable called row set it equal
to the very first row and only row that
came back and now print out that rows n
column let me rerun the program I'll
type in Mario again enter and I still
see
39 so this of course I don't strictly
need to do this I don't really need a
variable I can do Row Bracket Z instead
but let me focus on what this library is
now doing so per the documentation what
the C what the cs-50 execute function
always does for you is it returns a list
of dictionaries so if your query returns
nothing like no matches you get back an
empty list like Open Bracket close
bracket nothing in it any Loop is not
going to execute anything useful because
there's nothing in it if though you get
back one row you're going to get back a
list of size one in inside of which is a
single dictionary that dictionary is
going to have keys that correspond to
whatever you selected be it the columns
or the count so when I selected star
before I could have like I would have
gotten all of the columns that's how I
was able to access timestamp here I'm
just selecting count and I don't want to
have to type this down here that would
just look kind of atrocious it would
work but it would look weird to just
keep retyping count peren star close pen
so I just created an alias called n just
to like make this my life easier or
cleaner down here so to be clear the SQL
the cs50 execute function returns a list
of dictionaries when you're using select
and that is how I can now get back the
first and only row and then print out
that Row's n value it is identical to
let me do this let me highlight this
whole line of text let me in my terminal
window run SQL light three of favorites.
DB like we did before break let me just
copy paste this query enter that that's
the table I got back earlier when we
played with SQL manually and so when I
get back this table here's the key
here's the value and I only have one row
which is why I'm just blindly indexing
into rows bracket zero because I know
there's always going to be an answer
there it's going to be zero or one or
more but I know now it's going to be
called n because of this here so what
have I just done well this is SQL down
here and this is just me being like a
data scientist asking questions about my
data just using like black and white SQL
queries this is me now being a python
programmer who wants to talk to a SQL
database using Python and The Bridge
we're using happens to be the cs-50
library but again there's third party
free libraries you can also use as well
ours is just very simple and indeed the
documentation will explain how execute
behaves a little differently for inserts
updates and deletes you don't get back a
list because you're not selecting
anything but you do get back some return
values questions on
this that's the last of our python code
that ties everything together in
spirit
yeah uh what this this one
here yes so db. execute by definition
returns a list of rows and each of those
rows happens to be a dictionary because
it's convenient key value pairs if I'm
selecting the count of rows I just know
from Having learned squel an hour ago
that this is always going to give me a
single row whose column in this case is
called n so if I know it's a single row
I can just blindly just like in C go
into that list or an array in C and go
to the first location and then treat
that as the single row what you don't
want to do is this even if you the human
know the query returns one row you can't
just magically change the variable name
to be singular and expect to have only
one value you will always have a list so
even if there is only one value in it
it's up to you to do something like this
to get at it or if you prefer more
succinctness you can do rose bracket I
bracket n that'll achieve the same thing
without a variable
yeah good so I have been misleading this
whole time and cheating because this is
only ever going to return Mario I'm
ignoring the favorite that the human
typed in here on line five so let me fix
that and that's going to lead us to some
of the problems that arise ultimately
with SQL the right way to solve that
problem let me get rid of my terminal
window here the right way to solve this
problem is not to use an F string like
we did in Python generally because SQL
queries as we'll see in a moment can be
dangerous when you want to plug in users
uh data into a query that you've written
most of in advance you should you must
you had better use a placeholder namely
a question mark in this case this is
somewhat specific to cs50's library but
we just borrowed the convention that
like every other Library uses too in the
world of SQL single question marks are
used as placeholders and the way you do
this is as follows if you want to plug
in a value for that question mark just
like in print F in C you specify as a
second or a third or fourth argument all
of the values you want plugged into this
so in C weeks ago we were using percent
s same exact idea in SQL it's a question
mark that you use instead this now if I
open back my terminal window and I run
uh python of favorites. type in Mario I
should still get 39 but now I can also
type in scratch perhaps and get 44 for
that very first piece at zero and that
one is even more popular here so this
now is correct it would work to use an F
string here and then plug in a value
like favorite here but you'll see in
just a moment don't do that you will
expose yourself to potential hack or
attacks um by trusting the user's input
and so in fact let's transition from
that to exact some of these kinds of
challenges namely two before we wrap up
so in the world of SQL especially when
it's used at scale at the Twitter and
the Googles of the world like a lot of
lots of data is probably coming into the
database all at once because multiple
people are opening their phones at the
same time around the world they're
clicking on the same links roughly at
the same time around the world when you
have thousands of people all using your
site at once like order of operations is
going to be important but unfortunately
in SQL and in other contexts of
computing there's this risk of what's
known as a race condition so for
instance has anyone ever seen or liked
this this is like yes the world record
egg or it's like this thing that was
very popular while back it's still kind
of going strong but if you go to the
Instagram profile for world record egg
uh the goal was to make the most most
liked Instagram post ever and they did
pretty well it's just this it's just a
picture of an egg now at the height of
the popularity like there might have
been hundreds thousands tens of
thousands of people clicking pretty much
at the same time on this egg so it
actually creates a potential problem
with the Integrity of Instagram's data
why well if you're have all these
requests coming in at once how do you
possibly keep track of all of them and
update your counter in a way that can
keep up with all of that traffic why
well let's just hypothesize what meta
formerly Facebook was doing underneath
the hood with Instagram if this were
their code so suppose for the sake of
discussion that Instagram servers are
using a mix of python and SQL probably
not using the cs50 library but they
could absolutely be using those two
languages or two others together um
suppose they do this in order to update
the number of likes for that post they
first execute a SQL query like select
the current number of likes from a table
called posts where the ID of the post
equals whatever the unique identifier is
for that spec specific egg in the table
and then they store the result in this
row variable just like I did and then
they do this they grab uh they create a
variable called likes they set it equal
to rows bracket Z so the very first row
in the result set and they get the likes
key so this is literally what I just did
with the count let me hypothesize that
Instagram does something similar with
the total number of likes why are they
doing this because they then want to
execute a third line of code that
executes update the posts table set the
new number of likes equal to something
where the ID of the post equals this
other thing now notice just like in
printf there's the comma separated list
of values they want to update the
current number of likes from the current
value to the current value plus one so
it's likes plus one and then we plug in
the ID for this so suppose this is what
Instagram's doing unfortunately whenever
you execute multiple lines of code
independently and you're so popular like
Instagram that you have thousands
hundreds of thousands of servers
potentially it is quite possible that if
you and I and everyone else in the room
clicks that egg at the same time it's
not going to be the case statistically
that like three lines of code are
executed for me and then three lines for
you and then three lines for you they're
probably going to get interspersed like
this gets executed for me and then this
gets executed for you and then they get
back to doing work for me and so forth
just to kind of multitask just like a
human might but at a super speed here
the problem though is if these lines of
code get interrupted what could go wrong
well suppose that Carter and I both
click the egg at the same time and
suppose the current number of likes back
in the day is 100 that stores in this
variable the value 100 but if we click
so close in time we might get back the
same answer to this select query as of
that moment in time when David and
Carter clicked it had a 100 likes but
then this last line of code is executed
for me and then maybe Carter because
that answer the state of the database
was stored in this variable then both
Carter and I will result in this line of
code being executed with the same value
update the post table setting the likes
equal to
101 for that post's ID why because again
if each of these lines of code running
on different servers are checking the
value of the current number of likes but
then getting interrupted because Carter
clicked the darn thing too and then
resuming their work on my behalf we
might have a race condition where the
code is sort of racing to finish but
getting interrupted by other users
clicks and the problem with that is that
if you are inspecting the value of some
variable or in this case a database cell
and making a decision based on it like
how to update it you might now lose data
and Instagram probably not good for
advertising if they're losing likes and
so that's probably a problem not to
retain the value 102 and instead insert
the number 101 twice it's actually
similar in spirit to a story that uh was
told in a databases course I took myself
years ago
whereby uh it's somewhat analogous to
kind of a contrived scenario involving
like a refrigerator and this is the
closest thing to a refrigerator we could
get on stage but imagine you've got like
one of these little dorm fridges in your
dorm 2 and your roommate and maybe both
of you as the story was told to me
really like milk and one of you is at
class but the other of you comes home
and you open your dorm fridge and you're
like oh darn it we're out of milk and so
you close the fridge you walk across the
street to CVS or some other store and
you get in line to buy some milk
Meanwhile your roommate gets out of
class they come back to your dorm room
they're really thirsty for some milk
they open up the fridge they say oh
we're out of milk and then they take a
different route perhaps to CVS or some
other store nearby get in line to buy
some milk fast forward some amount of
time in this very contrived story and
what happens oh damn it we now ended up
with two gallons of milk and there's no
way we can fit gallons of milk in there
let alone two of them so that's a
problem but what's the relationship to
this here well both of us yeah did
what
exactly
exactly so to summarize both of us had a
very similar thought process made a
similar decision based on the same
information not realizing that the
information the fridge was in the
process of being updated and of course
in the Instagram World happens like this
in the fridge World it might take a few
minutes but the problem is ultimately
the result of our having made a decision
about the state of the world and the
state of the world was in the middle of
being updated the queries got mingled
with others or in this case someone was
already on their way to the store so
what's the solution in the real world
well you could you know very simply like
take a Post-It note and put like gone
for milk so as to communicate to your
roommate that they should not inspect
the value of that variable and make a
decision on it why because it's not yet
consistent with the outcome that's about
to happen you could be more traumatic
and you could actually lock the fridge
somehow put a pad lock around it or the
like so they can't even get in there and
that would achieve the result uh the
same effect too and that is actually
pretty much the solution to this problem
in code too it's not safe it's not
sufficient to only execute three lines
of code like this rather what you
probably want to do is use additional
SQL keywords that we won't spend much
time on in the class itself but these
there are solutions to this problem you
can begin what's called a transaction
and you can more explicitly commit to
making a decision like updating the
database to 10 1001 or 10 1002 or if you
realize wait a minute Carter's query
inist interrupting mine let me roll back
to the previous state and just uh rewind
let me undo contrl Z if you will there's
also another keyword that's not so much
used anymore in SQL which is locking you
could literally back in the day lock the
entire database table preventing anyone
from updating it or making changes or
even reading it while someone else was
accessing it that was a very
heavy-handed solution because it slowed
everything down but in short
transactions are now a feature of SQL
that you won't necessarily need to use
yourselves that do solve this problem by
doing the equivalent of saying while
David's like counter is in the process
of being updated keep Carter at Bay
ideally briefly and then let his data go
through too it's equivalent too to
putting a note or a lock on the fridge
and indeed I mean lock litter they they
were Once Upon a Time called and still
are in some texts called locks on
databases 2 and the last Pro and the
code for which you might do this is
almost the same you simply wrap the
three queries uh with a transaction
statement and a uh commit and the term
of art here is that this makes your uh
your uh statements Atomic so Atomic
means they're either all executed or not
at all that is they're all very tightly
coupled together without interruption
transactions solves that problem and
avoid having two gallons of milk and the
last problem that arises that Is
tragically so darn common in the real
world today is what's called a SQL
injection attack and it's what I alluded
to earlier with the question mark So
suppose you're in the habit of logging
in uh to Yale websites with your net ID
or password or at Harvard your Harvard
key and password as well suppose for the
sake of discussion that the people that
implemented like Harvard key login allow
you to type in your email address of
course and your password but suppose
that they are using SQL underneath the
hood to check your username and password
to make sure that you are David menen or
Carter zeni or whoever you claim to be I
haven't shown you the syntax yet but it
turns out that in SQL Das Dash is a
special way of indicating a comment it
means ignore everything to the right so
it's just like SL slash and C or the
hash symbol in Python dash dash just
means ignore everything to the right and
we've of course seen single quotes So
one way to wage a SQL injection attack
is to try to inject malicious SQL code
into someone else's database without
them realizing it how do you do this
well suppose I log in as M harvard.edu
single quote Das Dash I'm not double
quoting anything clearly and there's
nothing to the right of the dash dash
anyway but it this imbalance is going to
be useful why because if I'm a hacker
and I'm presuming you know someone at
Harvard probably is using SQL uh single
quotes to wrap the user's email address
and wrap the user's password what if I
try to like complete their thought for
them and close one of those quotes for
them what might happen well we could do
this here for instance let me
hypothesize is the code that Harvard
wrote hopefully not underneath the hood
so they're using CS library and Python
and they're using SQL inside suppose
that they have a query like this select
star from users where username equals uh
question mark and password equals
question mark and then suppose they just
plug in whatever username and password
was typed in and then if they get back
some number of rows dot dot dot they
assume I am David they assume Carter is
Carter if both the username and password
are in the database just end of story
there this is good this has the question
mark placeholders we discussed earlier
but what if you don't quite remember
that you don't quite take that to heart
and you use your more familiar last week
F strings whereby we use these curly
braces to plug in values what if you do
this instead so it's almost the same
idea it's still DB execute but now it's
select star from users where username
equals and now notice I'm doing the
single quotes which is required by SQL
but I'm using F strings with the curly
braces and the password equals single
quote password and then close single
quote the problem is if you're just
blindly pasting equ effectively the
user's input into that web form into the
username field and the password field
there's nothing stopping a malicious
user student faculty staff from
including a single quote in their name
or maybe even an uh uh you know
benevolently if their name happens to
have a single quote as some last names
in particular do so this is very fragile
why well suppose that if we plug in my
malicious value Ma at harvard.edu single
quote-- notice what happens to username
here the username variable inside of the
curly quotes will get replaced with this
and notice single quote which the
Harvard programmer wrote M an
harvard.edu single quote which I wrote
dash dash which I wrote single quote
which Harvard wrote and whatever else
they want after that what's the
implication though of the dash
dash everything to the right is going to
be ignored so the password is never even
checked in this scenario I'm tricking
the server into ignoring everything
after the dash dash but I have
constructed very cleverly very
maliciously a syntactically valid query
why because I provided the single quote
that's going to finish the thought of
that first single quote and now I would
only know how to do this if I saw the
code or if I just randomly try putting
apostrophes into web forms and see if
things break that's often how
adversaries attack systems they type in
potentially dangerous characters hit
enter if something breaks they're not
necessarily into the system but they
know that there might be a vulnerability
and then they start trying more
methodically things like this so This
Then is going to be bad because it
effectively Grays out the rest of the
query and this query is surely going to
return some rows without even knowing my
password and so this logic here dot dot
dot means well if a data came back from
this query Harvard is presumably going
to assume that men logged in show them
uh show him like uh his account or
whatever is being protected here so in
short using F strings bad using any
equivalent like p uh percent s in C bad
when it comes to SQL using question
marks or whatever a thirdparty library
like cs50's prescribed is the way to
solve this why because libraries like
ours are designed to at least be smart
and be paranoid and what we will do is
this when you use the question marks and
the values are plugged in we will escape
any potentially dangerous characters
inside of those placeholders and so
effectively the single quote will no
longer be considered a grammatical
single quote it will just be literally a
character in the username or password so
the library takes care of this for you
because you're plugging in the username
and password as separate arguments and
then we or the third party you're using
actually sanitize that is uh clean up
the data and prevent those bad
characters now this is kind of an
internet meme that went around for a
while um if you've ever uh driven a car
been in a car where there's like the
automatic reader for tolls uh this
person thought it might be funny to try
doing something like this what are they
presumably doing the presumption here is
whether or not it worked as unclear is
that here's like the end of a actual
license plate number but here's an
interesting single quote and a semicolon
that's especially bad because it means
you can maybe execute a second query on
the database this is someone having fun
trying to drop the entire database table
for whatever municipality is scanning
through cameras uh their license plate
code and I would be remiss if we didn't
end on this note at least in computer
science circles um there is someone
named no relation to the TF name we put
in the database earlier um little Bobby
tables which ends with this XKCD
comic and if you chuckle if you laugh
you're now legit SQL
programmers nice
nice like every CS student out there
knows about little Bobby tables so if
you name drop little Bobby tables now
like you're in all right that's it
though for today we will see you next
[Music]
time
[Applause]
[Music]
all the way to the top and then you're
passing
down this is for you Yale we love you
Yale we're here to Har
go
har
[Applause]
down it's going to
happen it's actually going to happen I
can't believe this what do you think of
Y they don't think
good can't does everyone have it does
everyone have their stuff does everyone
have their stuff probably that it's
going to beable very
small I
know what
houses how many exra how many
EXT no F forer yeah just make sure
everyone
has pass all the car distributed
all right we can do it
[Applause]
[Music]
now
what do you think of Y
sir go go one more time one
[Applause]
more there goes
again
[Applause]
all right this is cs50 welcome to week 8
last week we learned how to create read
update and delete databases using squl
but this
week Adam everyone happy
Halloween all right so this is cs50 and
this is week eight already my thanks to
Adam on today this happy Halloween uh in
the coming moments we're going to learn
all about how the internet itself Works
which of course is a technology that
like we're all take we all use every day
probably using in some form right now
but we'll see that if you start to
understand some of the underlying
building blocks that power the internet
itself we can actually start to build
interesting things on top of it and a
lot of the apps the websites that you
all use every day should become all the
more familiar things that you yourself
VES can create and honestly when things
go wrong you'll have all the more of a
mental model for how things work or are
not in fact working so that you can
ultimately diagnose diagnose all the
more issues yourselves so if we take a
look at the internet in the early days
it pretty much was just this this
happens to be of course the geography of
the United States and just some of the
first uh points on the internet were
these here this was so-called arpanet
back in 1969 and indeed the internet had
its Origins here in the United States
with just a few computers interconnect
somehow initially that of course began
to grow over time such that we
eventually had the West Coast connected
to the east coast and nowadays what you
can think of these dots on the screen is
representing are these things called
routers sort of computers or really
servers that somehow have wires or maybe
wireless connections between them that
allow data to flow from point A to B to
C and then this of course has been now
magnified across the entire Globe um and
even above ground as well so that we can
connect all the more readily uh to
systems anywhere now in order to Route
the data from one router to another we
need to somehow make routing decisions
and this is the kind of thing that the
internet service providers the isps of
the world just handle for us you and I
plug our Macs our PCS into the network
here at Harvard or equivalently at Yale
or we somehow get online via Wi-Fi or
cellular technology and then some of
these larger entities these bigger
companies or countries handle most of
the data getting from point A to point B
and if you think about what these
routers present they're indeed just
servers somehow interconnected not
unlike this grid of tiles here for
instance back in the zoom days and in
fact here we have I claim a grid of
routers implemented here by the courses
teaching fellows and course assistants
and Tas and if the goal at hand for
instance is for Phyllis to Route some
piece of information maybe it's an email
maybe it's a request for a web page in
the bottom right hand corner all the way
up to say Brian here in the top left
hand corner suffice it to say each each
of these tiles represents a router a
server that can move the data back forth
left and right that packet of
information so to speak from Phyllis to
Brian could take any number of different
possible routes up down left right to go
from the one corner to another so let me
go ahead and hit play on this video here
we're in the teaching fellows play the
same
[Music]
role
all right so in this particular case the
data was routed pretty straightforwardly
up and then to the left but suppose that
one or more of the staff were a bit busy
maybe one of the routers is congested
that is to say just got way more
envelopes at a moment in time that it
can handle thankfully the design of the
internet is such that there's often
multiple ways that data can get from
point A to point B maybe going through
Point C or Point D instead and so
there's a resilience there even as some
of these servers themselves might go
down so allow me to propose that we use
the same grid of routers now to Route
the data in a slightly different way
this
[Music]
[Applause]
time
so success you'll see perhaps later just
how many takes it took us to actually
get that routing right but it does in
fact manifest that you can uh travel
different paths in order to get the data
from point A to point B so as we talk
about routers as you think of the
internet I mean think of those humans as
just representing these routers points a
to p and everywhere in between now how
did the teaching staff know to route
that packet up and then down or left and
right in order to get get to the
destination well all of them were
programmed so to speak to understand
protocols it's called TCP and IP
Otherwise Known together typically as
tcpip and you've probably seen these
acronyms at some point in the real world
on the internet on some kind of
documentation a text even if you haven't
really thought hard about it but IP is
certainly the more common of the two
perhaps in common culture so what does
TCP and IP do for us well really two
primary things any computer or any
teaching staff member who understands
tcpip knows how to get data from point A
to point B but how well let's break down
what that problem to be solved is IP
otherwise known as Internet Protocol is
a protocol that computers speak that
allow them to know how to address
computers on the internet and a protocol
is just a set of conventions that
computers adhere to so someone wrote
code that probably has a whole lot of
conditionals that tells the computer
what to do if something happens like if
I receive a packet then send it to the
next server or something like that in
the human world we have protocols too
you know pre in healthier times it was
quite common to sort of extend your hand
to another human in order to greet them
and if they're following human protocol
they would presumably grab your hand and
shake it at least in a a culture like
this one here on campus and now that is
a human protocol in that someone
initiates it someone responds to it and
you both sort of know what to do you're
programmed to know what to do so same
idea with Internet Protocol computers
just know what to do when they've been
programmed to do so so what does this
mean IP had decides that every compter
computer in the world will have a unique
address just like uh a the science
center around the corner might have a
unique address of one Oxford Street
Cambridge Massachusetts 02138 USA IP
dictates that every computer on the
internet have a unique address of this
form and this too is probably something
you've seen in the real world even if
you haven't thought too hard about it
it's a number and what's called dotted
decimal notation which means it's a
decimal number do something do something
do something so four digits separated by
convention by decimal points although
there are newer and bigger versions of
the same and these so-called IP
addresses that might be as simple as
1.2.3.4 uniquely identify a computer on
the internet uh the numbers have to
range from 0 to 255 each and that's a
bit of a hint just as you start to think
more computationally if each of these is
a number from 0 to 255 how many bits
does that suggest each number is
using feel free to shout it
out how many bits gives us 255 256 total
possibilities so eight bits that should
just be sort of a heuristic in your mind
anytime you hear something that's in the
range of 0 to 255 or 256 values total
think back to week zero which gives us
eight bits plus another eight bits
another eight bits and another eight
bits which is to say an IP address
typically is 32 bits in total now if we
do another bit of quick mental math or
think back to week zero if every IP
address is 32 bits how many computers
can we have on the
internet at once give or take
roughly 4 billion is the ballpark and we
don't need to be super precise for
discussion's sake but roughly 4 billion
is how high you can account assuming no
negative numbers if you have 32 bits in
total now that's not terribly uh many
number uh numbers of addresses
especially considering the number of
humans in the world the number of us
that do have laptops or desktops or
devices more generally phones in our
pockets and the like so let me just
stipulate for today's purposes that
there's even a newer and improved
version of Ip otherwise known as version
6 this is version four but still super
popular version six uses 128 bits which
is a huge number of possible
premutations I dare say I can't even
pronounce that number it's so big so
there are ways around even this
limitation already so every computer has
an address like this what does that
really mean well suppose that I was
Phyllis in the story told visually
earlier and I want to send a message to
Brian well both Phyllis and Brian have I
IP addresses and suppose that Brian's IP
address happens to be 1.2.3.4 in that
top left hand corner well phyllis's Mac
or PC or phone would essentially do the
equivalent on this human envelope by
writing the two address in the middle of
the envelope as is our human convention
like this so this is an envelope a piece
of information an email a text message
whatever destined for Brian and so she
would have her computer put Brian's IP
address in the middle her IP address is
Maybe 5.6.7 do8 so just like our human
convention I might write 5.
6.7.8 at the top of the envelope
5678 thereby indicating what the return
address is and this is helpful because
if Brian's computer needs to acknowledge
receipt if he needs to reply in some
form this way the envelope has all the
information we need but in the real
world servers do a lot of things
nowadays not just email but maybe chat
Maybe video conferencing maybe any
number of other services as well and so
it turns out that an address alone might
not be sufficient because how do how
does Brian's computer know when he opens
the envelope so to speak that this
should be interpreted as an email or
interpret it as a chat message or
interpret it as like a video attachment
that Phyllis has sent well we need some
other mechanism some other hint on this
envelope to distinguish one type of
Internet service from another and so
that's where the other acronym in TCI
pip comes in which is TCP so this stands
for transmission control protocol which
is just a different set of conventions
that computers adhere to in order to
solve a couple of different problems one
is this problem of distinguishing one
type of service from another now what
does that mean well humans decades ago
decided as they started inventing all of
these various internet services the web
being the first one how they might or
the web now being one of the most
popular ones they decided to assign
different services that can be used on
the internet unique numbers and so two
of the most common are these 80 is the
number that a bunch of humans decided
years ago will represent what you and I
know as HTTP and we'll talk more
technically in a bit about what HTTP is
but obviously it's the thing that's in
the beginning of every URL nowadays or
https which of course has the S added to
it and that has its own unique number
and for now the S just means secure one
is encrypted or scrambled somehow for
privacy sake and the other is
unencrypted it's a little more
vulnerable to interception so these two
numbers are what the world decided when
implementing TCP shall uniquely identify
those services so what does this mean
well this means that if Brian's computer
in the story from before is hosting not
like an email server but maybe he has a
website and Phyllis is requesting
Brian's homepage or something like that
she would have her Mac or PC or phone
not only write Brian's IP address in the
middle of the envelope but also the
number otherwise known as a port number
that she wants this envelope to be
routed to now 80 would be insecure
nowadays HTTP col is sort of p and we
almost always see https colon now so I'm
just going to go with best practice and
I'm going to add a colon and then the
number
443 at the end of Brian's IP address so
now I have an IP address for Brian the
port number for the service that this is
relevant to and I'm not going to bother
writing it but it turns out that
phyllis's computer would also choose a
port number maybe a random port number
so that Brian can conversely reply and
then the computer can know which
response is in uh coming back for which
request but the most important one is
this one in the two field whereby this
distinguishes this from like an email a
chat message a video conference session
or a zoom or whatnot from anything else
happening on Brian's computer at the
same time so all this time if you've
seen these terms TCP and IP those are
really two of the most important things
that they do but TCP does one other
thing that's super useful too it turns
out that it's
super common nowadays especially to
transmit a lot of media on the internet
internet whether it's an image or maybe
it's a movie file and it would be a
little obnoxious to say the least if
you're downloading a really big file
meant that no one else in your dorm room
or your household could actually
download anything until you're actually
done so of course multiple people
nowadays can be on the internet at once
even if all of the connections are a
little slower but like one person's
usage does not block someone else's now
how does this work well TCP in
conjunction with IP can also allow you
to take like a really big image of a cat
which is the internet of course is
filled with and take a big image of a
cat or a big video file of a cat and
fragment it into multiple pieces so I'm
just going to sort of roughly tear it
down the middle and then maybe tear it
down the middle again so now it's four
different fragments and I'm I'm sorry
but the computer will be reassembling
these for us and what phyllis's computer
could do now if she's like uploading
this picture of a cat to Brian's web
server well she could put one fragment
in this envelope and then have three
separate envelopes for the other three
fragments and what you could then do on
the outside of this envelope is just
kind of number them somehow and in fact
this is something else that TCP and IP
together would do for us this first
envelope now might say something like
one out of four in the memo field so to
speak of the uh metaphorical envelope
here now this should be enough
information because now if Brian gets
all four of these envelopes he
presumably knows how to reassemble the
picture of the cat in order top to
bottom left to right but more
importantly suppose that one of the
routers one of the TFS in the video is
sort of distracted and they sort of drop
one of the packets and that's a metaphor
actually in practice for when a router
gets really busy it's got way too much
data coming in it might metaphorically
drop packets what does that mean in
practice I mean it literally just
ignores the zeros and ones it doesn't
save them to its memory because there's
just no room left so it's equivalent to
sort of dropping the packet so suppose
now that Brian gets one of four three of
four and four of four what can his
computer infer
now after receiving those three packets
one of four three of four and four of
four what's the use there yeah I think
you're you're signaling with your
fingers which one did which one can I
call on you yeah so he's missing two out
of four the second of the packets and
this is useful now because you could
imagine he can send some message back to
Phyllis saying hey please retransmit
number two of four without having to
redownload the entirety of the cat so
there's there's an efficiency there as
well so tcpip allows data really to go
from point A to point B while solving a
bunch of these problems along the way so
nowadays if you ever see mention on your
Mac or PC of your so-called IP address
that is the sort of problem that's being
solved questions now on these protocols
these conventions called TCP and
IP that's the extent to which we'll need
to understand them won't have to
implement them per se we'll just take
them Hereafter for
granted any questions that you've ever
been wondering wondering about your home
network
yeah a really good question uh how does
TCP know that a user got a message
another aspect another feature of TCP is
that Brian's computer by design of this
protocol will also acknowledge the
packets that he's received and it will
do it efficiently if Brian receives all
four packets in a pretty narrow window
of time his computer will send to
phyllis's computer a quick message
saying essentially received all four
otherwise he'll say the opposite which
is that I'm missing for for instance two
out of four and that just ensures
ultimately that all of the data is
indeed uh arrived so that you're not
missing like uh a quarter a quadrant of
the cat in question all right but th
that's not the only problem that needs
to be solved ultimately we also need to
make the internet userfriendly if you
will and it would be really tedious if
you had to visit websites for instance
by way of of their IP addresses right
1.2.3.4 is pretty memorable but there's
like 4 billion other possible addresses
available and it would be super tedious
to remember those it would be bad
marketing to advertise those in fact
most of you probably don't even know the
phone numbers of your closest friends
and family members anymore because you
instead store them in your contacts
you're in your dress book associating
with numbers that are completely opaque
with actual names or strings if you will
the same is goes for the internet too
even though every computer does have and
must have a unique IP address
numerically why well routers or
computers computers just crunch numbers
very readily but we humans work better
with strings of text we need some system
for converting userfriendly strings like
harvard.edu or yale.edu or google.com to
the underlying IP addresses and that's
where the next acronym comes in today
which is DNS domain name system so this
is just another technology that's been
in use for some time now and it's a
collection of servers on the internet
that whose purpose in life is to convert
domain names to IP addresses and maybe
vice versa as well so let me stipulate
for today's purposes there are some root
DNS servers in the world that long story
short know about all of the Dooms all of
the edus all of the dot dot dot all of
the other top level domains around the
world as well as in the US and then
there are some smaller DNS servers owned
by companies owned by universities and
even in your apartments or homes most
likely indeed if you have a home router
plugged into the wall somewhere that's
not only routing your data in and out of
your apartment or home or dorm room it's
also typically serving as a local
therefore faster DNS server a cash if
you will it's sort of locally saving
your most frequently accessed websites
and their IP addresses just to avoid
bothering the bigger more expensive
busier servers all day long so there's
DNS servers all over if you poke around
your settings in Windows or Mac OS or
Android or iOS you'll see mention of DNS
and you'll probably see the IP addresses
of the servers whose purpose in life is
to do this conversion for you but this
is a requisite feature if we just want
the internet to be user friendly and
allow us to use words instead of numbers
alone what's inside of these DNS servers
you know it's essentially a spreadsheet
or if we can say it more geeky it's
essentially like a hash table of some
sort which it has keys and values like
the key is the domain name harvard.edu
gale. edug google.com and the value is
the corresponding IP address or in many
cases IP addresses plural of the
corresponding servers so here already
even though I've drawn it fairly
abstractly like you would on a
chalkboard it's really probably
implemented as some kind of table maybe
a hash table maybe a database table
maybe SQL or something like that or
maybe it's even just a link list or an
array we just have to somehow enable
this computer to convert one to the
other now just to be super precise
DNS servers actually convert what are
called fully qualified domain names
which is generally not just harvard.edu
but more verbosely
www.harvard.edu and
www.google.com so the whole thing that
you would see as a substring of the URL
so that's what DNS does and that's what
your University your company your home
router are doing for you let me pause
here to see if there are any
questions this to is just a technology
now we'll take for granted just
works questions at all all right so
let's now transition among our protocols
really to the last for today which will
set the stage for actually solving
problems with these and writing some
code ultimately um HTTP this is
something that you see or hear all day
long even though you rarely have to
bother typing it anymore odds are if you
go to harvard.edu yale.edu google.com
you don't bother typing HTTP let alone
https manually anymore why because your
browser Auto completes that kind of
thing just to make life easier but it is
officially at the beginning of every URL
you visit either HTTP or the more secure
https whenever you're using your browser
to access some website so
HTTP stands for hyper text transfer
protocol and it's uh easily one of the
most popular dare say one of the most
powerful features of the internet
nowadays but the mental model to have
here is that HTTP or the web more
generally is kind of a service that runs
on top of the internet and maybe Zoom or
Microsoft teams is another service that
runs on top of the internet an iMessage
and Technologies like it is another
service that runs on top of the internet
so the internet is really like the lower
level Plumbing the tcpip stuff the DNS
stuff that just gets data from point A
to point B but now and we're in a a
software development class ultimately
here in cs50 HTTP is the application
Level protocol it's sort of what
programmers use what companies use what
uh developers use ultimately to use the
underlying Plumbing to build interesting
and Powerful things so what does this
mean when it comes to accessing Services
via HTTP or the more secure
https well here is a representative URL
even though you might not type the whole
thing if you poke around your address
bar this is what's up there with that
said a lot of browsers nowadays are kind
of simplifying if not dumbing down what
you see with your human eyes just to
shorten the strings especially on mobile
devices but almost always if you click
the URL or highlight it then you see the
whole thing but on many browsers you
might only ever see example.com but all
of this information is there it's just
getting more and more hidden just for
user interfaces sake well it turns out
when you visit a URL by default
especially if you type nothing after the
do com in this case you're technically
implicitly adding a single slash so a
single slash denotes the root of the
server that is the default page or
folder in the server and the slash
whether or not you type it or not is
implicitly going to be there and that
just means give me the default whatever
is at www.example.com give me that page
or that folder but URLs can be longer
than this and more generally there can
be a path so to speak and this is a term
of art a path is some sequence of folder
Andor file names after a URL like this
and so you might see more specifically
that a URL contains a very specific file
this isn't as common nowadays anymore
though we will begin to today by using
this technique but if there is a file
called literally file. HTML or something
else on the server that file is going to
be what this URL pulls up on the
computer meanwhile you might have slash
folder slash which just means show me
whatever is inside of this folder or you
might have more verbosely folder file.
HTML which will show you that file in
that folder and meanwhile just to give
some other terms of art this is the
so-called fully qualified domain name
and again these vocab don't matter all
that much but you'll hear or see them
over time we generally colloquially just
refer to this as the domain name which
is a little less precise but gets the
job done certainly in conversation and
this part here I described briefly
earlier what's the name for this suffix
at the very end of the fully qualified
domain
name the yeah yeah top level domain or
TLD and this is just some form of
categorization of the URLs now the
internet in got it start within the
United States and a lot of the first
websites of course came from the US and
so For Better or For Worse the sort of
steak was planted in the ground so
generally do indicated at least early on
that it was some kind of commercial
Enterprise a business that owned a
domain name edu is a educational
institution net was some kind of
network. goov was the US government now
there are also country code tlds cctlds
like UK or JP every country in the world
has its own two letter uh TLD um that
might very well be restricted to only
servers or companies or people in that
uh in that country many of them can be
used by anyone you've used a lot of URLs
in this class ending in
cs50. that doesn't mean input output um
it actually is a TLD from another
country that lets anyone on the internet
um pay for and on an annual basis using
that domain. TV for instance you might
see in some cases like twitch.tv and the
like um that too is owned by another
country that allows others in the
English-speaking World in this case to
use it as though it connotes TV but
those are just different types of TLS
that roughly categorize where the domain
lives but it doesn't necessarily mean
it's commercial anymore it doesn't
necessarily mean it's a Network anymore
for the most part there are hundreds of
tlds now for better for worse most of
which are less common than these big
ones um but most anyone can buy most of
them with just some restrictions on
things like edu and goov that are still
very much regulated this meanwhile is
what we might call the host name www
it's obviously a super common convention
like almost every website uses www as
its host name but that's a human
convention it's not a requirement and
indeed some websites don't even bother
having a host name they just use their
domain to advertise their websites this
now is going to be the scheme or the
protocol and this is just going to
indicate via what protocol the computer
your Mac your PC your phone should use
when accessing content at that address
because indeed there are other protocols
you can use but for the most part
will'll only focus on HTTP or
equivalently
https all right any questions now on
those just definitions building blocks
of URLs just so we all sort of share a
common
vocabulary any questions at all yeah
what is the
local sure we'll come back to this
actually later today there's a a
technical term known as Local Host which
is a generic name for your computer your
Mac your PC your phone especially when
you're doing software development and by
convention your own computer has not
only whatever IP address you get from
your University or your internet service
provider it also has a reflexive IP
address one that just always refers to
itself which is 127.0.0.1 and that's
just a human convention humans decided
that shall refer always to your computer
and it's actually going to be useful
today and onward because we can use that
when development on our own computers
ultimately other questions on URLs IP
DNS or any of these building
blocks all right so what do we mean by
HTTP being a protocol when I extended my
hand earlier as a human handshake you
know a typical human in healthy times
would know to respond in turn well how
does Brian's computer know to respond to
phyllis's envelope whatever message is
they're in well assuming that Brian is
indeed still a web server in the store
and Phyllis was trying to upload a cat
or maybe download a cat from Brian's web
server inside of phyllis's envelope
would have been a message literally in
text and it's English for the most part
and it would contain at the beginning of
that message literally one of these
English verbs either get which means
just that get me the homepage get me a
picture of a cat get me a picture of a
dog or a video or anything else or post
which often means post that is um put
that is um upload a picture of a cat or
a dog or something else to the server
instead that's not strictly the only use
cases for these but you can generally
think them as one is just getting
information and the other is posting
from the client from Phyllis to the
server in this case Brian so those are
the two keywords that we might see and
why is this useful well it turns out we
can start to see in our own Mac or PC
some of these very same messages for
instance if Phyllis were visiting not
Brian's but example.com that web server
inside of her metaphorical envelope
there would be a textual message that
literally starts with get slash then the
word HTTP then the version she's using
1.1 is very common two and three are
becoming more common but HTTP generally
looks like this the next line of text in
her envelope would probably say host
colon then literally the fully qualified
domain name of the server she's
accessing just in case and this happens
super commonly especially on small
websites if one server is hosting
multiple domain names multiple websites
this just distinguishes which one she
actually wants and then there's usually
a whole bunch of other lines of text as
well so where can you actually see this
well let me actually go ahead and do
this give me just a moment and I'm going
to open up on my computer here uh an
empty Chrome window in incognito mode
generally speaking incognito mode or
private mode is used when you don't want
there to be left remnants of what
websites you visited and it has the
effect for software developers of just
forgetting any things you might have
tried already within your browser
including things called cookies more on
those another time uh your autocomplete
history and the like so for development
purposes incognito mode is especially
helpful because it's sort of like
starting with a clean slate every time
you open a new private or incognito mode
so there's not going to be like any
remnants of previous testing or code
that you've been playing with and I'm
going to go ahead and do this I'm going
to go ahead and uh right click or
control click on Chrome I'm going to
choose inspect and it's going to pull up
this window sometimes on the side
sometimes on the bottom I'm going to
move it to the bottom just so we can see
it a little more readily and I'm going
to zoom in and it's going to look a
little Arcane at first and I'm going to
just highlight a few of these tabs we'll
see here along the top that there's
elements console sources Network and
whole bunch of other things as well this
is sort of the advanced mode in Chrome
and Safari and Firefox and Edge have
their own equivalent of these features
they've always been there even if you've
never clicked the right button to enable
these features and I'm going to focus
for a moment on network like this
this is a feature of the browser that's
going to allow me the programmer in this
case so the the engineer to just kind of
look at what messages my browser is
actually sending to a server so let me
go ahead and do something like this let
me go ahead and visit uh for instance uh
in my browser here and I'm going to
shrink the window just a little bit so
we can see it exactly I'm going to visit
https uh
www.harvard.edu and now I'm going to hit
enter
and a whole bunch of stuff just happened
along the bottom of my screen and I'm
going to try to pull my window up just a
little bit so we can focus on a subset
of this let me pull this up covering up
really the content of the page focusing
on these lower level details down here
and what I want to see first
is let me oh sorry let me go ahead and
reload this page here after retaining
the log so that we can see absolutely
everything on the screen and to be clear
I just checked because I forgot earlier
preserve log because I wanted to
preserve everything on the screen I want
to see everything all at once and we'll
see this the very first line of output
is completely overwhelming with detail
at first glance but what you'll see here
if I start to scroll down and down and
down and down are the so-called request
headers and let me zoom in here and what
you're seeing inside of chrome inside of
its Network tab in its so-called
developer tools again this is just for
engineering types you'll see all of the
headers all of the lines of text that
magically were sent by my Mac to
harvard.edu much like from Phyllis to
Brian server in that story so I can see
exactly what messages are being sent and
a lot of this we haven't talked about
yet but we do see some mention of get
and we see some mention of Slash and a
bunch of other Arcane details but notice
they're all sort of key value pairs with
the here indicating what the
corresponding value is now most of this
is not going to be interesting and we're
not going to focus too much on the weeds
of of all of this but it indeed gives us
a sense of what's inside of that virtual
envelope now harvard.edu is one thing
but there's other uh websites we might
visit as well um and no matter what they
are we're going to expect ultimately an
HTTP response so in addition to a
computer like my Mac or phyllis's
computer sending a request containing
gets and host and those details too
you'll see here in my slide form just
representative response from the server
and notice that key here is that the
server is responding in the same version
of HTTP in this example it's sending
back this so-called status code just a
numeric code that indicates in this case
that everything's okay and it includes
this header this HTTP header which again
is just a key value pair saying that the
type of this content that's coming back
from the server is text/html more on
HTML in just a little bit but for our
purposes now this just means that
harvard.edu is sending me back a web
page and indeed if we hide all of this
techn techical stuff that's the web page
that we saw up here with all of the
usual imagery and the like and in fact I
can see this if I scroll back up not to
request headers but response headers
you'll see up here that we get back
responses including the date that the
server responded and a whole bunch of
other details as well and honestly this
has always been under your fingertips
and it will soon be useful as we start
making web-based applications ultimately
but this very quickly gets overwhelming
quickly and so better in this might
actually be a tool that we can use
within our code space itself so let me
go back to vs code here I didn't open
any code tabs I'm just going to use my
terminal window for a moment and I'm
going to run a couple of commands that
are going to allow me to actually see
what is going on when I request one
website let me go ahead and use a
command called curl for connect URL and
this is like a command line black and
white program that's going to pretend to
be a browser and it's going to connect
to the URL show me the headers but it's
not going to show me the images are the
graphics which might very well be useful
to the humans but not to me right now as
the developer so I'm going to do curl
I'm going to do Dashi and then I'm going
to do
https www.harvard.edu as though I'm
pretending to be a browser requesting
the home page and what's nice about curl
is albeit overwhelming too you'll get
back a whole response from the server
containing only those header values the
key value pairs inside of the envelope
and we'll ignore almost all of these but
here is the response from the server it
responded using a new and improved
version of HTTP in this case version two
and it gave me back a 200 there's my
content type text/html and then this
Char set happens to do with the encoding
if it's Unicode or asky or something
else and then there's all this other
overwhelming detail for now but this is
the beginnings of my ability to just
kind of poke around and see how the
server works and it turns out too that
we'll be able to see other potential
responses as well so for instance uh
HTTP might not only return 100 what if I
do this instead let me go ahead and
visit c-i
HTTP
colon uh www.harvard.edu so notice I
deliberately use the insecure version of
the URL which maybe Harvard's
Administration system administration
doesn't like anymore well how can they
ensure that I the end user the student
nonetheless use
https even if I didn't type it myself
well let me run just that command with
just HTTP not https and you'll see that
everything is not okay it didn't come
back with a 200 it came back with 301 in
this message saying Harvard moved
permanently but here's where you can
look for another clue among all of these
lines most of which I don't care about
there's a location header colon that's a
little hint to me that says where
Harvard University has apparently moved
too on the web and what's different
about this URL just to be
clear it has the S included and what
your browser will do by default because
Google and Microsoft and Mozilla
programmed it this way whenever it sees
a 301 response instead of 200 it won't
show you any web page it will look for a
location header find that URL and then
automatically quote unquote redirect you
there to so this is why it doesn't
matter what we type in the browser
Harvard can have its server send these
semi-secret messages to our browsers and
then it will just visit a second URL all
automatically and you can do this with
host names as well suppose that Harvard
does not want to standardize on
harvard.edu why they just want it to
always be www maybe it's a branding
thing maybe it's a technical thing we
can see the exact same response here
this first tells me when I visit HTTP
harvard.edu with no www Harvard
minimally wants me to be using a secure
connection if I then okay fine cooperate
let me go ahead and clear my screen let
me add the s but not the www you can see
here that it again responded with 301 up
here and the location now adds the www
so it's just a way of bouncing users
from one place to another and this is
all thanks to http boiling down to
relatively simple messages inside of the
envelope that tell the computer the
browser in this case how to respond now
odds are you've seen others besides 301
even though you've probably never seen
that actual number unless you've done
this kind of thing before but there
probably is a number that like everyone
in this room has seen if if You' never
really wondered why is it that number I
think you're smiling what number are you
thinking of yeah so 404 why is 404 well
404 indicates by convention not found
and now why the world decided years ago
to show us normal humans on the internet
404 is anything significant is unclear
that's sort of like bad design like what
do I care if the status code is 404 but
it's common enough on the internet that
probably all of us have seen it but that
just means that some server when you
visit a URL that's incorrect maybe it's
outdated the URL has been changed if you
see a 404 it just means that the virtual
envelope that came from the server back
to your Mac or PC or phone contains not
200 okay not 301 moved permanently but
404 not found instead and it's usually
accompanied by a technical message maybe
a cute picture of a cat sort of hiding
because it means not found or something
like that the Aesthetics are entirely up
to the server but that's what the 404
means and there's other codes too a few
of which you'll use in the coming weeks
as we transition from commandline
programs in C and python to web-based
ones we've seen a few of these already
and several of them are kind of variants
of the same thing like these 300 ones
here but we'll see others like 403
Forbidden means like you probably forgot
to log in or you need to log in or
something like that uh internal server
error right now no in the coming weeks
you will absolutely encounter 500 errors
and they're always your fault it's going
to be the equivalent of like a
segmentation fault in C a 500 error
means like you or I screwed up when
writing some code so we're going to see
that but it's just going to be an
opportunity for us to fix it if a
server's overloaded you often see 503
like something's unavailable because
something's too popular uh or is maybe
worse getting attacked um this is an old
uh um April Fool's joke 418 is not
actually used in practice but someone
like took the time to write up an entire
formal text technical proposal so that
servers can respond saying I'm a teapot
so it's kind of part of Internet lore
and there's other ones of these status
codes as well but this is useful because
eventually we'll see in code you can use
this understanding uh high level as it
might be of HTTP to do some interesting
and Powerful things so for instance we
can even send fancier URLs to servers it
turns out as we'll soon see if you send
a message like this get/ search question
question mark Q equals cats and then
HTTP 1.1 or whatever version and you
send that message to Google server
www.google.com this is how you can
specify not just the path of a web page
that you want SL search in this case the
question mark it turns out is going to
be a convention in the internet in the
web specifically for passing hum human
uh user input to the server as well in
fact you've probably never paid close
attention to URLs but they very often
have question question marks they very
often have equal signs and indeed even
google.com supports a certain key Q in
this case for query and you can put
anything you want after that in order to
search for actual cats so if I actually
go back to Chrome itself here for a
moment let me pull back my uh pull back
open my Chrome browser here previously I
was using uh incognito mode for
harvard.edu I've gone ahead and Clos
that window and opened a new one so we
can start fresh by visiting Google
normally you and I are in the habit of
going to google.com and searching via
the form or nowadays you just type like
your search query in the browser itself
and it brings you automatically to
Google or Bing or something else but I
can really be pedantic here let me go
ahead and zoom in and I'll manually go
to
https
www.google.com search question mark Q
equals maybe cats now this would not be
a very userfriendly experience if all of
us had to manually type out something
crazy like that but that's what the form
is redirecting you to when you type in
more user friendly cats into like a text
box if I hit enter here we'll get back
indeed a whole bunch of search results
about cats if I zoom back in and maybe I
change it from cats to dogs that too is
going to change and notice it's
pre-populating the text box because
Google has written its code in order to
do so as well now appr propo of the
video with which we began today from
yester year one of the better uh Yale
pranks over the years um has anyone one
actually ever been to uh
safetyschool.org
and to our friends at Yale watching live
hi safetyschool.org so it's kind of fun
if you actually visit it uh depending on
who you are so if I open up a new window
here and I go to
https
safetyschool.org zooming
in enter my oh my look at where it goes
now how does that okay okay thank
you this is not a cs50 thing someone out
there who I don't know who they are for
like 20 years has been paying annually
for that domain safetyschool.org for
just this joke uh but if I now go back
into VSS code here in my terminal window
and a little more you know
sophisticatedly let me do curl dasi HTTP
col andsafety
school.org the browser of course
immediately redirected me to the website
but what's going on under underneath the
hood well 20 some years ago someone
bought the domain configured the server
quite simply to spit this out safety
school.org for years has moved
permanently to
www.yale.edu so just a little
demonstration of what you can do with
just a little bit of understanding of
HTTP that's been a lot already we've
laid the foundation for understanding
how the internet works now we're going
to use it with a language called HTML
hypertext markup language CSS cascading
stylesheets and JavaScript a proper
program in language but first it feels
opportune to take a 10-minute break we
have some wonderful Halloween candy in
the transcept and we'll be back in 10
with those
languages we're headed up to uh
Austin checking out the stadium for the
prank a few years ago I was at a math
conference and I was sitting around at
the table at dinner with a few other
mathematicians and uh one of them went
to Harvard and started telling the story
of this amazing prank that was you know
against Harvard and at that point I felt
I had to interrupt and said well
actually I can tell you a lot more about
that okay okay the idea was perfected in
a dorm room came up with the idea
actually to prank them with signs at the
football game we threw some ideas out
there as far as what what the signs
would say we uh eventually settled on we
suck and my immediate reaction was no
this will never work however the problem
solver in me started thinking well maybe
we can make this
work the problem they had to infiltrate
Harvard Stadium without getting caught
sneak in 1,800 placards distribute them
to unsuspecting Harvard fans and then
convince those fans to prank themselves
it's great we thought about basically
every possible thing that could go wrong
and tried to come up with a solution for
it and then you put two Reds on top of
it they made fake Harvard IDs and fake
backstories
fake placard designs and a 28 member
fake Pep
Squad on November 20th 2004 a fake
Harvard student smuggled the placards
into the game what do you think
[Music]
[Applause]
of but then trouble what houses
how many how many extra
are I you know just showed him the front
of this ID and all of a sudden he just
ran away and he felt so
embarrassed having escaped one
confrontation they couldn't risk another
it was
time this just looks like a total mess
we have absolutely no idea if this is
going to work look at the it's going to
happen it's actually going to
happen I can't believe this what was
once a
prank became a
legend and immediately we started
hearing chance from the other side
you and I think it was at that point in
time that we knew we had pulled it
off on
there it goes
[Applause]
again I really think it didn't matter
that Harvard won because of the prank
for a lot of Yale students in alumni we
definitely won that
[Music]
year all right
happy
Hallen thank you all okay thank you oh
here oh all right little Halloween candy
all right thank you all so glad I wore
the same thing
today so in just a
moment thank you okay so in just a
moment we'll transition to understanding
all the now what we can do with this
underlying infrastructure so again HTTP
and below it TCP IP is all about just
getting the data from point A to pointb
in some standardized way but now let's
talk about HTML this is the language in
which web pages themselves are written
hyper text markup language now some of
you might have used this before to make
personal homepages some of you might
have dabbled even if using some website
to create your own homepage but
understanding this language is useful
certainly for creating the Aesthetics of
a web page can vying data that's of
interest but at the end of the day it
and the language we look at next CSS uh
are not programming languages there's
going to be no functions no Loops uh no
programming logic but we will end today
with a teaser of a proper programming
language called JavaScript via which you
can manipulate all of these various uh
other languages as well so ultimately
HTML has like two features and this is a
language that we spend very brief amount
of time on because it really boils down
to just a couple of basic ideas and then
vocabulary that you'll build out over
time just by Googling looking up
references looking at other Pages source
code but tags and attributes are what
characterize HTML now what do I mean by
that here for instance is the HTML code
via which you can make probably the
simplest of all web pages one that quite
simply says in the uh browser window
hello title and hello body for instance
now what does this actually mean if you
imagine opening up uh this code in a
browser be it on a Mac or PC or phone
you'll see typically like some kind of
rectangular window and there's usually a
tab that has the title of that page and
then most of the rectangular region is
the web page itself what you're looking
at then is the code that's going to put
hello title in the title bar in the tab
at the very top and down at the bottom
hello body is going to be all that's in
the big black and white box that
composes the rest of the browser window
itself now what are the Salient
characteristics here that we'll now
start to take for granted well first
whoops uh first let's go ahead and give
me just a moment here um and actually do
something with this code so I'm going to
go ahead and do this back in vs code
here I'm going to first create a file
called say hello.html and in this tab
I'm going to go ahead and really repeat
exactly that same code now I had this
line first DOC type HTML then I had this
line HTML Lang equals quote unquote n
close quote then I had inside of that
head then I had inside of that title
then inside of that I had hello title
and I'm doing this quickly because we'll
tease apart in a moment what it actually
all means and then down here below that
so-called head I had just the text hello
body so at the moment I that I claim is
the entirety of a web page but it
currently lives in my code space so to
speak in a file called hello.html that's
fine if I want to create it but how do I
how do you how does anyone on the
internet actually view it well to serve
a web page you indeed need a web server
and it turns out that codespaces comes
with one of these pre-installed because
we cs50 staff uh did so for you and what
you can do in a terminal window once you
have an HTML file ready to go that you
want the world to see you can literally
run in your terminal window
http-server single command and what
that's going to do for you is start a
web server that is to say a program
whose purpose in life is just to serve
web pages and even though probably up
until now for years you probably if
you're like me equate server quote
unquote with a physical device server is
really aie piece of software it just
tends to run on big fancy devices so
when we say server we often all think of
in our Mind's Eye you know big expensive
devices perhaps but a server is just a
program whose purpose in life is to
respond to requests with responses and
that's the vernacular there now once you
run HTTP server and I'm going to do a
bit of magic because I set this up
before class just to make sure it goes
smoothly you'll see some output like
this whereby your server is now
available on a very long URL mine here
uh uh is a very long URL that will be
different from yours but what this is is
a unique identifier that your codes
space has temporarily generated so that
you can now access and ideally only you
can access that file using your browser
now if I flip the URL or you flip the
your all to public by right clicking or
control clicking the right features of
vs code you can enable anyone in the
world to visit it but we're not going to
ultimately host our websites in your
code space because as soon as you log
off for the night and the thing shuts
down like the website will go down but
at the end end of the semester
particularly for final projects we'll
show you ways that you can put your own
website your own code on the actual
internet
247365 even with your own domain name if
you want to get one so that it lives uh
independent of your own sleep schedule
and usage schedule of vs code here so
I'm going to go ahead now and visit um
this URL in another tab of my browser
and what I'll see here is this this is
the output of that program called HTTP
server and essentially what it is doing
is it's using TCP and IP in conjunction
with HTTP to just run your very own web
server on gith hubs own servers as well
and that's because of different ports
again we won't go too much into the
weeds of the TCP the IP and all of that
stuff but recall that different port
numbers can allow you to distinguish one
service from another now one of the
services is of course your code space
VSS code in the cloud that we've been
using for weeks but if you want to use
the same physical server that GitHub
controls but actually visit your own web
server that I just ran in my terminal
window in another tab that's fine
they're just going to be using different
TCP ports and you and I don't have to
care what they are but just that this is
a feature that TCP supports so what you
see here is somewhat Arcane this is not
like a thing that most people on the
internet should ever see I'm just doing
this for development purposes but this
is the index that is the directory the
the folder contents of my code space and
because I deleted everything from prior
weeks already all we see right now is
hello.html
which I just created so if I click on
hello.html within this folder listing
you'll be a little underwhelmed and I'll
zoom in just so there's something more
interesting there but now you see hello
comma body but what's interesting
perhaps is that after this long very