is the fourth bite and even though the
string itself is hi I think we can
corroborate this whole null thing make
high SL High enter and there it is you
could have done this last week if you
really wanted to geek out on strings but
like for now it's just revealing what's
going on underneath the hood questions
then on what these strings are
yeah why do we need the
bracket uh uh why do you not need
brackets good question why do I not need
brackets on line six uh to because uh s
is a string we'll see in a couple of
weeks that s is essentially implemented
underneath the hood indeed as an array
but that happens automatically for you
you can treat S as just a variable name
without square brackets you will use
square brackets when you have arrays of
ins or you manually create arrays of
chars or doubles or Floats or anything
else but strings are special why I mean
every program you write seems to use
strings text in some form we're humans
we like text not just numbers and and
such so this is just treated a little
specially in C and many other languages
as
well other questions on this here no
let's add then one other string to the
mix so instead of just saying hi why
don't we consider version of the program
that says both high and by and I claim
now that that back sl0 that null
character is going to be ever more
important now if we've got two strings
in memory so that c knows how to
distinguish one from the other so let me
go ahead and just get rid of these two
lines for the moment let me recreate
string s equals quote unquote double
quotes High Let me give myself another
one and because I'm just playing around
I'll choose very short variable names
string T equals quote unquote by
exclamation point and then let me just
print them both out uh let me go ahead
and print out percent s back sln comma s
and then print F percent s uh back sln
and then T so very simple demonstration
of just these two variables make high do
SL high and of course it prints out two
lines one after the other what's
actually going on underneath the hood
well let's go back to the computer's
memory High I think it's going to be I
claim pretty much the same so s I'll
claim is in the top left followed by the
back sl0 and that's important now
because by probably is going to end up
there and Visually it wraps just by
nature of how I've drawn this grid of
bytes but it's continuous B ye
exclamation point null AKA back0 this is
Now helpful to print F because now
printf knows where one begins and ends
by way of that special null character
but we can poke around now too what else
can I do here how about this how about I
go into my code here back to BS code and
let me go ahead and say something like
well if I've got two of these uh strings
you know let's put them in an array
let's kind of do this sort of arrays in
arrays sort of inception style here so
string words bracket two so give me an
array of two strings is what I'm saying
here in code even though we've not done
it with strings yet we only did it with
ins and now let me do this the first
word AKA words bracket zero will equal
as before high and now words bracket one
will equal quote unquote by bite so by
and now I've done the exact same thing
but again I'm just avoiding having s t
QR and like all these different
variables in my code I just now I'm
treating them as one single array of
strings how do I change my code down
here well if I want to print the first
word I do words bracket zero and if I
want to print the second word I do words
bracket one this is not a useful
exercise at the moment because I'm just
making my code more complicated but
again it allows us to post poke around
and see what's going on because there is
that high and by but watch this if I
really want to be cool I can do this
let's print out percent C percent C
percent C back sln and then here percent
C percent C percent C percent C so four
of those and now here's where things get
interesting words is an array of strings
but again if I may what's a
string an array of characters so just
use the same logic if words is an array
of strings you get at the first string
with words bracket zero how do you get
at the first character in the first
string bracket Zer words bracket Z
bracket one and lastly words bracket Z
bracket two and now down here words
bracket one but the first character is
there words bracket one the second
character is here words bracket one the
third character is here whoops third
character is here and words bracket one
one the fourth character is here like
this is not how people program this is
only for demonstration sake my God it's
so tedious and verbose already but if I
make high now do SL high now I'm like
manually Reinventing percent s if I
forgot it existed using percent C alone
but you can indeed manipulate arrays in
this way but because strings are arrays
of characters you can manipulate strings
uh in this way too any question now on
this syntax
any questions here no no all right well
let's go ahead and propose that we solve
a couple of other problems we might not
have as before but first a quick visual
of what's been going on underneath the
hood here if here again is where we left
off on the screen high and by uh back to
back here is really how I just treated
these things s bracket 0123 and then t0
1 2 3 4 but really once I put them in an
array the picture becomes this words Z
is the whole High words bracket one is
the whole by but if I really get into
the weeds and start indexing into
individual characters in those strings
all I'm using is new syntax in order to
represent these same values here
questions then on these
representations before we Forge
ahead no
yeah does the new line character say
that one
more ah really good question does the
new line character take up any space uh
it does when so far as printf is
concerned but I'm not storing the back
slash n in my strings printf is being
manually handed that thing
instead all right so let's go ahead then
and consider how we might solve some
problems that have Arisen now with these
strings as follows here suppose I let's
do this let me go back to VSS code here
and let me go ahead and open up a new
file called how about uh length uh. C
and let's consider for a moment how I
might actually figure out what the
length of a string is which is distinct
from the length of an array I claimed
earlier you cannot figure out
dynamically what the length of an array
is but I can figure out the length of a
string specifically because of this
implementation detail of that null
character so let me go ahead and do this
let me include cs50.h in this second
program here let me include standard i.h
as before and let me do this int main
void and in the first thing I'll do is
just get a string from the user I'll ask
the user as always for their name so
I'll call get string and say what's your
name question mark as always and then
down here if I want to figure out the
length of this string and print the name
the print the length out on the screen
well I can kind of do this similar in
spirit to the average where I'm
accumulating something let me go ahead
and initialize n to zero let me give
myself huh it's not not a for Loop
because I don't have a I don't know in
advance how long it is but what if I do
this
while the value at name bracket n does
not equal single quote back
sl0 crazy syntax at the moment but it's
just the culmination of these various
building blocks let me just finish the
thought here
n++ and then down here let's just print
out with print F and percent I that
value of n
so I claim this is going to show me the
length of any string I type in whether
it's high or by or David or anything
else I initialize a variable to zero and
that's good because that's where you
start counting in general while name
bracket 0 does not equal back0 what is
this saying well if name is the string
the user typed in and name is just an
array as you noted then name bracket
zero is going to be the first character
and I'm asking the question well does
the first character not equal back0 and
if I type in David D is it's not so I
keep going and I add one to n then I'm
going to check name bracket one well if
I typed in David name bracket one is
going to be a a does not equal back0 and
so it's going to go again and again and
again but five steps in total later it's
going to get to the bite after David
realize wait a minute that is a back
slash n the Loop finishes and I print
out the total length arrays in general
do not have this null character however
strings do again strings are special
versus all of the other data types we've
talked about thus far but how could I
for instance uh do this differently well
let's actually Factor this out as a
function as I've I've commonly done but
rather than implement it myself you know
what it turns out what's nice about
strings being so common there are many
other people who have solved these
problems before and in fact there's a
whole string library in C it is used by
way of a header file called string.h and
what string H is is a library of string
related functions in fact you can see in
cs50's manual pages for C uh the
string.h functions at least those that
we recommend as most useful and in
particular if you poke around there
you'll see that there's a function
called Sterling means string length it
was named very succinctly just because
it's a little easier to type than string
length but Sterling tells you the length
of a string so how might I use this in
my code here well it turns out I can
simplify this quite a bit let me get rid
of my Loop get rid of my uh my counting
manually and do something like this int
n equals Sterling of the human's name
name and now I'll just use print f as
before with percent I back sln and
output the value of n but but there's a
bug at the moment what have I forgotten
to
do yeah I have to include the header
file at the top of the screen so let me
at the top of the code so let me also
include string.h at the top of my file
so that c knows that in fact sterl
exists let me go ahead and make length
as
before length uh or actually really for
the first time what's your name David
and hopefully I'm going to see in fact
five by contrast if I run it again and
type in high exclamation point now I see
three so Sterling is just one of the
functions in that library and there's so
many more in fact yet another library
that might be useful moving forward is
this one C
which relates to C data types and lots
of functions therein that can be useful
for instance if you review its
documentation in the manual pages online
you'll see that there are functions via
which we can solve problems like this
let me go ahead and propose here let me
see let's do um example here
involving how about uh checking if
something is uppercase or lowercase and
converting it uh to uppercase only let
me go back to vs code and code a program
called uppercase Doc in this file I'm
going to start by including now as
always
cs50.h I'm going to include standard i.h
and I'm going to add one other to the
mix which is
string.h now2 so I can access the length
of things as needed int main void comes
next and then within my main function
I'm going to go ahead and declare a
string called s I'm going to call get
string as before and I'm going to go
head and just ask the user for a string
called before I want to do it before and
after whatever the user types in is
before but I want to force everything to
uppercase thereafter let me now in this
Loop here do this let me print F quote
unquote after just so we can see this on
the screen and let me do four in I gets
zero I is less than stir Lang of s I ++
what am I about to do I'm about to
iterate over every every character in
the string from left to right from zero
on up two but not through the length of
s and how do I check if something is
lowercase so that I can actually force
it to uppercase well it turns out I
could do this literally if the character
in s at location I is greater than or
equal to Capital a Ampersand Ampersand
which means and instead of or which we
saw in the past s braet i is less than
or equal to little Z that means
logically in English that this is indeed
a lowercase how do I now convert it to
uppercase this character well I could
just literally print out the same
character but that would not be the
answer here because that's not changing
the value but what could I do instead
well let me actually pull up here real
fast the asky chart as before and let's
see if we can't glean some insight if I
pull up the same ask each chart and
suppose the human has typed in a
lowercase a that's
97 what letter I want to convert it to
uppercase a so what number do I want to
convert the 97 to per week zero so 65 we
keep coming back to that one what if the
user types in lowercase B I want to
change the 98 value to 66 and so forth
and any quick math how far part of those
so it's always 32 like uppercase to
lower case is always wonderfully good
design 32 away one from the other so
what does this mean well I think we saw
earlier that underneath the hood a Char
is just a number you can certainly do
arithmetic on it and here again if you
understand these lower level Primitives
what if I do this whatever s bracket I
is if I know on line 13 that it's up
that it's lowercase do I want to add or
subtract
32 so I want to subtract because I want
to go from like 97 to 65 or 98 to 66 so
indeed if you do some quick math that
gives you 32 so it suffices to just
treat chars as numbers subtract the 32
and printing it with percent C I think
will just convert lowercase to uppercase
if you now fast forward to like the real
world Microsoft Word or Google Docs if
you've ever chosen the menu option that
forces things to uppercase or lowercase
on occasion literally that's what
Microsoft and Google have done they
iterate over every character in the
document check if it's lowercase and if
so they subtract 32 from it and show you
the new value what if though it is not a
lowercase letter I think I can keep it
easy and just print out the current
letter unchanged if my goal is to Simply
Force things to all uppercase and that
letter then would be S bracket I so let
me go ahead now and make uppercase
hopefully no errors do/ uppercase and
I'll now now type in David with an
uppercase D but lowercase everything
else but now the after version is David
an aesthetic bug notice here I forgot to
include just for prettiness sake about
back sln at the end no problem I'll add
that let me fix my mistake make
uppercase SL uppercase enter daid enter
and voila and I I deliberately added
another space after the after just so
they would line up pretty even though
before and after have different numbers
of letters questions then on this
implementation of forcing something to
uppercase which in and of itself is not
all that enlightening but is
representative now of how you can
leverage these low-level
Primitives question
now all right well this honestly is
tedious my God like does Microsoft
Google everyone you have to literally
write out this code just to do something
simple well no that's again why we have
things like libraries and increasingly
now for problem sets projects and Beyond
well you just use libraries more often
off the shelf so as to solve problems
that surely other people have had before
you so how can I now use this uh Library
ctype.h well let me go back into my code
let me include this among my header
files here I tend just so I can skim
things easily I tend to alphabetize my
headers but that's not strictly
necessary but it allows me at a glance
to realize did I or did I not include
something I need now let me go ahead and
do this it turns out if you read the
documentation for the ctype library
there is a function wonderfully called
if is lower that takes in a character as
its argument essentially so s bracket I
and if that returns true a Boolean value
if you will well I'm going to force it
to lowercase but I don't have to do this
this math anymore turns out in the ctype
library there's also a function called
two upper that takes a character as
input like s bracket I and it just does
the math for you so that you can
abstract away the 32 thing and just know
that someone else has solved that
problem for you otherwise I can leave my
code unchanged down below because I'm
not changing anything else so if I do
make uppercase now and then do SL
uppercase daavid with just a capital D
and now it still works but if you read
the documentation further it turns out
that two upper is smart if you pass in a
character to two upper that's lowercase
it obviously converts its uppercase by
doing that math but if you pass in a
character to to Upper that's already
uppercase the documentation you would
see tells you that it leaves it
unchanged so I can tighten all of this
up I can get rid of the whole else I can
get rid of the whole if and arguably now
Implement a program that's just as
correct but better designed why fewer
lines of code easier to read Le lower
probability of mistakes assuming the
library is correct it just makes it
easier and faster for me now to write
code so if I now do one last time make
uppercase enter uppercase and type in my
name still working but now notice we've
whittel this down to far fewer lines of
code albeit using now this additional
Library questions then on how we did
this no well even even though this code
I dare say is correct it's not
necessarily welld designed just yet in
fact there's one line of code one
function call in this current
implementation that's more inefficient
than it needs to be and allow me to draw
our attention to this here line 10
wherein we're calling Sterling but we're
calling it inside of this for Loop
specifically inside of the condition and
why might that not necessarily be the
best
idea well is the length of the string s
changing ever I mean certainly not
within the span of this Loop and so here
we are within our for loop on line 10 11
12 and 13 asking on every iteration that
same question what's the length of s
what's the length of s what's the length
of s and in turn we're calling Sterling
every time even though we're getting
back the same answer so I dare say a
better solution here would be to maybe
figure out the length of s earlier on in
my code and maybe declare a variable or
perhaps do something that's
syntactically a little more elegant and
in fact a very common design in Loop
like this would be to declare not just
one variable like I but to actually
declare a second variable called n for
instance where n is just some number Set
n equal to the length of s but
thereafter inside of this condition
instead of calling Sterling of s again
and again and again what might I now do
I could instead just compare I against n
itself because n now will only be
calculated once when it's initialized
just as I is initialized to zero and
thereafter we're going to be compar
comparing I which is changing against n
which will not be so it's going to be
marginally more efficient by Design now
with that said a good compiler could
also recognize that there was this
optimization possibility and maybe do it
for us but for now best to get into the
Habit best to develop the muscle memory
for making those better design decisions
yourselves questions then on how we did
this no all right a few final building
blocks for the day so we started by
talking about those command line
arguments that clang uses whereby
anything after the command that you type
at a prompt be it make or clang or even
CD in Linux any word thereafter or
something cryptic like- O is a
commandline argument it's an input to
the command it's different from a
function argument because a function
argument of course is an input to a
function but it's the same idea it's
just different syntax after the dollar
sign at the prompt well it turns out
that command line arguments are
something you can now use in your own
programs by
accessing uh words after the prompt and
let me propose that we invent we invent
this as follows let me propose that we
switch back to vs code here and I'll
open a new file here called greet doc so
in greet Doc is going to be a program
that very simply greets the user had we
written this last week we would have
done this include
cs50.h and then include uh standard
i.h and then int main void and then we
might do something simple like string
name equals get string quote unquote
what's your name question mark and then
we would have printed out as always
hello comma percent s and then plugging
in that name so this is the same program
we've implemented many times just to
make sure it works although nope that's
not quite the same program semicolon in
the wrong place this now is the same
program so make greet /g greet and I'll
type in my own name hello David so we're
back there now what's arguably a little
Annoying about this program if I type in
something else like Carter enter you
know I have to run the program wait for
the prompt type in my name hit enter and
that's fine but imagine if every program
worked like this like make suppose you
could only type make then you wait for a
prompt then you type the name of the
program you want to make then you hit
enter or worse in Linux when you have to
change directories as you might have for
problem set one what if you had to type
CD enter now type the name of the folder
you want to change into enter I mean it
just slows life down and so it just gets
annoying quickly so commandline
arguments just let you express your
whole thought all at once so how can I
do this well if I want to express the
notion of command line arguments in my
code I could do something like this I
could for the very first time go up and
get rid of this void which as of today
means this program takes no command line
arguments and I can change it to exactly
this int ARG C string argv with brackets
now it's cryptic admittedly and let me
zoom in but I think we can perhaps infer
now what's going on if main Now does not
have void as its input which means it
takes no arguments surely the spoiler
here is that now main will take command
line argument somehow any guesses as to
what argv is or will be
what might this
represent it's an array of strings right
by way of the syntax
yeah exactly it will be all of the
characters or really all of the words
that you type at the prompt argc as an
INT any
guess
argument count is what it generally
stands for though technically you could
call these things any anything but this
is the convention because I claimed
earlier that arrays don't keep track of
their own length if you want to know how
many words the human typed at the prompt
after your program's name you have to be
told not just the array of the words but
the length of that array the strings you
can figure out the length of using
Sterling but you can't figure out the
length of the array of strings the
collection of words that the human typed
in so how can I now use this well let me
go ahead and do this let me go ahead and
change this program now just to be print
F quote unquote
hello comma uh percent s back sln then
Arvy bracket 1 so this is not the best
version of my code yet but it's my first
make greet and now let me dog greet
David all at once enter hello David now
let me run it again dogre Carter enter
hello Carter you know it's a marginal
Improvement but I don't have to wait for
get string to prompt me to hit enter
it's just speeding things up you know is
fast one less command to type in but I
deliberately did bracket one but where
what's the beginning of arv it would be
bracket zero well what's that this is
sometimes useful though for now it's not
suppose I recompile my code and run this
program now greet David anyone want to
guess what's in argv
Z say
again greet enter hello. SLG greet so if
you want sort of inception style your
program to figure out what its own name
is or at least how it was executed at
the command line at the terminal you can
look at ARG v0 in general probably not
that useful probably better to start
looking at bracket one which was the
first word after the program name and if
there were more I could do this how
about RV bracket 2 let me add in a
second percent s let me recompile greet
let me do greet David maen enter and
that two now works taking in two words
at the prompt if I really want to be
smart at this now I could do something
like this though how about if the count
of arguments AKA AR C equals equals 2
then assume that the human typed in only
their first name and do print F uh hello
comma percent s back sln and then uh
argv bracket 1 else if the human did not
provide exactly two arguments the name
of the program and their own name let's
just print out a default value L they
forgot their name or they typed in two
names or three names let's just do uh
hello comma world as a default and we'll
just ignore what the human typed in if I
recompile this make greet I can dog
greet and David again enter oops uh
sorry what am I missing yeah so newbie
mistake else all right make greet again
dog greet David enter there's my hello
David
but if I omit my name I just get the
generic like a default value and if I
get a little curious and I type in both
names then I get ignored two why because
I just haven't built in support for arxy
of three I could do anything I want but
now we have access to these kinds of
building blocks all right what else
might I do here well it turns out there
might be some final features for us to
now execute um notice though that in C
despite what you might see in books or
online tutorials nowadays the two
official formats for defining a main
function are either this which we've
been using now for Two Plus weeks or now
this whereby you change the void to int
argc and then for now string argv and
then empty brackets and we'll see that
this two is an a simplification some
training wheels if you will but for now
those are the two forms even though you
will see in online tutorials and even
books some people use Maine in different
ways these are the two now to keep in
mind and I'll note that these command
line arguments are kind of all over the
place didn't probably expect to see this
word on the screen here and what does it
mean well it turns out that for decades
there's actually this program that comes
with Linux systems in particular called
coway why probably because someone had
too much free time once and decided to
write a program that creates asy art out
of a cow saying something textually on
the screen but you use coway Just For
Fun by way of command line arguments so
for instance let me propose that uh I go
back to vs code here not because I want
to write any code but I just want to use
my terminal window and let me uh
maximize my terminal window here and let
me go ahead and type in something like
how about c space moo so cow is not a
program I wrote It's been around for
decades but we installed it in vs code
for you in the cloud it takes at least
one command line argument what do you
want the cow to say I can say cow say
moo and hit enter and voila there's my
asky art of a cow saying moo on the
screen it can say multiple words so I
can say hello world and enter and now it
says hello world so this is just an
example of a silly program that uses
command line arguments but it takes
others too just like clang use this
convention of hyphens to change the
output of the program Dash something is
just a super common convention with
commandline arguments when you want a
very tur notation for some option like
output um in C I read the documentation
and it turns out there's a-f command
line argument that allows you to change
the uh the appearance of the cow if you
will so if I do coway dasf duck and then
some other word like quack it's no
longer a cow that command line argument
turns it into a tiny adorable duck
instead and then lastly just for fun
because I spent way too much time
playing with command line arguments uh
c-f dragon and then how about like raar
enter you can even get this on the
screen here so this too is just an
example of what you can do with these
command line arguments now that we have
this building block and there's one
final thing we can now do with code
there's one last feature today that
we'll introduce before we now connect
all of these dots to readability and and
encryption by talking lastly about
something called exit status it turns
out that whenever your main function
exits it returns a secret integer that
you can figure out as the programmer or
an advanced user what it was and these
exit codes exit statuses are typically
used to indicate errors so for instance
over over the past couple of years if
you us zoom and you ever got some kind
of error you might have seen a screen
like this it's usually not that helpful
maybe tells you to click report problem
or contact support but very often in our
human world on Macs PCS and phones you
see cryptic error codes like literally
numbers that probably only Zoom knows or
Microsoft or Google or whatever company
wrote the software you're using but that
number corresponds to a specific error
that some human somewhere knows might
very well happen these are used similar
L although under a different name that
we'll talk about later in the term uh on
the web as well have you ever seen this
maybe not character but number so 404
means
what so error yes but really not found
so why I mean this is the most Arcane
thing and we'll talk in a few weeks
about like what this and other numbers
mean but numbers are all around us in
technology and they very often mean
something to the technical people who
wrote the software less so to humans
like you and me why so many of us
recognize 404 is kind of weird that like
that's been around long enough that we
all know it but it really is just a
special number that represents an error
of some sort so it turns out the last
thing we'll reveal today about what
we've been taking for granted for two
weeks is what the int is in Maine we've
seen just a moment ago that the thing in
the parentheses which up until now has
been void which means no command line
arguments now in Arc string arv brackets
just means yes command line arguments
and we've seen how to access them so the
last piece of the puzzle honestly of all
the cryptic syntax the past two weeks is
just what int means int is always there
for Maine and it indicates that Maine
will always return an integer even
though you and I have never done so
explicitly usually Maine returns Zero by
default but it would be weird if you saw
an error message saying zero so zero is
just hidden you would never see it on
the screen but it's happening
automatically by way of how C is
designed so let me write one final
program here I'll call it for instance
status . C to show you these exit
statuses code of status. c and then up
here let me do something simple like
include
cs50.h then include standard i.h and
then int main uh let's do actually let's
use a command line argument in argc
string argv so that's copy paste but now
let's do this if argc does not equal to
why don't we do something like this
let's not just um default to hello world
like last time let's yell at the user so
let's say something like printf missing
command line argument so that they know
they screwed up and they need to run the
program again correctly else let's go
ahead and say print out uh as before
hello comma percent s and then plug in
argv bracket one so the human's name
from The Prompt now at this point let me
go ahead and run
statusstatus and I'll will type nothing
first first I get yelled at this time
I'll type it again/ status David and it
works properly but now let me show you a
somewhat secret cryptic command you can
type this at your prompt and it's just a
coincidence that there's another dollar
sign Echo dollar sign question mark
totally Arcane but it allows you to see
what exit status your program has ended
with so let me run this again the wrong
way/ status okay I get the error message
what was secretly returned I can't can't
see it there's obviously no error screen
but by typing Echo dollar sign question
mark I can see that oh my program
automatically by default return zero
however if I run it again correctly
status David enter this is the correct
version but if I run Echo question mark
status again it's still entered with
zero and long story short this is just a
missed opportunity when something goes
wrong why don't I return a value other
than zero zero by default means success
and it's always there automatically but
but you can control this I can go into
my code here and return one else if
something works fine I can return zero
by default and honestly if I omit the
return zero again zero automatically is
returned so let me go ahead and though
be explicit just so I know what's going
on make status
again/ status and let's do this
correctly with David enter hello David
Echo question mark uh Echo dollar sign
question mark zero so all is well
but now if I do/ status and nothing or
multiple things but not just David enter
I get the error message but now if I do
Echo dollar sign question mark waa there
now is the one so what does this now
mean this is in the graphical world we
would just show something like this on
the screen which is a little more
informative to the user but even in the
Linux world we don't have a guey
necessarily even for the programs we've
written you can check these exit
statuses and in fact more comfortable
more advanced programmers when they
write code that calls programs be it
coway or anything else you can encode
check what the exit status is of a
program and then decide did my program
work or did it not and now let's connect
the final dots uh before we adjourn for
some fruit snacks uh cryptography namely
one of the applications this week via
which you'll be able to send if you will
secret messages and better yet decre
secret messages this will be in addition
to perhaps analyzing the readability of
text using puristic like we identified
at the start of class 2 so a
cryptography is just the art the science
of encrypting information scrambling
information so that if you have a secret
message to send in so-called plain text
you can run it through some algorithm
and turn it into what's called Cipher
text thereby encrypting it and only
someone who knows what algorithm you've
used and what input you've used to the
algorithm theoretically can decrypt that
process and convert it back to the
original message so if we use our mental
model from last week here is a problem
here is an input and output the goal I
claim here is to take some plain text
like the message you want to send think
back to grade school if you ever passed
a note to a friend or to your crush
saying I love you it's a little awkward
if the teacher or someone else
intercepts the paper and in English it
just says I love you or whatever it is
it'd be nice if you had at least
encrypted it in some way but the other
person needs to know what algorithm you
used and what inputs you used to that
algorithm so that ultimately they can
decode the so-called Cipher text which
is the output so what go inside of the
box today well an algorithm as it
relates to cryptography is called a
cipher and a cipher is a fancy name for
an algorithm that encrypts text from
plain text to Cipher text the catch is
there needs to be not just the algorithm
there needs to be an input to it and so
for instance you might draw the picture
like this for the first time today and
we've seen this in code you can give
multiple inputs or arguments to
functions so in this black box can you
imagine passing in the message you want
to send and then some Secret so for
instance suppose that the simplest thing
I could think of as a kid was instead of
sending the letter A why don't I write
the letter b instead of the letter B why
don't I write the letter c so I can kind
of shift the English alphabet by one
space so a becomes b b becomes C dot dot
dot Z becomes a you can wrap around at
the end and let's assume no punctuation
in this part of the story so that's a
very simple algorithm add a value to
each letter and send the value as the
cipher text and now the teacher the
classmate they have to know that you use
not only this rotational algorithm also
known as a Caesar Cipher they also need
to know what number you use did you add
one to every letter two to every letter
25 to every letter now if they're super
smart and probably not the the young age
in this story they could also just try
all possibilities and that would be an
attack on the algorithm this is not a
sophisticated algorithm but it's enough
to send a message in class so if the two
inputs now are high as the plain text
message and one as the so-called key the
secret number that only you and the
other person know you might uh be able
to encrypt a message from one way to the
other and so in this case for instance
high would become i j exclamation point
in this version of the algorithm we're
not going to bother with numbers or
punctuation will only operate on a
through z be it uppercase or lowercase
so now if you were to receive a a slip
of paper in class with i j on it you
know you the recipient would know what
it is so long as you know that the
sender used one because you just reverse
the algorithm and you subtract one
instead the teacher you know they
probably don't know what this means and
they're not going to spend time hacking
the message so it just looks scrambled
to them and that's what we get from
encryption someone who intercepts it be
it in class or in the real world on the
Internet or anywhere else can't actually
figure out ideally what it is you have
sent the opposite of course is indeed
called decryption but the process is the
same we now pass in negative one and so
how about this why don't we end with a
demonstration here
u y JT xbt
dt50 there's a bit of a tell there if we
pass that in and do Nega -1 well how do
we get out the plain text originally
well if this is the cipher text and we
subtract one from each letter I think U
becomes t i becomes h j becomes i t
becomes s x becomes w b becomes a t
becomes s d becomes c t becomes s and
this was indeed cs50 have a duck on your
way out and some snacks in the
[Applause]
[Music]
lobby
oh
[Music]
all right all right this is cs50 and
this is week three already wherein we'll
take a look back actually at week zero
where we first began and in week zero
recall that everything was very
intuitive in a sense we talked not just
about representation of information but
algorithms and we talked about tearing a
phone book again and again and that
somehow got us to a better solution but
today we'll try to start formalizing
some of those ideas and capturing some
of those same ideas not in pseudo code
just yet but in uh actual code as well
but we'll also consider the the
efficiency of those algorithms like just
how good how welld designed our
algorithms actually are and if you
recall when we did the phone book
example where in I first had an
algorithm searching one page at a time
and then second when two pages at a time
and then third started tearing the thing
in half recall that we with a wave of
the hand kind of analyzed it as follows
we proposed that if the x-axis here is
the size of the problem like number of
pages in a phone book and the y- axis is
the time required to solve the problem
in seconds minutes page tears whatever
your unit of measuring is recall that
the first algorithm was this straight
line such that if you had n pages in the
phone book it might have this slope of N
and there's this one toone relationship
between pages and tears two pages at a
time of course was twice as fast but
still really the same shape the yellow
line here indicating that yeah it's n /
two maybe plus one if you have to double
back as we discussed but it's really
still fundamentally the same algorithm
one or two pages at a time but the third
algorithm recall was this one here in
green where we called it logarithmic in
terms of how fast or how slow it was and
indeed the implication of this algorithm
was that we could even double the size
of the phone book and no big deal one
additional page tear and we take yet
another thousand page bite out of the
phone book so today we'll revisit some
of these ideas formalize them a bit but
also translate some of them ultimately
to code and all of that now is possible
because we have this lower level
understanding perhaps of like what's
actually inside of your computer this of
course is your computer's Ram or memory
and recall that if we kind of start to
abstract this away your compter
computer's memory is really just a grid
of bites in fact we don't have to look
at the hardware anymore and we looked at
a grid of bites like this whereby each
of these bites could be used to store a
Char an INT a long or even an entire
string at that but let's focus perhaps
just on a subset of this because last
week of course we emphasized really
arrays storing things in arrays and that
allowed us to start storing entire
strings sequences of characters and even
arrays of integers if we want to have
multiple ones and not just multiple
variables as well but the catch is that
if you look inside of an array in the
computer's memory and for instance
suppose these integers here are stored
it's pretty easy for us humans to glance
at this and immediately find the number
50 you sort of have this bird's eye view
from where you're seated of everything
on the screen and so it's pretty obvious
how you get to the number 50 but in the
world of computers of course it turns
out that this is hardware and computers
for today's purposes can only do one
thing at a time they can't just take it
all in and find instantly some number
like 50 so perhaps a decent metaphor is
to consider the array of memory inside
of your computer really is a sequence of
of closed doors and if the computer
wants to find some value in an array it
has to do the digital equivalent of
opening each of these doors one at a
time now how can code do that well of
course we introduced indices or indexes
last week whereby we by convention call
the first element of an array location
zero the second location one the Third
location two and so forth so-called zero
indexed and this allowed us to now
bridge this conceptual world of like
what's going on in memory with actual
code because now we had this square
bracket syntax via which we could go
searching for something if we so choose
and it turns out if I now uh paint these
red instead of yellow it would seem that
we actually have a pretty good physical
metaphor here standing in place for what
would be a computer's uh array of memory
if for instance you're storing some
seven numbers like that and so today we
begin with a look of a specific type typ
of algorithm that is for searching like
searching is all over the place all of
us have probably gone to google.com or
some equivalent like already multiple
times per day and getting back answers
fast is what companies like Google are
really good at so how are they doing
that how are they storing information in
computers uh memory well let's consider
what this really is it's really just a
problem as it was back in week zero the
input though to the problem for now
might be this array of seven lockers so
that's the input to the problem inside
of which is a number and maybe for
Simplicity now we just want a yes no a
true false answer a bull that is to say
of whether or not some number like 50 is
in that array it's not quite as fancy as
Google that doesn't just tell you yes we
have search results it actually gives
you the search results but for now we'll
keep it simple and just output as part
of this problem yes or no true or false
we have found the number we're looking
for given an input like that array but
it turns out inside of this black box
that we keep coming back to there's all
sorts of possible algorithms and we talk
about this at a high level conceptually
in week zero with the phone book but
today let's consider it a little more
concretely uh by way of a game that some
of you might have grown up with namely
Monopoly and so behind these doors it
turns out we'll be hidden some
denominations of Monopoly money but for
this we now have two volunteers if you'd
like to greet the world hi I'm
Jackson yay hi my name is Stephanie
Steph and you want to say a little
something about yourselves years house
first year living in Matthews
nice and I'm a first year in Canada nice
well Welcome to our two
volunteers so why don't we do this would
one of you like to volunteer the other
to go
first all go first okay all right so
Stephanie's up first and behind one of
these doors here we've hidden the
Monopoly money 50 and so we'd like you
to find the 50 we'll tell you nothing
more about the lockers but we would like
you to execute a certain algorithm and
in fact I'm going to give you some
pseudo code for this and I'm going to
give you the name for it it's called
linear search and as the name implies
you're pretty much going to end up
walking in sort of a straight line but
how are you going to do this well let me
propose that in a moment your first step
will be to think kind of like a loop for
each door from left to right what do we
want you to do on each iteration well if
50 is behind that door then we want to
go ahead and have you return true and
sort of hold up the 50 proudly if you
will for the group otherwise if you get
through that whole Loop and you haven't
found the number 50 you can just throw
up your hands and disappointment false
you've not found the number 50 so to be
clear step one is going to be for each
uh door from left to right how would you
like to
begin yep oh and then yep there we go
yep oh and if you'd like to at least
tell oh good good acting here what have
you found instead it's not 50 but 20 oh
okay so step one was a fail so let's
move on to step two inside of the Loop
what are you going to do next I'm going
to move to the next door
okay almost okay almost sort of a 500
instead next Locker I would rather
take
no okay we're not telling the
audience oh okay so keep going this is
step three
now
oh
[Music]
man five okay few more lockers to
check a little sad
guys all right second to last
step this one kind of close all right
and finally the last clearly you've been
perhaps set up here let's go all right
so the number
50 and Stephanie if I may let me ask you
a question here so on the screen this is
the pseudo code you just executed
suppose though I had done what many of
us have gotten into the habit of doing
when you have a if condition you often
have an else Branch as well suppose that
I had done this now and I'm marking it
in red to be clear this is wrong but
what would have have been bad about this
code using an if and an else might you
say any
instincts
um then you would end up like cancelling
canceling the code before you found the
50 yeah exactly just be eternally sad
indeed when Stephanie had opened the
first Locker she had found 20 20 of
course is not 50 she would have decreed
false but of course she hadn't checked
all of the rest of the locker so that
would seem to be a key detail that would
this implementation of the SoDo coat we
actually do go through as we did and
only return false not even with an else
but just at the end of the loop such
that we only reach that line if we don't
return truer uh earlier than that well
let's go ahead and do this let me take
the mic from you if you'd like to take a
seat next to Jackson Jackson in just a
moment we'll have you come up Carter if
you don't mind reorganizing the uh
lockers for us but in the meantime let
me point out how we might now translate
that same idea to code pretty high level
pretty English oriented with that pseudo
code but really now as of last week we
have syntax via which Stephanie and soon
Jackson could treat this Locker the set
of lockers as really indeed an array
using bracket notation so we can now get
a little closer in our pseudo code to
actual code and the way a computer
scientist for instance would translate
fairly high level English pseudo code
like this to something that's a little
closer to C or any language that
supports arrays would be a little more
cryptically like this but you'll see
more of this syntax in the coming days
for I from 0 to n minus one this is
still pseudo code but that's kind of
like the english-like way of expressing
what we've known come to know as a for
Loop if 50 is behind doors bracket I so
I'm assuming for the sake of discussion
that doors now is the name of my
variable this array of seven doors but
then the rest of the logic the rest of
the pseudo code really is the same way
and so you'll find in time that
programmers computer scientists more
generally when you start expressing
ideas algorithms to someone else instead
of maybe operating at this level here
you now have in your vocabulary really a
new new syntax that you can be a little
more specific not getting so into the
weeds of writing actual C code but at
least now doing something that's a
little closer to manipulating an array
like this so Jackson would you like to
uh stand on up all right yes yes support
for Jackson here too
nice and here now I'm going to allow you
an assumption that Stephanie did not
have Stephanie clearly was really doing
her best searching from left to right
using linear searches we'll Now call it
but they were pretty much in random
order right there was a 20 over there
there was a one over there and then a 50
so we deliberately jumbled things up and
did not sort the numbers for her but
Carter kindly has just come up to give
you a leg up Jackson by sorting the
numbers in advance and we'd like you
this time much like in week zero to do
something again and again but this time
using what we'll Now call binary search
it's exactly the same algorithm
conceptually as we did in week zero but
if we translate to the context of this
array we might now might say something
like this the first step for Jackson
might be to ask ask the question if 50
is behind the middle door where
presumably he's done some mental math to
figure out what the middle is then he's
going to just return true and hopefully
we'll get lucky and 50 will be right
there of course there's two other
possibilities at least which would be
what 50 is with respect to these
doors yeah so to the left or to the
right alternatively so if 50 is less
than the middle door then presumably
Jackson's going to want to go left else
if 50 is greater than the middle door
he's going to want to go right much like
I did uh physically last week with the
phone book dividing and conquering left
to right but there's actually a a fourth
case let's put it on the board first
what else might happen here that Jackson
should
consider yeah oh it's not there it's not
there so let me actually go back and
amend my my pseudo code here and just
say Jackson if we don't hand you any
doors at all or eventually as he's
dividing and conquering if he's left
with no more doors we have to handle
that situation so that the def behavior
is defined find all right so with that
said Jackson do you want to go ahead and
find us the number 50 and walk us
through verbally what you're doing and
finding all right so it looks like this
one is the middle door so I'm going to
open
it but it's 20 not 50 oh sad okay what's
going through your head now so now I'm
looking because 50 is higher than 20 I
want to look to the right good um and
look for the new middle door which would
be here nice and it's 100 sad um but 50
is less than 100 so now we know to look
left which would be here and Tada nice
very well done this time around
too
so thank you first to our volunteers
here and in fact um since you're fan of
Monopoly as we're so informed we have
the Cambridge edition of Monopoly with
all your Harvard favorites here you go
thank you so thank you to our volunteers
for finding us 50
so kind of was more popular than we
expected so here we can translate this
one more time into something a little
closer to code and again still pseudo
code but here now might be another
formulation of exactly what Jackson just
did just using the nomenclature now of
arrays where you can be a little more
precise with your instructions and still
leave it to someone else to translate
this finally to code but here we have
same question at the beginning if no
doors left return false if 50 is behind
doors bracket middle so I'm assuming
here because this is pseudo code that
somewhere I've done the mental math or
the actual math to figure out what the
index of middle is for instance if these
are seven doors in an array this would
be location zero 1 2 3 4 5 6 so somehow
I've taken the total number of doors
seven divided by two to find the middle
that's three and a half we have to deal
with rounding but suffice it to say
there's a well- defined formula for
finding the middle index given the total
number of lockers divide by two and then
round accordingly so that's presumably
what Jackson did just by counting in his
head to find us door number three not
the third door the fourth door but door
bracket three so this is just saying if
50 is behind door is bracket middle
return true that was not the case he
found a $20 bill instead else if 50 is
less than the uh doors bracket middle go
ahead and now it gets interesting search
doors zero through doors middle minus
one so it's getting a little more to the
Weeds now but if middle is three this
one here well we want to now have
Jackson search if 50 had been uh if the
number had been less we want to start at
bracket zero and go up through this one
when we deliberately subtract one CU
what's the point of looking in the same
Locker again we might as well do zero
through middle minus one else if 50 is
greater than doors bracket middle which
it was what did we then do Jackson
intuitively searched for doors middle
plus one through door
n minus one and honestly it gets a
little Annoying having the pluses and
the minuses here but just think of what
it means this is the middle door and
Jackson then did proceed to search
through doors middle plus one because
there's no point in searching this one
again and then the last element in any
array of size n where n is just our
go-to number uh for the size is always
going to be n minus one it's not going
to be n it's going to be n minus one
because we always start counting at Rays
at zero so here then we have a
translation into pseudo code that's a
little closer to C of this exact same
idea and here we come full circle to
week zero like in week zero is pretty
intuitive to imagine dividing and
conquering a problem like this but if
you now think back to actual your iPhone
your Android phone or the like when
you're doing autocomplete and searching
the list it's possible if you don't have
many friends or family or colleagues in
the phone you know what linear search
just checking every name for the person
you're searching for might be perfectly
fine but odds are your phones being
smarter than that especially if you
start to have dozens hundreds thousands
of people in your contacts over the
years what would be better than linear
search well perhaps binary search but
but but there's an assumption a
requirement which is what why was
Jackson ultimately able to find the 50
in just like three steps instead of a
full seven like
Stephanie because the array was sorted
and so this is sort of a teaser for what
we'll have to come back to later today
well you know how much effort did it
take someone like Carter how much effort
does it take your phone to sort all of
those names and numbers in advance
because maybe it's not actually worth
the amount of time now someone like
Google probably somehow keeps the
database of web pages sorted you could
imagine it being super slow if when you
type in cats or something else into
google.com if they searched linearly
over their entire data set ideally
they're doing something a little smarter
than that so we'll formalize now exactly
this kind of analysis and it's not going
to be so much mathy as it still will be
in intuitive but we'll introduce you to
some some jargon some terminology that
most any programmer or computer
scientist might use when analyzing their
own algorithms let's formalize now what
this kind of analysis is so right right
now I claim binary search better than
linear search but how much better and
why exactly well it all comes back to
this kind of graph so this recall is how
we analyzed the phone book back in week
zero and recall that indeed we had these
these formulas rough formulas that
describe the running time of those three
algorithms one page at a time two pages
at a time and then tearing the thing
again and again in half and precisely if
you count it up the number of pages I
was touching or the number of pages I
was tearing it's fair to say that the
first algorithm in the worst case might
have taken n total Pages it didn't
because I was searching for John Harvard
at the time which is somewhat early in
the alphabet but if I were searching
with some for someone with the last name
of Z I would have had to keep going and
going in the worst case through all n
Pages not as bad for the second
algorithm and that's why we do n divided
by two and even that's a bit of a white
lie right it's probably n / 2 + 1 in
case I have to double back but again I'm
sort of doing this more generally to
capture the essence of these things and
then we really got into the weeds with
like log base 2 of n for that third and
final algorithm and at the time we
claimed anytime you're doing dividing
something in half in half in half odds
are there's going to be some kind of
logarithm involved and we'll see that
today but today we're going to actually
start using computer science terminology
and we're going to sort of formalize
this imprecision if you will we are not
going to care generally about exactly
how many steps some algorithm takes
because that's not going to be that
enlightening especially if maybe you
have a faster computer tomorrow than you
did today it wouldn't really be fair to
compare numbers too precisely we really
kind of want to with a wave of the hand
just get a sense of roughly how slow or
how fast an algorithm is so the notation
here is deliberate that is literally a
capital O often italicized referred to
as Big O and so the first algorithm is
in Big O of n the second algorithm is in
Big O of n / two the third algorithm is
in Big O of log base 2 of n but even
that is kind of unnecessary detail when
using Big O notation you really don't
care about we'll see the smaller ordered
terms right we're not going to care
about the divided by two because you
know what the shape of these algorithms
is almost the same and really the idea
the algorithm itself is sort of
fundamentally the same okay and instead
of one page at a time I'm doing two but
if you throw millions of pages billions
of pages at me those algorithms are
really going to kind of perform the same
as n gets really large goes off toward
infinity and the same is true for
logarithms even if you're a little rusty
it turns out that whether you do the
math with log base 2 log base 3 log base
10 you can just multiply one by the
other to really get the same formula
this is only to say a computer scientist
would generally say that the first two
algorithms are on the order of eps the
third algorithm is on the order of log
end steps and we don't really care
precisely what we mean beyond that and
this Big O notation as we'll see and
actually let me let me zoom out if you
can imagine suddenly making the x- axis
much longer so more pages on the screen
at once it is indeed going to be the
shapes of these curves that matter
because imagine in your mind's eye as
you zoom out zoom out zoom out zoom out
and as n gets much much much bigger on
the xaxis the red and the yellow line
are essentially going to look the same
once n is sufficiently large but the
green line is never going to look the
same it's going to be a fundamentally
different shape and so that's the
intuition of bigo to get a sense of
these uh rates of performance like this
so here then is Big O here is perhaps a
cheat sheet of like the common formulas
that a computer scientist certainly in
an introductory context might use when
analyzing algorithms and let's consider
for a moment which of our first two
algorithms linear search and binary
search fall into these categories so
I've ordered them from sort of slowest
to fastest so order of n s it's not
something we've actually seen yet but it
tends to be slow because it's quadratic
you're doing n * n that's got to add up
to a lot of steps better today is going
to be n Lin even better is going to be n
even better than that is login and best
is soall order of one like one step or
maybe two steps maybe even a thousand
steps but a fixed finite number of steps
that never changes no how matter how big
n is so given this chart just to be
clear linear search let's consider the
worst case in the worst case how many
steps did it take someone like Stephanie
to find the uh solution to the problem
assuming not seven doors but n doors
yeah so on the order of N and in this
case it's exactly n but you know what
you know maybe it's arguably too n right
because it took Stephanie a couple of
steps like she had to lift the latch she
had to open the door maybe it's three
steps you had to show the money so now
it's 3n 2 N but there we don't really
care about that level of precision we
really just care about the fundamental
number of operations so we'll say yes on
the order of n so that might be an upper
bound we'll call this for linear search
and how about binary search in Jackson's
case or in general me and week zero if
there's end doors how many steps did it
take Jackson or me using binary
search in this case it was literally
three but that's not a
formula yeah so it's on the order of log
n and indeed if there's seven doors well
that's almost eight if you just do a
little bit of rounding and indeed if you
take log base 2 of eight okay so that
does actually give us three so the math
actually checks out and if you're not
comy with logarithms no big deal just
think about it intuitively uh logarithm
of base two is just dividing something
again and again so on this chart when we
consider Big O which to be clear allows
you to describe the order of an
algorithm's running time like the
magnitude of it but it also describes
more specifically an upper bound so in
the worst case for instance these are
pretty good measures of how good uh or
rather of how bad linear search and
binary search might be why well suppose
you're searching a thousand page phone
book and the person's name starts with z
the algorithm is still going to be on
the order of n steps why because it
might take you as many as all end steps
to find it now that's not necessarily
going to be the case in practice if I
use Big O as an upper bound well it
would be nice if there's sort of a
corresponding lower bound especially if
you want to consider not just best uh
worst cases but maybe best cases so what
might we use here well so this is a
capital Greek omega symbol so Omega is
the symbol that a computer scientist
uses generally to describe a lower bound
on an algorithm often in the context of
best case though not necessarily so a
lower bound means how few steps might an
algorithm take and here too same
formulas and we'll fill in these blanks
over time some algorithms might always
take a minimum of n squ steps or on the
order of n steps some might only take n
logn or n or log n or one so something
like uh linear search when Stephanie
started with linear search she didn't
get lucky this time on stage but what if
she had and the first door she opened
were 50 how much you then describe the
lower bound on linear search in this
so-called best
case using this list of possible
answers yeah yeah so Omega of one so in
the best case the lower bound on how
many steps it might take uh linear
search to find something might just be
one step why because maybe Stephanie had
gotten lucky and we had pre-filled these
lockers with the numbers in some other
order such that she might have open the
first locker and waila the number 50
could have been there so a lower bound
arguably could indeed be Omega of one
for linear search and how about now for
Jackson he used binary search so he
dived right into the middle of the
problem but what would be a lower bound
on binary search using this logic yeah
yeah so again Omega of one why because
maybe he just gets lucky and indeed
right in the middle of the lockers could
have been the number 50 it wasn't and so
more Germain in Jackson's uh actual
practice would have been the Big O
discussion but Big O and Omega upper
bound and lower bound just allow a
computer scientist to kind of wrestle
with what could happen maybe in the
worst case what can happen in the best
case and you can even get even more
precise like the average case or the
like and this is indeed what Engineers
might do at a whiteboard in a company in
a university when designing an algorithm
and trying to make arguments as to like
why their algorithm is better than
someone else's by way of these kinds of
analyses and just so you've seen it it
turns out that if some algorithm happens
to have an identical upper bound and
lower bound you can actually use a
capital Greek Theta as well and this is
the last of the the Greek symbols today
but a Greek Theta indicates a coinci
idents of both upper bound and lower
bound that is they are one and the same
that was not the case for our discussion
a second ago of linear search not the
case for binary search but you could use
the same kinds of formulas if it turns
out that your upper bound and lower
bound are the same so for instance if I
were to count everyone like literally in
this room 1 2 3 4 five six and so forth
you could actually say that counting in
that way is in Theta of n right because
I in the best case it's going to take me
end points at the uh people in the
audience in the worst case it's going to
take me n it's always going to take me
end steps if I want to count everyone in
the room you can't really do better than
that unless you skip people so that
would be an example off the cuff of
something where Theta is instead germine
are any questions now on Big O on Omega
or Theta which are now just more formal
tools in the toolkit for talking about
the design of our
algorithms any
questions
no seeing none yeah oh is this yes no
okay so we're good so let's go ahead and
translate this perhaps to some some
actual code let me go over to vs code
here and let's see if we can't now
translate some of these ideas to some
actual code not so much using new syntax
yet we're going to still operate in this
world of arrays like last week so let me
go ahead and create a program called
search. C by executing code space
search. c in my terminal and then up
here let's go ahead and include our
usual so include cs50.h so I can get
some input include standard i.h so I can
print some output we'll do int main void
which the meaning of which we did start
to tease apart last week the fact that
it's void again today just means no
command line arguments and let me go
ahead and do this let me go ahead and
declare just for discussion's sake a
static array like an array that never
changes and the Syntax for this is going
to be give me an array called numbers
using the square bracket not ation and
I'm going to immediately initialize it
to 20 500 10 5 100 1 and 50 reminiscent
of those same denominations as before so
this is a slightly new syntax that we've
uh perhaps not seen and the curly braces
here which are different from for loops
and while loops and functions just tell
the compiler please give me an array of
whatever size this is containing those
numbers left to right I could
alternatively use last week's syntax of
saying something like this let's see one
2 3 4 5 six seven denominations I could
alternatively do this and then I could
say numbers bracket 0 uh numbers bracket
0 equals 20 numbers bracket 1 equal 500
and I could do this five more times
that's just a little tedious if you know
the numbers in advance you don't have to
tell the compiler how many there are you
can just let it figure it out that your
numbers are be will be 20 500 10 5 100 1
and 5050 so this is how you statically
Define an array all right let me just go
ahead and ask the user now for a number
we'll call it n by using get int and
prompting them for a number so nothing
new there and now let me go ahead and
Implement linear search and the pseudo
code we had for this before used some
array like notation let me go ahead then
and start similarly four in I and it's
you almost always start counting at I by
convention so that's perhaps a good
starting point I'm going to do this so
long as I is less than seven not the
best design to hard code the seven but
this is just for demonstration sake for
now because I know how many numbers I
put in there and then I'm going to do
i++ so now I have the beginnings of a
loop that will just allow me to iterate
over the entire array and let me ask
this if the current number at location I
equals equals n which is the number the
human typed in then let's go ahead and
do something simple like print F quote
unquote found back sln and then per our
discussion last week to indicate that
this is successful I'm going to going to
return zero if I found it and if I don't
find it I'm just going to go down here
and by default say not found back sln
and just for convention whoops just for
good measure per convention I'll return
one or really any value other than zero
zero recall means success and any other
integer tends to mean error of some sort
irrespective of the number I'm looking
for so just to revisit the only thing
that's new here is the syntax for
creating an array of seven numbers these
numbers and then after after that we
have really highlighted here an
implementation of linear search I mean
this is the C version I dare say of what
Stephanie did on the board whereas now
the array is called numbers instead of
doors but I think it's pretty much the
same let me go ahead and open my
terminal window and run make
search seems to compile okay search and
let's go ahead and search for a number
we'll start with what we did before 50
and it's found let's go ahead and run it
again/ search let's search for maybe 20
at the beginning that one too is found
let's run it one more time searching for
like 1,000 which is not uh in among the
uh denominations and that one indeed is
not found so we've taken an idea from
week zero now formalized in week three
and just translated it now to code
questions on this implementation of
linear
search linear
search nothing oh so successful so far
today okay so let's see if we can't
maybe make this a little more
interesting and see if we can't trip
over a detail that's going to be
important in C instead of doing numbers
let me go ahead and do this we'll stay
on theme with Monopoly and I went down
the rabbit hole of reading the
wikkipedia article on Monopoly and the
original uh pieces or tokens that came
with Monopoly and it turns out we can
represent those with strings so I'm
going to create an array called strings
plural of whatever size I defined here
and the very first first Monopoly pieces
back in the day were a battleship that
you could play with a boot a cannon an
iron a
thimble and a top hat some of which you
might know from the game nowadays turns
out they've been changing these uh had
no idea over the years so here is now an
array of strings let me go ahead and
prompt the user now not for an integer
anymore I want to Now search for one of
these strings still using linear search
so let me create a string s set it equal
to string prompt the user for a string
to search for and then I think my code
here is almost the same except for one
detail I now have an array called
strings I now have a variable called s
but it turns out for reasons we'll
explore in more detail next week this
line of code is not going to work and it
turns out the reason has to do with what
we discussed last week of like what a
string really is and what is a string
again a string is an array and it turns
out though that equals equals is not
going to generously compare all of the
characters in an array for you just
because you use equal equals it turns
out it's not going to compare every
letter and so thankfully there is in the
uh string library that we introduced
last week a solution to this problem the
reason for the problem we'll explore in
more detail next week but for now just
know that when you want to compare
strings in C especially if you've come
into the class knowing a bit of Java or
python or some other language you cannot
use equals equals even though you could
in scratch you cannot in C so what I
have to actually do here is this I have
to ask the question does the return
value of a function called stir compare
or stir
comp equal zero when passed in the
current string and that user input so if
you read the documentation for this
function called stir compare you'll see
that it takes two strings as input first
one and second one it then someone
decades ago wrote the code that probably
uses a four Loop or a while loop to
compare every character in each of those
strings and it turns out it returns zero
if they are in fact equal turns out too
it will return a positive number or a
negative number in other situations any
intuition for why it might actually be
useful to have a function that allows
you to check if two strings are equal
if they're not equal what else might be
interesting to know when comparing two
strings are if certain values
are okay possibly maybe you want to know
just how similar they are um and that's
indeed an algorithm unto itself but stir
compare is a little simpler than
that exactly if you're trying to like
alphabetize a whole list of strings just
like your phone probably is for your
context or address book it turns out
that stir compare will actually return a
positive number or a negative number or
a zero based on whether maybe it comes
alphabetically first or later or or in
fact equal so that can be a useful thing
and that's just a teaser for a lower
level explanation that we'll see next
week so now let me cross my fingers and
see if I got this right let me go ahead
and do make
search did compile okay albeit slowly
do/ search and let's search for
something like the thimble and we see
that that's indeed found otherwise let's
search for something that I know isn't
there like a race car which was there
when I grew up but huh segmentation
fault core dumped like and actually some
of you have tripped over this error
before anyone want to admit seeing this
so yeah not something we've talked about
and um honestly not something I intended
just now but that too we'll see next
week any intuition for why my program
just
broke I didn't really change the logic
it's still linear search let me hide the
terminal so you can see all of the code
at once the only thing I did was
switched from integers to Strings and I
switched to stir compare here but
segmentation fault happened and the
teaser is that that somehow relates to
the computer's memory
yeah yeah and this is subtle but spot on
so 1 2 3 4 5 six elements total in this
array versus the seven number
of Monopoly denominations that we had
earlier and this is where see sort of
case in point this came back to bite me
the fact that I hardcoded this value as
to opposed to maybe separating it out as
a constant or declaring it higher up
kind of bit me here because now I'm
iterating over an array of size six but
clearly I'm going one step too far
because I'm literally going to iterate
seven times not six so it's as though
I'm looking at memory that's over here
and indeed next week we'll focus on
memory and that's just a bad thing so
odds are not even and seeing your code
from this past week if any of you have
had segmentation faults odds are you
touched memory that you shouldn't have
you maybe looped too many times you
might have uh used a negative number to
get into your array in general you
touched memory that you shouldn't have
and you touched a segment of memory that
you shouldn't have the fix though at
least in my case is simple just don't do
that so let me go ahead and recompile
this make uh
search do/ search and I'll search again
for uh race car and
and now it does not crash but it does
tell me it's not found so subtle but
something you might yourself have
tripped over already questions then on
what I just did intentionally or
otherwise yeah in
front return don't return Z return so
what
the a really good question so the
program will still work even if I don't
return zero or return one in fact let me
go ahead head and do that and just hide
my terminal window for a second let's
get rid of the return here let's get rid
of the return here however Watch What
Happens here uh let me go ahead and
recompile this make search Let Me scroll
up in my code here let me go ahead and
do do/ search and let me go ahead and
search for the first thing in the list
Battleship so I know that this should be
found I hit
enter huh interesting so it's saying
found not found but do you see why
logically in this case
exactly so the loop is still running so
there's a couple of solutions to this I
could for instance somehow break out of
the code here but that's going to still
result in line 18 executing I could then
instead just return here I don't
strictly need to return one down at the
bottom but I made this claim last week
that it tends to be helpful as your
programs get more sophisticated to at
least signify just like a real world
programmer error codes when something
goes wrong so returning zero in main is
the easiest way to signify my code is
done I'm ready to exit successfully
that's it but down here I could
absolutely still return zero because
it's not a huge deal it's not really an
error that deserves annoying the user
with some kind of popup that something
went wrong but return one is just a
lower level way of signaling H it didn't
really find what I was looking for and
remember from last week you can see this
as follows if I recompile this again now
that I've reverted those changes so make
search and if I do uh /search and search
for Battleship which is indeed found
recall I can execute this magical
command Echo dollar sign question mark
which you're not going to often execute
but it shows you what main returned if I
run search again and search for race car
which is not found I see not found but I
can also run this command again and see
that oh it returned one so now if you
fast forward a few months a few years
when you're actually writing code in a
company or for larger projects you might
want to be automating software you might
not want the human to necessarily be
running it manually you might want um
code to be automated by some nightly
process or something like that using
these exit codes can a program determine
yes or no that other code succeeded or
failed other questions on linear search
in this
way no all right well let's translate
this to one other feature of uh C here
by incorporating these ideas now into
one other program so I'm going to create
a phone book in C by doing code space
phone
book.car a phone book for an actual name
and getting back a number so I'm going
to go ahead and quickly include some of
the same things cs50.h so we can get
input uh standard io. so we can print
output and I'm going to preemptively
include string.h in case we need that
one as well uh int main void no need for
uh command line arguments today and let
me me give myself now an array of names
for this phone book so string names
equals and then in curly braces how
about Carter will be one person in the
phone book and David myself will be the
other so we'll keep it short so we don't
have to type too many names but this is
a phone book with two people thus far
suppose now we want to also store
Carter's phone number in mind so it's
not just saying found or not found it's
literally looking up our phone numbers
like a proper phone book well at the
moment there's really no way to do this
I could do something hackish like I
could put a number like
617495 1000 after Carter I could maybe
do something like 949 uh 468 2750 after
me but now you're kind of doing the
whole apples and oranges thing right
like now it's not strings it's a string
int string int all right so maybe I
could just make all of these strings but
now it's just a conceptual mixing of
apples and oranges like yes that's an
array of four strings but now you're on
the honor System to know that the first
string is a name the second string is a
number the third string is like you can
do it but it's a bit of a hack so to
speak so what might be cleaner than this
instead of combining our phone numbers
into the same array as our names what
else might we do that's perhaps a little
better say a little
Lou a 2d array uh possibly something we
could do I'm going to keep it even
simpler now because we haven't used
those by name even though that is we saw
last week technically what argv is what
else could I do if I want to store names
and numbers
yeahp yeah let me go with this
suggestion just it's a little simpler
rather than complicate things in
literally different dimensions let me go
ahead and do string well I could do int
numbers but you know what so that we can
support punctuation like dashes or even
parentheses or country codes I'm going
to do this instead I'm going to do
string numbers so that I can represent
Carter's number as quote unquote plus
one for the US 617 495 1,000 complete
with hyphens as is us convention and
then for mine I'll go ahead and do + one
949 how about 468
275 semi colon and now down below let's
actually enable the user to search this
phone book just like in week zero we did
string name equals get string and let's
ask the user for a name presumably David
or Carter or someone else and now let's
re-implement linear search so four in I
gets zero I is less than two and do as I
say not as I do I think we should beware
this coding but we'll keep it simple for
now i++ and then in this for loop I
think we have all of the ingredients to
solve this so if the return value of
stir compare of all of the names bracket
I comparing against the name that the
human typed in if all of that equals
equals zero that is all of the
characters in those two strings are
equal then I think we can go ahead and
say found just like last time but you
know what let's actually print Carter or
my phone number so found percent s and
we'll plug in numbers bracket I and then
just for consistency I'll return zero
here and down here how about I'll say
something like uh print F not found just
to be clear and then I'll return one as
well so just a recap here's all of the
code it's almost the same as before
except now it's useful I'm not just
saying found or not found I found a
number in Monopoly or I found a a piece
in Monopoly I'm looking up in one array
of the strings and then I'm printing
from the other array the answer so let
me go ahead here and run the compiler
make phone book enter okay that's
promising no errors do/ phonebook now
and let's search for for instance Carter
enter all right so we found Carter's
number all right let me do that again
phone book Let's search for David all
right we seem to have found David's
number all right let's do it one last
time phone book enter and now we'll
search for like John Harvard enter not
found
all right so I dare say albeit with
minimal testing this code is
correct would anyone now like to
critique the design does something rub
you the wrong way perhaps about this
approach
here and as always think about how if
the program maybe gets longer more
complicated how decisions like this
might unfold
yeah okay so if I is less than two so
technically I if I change the number of
people in this phone book I'm going to
have to update I and we've already seen
that I get myself into trouble so that's
bad design
goodes yeah so again I'm sort of
trusting myself not to screw up if I add
John or anyone else to the first array
but I forget to add their number to the
second array you know eventually things
are going to drift and be inconsistent
and then the just code will be incorrect
at that point so so sort of a poor
design setting me up for future failure
if you will other thoughts
yeah yeah really good we're assuming the
same order from left to right the names
go and from left to right the numbers go
but that's kind of just the honor System
like there's literally nothing in code
preventing me from reversing the order
for whatever reason or maybe sorting the
names like they're sorted now and maybe
that's deliberate but maybe it's not so
this honor System here too is just not
good right I could put a comment in here
to remind myself to uh you know note to
self always update arrays the same way
but like that's something's going to
happen eventually especially when we
have not two but three but 30 300 names
and numbers it would be nice to keep all
of the related data together and so in
fact the one new feature of C we'll
introduce today is one that actually
allows us to implement our very own data
structures you can think of a raay as a
very lightweight data structure and that
allows you to Cluster related data back
to back to back to back and this is how
strings are implemented they are a data
structure effectively implemented with
an array but with c and with other
languages it turns out you can invent
your own data types whether they're one
dimensional two-dimensional even or
Beyond and with uh with C can you
specifically create your own types that
have their own name so for instance
wouldn't it have been nice if C came
with not just Char and int and float and
uh uh long and and others wouldn't it be
nice if C came with a data type called
person and ideally a person would have a
name and a number now that's a little
naive and unrealistic like why would
they define a person to have just those
two Fields certainly people could have
disagreed what a person is so they leave
it to us like the authors of C gave us
all of these Primitives inss and floats
and strings and so forth but it's up to
us now to use those in a more
interesting way so that we can create an
array of person variables if you will
inside of an array called people just to
pluralize it here so how are we going to
do this well for now let's just
stipulate that a person in the world
will have a name and a number that we
could argue all day long what else a
person should have and that's fine you
can invent your own person
eventually at the moment I'm using just
two variables to define a person's name
and number but wouldn't it be nice to
encapsulate that is combined these two
data types into a new and improved data
type called person and the Syntax for
that is going to be this so it's a bit
of a mouthful but you can perhaps infer
what some of this is doing here so it
turns out C has a keyword called type
def as the name kind of suggests this
allows you to Define your own type
struct is an indication that it's a
structure it's like a a structure that
has multiple values inside of it that
you are trying to Define and then at the
very bottom here outside of the Curve
early braces is the name of the type
that you want to create so you don't
have discretion over using type def or
struct in this particular case but you
can name the thing whatever you want and
you can put anything in the structure
that you want as well and as soon as
this semicolon is executed at the bottom
of the code every line thereafter can
now have access to a person data type
whether as a single variable or as an
entire array so if I want to build on
this then let me go ahead and do this
let me go back to my C code here and I'm
going to go ahead and uh change just a
couple of things let's go ahead and do
this I'm going to go ahead and first get
rid of those two hardcoded arrays and
let me go ahead and at the top of my
file invent this type so type def struct
inside of it will be a string name and
then a string number and then the name
of this structure will be person and
best practice would have me Define at
the very top of my file so that any of
my functions in fact could use it even
though I just have Main in this case now
if I want it I could do this like person
P1 and person P2 but we know from last
week like that already is bad design if
you want to have multiple instances of
the same type of variable we should
probably use what
instead and yeah an array so let me not
even go down that road let me instead
just do this person uh will be the type
of the array but I'm going to call it I
could call it persons but in English we
typically say people so I'll call the
array people and I want two people to
exist in this array though I could
certainly change that number to be
anything I want how now do you put a
name inside of a person and then put the
number inside of that same person well
slightly new syntax today I'm going to
go ahead and say this people bracket
zero just gives me the first person in
the array that's not new but if you want
to go inside of that person in memory
you use a DOT and then you just specify
the name of the attribute therein so if
I want to set the first person's name to
Carter I just use that so-called dot
notation and then if I want to set
Carter's number using dot notation I
would do this plus one
617495 1000 and then if I want to do the
same for myself I would now do people
bracket
1name equals quote unquote David and
then people bracket one still number
equals quote unquote + 1
2750 and now at the bottom of my file I
think my logic can pretty much stay the
same I can still on this line here
prompt the user for the name of the
person they want to look up for now even
though I admit it's not the best design
I'm just doing this for demonstration
sake I'm going to leave the two there
because I know I have two people but
down here this is going to have to
change I don't want to compare names
bracket I anymore what do I want to type
here as the first first argument to stir
compare what do I want to do here
yeah so people i. name yeah so I want to
go into the people array at the I
location because that's what my Loop is
doing it's updating I again and again
and then look at name and that's good I
think now I need to change this too what
do I want to print if the person is
found someone
else what do I want to print here if I
found the person's name
yeah say a little
louder perfect so people bracket. number
if indeed I want to print the
corresponding number to this person and
then I think the rest of my code can
stay the same so let me go ahead and run
make phonebook to recompile this version
so far so good/ phonebook let's go ahead
and type in Carter's name found all
right let's go ahead and run it again
David's name found let's go ahead and
run it one more time type in John
Harvard for instance not found in this
case so fundamentally the code isn't all
that different linear search is still
behaving the same way and I admit this
is kind of ugly looking like we've kind
of made a two-line solution like five
lines of code now but if we fast forward
a week or two when we start saving
information to files uh we'll introduce
you to files like CSV value CSV files
comma separated values or spreadsheet
files which you've surely opened on your
Mac or PC at some point in the past
suffice it to say We'll soon learn
Techni for storing information like
names and numbers in files and at that
point we're not going to do any of this
hackish sort of hardcoding of the number
two and manually typing my name and
Carter's name and number into our
program we'll read the information
dynamically from a file and in a few
weeks we'll read it dynamically from a
database instead but this is for now
just syntactically how we can create an
array of size two containing one person
each we can update the name and number
of the first person update the name and
the number of the second person and then
later search across those names and
print out the corresponding numbers and
in this sense this is a better design
why because my person data type
encapsulates now everything that it
means to be a person at least in this
narrow world and if I want to add
something to the notion of a person for
instance I could go up to my typed Def
and tomorrow add an address to every
person and start reading that in as well
and now it's not the honor System it's
not a names array a numbers array and a
addesses array and everything else you
might imagine related to a person it's
all encapsulated which is a a term of
art inside of the same type reminiscent
if some of you have programmed before of
something called objectoriented
programming but we're not there yet C is
not that questions on this use of struct
or this new syntax the dot operator
being really the juicy part
here any questions
yeah
on what line
number 16 so yes so syntactically we
introduced the square brackets last week
so doing people bracket zero just means
go to the first person in the array that
was like when Stephanie literally opened
this door that's uh that's doors bracket
zero but this is of course people
bracket zero instead today the dot is a
new piece of syntax it means go inside
of that person in memory
and look at the name therein and set it
equal to Carter and do the same for
number so that's all it's like open the
locker door go inside of it and check or
set the name and the number
yeah attributes is fine uh good question
in the struct can you set default values
short answer no and this is where C
becomes less featurable than more more
modern languages like Python and Java
and others where you can in fact do that
so when we transition to python in a few
weeks time we'll see how we can start
solving problems like that but for now
it's up to you to initialize name and
number to something
yeah really good question how can we
adjust or critique the design of what
I'm doing
this is one of the few situations where
I would say hypocritically do as I say
not as I do I am using pretty ugly lines
like this just to introduce the syntax
but my claim pedagogically today is that
eventually when we start storing names
and numbers or other things in files or
in databases you won't have this
redundancy you'll have one line of code
or two lines of code that read the
information from the file or database
and then fill the entire array with that
data for now I'm just doing it manually
so is to keep our Focus only on the new
syntax but that's it so forgive the bad
Design By Design today other questions
on
this all right that's been a lot already
why don't we go ahead and take our
10-minute break with snacks first we
have some delightful brownies in the
lobby all right we are back and up until
now it clearly seems to be a good thing
if your data is sorted because you can
use binary search you know a little more
some little something more about the
data uh but it turns out that sorting of
itself is kind of a problem to solve too
and you might think well if sorting is
going to be pretty fast we absolutely
should do it before we start searching
because that'll just speed up all of our
searches but if sorting is slow that
kind of invites the question well should
we bother sorting our data if we're only
going to search the data maybe once
maybe twice and so here is going to be
potentially a trade-off so let's
consider what it means really to sort
data in our case it's just going to be
simple and use numbers but it might in
the case of the Googles of the World be
actual web pages or persons or the like
so here is our typical picture for
sorting input uh for solving any problem
input at left and output at right the
input to our sort problem is going to be
uh some unsorted set of values and the
output ideally will be the same set of
values sorted and if we do this
concretely let's suppose that we want to
go about sorting this list of numbers 7
2 5 4 1 6 03 so it's all of the numbers
from 0 to 7 but they're somehow jumbled
up randomly that's going to be the input
to the problem and the goal is now to
sort those so that you indeed get out 0
1 2 3 4 5 67 instead so it turns out
there's lots of different ways we can
actually sort numbers like these here um
and in fact just to complement our
search example earlier could we perhaps
quickly get some eight volunteers to
come up if you're comfortable appearing
on the internet if you want to do one
okay uh two three four five 6 7 eight
how about all right come on
down all
right come on over here and I'll give
you each a number and if you want to
start to organize yourselves in the same
order you see the numbers on the
board okay so look up on the overhead
and organize yourselves from left to
right in that same
order and let's have the first of you
perfect if you want to come uh right
over here
how about right in line with this all
right and a few more
numbers all right number
two six
and perfect just the right number all
right no uhoh all right there we go
number three all right so let's just do
a quick check we have 7 2 5 4 1 603 very
good so far do you want to just scooch a
little this way just to make a little
more of room all right and let's
consider now who we have here on stage
you want to each say a quick hello to
the audience hi my name is Ryan uh I'm a
first year from Penny
Packer hi my name is Cel I'm a first
year at Strauss um hi my name is Lucy
I'm a first year from
greo hi my name is Shiloh I'm a first
year in
Wigglesworth hi my name is Jack and I'm
a first year in
St hi my name is Katherine I'm a first
year in stra hi my name is Michael and
my first year at Penny Packer hi my name
is Muhammad at my first here in massuse
nice welcome aboard all right so let's
consider now how we might go about
sorting Our Kind volunteers here the
goal being to get them into order from
uh smallest to largest so that
presumably then we can use something
smarter than just linear search we could
actually use binary search assuming that
they are already then sorted so let me
propose that we first consider an
algorithm that actually has a name
called selection sort and selection sort
is going to be one that literally has me
or really you as the programmer
selecting the smallest element again and
again and then putting them into the
appropriate place so let me go ahead and
start this here uh starting with the
number seven at the moment seven is the
smallest number I found so I'm going to
make mental note of that with a mental
variable if you will I'm going to move
on now oh number two is obviously
smaller so I'm just going to update my
mental reminder that two is now the
smallest effectively forgetting for now
number seven uh five not smaller four
not smaller one smaller and I'm going to
make mental note of that six not smaller
zero smaller I'll make mental note of
that having forgotten now everything
else and now number three is not smaller
so what's your name again Michael so
Michael is number zero he belongs of
course way down there but unfortunately
you are Ryan Ryan Ryan is in the way so
what should we do how should we start to
sort this
list where should number zero
go yeah do you want to say the
L yeah so let's just go ahead and swap
so if you want to go ahead and zero go
on where seven is we need to make room
for number seven it would kind of be
cheating if maybe everyone kind of
politely stepped over to the side why
because if we imagine all of our
volunteers here to be in Array like
that's a crazy amount of work to have
every element in the array shift to the
left just to make room so we're going to
keep it simple and just evict whoever is
there now maybe we get lucky and number
seven is actually closer to its
destination maybe we get unlucky and it
goes farther away but we've at least
solved one problem if we had n problems
at first now we have n minus one because
number zero is indeed in the right place
so if I continue to act this out let me
go ahead and say two okay currently the
smallest five no four no one currently
the smallest I'll make mental note 6 7 3
and now let me pause one is obviously
the now smallest element so did I need
to keep going well it turns out at least
as I've defined selection sort I do need
to keep going because I only claim that
I'm using one variable in my mind to
remember the then smallest element I'm
not smart enough like us humans to
remember oh wait a minute one is
definitely the smallest now I don't have
that whole recollection so I just am
keeping track of the now smallest so
number one what your name was Jack Jack
where should jack go probably there and
what's your name itel itel okay so Jack
and itel if you want to swap places
we've now solved two of the end total
problems and now we'll do it a little
faster if each of you want to sort of
start to swap as I find the right person
so five smallest four is smaller two is
smaller got to keep checking okay two
was smaller all right now I'm going to
go back to the beginning all right four
is small five is not six is not seven is
oh three is small where do you want to
go okay good I'm going to go back here
and I can be a little smart I don't have
to go all the way to the end because I
know these folks are already sorted so I
can at least optimize slightly so now
five is small six is small seven is four
four is smaller if you want to go in
place
there and now here things get
interesting I can optimize by not
looking at these folks anymore more cuz
they're obviously problem solved but now
five is small six is not seven is not
okay five you can stay where you are now
a human in the room is obviously going
to question why I'm wasting any more
time but with selection sort as I've
defined it thus far I still have to now
check six is smallest not seven and now
my final step okay they're all in place
so here too is this dichotomy between
what we all have is this bird's eye view
of the whole problem where it's obvious
where everyone needs to go but a
computer implementing this with an array
really has to be more methodical and
we're actually saving a step here if we
were really doing this none of these
numbers would be visible all eight of
our volunteers would be inside of a
locked door and only then could we see
them one at a time but we're focusing
now just on the Sorting aspect so let me
just before we do one other
demonstration here proposed that what I
really just did here in pseudo code was
something like this 4 I from 0er to n
minus one keeping in mind that zero is
always the left of the array n minus one
is always the right end of of the array
for I from 0 to N minus1 I found the
smallest number between numbers bracket
I and numbers bracket n minus one and
that's the very geeky way of expressing
this optimization I'm always starting
from numbers bracket I wherever I am and
then everything else to the right and
that's what was allowing me to ignore
the already sorted volunteers if though
my last line says swap smallest number
with numbers I I think that implements
what our humans were doing by physically
walking to another spot all right so
that then would what we'll call
selection sort let's go ahead and take a
second approach here using an algorithm
that I'm going to call bubble sort but
to do this we need you all to reset to
your original locations we have a little
cheat sheet on the board if you'd like
to go back to this position here and let
me take a fundamentally different
approach because I'm not really liking
selection sort as is because it's kind
of a lot of walking back and forth and a
lot of walking suggests like a lot of
lot of steps again and again so what
might I do instead well bubble sort is
going to have me focus a little more
intuitively on just smaller problems and
let's see if this gets me somewhere else
so if I just look at this list without
looking at everyone else seven and two
this is obviously a problem why because
you're out of order so let's just solve
one tiny problem first so seven and two
why don't you swap I know two is in a
better place now because she's
definitely lower uh less than seven so I
think I can now move on seven and five
problem so let's solve that seven and
four problem let's solve that s and one
let's solve that 7 and six let's solve
that 7 and zero solve that 7 and three
solve that okay done sorted right all
obviously not if you just glance at
these numbers here but we have
fundamentally taken a bite out of the
problem seven is indeed in the right
place so we maximally have n minus one
other problems to solve so how do I do
this I think I can just repeat the same
logic let me go over here two and five
good five and four no five and one no
five and six yes 6 and zero no six and
three no so so now we've solved two of
the problems and what's nice about
Bubble sword at least as this glance
it's nice and simple it's nice and local
and you just keep incrementally solving
more and more problems so let's go ahead
and do this again and I'll do it we can
do it faster two and four we know are
good four and one four and five five and
zero five and three five and six six and
seven good so we go back two and one ah
now another problem solve two and four
four and zero four and three
four and five five and six six and seven
and so notice too as per its name the
largest elements have bubbled their way
up to the top and that's what seems to
be happening just as we're fixing some
remaining problems so almost done one
and two two and zero two and three three
and four four and five five and six six
and seven almost done obviously to us
humans it looks done how do I know as
the computer for sure what would be the
most Surefire way for me to now oh it's
not done sorry uh that's a bug
okay one and zero okay one and two two
and three three and four three four and
five five and six six and seven okay so
now it's obviously sorted to the rest of
us on stage how could I confirm as much
as code right you're doing it with your
mind just glancing at this how would the
computer the code know for sure that
this list is now sorted
yeah let's do one more time and look uh
draw what
conclusion yeah let's do it one more
time even though it's a little wasteful
but logically if I go through the whole
list comparing pairs again again and
again and I don't do any work that time
now it's obviously logically safe to
just stop because otherwise I'm wasting
my time doing the same thing again and
again if no one's actually moving so I'm
afraid we don't have Monopoly games for
all of you but we do have eight stress
balls and a round of applause if we
could for our
volunteers if you want to put your
numbers on the Shelf
there so if we consider for a moment
thank you thank you so
much
sure thank you thanks sure so if we
consider now these two algorithms which
one is better any intuition for whether
selection sort the first is better or
worse than bubble sort the
second any
thoughts
yeah okay so bubbl swort seemed like
less work especially since I was
focusing on those localized problems
other
intuition selection sort versus bubble
sort well let me propose that we try to
like quantize this so we can actually
analyze it in some way and this is not
an exercise we'll do constantly for lots
of algorithms but these are pretty
representative of algorithms so we can
wrap our minds around indeed the
performance or the design of these
things so here is my pseudo code for
selection sort whereby as it's as per
its name I just iteratively select the
next smallest element El again and again
so how can we go about analyzing
something like this well we could just
do it on paper pencil and count up the
number of steps that seem to be implied
logically by the code we could literally
comp count like the number of steps I
was taking again and again left to right
we could also just com uh count the
number of comparisons I was making with
each of the persons involved and I was
doing it kind of quickly in selection
sort but every time I was looking at a
person trying to decide do I want to
remember that number is small as that
number I was comparing two values with
an equals equals or less than or greater
than sign at least if we had done this
in code so that tends to be the norm
when analyzing algorithms like these
counting the number of comparisons
because it's kind of a global uh it's
kind of a global unit of measure we can
use to compare different algorithms
entirely so think too that in the
general case when we have more than
eight volunteers more than seven doors
we can generalize our our array in
general as this is the first element at
bracket zero and the end of it is always
n minus one so arrays uh or doors in
this case or volunteers are always
numerically indexed from zero on up to n
minus one if there's n of them in total
so how do we analyze the code of
selection sort well how many steps did
it take me to find the first smallest
element or more precisely how many
comparisons did I need to make when I
walked left to right to find our first
smallest person which ended up being
zero how many comparisons did I do when
walking left to right if there were
eight people on
stage how many total comparisons did I
do like if there's eight people I
compared these folks then then like this
person this person yeah yeah so seven
total right because if there's eight
people on stage you can only do seven
comparisons total because otherwise
you'd be comparing one number to itself
so it seems like in the general case if
you've got n numbers that you're trying
to sort finding the smallest element
first takes n minus one comparisons
maybe n it's total steps left or right
but the number of comparisons which I
claim is just a useful unit of measure
is n minus one how about finding the
next smallest person how many steps did
it take me to find the next smallest
number which ended up being the number
one
yeah yeah so just n minus two why
because I'd already solved one problem
someone was already in the right
position it would be silly to keep
counting them again and again so I can
Whittle down my number of comparisons
for the next past n minus 2 the third
past to find the third smallest number
would be n minus 3 and then dot dot dot
presumably this story this formula ends
when you have just one final pair the
people at the end to compare so if this
is looking a little reminiscent of some
kind of recurrence from high school or
high school math or physics or the like
let me just stipulate that if you
actually do out this math and generalize
it that is the same thing as n * nus1 /
2 and if you're Rusty on that no big
deal just kind of commit to memory that
anytime you add up this kind of series
something plus something slightly
smaller plus something slightly smaller
Each of which differs by one you're
going to get this formula n * n -1/ 2 if
we of course uh uh multiply that out
that's really n^ 2 minus n all divided
by two if we keep multiplying it out
that's n^2 / 2 minus n /2 and now we
have kind of a vocabulary with which we
can talk about the efficiency the design
of this algorithm but honestly I don't
really care about this level of
precision like n^2 / 2us n / 2 as n gets
really large which of these symbols
which of these terms is really going to
dominate become the biggest influencer
on the total value of
steps right it's the square right like
it's definitely not n divided by two
that's shaving some time off but N
squared as n gets big is going to get
really big if n is 100 then n squar is
bigger if N is a million n squ is really
bigger and so at the end of the day when
we really just talking about sort of a
wave of of the hand analysis and upper
bound if you will let's just say that
selection sort as analyzed here it's on
the order of n s steps it's not
precisely n squar steps but you know
what n^2 divided two the intuition here
might be that well it's half of that you
n squ is what really matters as n gets
really really large and that's when you
start thinking about and trying to solve
the Google problems of the world when n
gets large that's when you have to be
smarter than just sort of naive
implementations of any algorithm so
where then does this algorithm fall into
this categorization here well n^2 it
turns out is on the order of n squ steps
in the worst case whether it's sorted or
not it turns out though lower bound if
we consider this same code suppose the
best case scenario like our eight
volunteers came up on stage and just
because they already sorted themselves 0
through seven suppose they just happen
to be in that state how many steps would
selection store
take to sort an already sorted list of
volunteers any intuition
yeah would it still be
n so for the first pass it would still
be seven for the first per uh pass
across the humans because even though
yeah I'm claiming zero is here I don't
know that zero is the smallest until I
make my way all the way over there doing
all seven comparisons okay fine first
pass took seven more generally n minus
one steps what if I look for the next
smallest element and the humans in this
story are already sorted 0 through 7
well yes the number one's here and I see
them first but I don't know they're the
smallest until I compare against
everyone else get to the end of the list
oh well that was stupid I already had
the smallest person in hand then and so
this pseudo code this implementation of
selection sort is sort of fixed like
this there's no special case that says
if already sorted quit early it's always
going to take n squ steps and so in this
case if we borrow our uh jargon from
earlier using Omega notation just to be
clear selection sword is also going to
be in this Incarnation on an Omega of n
s because even in the best case where
the list is already sorted you're going
to waste a huge amount of time
essentially verifying as much or
discovering as much even though we
humans of course could see it right away
so selection sort would seem to take
both N squared steps in the uh worst
case n s steps in the best case and so
you know what we can use our Theta
terminology for that here would be an
algorithm just like counting earlier
that always takes N squared steps no
matter whether the array is sorted or
not from the get-go all right so
hopefully we can do better and someone
proposed earlier that bubble sort felt
like it was using fewer steps well let's
consider that next with bubble sort we
had this pseudo code I claim whereby
let's focus on the inside of the code
first down here what was I doing for I
from 0 to n minus 2 that's curious we've
never seen n minus 2 before but I asked
this question if numbers bracket I and
numbers bracket I + 1 are out of order
swap them so that was when I was
pointing at our first two volunteers
here I saw that they were out of order
so I swapped them how come I'm doing
that again and again up to nus 2 though
instead of n
minus1 which we've always used up until
now as our rightmost
boundary any intuition for why I'm doing
this from 0 to n minus 2
yeah exactly because I'm looking at the
E person per this pseudo code here and
the E plus one person I better make sure
I don't go Step Beyond the at boundaries
of my array so if you think of like my
left hand when my back was two here
pointing at the current person at the
first position my right hand for this if
conditioner is essentially pointing at
the person next to them and you want to
iterate with your left hand all through
these people but you don't want your
left hand to point at the last person
you want it to point at the second to
last person but we know that the last
person is always at n minus one so the
second to last person just
mathematically is at n minus 2 so it's a
subtlety but this is like a Segal
waiting to happen if you implemented
bubble sort using n minus one you will
my right hand would go beyond the
boundaries of the array so just bad all
right so why am I saying this end times
Well we did it very organically with
humans but each time someone uh each
pass I did through the array someone
bubbled their way up to the end number
seven then number six then number five
so if on each pass through the array of
volunteers I was solving at Mo at least
one problem it seems like bubble sort
can just run n times total to solve all
n problems cuz the first pass will get
at least one one number into place
second pass second number into place you
might get lucky and it would do more but
worst case this feels like enough just
do this blindly end times and they'll
all line up together well technically
all right now we're getting into the
weeds technically you can just repeat it
n minus one times because if you solve
all n minus one other problems and
you're left with one like literally that
person's where they need to be just
logically if you've already sorted
everything else and you've got just the
one left it's already bubbled up so how
do we analyze this well in bubble sore
we might do something like this I'm
essentially doing n minus one Things N
minus one times now let me back up to
the pseudo code because this one's a
little less obvious this is where you
can actually mathematically infer from
your Loop uh how many steps you're
taking so this first line literally says
repeat the following n minus one times
so that's going to translate very
straightforwardly to our mathematical
formula do something n minus one times
this Loop just because I'm using four
Loop terminology it's framed a little
differently but but if you're iterating
from 0 to nus 2 you're iterating a total
of nus1 times and again the arithmetic
is getting a little annoying but this
just means do the following n minus one
times so do n minus one Things N minus
one times we can now uh run out the math
as follows we have the formula n minus1
* n minus1 we do our little foil method
here N2 -1 * N - 1 * n + 1 we can
combine like terms n^ 2 - 2 n plus one
but at this point when n gets really
large which term are we really going to
care about this is on the order
of yeah n s so at least ASM totically
ASM totically means as n approaches
Infinity gets really large turns out
that the upper bounds on selection sort
and bubble sort are essentially the same
now if we really nitpicked and compared
the total number of comparisons they
might differ slightly but as n gets
large honestly you're barely going to
notice the difference it would seem
between these two algorithms
but what about um the lower bound if the
upper bound on Bubble sword is also Big
O of n what about the lower bound here
well with this pseudo code what would
the lower bound be on bubble sort even
in the best case when all of the
volunteers are
sorted any
intuition in this pseudo code yeah in
the
middle
good question isn't bubble sorts
designed such that you wouldn't need to
compare numbers that have already uh
bubbled up that's what's happening here
in the middle implicitly I'm always
going from left to right but remember
that even when I screwed up at the end
and the last two people were out of
order I do always need to restart at the
beginning because the big numbers are
going that way and the small numbers are
coming this
way so that is true there are some
slight optimizations that I'm kind of
glossing over here let me stipulate that
it would still end up being on the order
of n squ but that would definitely shave
off some actual running time here but
what if the list is already sorted our
our pseudo code at the moment has no
allowance for if list is already sorted
quit early so we're going to blindly do
n minus one Things N minus one times
unless we modify our pseudo code as I
did verbally earlier I propose this
inside of that outer loop if you make a
pass across all of the volunteers and
your mental counter has made no swaps
you have to keep track with some kind of
variable well then you might as well
stop because if you do a whole pass and
make no swaps why would you waste time
doing it again expecting different
Behavior so to help visualize these
whereby now bubble sort can be
advantageous if the data is already
sorted or mostly sorted why because it
does have this short circuit detail at
least if we implement it like that how
can we go about um visualizing these
things a little more clearly well let me
go ahead and do this let me pull up here
a visualization of exactly these
algorithms thanks to a third party tool
here that's going to help us visualize
these sorting algorithms as follows
small bars represent small numbers big
bars represent big numbers and so the
idea now is when I hit a button here to
get all of the small bars this way all
of the big bars this way so just like
our volunteers but instead of holding
lighted numbers its bars representing
their magnitude so let's go ahead and
start with for instance select
sort and you'll see in pink is being
highlighted the current number that is
being selected and then pulled all the
way to the left so this is selection
sort and again it's selecting the next
smallest element but you can see here
all the more visibly that just like my
human feet were taking a lot of steps so
is this algorithm touching these
elements again and again and again and
this is why the N squ is really a thing
there's got to be some inherent
redundancy here like why do we keep
looking at the same darn elements again
and again we do in terms of our pseudo
code need to do so but it's this
redundant comparisons that kind of
explains why n s is indeed the case so
now it's done small bars here big bars
there and I had to just keep talking
there to kill time because it's
relatively slow well let me randomize
the array just so we start with a
different order and now let me click on
bubbl sore and you'll see similar idea
but different algorithm so now the two
bars in pink are the two that are being
compared and fixed potentially if
they're out of order and you can see
already that the biggest bars are
bubbling their way up to the top but now
you can also see like this redundancy
like we keep swooping through the list
again and again just like I kept walking
back and forth and this is n squar this
is not that many bars what 10 20 there's
like 40 or something bars I'm guessing
that's pretty slow already just to sort
40 numbers and I think it's going to get
tedious if I keep talking over this so
let's just assume that this two is
relatively slow had I gotten lucky and
the list were almost sorted already
bubble sort would have been pretty fast
but this was a truly random array so we
did not get lucky so indeed the worst
case might be what's kicking in here so
I don't I feel like it'll be
anticlimactic like holding in a sneeze
if I don't let you see the end of this
so here we go nothing interesting is
about to happen almost
done ah okay done all right so thank you
thank
you so still somewhat slow though how
though can we perhaps do a little better
fundamentally so we can do so if we
introduce yet another technique and this
one isn't so much a function of code as
it is concept and it's something that
you might have seen in the real world um
but perhaps not so obviously so so it
turns out in programming recursion
refers to the ability of a function to
call itself in the world of mathematics
if you have a function f if F appears on
both the left side and the right side of
a formula that would be a recursive
function in the math world too whenever
f is defined in terms of itself or in
our case in Compu in programming anytime
a function calls itself that function is
said to be recursive and this is
actually something we've seen already in
class even though we didn't call it as
much so for instance consider this
pseudo code um from earlier whereby this
was the pseudo code for searching via AR
search a whole bunch of doors if no
doors are left return false that was the
the additional conditional we added but
then if number behind middle door return
true and here's the interesting part if
number is less than middle door search
the left half else if number is greater
than middle door search the right half
this pseudo code earlier was itself
recursive why because here is an
algorithm for searching but what's the
algorithm telling us well on this line
and this line it's telling us to search
something else so even though it's not
explicitly defined in code as having a
name if this is a search algorithm and
yet the search algorithm is using a
search algorithm this pseudo code is
recursive now that could quickly get you
into trouble if a function just calls
itself again and again and again but why
intuitively is it not problematic that
this code this pseudo code calls
itself why will the algorithm still stop
yeah
exactly it has some exit condition like
if no do is less and more more
importantly anytime you search the left
half you're searching a smaller version
of the problem anytime you search the
right half you're searching a smaller
version of the problem literally half
the size so this is why in the phone
book obviously I couldn't tear the phone
book in half uh infinitely many times
because it was literally getting smaller
each time so recursion is this ability
to call yourself if you will it's but
what's important is that you do it on a
small smaller smaller problem so that
eventually you have no more problems to
solve or no more data no more doors at
all so these two lines here would be the
recursive elements here but if we go
back to week zero we could have used
recursion in some other way so this was
our Cudo code for the phone book back in
week zero and recall that we described
these yellow lines as really
representing a loop some kind of cycle
again and again but there was a missed
opportunity here what if I had reinvent
reimplemented this code to do this
instead
instead of saying open to middle of left
half of book and then go back to line
three like literally inducing a loop or
open to Middle right half a book and go
back to line three inducing another loop
why don't I just recognize that what I'm
staring at now is a algorithm for
searching a phone book and if you want
to search a smaller phone book like a
through M or n through Z we'll just use
the same algorithm so I can replace
these yellow lines with just this
casually speaking search left half a
book search right half a book this would
be implicitly and now I can shorten the
whole thing a recursive implementation
of the phone book pseudo code from week
zero and it's recursive because if this
is a search algorithm and you're saying
go search something else that's fine
that's recursive but because you're
searching half of the phone book it's
indeed going to get smaller and smaller
even in the real world or the real
virtual world you can see recursive data
structures in the wild or at least in
Super Mario Brothers like this let me
get rid of all the distractions here and
focus on this pyramid where you have one
block then two then three then four well
this itself is technically recursively
defined in the sense that well what is a
pyramid of height four well it's really
what how would you describe a pyramid of
height four is actually the same thing
as a pyramid
of of of height three plus one
additional layer well what's a pyramid
of height three well it's technically a
pyramid of height two plus one
additional layer and so even physical
structures can be recursive if you can
Define them in terms of itself now at
some point you have to say that if the
pyramid is of height one there's just
one block you can't forever say it's
defined in terms of a height negative 1
negative2 you would never stop so you
have to kind of have a special case
there but let's go ahead and translate
something like this in fact to code let
me go back to uh vs code here and let me
Implement a program called iteration
that refers to a loop iterating and let
me Implement a very simple pyramid like
that so let me go ahead and include the
cs50 library I'll include our standard
i.h in main void no command line
arguments today and let's go ahead and
do this let's declare a variable called
height ask the human for the height of
this pyramid and then let's go ahead and
draw a pyramid of that height now of
course draw does not yet exist so I'm
going to need to invent the draw a
function let me go ahead and Define a
function that doesn't have a return
value it's just going to have side
effects it's just going to print bricks
on the screen call draw and it takes in
an integer n as its input and how am I
going to implement this well again I
want to print one block then two then
three then four that's pretty
straightforward at least once you're
comfortable with loops let me go back to
the code here let me go ahead and say 4
into I gets zero I is less than n i ++
and that's going to iterate essentially
row by row and on each row I want to
print out one then two then three then
four bricks but I'm iterating from Z to
1 to two to three so I think that's okay
I can just say something like 4 in J
gets zero J Let's Be Clever about this
is less than I
j++ and now let me go ahead and inside
of this loop I think I can get away with
just printing out a single hash sign but
then outside of that Loop similar to
last week I'm going to print my new line
separately so a little non-obvious at
first but this outer loop iterates row
by row line by line if you will and then
the inner loop just Mak sure that when I
equals zero um let's see oh nope there's
a bug I need to make sure that it's j is
less than I + 1 so when I is zero on my
first line of output I'm going to print
out one brick when I is one I'm going to
print out two bricks and so forth so let
me go ahead and run make iteration
all right and now seems to compile
uhoh huh implicit Declaration of
function draw so I'm making week one
mistakes
again what say
again yeah the the Prototype is missing
I didn't declare it at the top that's an
easy fix and the only time really it's
okay and necessary to copy paste let me
copy the functions declaration there end
it with a semicolon so that clang now
knows that draw will exist make
iteration now it works thank you /
iteration we'll type in something like
four and there we have it our pyramid of
height 1 2 3 4 that looks pretty similar
to this albeit using hashes so that's
how we would have implemented this like
two weeks ago in week one maybe last
week but just using arrays but let me
propose that we could do something
recursively instead let me close this
version of the code and let me go back
to VSS code and open up recursion doc
just to demonstrate something
recursively and I'll do it incorrectly
deliberately the first time so let me
include cs50.h let me include standard
i.h let me do uh int main void and let
me just blindly draw a pyramid initially
of height one but now in my draw
function let me reimplement it a little
differently so my draw function this
time is still going to take a number n
but that's how many hashes it's going to
print so let's do four into I gets zero
I is less than n i
++ then let's go ahead and print out a
single hash mark here and then after
that let's print out the end of the line
just as before but now this of course is
only going to draw a single um row it's
going to print out one hash or two
hashes or three hashes but only on one
line let me now incorrectly but just
kind of curiously say all right well if
this draws a pyramid of height one let's
just use ourself to draw a pyramid of
height n plus one so the first time I
call draw it will print out one hash
then the second time I call draw it will
print out two hashes then three then
four so we're kind of laying These
Bricks down from top to bottom uh make
recursion uh oops I screwed up again so
let's copy the Prototype here let's put
this down over here semicolon let's do
this again uh make recursion all right
all good/ recursion and now let me
increase the size of my terminal window
just so you can see more of the output
and here we
have okay bad but thank you so we have
an infinitely tall pyramid and it's just
flying across the screen which is why it
looks kind of like a mess but I printed
out a pyramid of height one and then two
and then three and then four and
unfortunately what am I lacking any sort
of quick condition any kind of condition
that says wait a minute when it's too
tall stop all together so this is an
infinite Loop but it's not a loop it's a
recursive call and actually doing this
in en is very bad we'll see next week
that if you call a function too many
times you can actually trigger yet one
yet another of those segmentation faults
cuz you're using too much memory
essentially but for now I haven't
triggered that yet control C is your
friend to cancel and as an aside if
you're playing along at home or play
with this code later I actually cheated
here we have a special clang
configuration feature that prevents you
from calling a function like that and
creating a problem I overrode it just to
for demonstration sake but odds are at
home you wouldn't be able to compile
this code yourself but let me do a
proper version recursively of this code
as follows let me go back into the code
here let me go ahead and not just
blindly start drawing one then two then
three layers of bricks let me prompt the
human as before for the height of the
pyramid they want using our get in
function and now let me call draw of
height again so now I'm going back to
the looplike version but instead of
using a loop now this is where recursion
gets rather elegant if you will let me
go ahead and execute and code uh the
draw function as
follows per your definition if a pyramid
of height four is really just a pyramid
of height three plus another row well
let's take that literally let me go back
to my code and if you want to draw a
pyramid of height four well go right
ahead and draw a pyramid of height uh
three first or more generally n minus
one but what's the second step well once
you've drawn a pyramid of height three
draw an extra row so I at least have to
bite off that part of the problem myself
so let me just do for in I gets zero I
is less than n i++ and let me the
programmer of this function print out my
hashes and then at the very bottom print
out a new line so the cursor moves to
the next line but this is kind of
elegant now I dare say in that draw is
recursive because I'm literally
translating from English to code this
idea that a pyramid of height four is
really just a pyramid of height three so
I do that first and I'm sort of trusting
that this will work then I just have to
lay one more layer of bricks four of
them so if n is four this is just a
simple for Loop Allah week one that will
print out an additional layer but this
of course is going to be problematic
eventually why it's not done yet this
program how many times will draw call
itself in this
model infinitely many times
why yeah there's no there's no
equivalent of quit like if you've
printed enough already then quit well
how do we capture that well I don't
think we want this to go negative right
it would make no sense to draw a
negative height pyramid so I think we
can just pluck off as the programmer a
an easy case an easy answer a so-called
base case and I'm just going to do this
at the top of my draw function let me
just say if n is less than or heck less
than or equal to zero that's it go ahead
and just return there's nothing more to
do and that simple condition technically
known as a base case will ensure that
the code doesn't run forever why well
suppose that draw uh is called with an
argument of four four is of course not
less than zero so we don't return but we
do draw a pyramid of height three and
here's where things get a little
mentally tricky you don't move on to
line 20 until draw has been called so
when draw is called with an argument of
three it's as though you're executing
from the top of this function again
three is not less than zero so what do
you do you draw two okay how do you draw
two well two is not less than zero so
you don't return so you draw one got to
be careful here draw one and now we go
ahead back to the beginning how do you
draw One well one is not less than zero
so you don't return you draw height zero
how do you draw height zero wait a
minute 0o is less than or equal to zero
and you return and so it's kind of like
this mental stack this to-do list you
keep postponing executing these lower
lines of code because you keep
restarting restarting restarting the
draw function until finally one of those
function calls says there's nothing to
do return and now the whole thing starts
to unravel if you will and you pick back
up where you left off and this is
perhaps the best uh scenario we won't do
it in class but if you'd like to wrestle
through this on your own using debug 50
to keep stepping into step into step
into each of those lines logically
you'll see exactly what's actually
happening so let me go to my terminal
and do make recursion which is now this
correct version of the code do/
recursion let's type in a height of four
and voila now we have that same pyramid
not using iteration per se though
admittedly we're using iteration to
print the additional layer we're now
using draw recursively to print all of
the smaller pyramids that need come
before
it no question is can you only use
recursion with a void function no not at
all in fact it's very common to have a
return value like an integer or
something else so that uh you can
actually do something constructively
with that actual value other questions
on
this say a little
lad when is line 21 getting executed so
if you continue to UNR let me uh scroll
down a bit more so you can see the top
of the code so line 21 will be executed
once line 19 is done executing itself
now in the story I told we kept calling
draw again again again but as soon as
one of those function calls where n
equals z returns immediately then we
don't keep drawing again and again so
now if you kind of think of the process
as reversing then you continue to line
21 then a line 21 again then line 21
again and as the sort of logic unravels
and next week we'll actually paint a
picture of what's actually happening in
the computer's memory but for now it's
just it's very similar to the pseudo
code for the phone book you're just
searching again and again but you're
waiting until the very end to get back
the final result uh can Google Now whom
I keep mentioning by coincidence today
is full of programmers of course um
here's a fun exercise let me uh go back
to a browser I'm going to go ahead and
search for recursion because I want to
learn a little something about recursion
uh here is kind of an internet meme or
joke if I zoom in here the engineers at
Google are kind of funny funny see
why ah there we go yes yes this is
recursion and there's going to be so
many memes you'll come across now where
recursion like if you've ever pointed a
camera at the TV that's showing the
camera and you sort of see yourself for
the image again and again that's really
recursion and in that case it only stops
once you hit the base case of a single
Pixel um but this is a very funny joke
in some circles uh when it comes to
recursion uh and Google so how can we
actually use Google or rather how can we
actually use recursion constructively
well let me propose that we actually
introduce a third and final algorithm
for sorting that hopefully does better
than the two sorts thus far we've done
selection sort and bubble sort bubble
sort we liked a little better at least
in so far is in the best case where the
list is already sorted bubble sort is at
least smarter and it will actually
terminate early giving us a better lower
Bound in terms of our Omega notation but
it turns out that recursion and this is
not necessarily a feature of recursion
but something we can now leverage it
turns out using recursion we can take a
fundamentally different approach to
sorting a whole bunch of numbers in such
a way that we can do far fewer
comparisons and ideally speed up our
final results so here is the pseudo code
for what we're about to see for
something called merge sort and it
really is this tur sort the left half of
numbers sort the right half of numbers
merge the sorted halves right this is
almost sort of non sensical because I uh
if you're asked for an algorithm to sort
and you respond with well sort the left
half sort the right half like that's
being sort of difficult because well I'm
asking you for a sorting algorithm
you're just telling me to sort the left
half and the right half but implicit in
that last line merging is a pretty
powerful feature of this sort now we do
need another base case at the top so let
me add this if we find ourselves with a
list an array of size one well that
array is obviously sorted if there's
only one element in it there's no work
to be done so that's going to be our
base case but allowing us now in just
these what uh four six lines of pseudo
code to actually sort some elements but
let's focus first on just a subset of
this let's consider for a moment what it
means to merge sorted have so Carter has
wonderfully come up to volunteer here
just to help us reset these numbers
suppose that in the middle of the story
we're about to tell we have two sorted
halves I've already sorted the left half
of these numbers and indeed 2 4 57 is
sorted from smallest to largest and the
right half appears to be already sorted
0136 already sorted so in my pseudo code
we're already done sorting the left half
and the right half somehow but we'll see
how in a moment well how do I go about
merging these two halves well because
they're sorted already and you want to
merge them in order I think we can flip
down we can hide all but the first
numbers in each of these subl lists so
here we have a half that starts with two
and I don't really care what the other
numbers are because they're clearly
larger than two I can focus only on Two
And Z too zero also we know that zero is
the smallest there so let's just ignore
the numbers that Carter kindly flipped
down so how do I merge these two lists
into a new sorted larger list well I
compare the two on my left with the zero
on my right obviously which comes first
the zero so let me put this down here
and Carter if you want to give us the
next element now I have two sorted
halves but I've already plucked one off
so now I compare the two against the one
one obviously comes next so I'm going to
take out the one and put it in place
here now I'm going to compare the two
halves again two and three which do I
merge first obviously the two comes next
and now notice each time I do this my
hands are theoretically making forward
progress I'm not doubling back like I
kept doing with selection sort or bubble
sort back and forth back and forth my
fingers are constantly advancing forward
and that's going to be a key detail so I
compare four and three three obviously I
compare three and uh I compare four and
six four obviously I compare five five
and six five obviously and then I
compare seven and six six of course and
then lastly we have just one element
left and even though I'm kind of moving
awkwardly as a human my hands
technically were only moving to the
right I was never looping back doing
something again and again and that's
perhaps the intuition and just enough
room for the seven so that then is how
you would merge two sorted halves we
started with left half sorted right half
sorted and merging is just like what you
would do as a human and Carter just
flips the numbers down so our Focus was
only on the smallest elements in each
any questions before we Forge ahead with
what it means then to be merged in this
way so now here is an original list we
deliberately put it at the top because
there's one detail of Mer sort that's
key mer sort is technically going to use
a little more space and so whereas
previously we just kept moving our
humans around and swapping people and
making sure they stayed ultimately in
the original positions with mer sort
pretend ends that here's our original
array of uh memory I'm going to need at
least one other array of memory and I'm
going to cheat and I'm going to use even
more memory but technically I could
actually go back and forth between one
array and a secondary array but it isn't
going to it is going to take me more
space so how do I go about implementing
merge sort on this Al on this code well
let's consider this here's a array of
size eight if only one number quit
obviously not applicable so let's focus
on the juicy part there sort the left
half of the numbers all right how do I
sort the left half of the numbers I'm
going to just nudge them over just to be
clear which is the left half how here is
now a sub list of size four how do I
sort the left
half well do I have an algorithm for
sorting yeah what do I do here's a list
of size four how do I sort it what's
step one sort the left half so I now
sort of conceptually in my mind take
this sublist of size four and I sort it
by first sorting the left half focusing
now on the seven and two all right
here's a list of size two how do I sort
a list of size
two sorry I think we just keep following
our instruction sort the left half all
right here is a list of size one how do
I sort a list of size
one I'm done like it's done so I leave
this alone what was the next step in the
story I've just sorted the left half of
the left half of the left half what
comes next I sort the right half of the
left half of the left half and I'm done
cuz it's just a list of size one what
comes after this merge so this is where
it gets a little trippy because you have
to remember where we're pausing the
story to do things recursively again and
again but if I've just sorted the left
half and I've just sorted the right half
now I merge them together this is a
super short list so we don't need um uh
Carter's help here as before but I think
the first number I take here is the two
and then the second number I take
because it's the only option is the
seven but what's nice now is that notice
the left half of the left half is indeed
sorted because I trivially sorted the
left half of it and the right half of it
but then merging is really where the
magic happens all right again if you rem
if you rewind now in your mind if I've
just sorted the left half of the left
half what happens
next sort the right half of the left
half so again you kind of rewind in time
so how do I do this I've got a list of
size two I sort the left half the just
the five done sort the right half four
done now the interesting part I merge
the left half and the right half of the
right half of the left half so what do I
do four comes down here five comes down
here and
now notice what I have left half is
sorted right half is sorted if you
rewind in time where is my next step
three merge the two halves and so this
is what Carter helped me do before let's
focus only on the smallest elements just
so there's less distraction I compare
the two and the four two comes first so
let's obviously put that here now I
compare the new beginning of this list
and the old beginning of this list four
obviously comes next and now I compare
the seven against the five five
obviously comes next and now lastly I'm
left with one number so now I'm down to
the seven so even if you've kind of lost
track of some of the nuances here if you
just kind of take a step back we have
the original right half here still
untouched but the left half of the
original input is now indeed sorted all
by way of doing sorting left half right
half left half right half but with those
merges in between all right so if we've
just sorted the left half we rewind all
the way to the beginning what do I now
do all right so sort the right half so
sort the right half how do I sort a list
of size four well I first sort the left
half the one and the six how do I sort a
list of size two you sort the left half
just the number one obviously there's no
work to be done done sorting the left
half six done sorting the right half now
what do I do I merge the left half here
with the right half here and that one's
pretty straightforward now what do I do
I've just merged so now I sorted I've
just sorted the left half of the right
half so now I sort the right half of the
right half so I consider the zero done I
consider the three done I now merge
these two together zero of course comes
first then comes the three and now I'm
at the point of the story where I've
sorted the left half of the right half
and the right half of the right half so
step three is merge and I'll do it again
like we did with Carter all right one
and zero obviously the zero comes first
now compare the one and the three
obviously the one comes first compare
the six and the three obviously the
three and then lastly the sixth so now
where are we we've taken the left half
of the whole thing and sorted the left
and sorted it we then took the right
half of the whole thing and sorted it so
now we're at lastly step three for the
last last time what do we do merge and
so just to be consistent let me push
these down and let's compare left hand
to right hand noticing that they only
make forward progress none of this back
and forth comparisons two and zero of
course the zero so we'll put that in
place two and one of course the one so
we put that in place two and three we
merge in of course the two in this case
four and three we now merge in the three
in this case four and six we now merge
of course the four in place and now we
compare five and six we keep the
five
bug okay well pretend that the five is
on uh oh this is why all right so now we
compare the seven and the six sixth is
gone and lastly seven is the last one in
place and even though I grant that of
all the algorithms this is probably the
hardest one to stay on top of especially
when I'm doing it as a voiceover realize
that what we've just done is only those
three steps recursively we started with
a list of size eight we sorted the left
half we sorted the right half and then
we merged the two together but if you go
down each of those rabbit holes so to
speak sorting the left half involves
sorting the left half of the left half
and the right half of the left half and
so forth but this germ of an idea of
really dividing and conquering the
problem not such that you're having the
problem and only dealing with one half
clearly we're sorting one half and the
other half and merging them together
ultimately it does still lead us to the
same solution and if we visualize the
remnants of this now if I depict this as
follows where on the screen here you see
where the numbers originally started in
the top row from left to right
essentially even though this is in a
different order I divided that list of
size eight ultimately into eight lists
of size one and that's where the base
case kicked in and just said okay we're
done sorting that and after that
logically I then sorted I merged two
lists of size one into many lists of
size two and those lists of size two
into lists of size four and then finally
the list of size four into one big list
sorted of size eight and so I put forth
this picture with the little line
indicators here because how many times
did I divide divide divide in half or
really double double double so exponent
is the opposite oh spoiler uh how many
times did I divide so three concretely
but if there's eight elements total and
there's N More generally it really is a
matter of dividing and conquering login
times you start this and you can divide
one two three times login times or
conversely you can start here and
exponentially uh double double double
three times which is log n but on every
row every shelf literally I made a fuss
about pointing my hands only from the
left to the right constantly advancing
them such that every time I did those
merges I touched every element once and
only once there was none of this back
and forth back and forth on stage so if
I'm doing something log n times if I'm
doing rather N Things log n times what
would be our Big O formula perhaps N
Things log n
times yeah so n log n the order of n log
n is indeed how we would describe the
running time of merge sort and so of all
of the sorts thus far we've seen that
merge sort here actually is n log n
which is strictly better than n squ
which is where both merge uh both
selection sort and bubble sort landed
but it's also slower than linear search
for instance but you would rather expect
that if you have to do a lot of work up
front sorting some elements versus just
searching them you're going to have to
put in more effort and so the question
of whether or not you should just search
something blindly with linear search and
not bother sorting it really boils down
to can you afford to spend this amount
of time and if you're the Googles of the
world odds are you don't want to be
searching their database linearly every
time why because you can sort it once
and then benefit millions billions of
people subsequently using something like
binary search or frankly in practice
something even fancier and faster than
binary search but there's always going
to be this tradeoff you can achieve
binary search only if the elements are
sorted how much does it cost you to sort
them well maybe N squared if you use
some of the earlier algorithms but it
turns out n log n is pretty fast as well
so at the end of the day
these running times involve tradeoffs
and indeed in merge sort 2 I should note
that the lower bound on merge sort is
also going to be Omega of n log n as
such we can describe it in terms of our
Theta notation saying that merge short
is indeed in Theta of n log n so
generally speaking probably better to
use something like merge sort or some
other algorithm that's in N log n in
practice most programmers are not
implementing these sorting algorithms
themselves odds are they're using a
library off the shelf that themselves
have made the decision as to which of
these algorithms to do but generally
speaking and we're seeing now this for
the first time if you want to improve
time like use less time write faster
code you got to pay a price and that
might be your human time just takes you
more time to code up something more
sophisticated more difficult to
implement or you need to spend something
like space and as these shelves suggest
that too is one of the key details of
merge sort you can't just have the
elements swapping in place you need at
least an auxiliary array so that when
you do the merging you have a place to
put them and this is excessive this
amount of memory I could have just gone
back and forth between top shelf and
bottom shelf but it's a little more
interesting to go top down but you do
need more space back in the day decades
ago space was really expensive and so
you know what it might have been better
to not use merge sort use bubble sort or
uh selection sort even or some other
algorithm alog together nowadays space
is relatively cheap and so these are
more acceptable trade-offs but it
totally depends on the application the
very last thing we thought we'd do is
show you an actual compar comparison of
some of these sorting algorithms it's
about 60 seconds long and it will
compare for you uh selection sort bubble
sort and merge sort in parallel
simultaneously uh with some fun sorting
music showing you ultimately what it
really means to be an O of n s or better
yet Big O of n
Logan selection on the top bubble on the
bottom merge in the
[Music]
middle
[Applause]
[Music]
all right that's it for cs50 we'll see
you next
[Music]
time
e
[Music]
all right this is cs50 and this is week
four and if you think back a few weeks
ago already in week zero we started
talking about like what images are and
we talked about representation of images
as this grid of pixels and each pixel
has like some pattern of bits that
defines its color well it turns out
today we'll take a deeper look
underneath the hood at how things like
images and so much more is actually
implemented using just these zeros and
ones and how now as a programmer you can
actually harness that for better for
worse to better understand and better
manipulate what's going on inside of a
computer's memory using a language like
C in fact even this bowl of stress balls
that we keep happening is just a
photograph of course but if you think
back to week zero if you sort of enhance
enhance enhance this image like they do
in the movies it actually doesn't work
out the way you would think from
Hollywood as I keep continue to zoom in
and zoom in and zoom in on a screen like
this you'll see that yes it gets bigger
but if it gets too big what do you start
to notice the so-called pixelation and
indeed you can see the individual dots
so next time you watch some uh show or
movie on uh TV that has this sort of
notion of enhancing you know there's
actually a finite limit there you can
only enhance so far as there's actually
information there but once you zoom in
to a certain level like this like that's
all that there you're not going to see
the glint of the suspect in some crime
drama in their eye just because you've
enhanced the image there's only a finite
amount of information actually there but
we'll see today too that by
understanding what's going on inside of
a computer's memory we can start to
represent and even create and code more
interesting things so for instance here
is a bit map if you will which is a term
of art a bit map is a type of image and
it's a map of bits in the sense that you
have this coordinate system of up top
down left right at least in this artist
representation here and suppose that
maybe we all defi decide as a as as the
world that one shall represent the color
white and zero shall represent the color
black what might this map of bits this
bit map actually be can you see through
it yeah it is indeed a smiley face so an
amazing eye if I actually turn all of
the ones to White just to visualize this
you'll see indeed this is what was
embedded there but of course on our
computer monitors and phones we have
this grid of square is this grid of
pixels so indeed if you were to actually
see on your screen a smiley face like a
black and white one at that what's
probably going on underneath the hood is
just some pattern of zeros and ones and
maybe single bits one bit color if you
will where one here represents white and
zero represents black so if you kind of
like this thing it turns out you can do
pretty uh pretty beautiful pretty
interesting pretty artistically inclined
things if you go to this URL at your
leisure cs50. lart it'll actually
redirect you to a Google spreadsheet
that we've made in advance and we've
kind of Shrunk the rows and columns to
resemble a grid of pixels tiny little
squares all of which are white by
default not unlike this easel here that
we have a couple of volunteers working
away at in fact would you guys like to
come forward for a moment and say a
quick hello before we come back to you
uh hello my name is Daniel I'm from
Chicago welcome to Daniel and hi
everyone I'm Adam and I'm from chindon
Tobago nice well welcome to you both
thank you you'll see that in their hands
are actually a whole bunch of pixels uh
Post-it notes that we've handed them in
in advance so if you don't mind we'll
come back to you in a couple of minutes
and see what they've created if you will
on this grid of white paper much like
you could create on this Google
spreadsheet in fact feel free to send us
your Creations if so inclined uh via the
URL you'll get at cs50. lart now let's
come back to week zero where we Define
some of the building blocks for images
we talked about RGB which is just red
green blue and it's just one of the
systems a popular system via which you
can represent any color of the rainbow
using some combination of red and green
and blue and if any of you are
artistically inclined or have used
Photoshop or similar programs you might
typically have some means of selecting a
color by some grid like this but down
here notice there's explicit mentions of
the types of color systems in use R GB
and in fact here you see 0000 0 and up
here under new you see the color black
and that implies that if you have no red
no green no blue well that indeed would
represent by convention the color black
by contrast if we play around with
Photoshop or similar program if you have
a lot of red a lot of green and a lot of
blue for instance 255 255 255 like
really crank it up to the max value you
can represent with eight bits per week
zero well then it turns out you get the
color white here and we can play with
these numbers endlessly for instance if
we use 255 of red but zero green and
zero blue not surprisingly the square at
the top of the screen Becomes Of course
red entirely because it's all red and no
green no blue if we change it instead to
255 for green but zero for red and blue
of course we get green and then lastly
if we crank up the blue but leave red
and green as zero we of course get blue
but all this while down here highlighted
is something that maybe some of you have
seen before like some combination of
numbers and letters if any of you have
made personal web pages or use programs
like Photoshop you might have used these
so-called color codes so indeed the
world has this convention whereby using
six digits or sometimes three you can
represent a little more succinctly some
amount of red green blue and you'll see
here maybe by inference that if RGB is0
0 255 respectively perhaps where we're
going with this is that
0000 FF is just an alternative way of
expressing the exact same idea no red no
green and a lot of blue but why is that
and in fact we'll come full circle here
to introducing something that we could
have done in week zero but it doesn't
really solve a problem then but today as
we focus more on images and on memory
itself turns out understanding these
patterns is pretty useful so back in
week zero we talked of course about
binary and binary by implying two only
gives you two digits zero and one you
and I as humans almost always use the
decimal system in normal conversation
deck meaning 10 so we have 0 through n
instead if a human like us wants to
count up as high as 10 or 11 or 12 we
don't have a digit per se for 10 11 and
12 we start reusing digits so it's 1 0 1
1 1 2 and so forth but in other systems
not binary not decimal but systems
called heximal hex implying 16 there are
actually more digits than these which
might come as a surprise um it's not
pairs of digits like in decimal single
digits and frankly it doesn't really
matter what the digits are because at
the end of the day these are just
symbols that you and I immediately
associate with some notion of math but
just Strokes on the screen that
represent some have represent some
actual value so it turns out that by
convention
when you want more than n 10 digits 0
through 9 you start using letters of the
English alphabet A B C D E and F and you
can represent them in lower case it's
case insensitive so it doesn't really
matter you might see it in upper case or
lower case but this is how you can count
Beyond N9 not using decimal but using
indeed something called hexadecimal if
we get really technical this is also
known as base 16 and it's the same idea
as week zero where instead of using base
2 for binary base 10 for decimal use 16
as the base for heximal and so if we run
through just some simple examples here
in the world of heximal your columns are
just powers of 16 16 to the 0er 16 to
the 1 16 to the 2 and so forth but in
the world of hex we usually at least
thus far and today we'll see just pairs
of digits like this so here for instance
is the ones column and the 16's column
if we multiply that out so if you wanted
to represent the number you and I know
in in uh the real world as zero in
heximal it would just be 0 0 if you want
to represent the number one it would be
01 and from there we get 02 03 04 0 five
06 07 08 09 now things get potentially
interesting in decimal it would
obviously become 10 but in heximal it
just becomes 0 a and then 0 B which is
to say if I rewind after nine comes in
heximal if I pronounce it in in decimal
this is how you'd represent 10 this is
how you'd represent 11 12 13 14 and then
lastly in heximal the 16th value is f
which is just always going to represent
15 so where to how do we connect this to
some of the past math well once you get
to Zer F in heximal if f is the highest
you can count just like in decimal nine
is the highest you can count what comes
next if this is 15 I claim how do I
represent 16 in heximal with what
pattern of
symbols what pattern of symbols for
heximal yeah so one Z not 10 even though
you might read it like that as a typical
human but one zero because why well even
if this is completely new to you the
whole column system the places are
exactly the same intuitively so you need
a one in the 16's place and a zero in
the ones place and we won't count all
the way up to 255 but we count if we
count a little higher this would be 1 Z
AKA 16 in decimal this would be 1 one
AKA 17 in decimal and then 18 19 20 and
so forth dot dot dot and we can count
all the way up to FF CU if f is the
biggest digit in hexadecimal FF is
indeed as high as we can count and if
each F represents 15 well let's just do
the math like in week zero so 16 * F + 1
* f is how all of us learned to do uh
math in grade school even though not in
heximal that's of course 16 * 15 + 1 *
15 multiply that out you get 240 plus 15
and air go you can count as high as
255 using two heximal digits now this is
not the kind of thing where like this is
going to be an interesting exercise
mentally to ever convert in your head
generally you'll get used to the fact
that after nine comes a and the biggest
digit is f and you'll just start to see
patterns like this in the worlds of
Photoshop web pages in a few weeks and
Beyond but like why is heximal useful
like why are we complicating the world
and adding on top of decimal something
else well it turns out that a single
decimal digit like f the biggest one for
instance is 15 and here let me just
propose a bit of Mental Math how many
bits do you need to represent the number
15 in binary if you've got the ones
place two's Place fours and so forth how
many bits
total so fewer than five to count this
highest 15 I think but
close someone
else sing in hand yeah so four bits I
think suffice because if you want to
count as high as F that is to say 15 I
think if you have four bits you can do
that because if over here is the one's
place from week zero for binary this is
the two's place this is The Four's place
this is the e place do out some quick
math so 8 + 4 is 12 + 2 is 14 + 1 is 15
so it turns out that by convenience
heximal digits can just be represented
consistently with four bits or fewer but
four and four of course is half of eight
and eight is like everywhere like eight
bits is a bite which is again just a
convention we've seen and so the reason
that you see hexad desmal in the world
of Photoshop and eventually web pages is
it actually just Maps really nicely to
expressing binary numbers more
succinctly with a fixed number of digits
so for instance anytime you see 11 one
one one 1111 in the world as binary you
know what that's a little tedious to
both say and write you can represent
more succinctly
any uh group of four one bits more
succinctly in heximal as just F so 111
1111 in binary more succinctly and more
commonly now in the world of Photoshop
memory images and the like is
represented more succinctly as FF and
that's why because it just Maps really
nicely to four bits and so we can be a
little more succinct so any questions on
heximal which is just another way of
representing information but using the
same grade school approach yeah good
question if you represent 15 with f it
would use four bits so base systems are
really just a way for us humans on paper
or on screens to represent information
if F represents the decimal number 15
the computer underneath the hood has to
use four bits to represent it so one
heximal digit by convention always
implies four bits underneath the hood so
therefore if you have two heximal digits
like 0 0 that means eight zero bits
underneath the hood like for red or for
green if you see FF now we know that's
four one bits and another four one Bits
And if we do out the math that's 255
that's why in Photoshop
000000 FF means no red no green and
255 of blue and it's just way more
succinct than writing out like what 8
plus 8 plus 8 24 zeros and ones and it's
just cleaner than even using decimal
when you're using units of eight which
again computers just use everywhere so
it's just another system it's not one
you need to dwell on very much but again
it's fundamentally no different from
binary or decimal we're just using a
slightly different base no all right
well we had this blank canvas here and I
think uh are you two perhaps ready to
reveal for the world what you've created
do you want to go ahead and I'll I'll
swivel it around for you all right here
we go big reveal and today's pixel
art a round of applause if we
could very nicely done well thank you
both if you want to come up after and
tear this off and bring it home you're
welcome to and keep the Post-it notes
too well thank you to our volunteers
there let's now translate this to really
more technical worlds where we're going
to see and consider it more often
because in fact sometimes when you've
had error messages over the past few
weeks from clang the compiler you might
have even seen evidence of heximal we
didn't call it out it wasn't useful to
know at the time but it turns out a lot
of programs use and a lot of code uses
heximal for those reasons of more prec
more representation so for instance
where else might we see it well here's
that picture we keep pulling up of our
computer's memory and each of these
squares in this grid represents a bite
sort of top left to bottom right in the
computer's memory but again just an
artist's representation a few weeks ago
I claimed that each of these bytes can
be numbered of course like this is bite
zero at top left then bite one then bite
two then bite two billion if you have
two gigabytes of memory and so we could
just number them like this 0 through 15
on up 16 17 18 and so forth but per the
reasons earlier it's just more common in
computer systems and in software to
actually use hexadecimal just to
describe the locations of the addresses
of things in memory so instead a typical
programmer or computer scientist would
call these first 16 bytes 0 through F
just because but that's because it's a
predictable number of bits so if we keep
going beyond that you would get not 10
not 11 not 12 but in heximal 1 0 1 1 1 2
and so forth all the way down on the
screen to 1 F and if I you know shrunk
this down or had a bigger monitor we
would see eventually 255 bytes later
from the start 255 as well but there's a
potential problem here with using
heximal in this way there's an
ambiguity can anyone imagine like what
can go wrong if we use hex to just
simply describe locations in memory like
this
yeah yeah yeah like one zero might also
be 10 and you know maybe if you're you
know really thorough okay wait a minute
it can't be 10 cuz here's F over here so
it's obviously not decimal but why
create potential confusion especially
when you're collaborating building
something with someone we want to avoid
that ambiguity and so the convention
humans decided on years ago is that if
you want to make clear that a number is
in hexadecimal just by convention you
prefix all of the digits with Zer X the
X is not like another character it's not
like a 17th character it's just a human
conven
of putting 0x to imply here comes
heximal and now it's unambiguous so now
we see 0x10 obviously is not 10 as we
know it in decimal but rather it's the
number that comes after a single F so
it's really the number in decimal 16 so
0x anytime you see it that's just a
visual cue that what is ahead is
actually heximal so let's now start
playing around with this information so
here's a super simple line of code from
like week one where I'm just declaring
ing a variable n and I'm defining it to
be the value 50 and this is out of
context we probably need a main function
and all of that but let's just rewind to
week one where we actually saw code like
this and do something useful with a line
of code like this so let me go over here
to VSS code and in vs code I'll create a
program called how about addresses since
the goal of this uh the goal here is to
just play around ultimately with a
variable like n and let me go ahead and
do this I'll include how about standard
i.h I'll do int main void so no command
line Arguments for now in N gets 50 and
now so that we can do something mildly
useful with it let's just go use print F
and print out with percent I and then a
new line whatever that value of n is so
this is not going to be interesting per
se it's just week one stuff where I'm
defining a variable and printing it out
to the screen so let me go down to my
terminal window and do make
addresses no errors so that's good I'll
do do/ addresses and of course I should
see the number 50 here now what's going
on underneath the hood let's translate
now code to really what's going on under
under underneath the hood of the
computer so if this is our grid of
memory I don't necessarily know as the
programmer and I definitely don't care
as the programmer where exactly it's
ending up in memory that's the whole
point of using Code let the computer
figure this out but at least
conceptually I know that by declaring a
line of code like that the number 50
ends up somewhere in the computer's
memory and it's assigned the name n a
symbol n via which I the programmer can
refer to it and I very deliberately used
four of these squares for what
reason what might be the reason for
using four squares specifically yeah
yeah so an integer is four bytes at
least most of the time on Modern systems
an integer is four bytes on an older
computer it might just use one or maybe
even uh two bytes But Here by convention
we're almost always going to see four
bytes I don't know if it's going to end
up here it might end up over here but
for now who cares I just know that the
computer can store the the information
in this way underneath the hood so let's
now introduce another feature of C that
we haven't had occasion to use just yet
that's going to allow us to start poking
around the computer's memory For Better
or For Worse and this is one of those
situations where you're about to learn
acquire a a skill a power that can
actually come back to bite you because
once you know how to start poking around
a computer's memory you can do very
powerful things and next week we'll see
what you can build in a computer's
memory but you can also screw up pretty
easily and cause more of those
segmentation faults that a few of you
have already suffered so with that said
let's just stipulate that you know what
I don't care necessarily where the 50 is
in memory but I know it exists at some
address in memory and just so I have an
easy address to pronounce let's just
suppose it lives at ox123 so that's the
address in memory in heximal by
convention and that just happens to be
where it ends up when I write that line
of code but it turns out C has some
other operators we can use when we've
seen the asterisk before the star and
we've used it for multiplication but
today we're going to use it for
something more powerful and we're also
going to introduce an Amper sand which
allows us to do something as well the
Amper sand operator is going to allow us
to get the address of a piece of data in
memory like by literally putting
Ampersand before the name of a variable
C will tell us tell you what address
that variable lives at maybe it's ox123
maybe it's Ox 456 who knows but that
will give you back the answer the Star
does the opposite it's sort of means go
there so using the star otherwise known
as the D reference operator I can
actually go to a specific address if I
want and we'll see what this means in
code so how can I leverage this in some
mildly interesting way to start poking
around but eventually we'll use this
primitive to build more interesting
things so let me go back to save vs code
here and let me go ahead and do this
I'll clear my terminal to start fresh
and I'll introduce another format code
for printf percent p and for now just
take on faith that this it is percent P
because but percent p is going to allow
me to print the address of a variable if
I additionally tell C get the address of
n so I'm changing percent I to percent p
and that's just something you have to do
when printing addresses for now but I
need to change an ampersand in front of
the variable name so I don't print in
the number 50 I print out something like
ox123 and it's not going to be as simple
as that we'll see on the screen though
where it actually ended up in my code
spaces memory so here we go uh dot uh
down in my terminal make addresses again
to recompile and now dot SL addresses
should reveal not the value of 50 but
the address of 50 and there it is it's
pretty long it's not quite as simple and
pretty as ox123 but there's the ox
meaning here's a hexadecimal address and
it's 7f FC c784 a04 C suffice it to say
your codes space and even your Macs and
PCs nowadays have a lot of memory that's
why in part this address is so big not
as small as the thing on my slide so
this at the moment isn't that useful yet
but it introduces us to a concept that
we'll Now call pointers and pointers are
admittedly one of the more challenging
aspects of c and if in future life you
tell friends that oh I took a class
called cs50 and we learned C like you'll
probably get kind of a look at people
like why did you learn C or like oh c
was hard and it's largely because of
this topic which isn't to say that it's
that hard to wrap your mind around but
it's definitely very different and it's
not a feature that you can harness in
higher level languages that we'll see in
class two like Python and Java and the
like C is about as close to the
computer's Hardware so to speak that you
can get before things get actually scary
the so-called Assembly Language we saw
in week two when I had a link and
compile and assemble and all of that
like that gets really lowlevel and you
really have to be an expert with the
computer's CPU or brain to understand
that but with C you can actually poke
around the computer's memory and do
powerful things with that but again with
great power comes responsibility it's
very easy to break programs by misusing
memory or just having a bug that touches
memory in some way that you don't intend
so pointers at the end of the day are
pretty much what we just saw a pointer
is really just a variable that contains
the address of some value a pointer is a
variable that contains the address of
some value or more simply it's fine to
think of it as an address a pointer is
an address of something in the
computer's memory now what might we do
to uh to uh actualize this well here's
two lines of code it turns out by using
our two new operators today I can
declare an INT call it n and assign it a
value like 50 just like before if I want
to store the address of n in a variable
and not just print it immediately via
printf I can declare a variable for
instance called P but I could call it
anything I want like any variable but
because it's an address it's not int P
it has to be int star P so to speak and
the star here on the left hand side of
the equal sign is just a clue to C that
means p is going to be a pointer that is
p is going to be the address of what the
address of an integer now technically
it's still an integer itself right
because an address is just a number
whether it's 1 2 3 or ox123 so this is
really just a semantic difference so in
Star p just means that this variable
doesn't contain any old number like 50
it specifically contains a number that
is the address of something
else so how can I now use this well let
me go back to VSS code and let me
propose that we add a line of code like
that so instead of just directly
printing out that value let's go ahead
and Define a second variable called uh P
that's of type in Star P set it equal to
Ampersand n and then this time let's not
just print out Amper sand n let's
actually print out the value of P so the
only two new things here if I zoom in
are I've used not only the Amper sand on
the right to get the address of n I'm
now using the star on the Left To Tell C
that P is still a still a variable as
always but it's a pointer it is the
address of some other value like this
and I'm still going to print it with the
same format code percent P so that
doesn't change so let me go ahead and
zoom out and do make addresses and slash
addresses and there it is exactly the
same thing now in and of itself not that
useful yet but the fact that you can now
access the addresses of things in memory
means that we'll be able to build things
and construct things and Link things
together by knowing where they live so
to speak so any questions on this
technique thus far
[Music]
yeah a good question on line six must it
be starp and Ampersand and in this case
yes because what am I doing on the left
and I'll get rid of the equal sign for
now this would give me a variable called
P that's not an integer per se but
that's the address of an integer but
without the equal sign I'm not storing
anything in that variable so by adding
the equal sign and then Ampersand N I am
explicitly figuring out with Ampersand
what the address of n is which already
exists per line five and tucking it away
in this new variable called
P other questions yeah every time you
run good question every time I run the
program it uses up a different piece of
memory short answer yes computers though
long story short also have something
called virtual memory so if you run it
again and again you might actually see
the same addresses on the same Mac or PC
or cloud-based server but we'll see in a
bit where uh at a high level it's laid
out but it will always exist at some
address good question yeah some correct
Ampersand n is the address of N and in
Star p
is a pointer called p and honestly in an
Ideal World if C were made today and not
decades ago when humans were first
creating languages you know ideally we
would just have a data type called
pointer and then this would be a little
less complicated because it would
literally be what it says you know the
humans who invented SE didn't do this
but this is the idea so pointer is not a
legitimate word in the code it is a term
of Art in English but this is really
just the idea but the way you express
pointer as a data type type is a little
more cryptic as int star P here but
notice in line seven when I print out p
i don't use a star I don't use an
ampersand y I literally just want to
print the value of p and we've been
doing that since week one if you want to
print a variable just describe the
variable by its name no special syntax
any other questions on this thus
far uh what's the advantage of using
pointers with pointers we'll see today
some applications of them really the
idea is going to come to fruition next
week when we're going to create what are
called uh data structures in memory
where we can build not just uh for
instance uh one-dimensional data
structures like an array we'll see next
week we can actually create the
equivalent of two-dimensional data
structures or even threedimensional data
structures by using these addresses and
sort of linking things together and
we'll see the beginnings of that this
week but for now focus at least for now
on just really the syntax and what these
building blocks can do for us um does
the poin have to be does the p uh in
does the pop pointer have to be an point
to an integer short answer no and we'll
come back to this for now for the sake
of discussion we're only dealing with
integers like the number 50 uh you
mentioned strings or characters
absolutely we're about to go there soon
so you can use the address of anything
you want in the computer's memory so in
fact let's translate this now to just
the same picture just to help you wrap
your minds around what these two lines
of code really fundamentally are doing
so if I come back to my grid of memory
here let's plop the number 50 in the
variable n at the bottom right like it
was before so this is that first line of
code as before but with the new second
line of code as soon as I create P what
do I do well first remember that n lives
somewhere in the computer's memory
usually I don't care precisely where it
is but for the sake of discussion let's
suppose it's at ox123 which is easier to
say than where it actually ended up and
now what is p well p is just another
variable and variables live in memory
too so let me just hypothesize that P
lives up here and it turns out that P
once you assign it the value of
Ampersand N means that c will take a
look at the variable n realize oh it
lives at ox123 and what goes in the
value of p is literally
ox123 so again it's still an integer
which is confusing but it's technically
an integer being used as an address and
now just a a prompt here notice that
this pointer is pretty darn big it's
like eight squares what's the
implication of that because I did that
deliberately
how big must a pointer apparently be in
most modern systems would you say okay
good computers today are very big you
have gigabytes of RAM in your computer
you therefore need big pointers to be
able to point at memory that's
conceptually pretty far away so to be
clear how many bytes does a pointer
apparently take up well it seems to take
up eight in total integers by convention
nowadays are usually four pointers
though nowadays are typically eight in
this case so I'm drawing it in a manner
consistent with the reality even though
at the end of the day it's not really
that interesting what values are in here
in fact let's emerge from these weeds I
don't really care what else is going on
in my computer's memory at the moment
because I've only got those two lines of
Juicy code defining n and defining P so
let's hide all of the other squares and
honestly I mean it when I say that
programmers need to know that a variable
exists somewhere in memory and needs to
be able to get that address using like
the Ampersand but you're never going to
print F like I did the actual address
like it's not generally interesting
unless you're debugging your code but
you're not going to like start typing
out crazy Ox numbers in your code to
move things around you just need to know
that the computer can figure out where
things are so frankly by that logic who
cares that it's ox123 right tomorrow it
could be Ox 456 or something else so one
of the ways to think of a pointer is
literally as a variable that points at
something else and indeed in this case P
yeah technically it has an address and
yeah technically it's ox123 in the story
but honestly who cares I just need to
know that you using p i can get to the
value n and so what are these addresses
and in fact if Carter wouldn't mind
joining me up here for a moment what are
these addresses well just like in our
human world we have mailboxes even
though you might not check it very
frequently nowadays but to get physical
mail every uh home every business has a
unique address the uh science and
engineering complex is 150 Western
Avenue Austin Massachusetts 02134 USA
and theoretically that uniquely
identifies that building in the world
well here we we have two mailboxes um
over here we have a value n that happens
to live I'll claim it address ox123 and
then over here I claim there's another
address uh called by name p i don't
actually care where it is even though it
definitely exists somewhere in the
computer's memory but if this is p which
is a variable and that's n another
variable ideally this mailbox would be
twice as big because of the number of
btes using but Home Depot only had
identical size mailboxes but here is p
one variable there is in another
variable if I open up this mailbox what
should I find inside of it based on our
story thus far like what value will I
pull out dramatically in just a
moment yeah I think ox1 123 Now using
this you can kind of think of this as
like x marks the spot no pun intended
where I can now like walk around the
computer's memory and find my way to
that location by sort of following the
treasure map or if I want it more
dramatically uh thanks to our little
Yale foam finger here here you can think
of it more abstractly as p is just
pointing at n okay that's not going over
well so let's switch over to the Harvard
one so p is
pointing so p is pointing at n and so it
turns out we will be able to write code
now that will do the equivalent of me
walking over to n but for now Carter if
you want to reveal what's in the mailbox
we should see indeed the number 50 so
that's really all that's oh I feel
Carter's waiting for Applause so like
really well nicely done
thank you so that's just like a physical
metaphor of what's going on here in one
variable we have an address and that
variable by convention is called a
pointer in the other variable per week
one we just have a value like n and you
can yes follow the map and walk yourself
to that particular address and we'll see
how to do that in code but what's really
interesting is this abstraction that
pointers literally or really I guess
figuratively point at some other value
in memory all right questions then on
pointers in this form pointers point to
each other can pointers point to each
other so yes there's things called
double pointers we're not going to see
them anytime soon but using star star
you can express an address of an address
um but we won't see that just yet other
questions on
pointers yeah in
front our array so to summarize our
arrays then pointers so short answer
there's a relationship and we'll come
back to that in a little bit but arrays
are technically different from pointers
but we we're going to be able to blur
the lines a little bit by using one like
the other but let me come back to that
in just a bit of time all right so if we
have now this mental model if you will
of like what a pointer is in memory I
think we can start to peel back a layer
of uh simplification that we've been
assuming for the past few weeks since
week one so a string recall is a
sequence of characters and so if you
want to create a string that says Hi in
all caps and an next exclamation point
we do string s equals quote unquote high
and we can hard code it like this or we
could use get string but for now just
assume that I hardcoded it into my code
to always say hi in all caps with an
exclamation point well what does that
look like in the computer's memory well
let's stop looking at the entire memory
let's just focus on really what's going
on once you create a string called s and
store in it hi you know that a couple of
things are happening H and I and the
exclamation point are ending up in the
computer's memory we know from week two
that this thing the so-called null
character n AKA back slz is also being
added for you and it's somewhere in
memory at the moment I don't really care
where I drew it at the bottom right yes
it has an address but for now it just
ends up somewhere and in fact here's a
little visual cue as to how this happens
in C anytime you use double quotes to
give you a string you can imagine that
the double quotes are like a a clue to
not only store Hi exclamation point but
also put the null character there for
you and this is in contrast to what
chars if you want individual characters
what syntax did we use
instead so single quotes single quotes
do not add magically a back SL zero they
literally just store one character so
again strings have always been a little
special you get some extra an extra bite
for free so that you know where the
string ends and functions like stir
compare can then find their way there so
in memory it might indeed look a little
like this and if we assume that there's
going to be somewhere in memory these
things are going to be somewhere in
memory we can address them per week two
by way of the name of the variable so if
s is the name of the variable S braet 0
is how you would refer to the first
letter s bracket 1 s braet two and if
you really want s bracket 3 would get
you at the uh null character at the very
end but what is s so technically in this
line of code here not only is the
computer giving you memory for h i
exclamation point back sl0 we turns out
that s itself must take up some amount
of space right because s is the variable
and every time we' talked about
variables thus far I've given you a
rectangle on the screen in which to
store its value so let's assume for the
sake of discussion that the H is at
ox123 and I is at o x124 exclamation
points at o x125 and the null characters
at ox1 126 well what then is s well s is
just going to be some other variable and
I'll draw it somewhat abstractly without
all the other boxes up here and I'll
claim that the name of this variable is
s but it turns out what is s really how
do strings Really Work Well s is a
variable and has been since week one but
when you define it what the computer is
doing for you automatically is when it
knows you want to store Hi exclamation
point it puts that somewhere in memory
the computer then figures out for you
what's the address of the very first
character and it stores that address and
only that address in the variable you
created on the left hand side of the
equal sign and that's enough like to
represent a string with three letters of
the alph alphabet or punctuation you
don't need three variables you just need
one you just need to know the beginning
of the string why why is it sufficient
for a variable to Only Store the first
byes address and not all of the bytes
addresses exactly because of the design
of strings per week two we always null
terminate them so it suffices to only
remember the first bites address because
from there you can sort of follow the
breadcrumbs bite after bite after bite
and until you see the new line Sorry the
the null character you know that all of
those characters are apparently part of
the same string so this is what's been
going on in the me computer's memory all
since week one and in fact if we
abstract this away you can really think
of s as being just this really a pointer
to that chunk of memory so in fact what
do we have here well in the left to
recap on the code here on the left hand
side string that's what ensures that
we'll actually be able to store a string
in a variable called s we're going to
have on the uh right hand side though
the actual value so let me switch back
to VSS code here and let me change my
code to no longer involve integers alone
so I'm going to add the uh cs50 Library
just so that I can use some shortcuts in
there cs50.h and then in my main
function I'm going to go ahead and do
this string s equals quote unquote high
in all caps exclamation point and then
I'm going to go ahead and print out
using percent S as always back sln the
value of s so this program at the moment
not interesting at all it's just week
one stuff again/ addresses indeed prints
out high but it turns out that now that
I know this what's really been going on
underneath the hood all this time well
here's that same line of code that
defines the variable called s and it
turns out anyone want to guess what
string is actually a synonym
for string it turns out is kind of a
white lie we've been telling since week
one there is no such thing as string as
a keyword in in C it's technically a
cs50 thing
yeah it's a pointer to a character so
really all this time we've kind of been
lying to you there is no string quote
unquote it's actually Char star and if I
may it dramatically here go the training
wheels like okay that didn't land very
well so uh what have we been doing well
it turns out that string is a much
easier way conceptually to think about
what a string of characters is like my
God if we had to start in week one by
having you type char
like yeah you might get past it but like
this is just way too much ugly syntax
not intellectually interesting at all so
we abstract it away what a Char star was
in the first week of C by telling you
it's actually called string now string
is a term of art like C programmers
programmers are in any language we'll
use the word string to mean a sequence
of characters but in C it's not
technically a word unto itself it's
rather a synonym that we ourselves
created in some form so in fact how did
we do this well think back to just last
week last week I proposed that it'd be
really nice if we had a person data type
which the creators of C did not think of
decades ago but that's okay we can
Define it ourselves what did we do here
well using syntax like this recall that
we defined a person to be what to be
this structure this structure using the
new keyword last week struct means that
a person is just a name and a number and
it could have been other things we just
kept it simple but how did I associate
person with that structure well we
claimed that it was this value here type
def which as you might expect defines a
data type so what did we do as cs50 back
in week one without telling you well we
could have done something like this like
int itself is a little cryptic and maybe
we should have to keep things even
simpler said hey everyone turns out you
can Define integers in C and if you
wanted to do this well if you want to
create the keyword integer as a data
type you can just typ def it to int so
typed def creates the word on the far
right integer and U creates a synonym
for it in this case called int so what
did we do in week one without telling
you we have a line of code like this in
the cs-50 library that Associates quote
unquote string with more cryptically
charar and this is why in week one
onward anytime you use the cs50 library
you can write the word string as though
it's a real C data type and that's just
because we wanted to have this
abstraction these training wheels on for
the first weeks so we don't have to get
weeds of all this crazy memory stuff we
can sort of talk about strings at a
higher level but that's all they are
strings are the address of the first
character in that sequence of characters
questions now on any of these details
yeah strings
liar good question what about the
strings Library which we have used um
unrelated so it does not define the word
string everything in there actually
relates to char stars and so in fact if
you've used the CS5
uh manual uh which is just our
userfriendly version of the actual
manual pages for the official language C
you'll see throughout that now if you
start poking around or turning off less
comfortable mode you'll actually see
that we've changed any mentions of
charar in the official documentation for
these first weeks to just string to
simplify it but underneath the hood C
does not know the word string per se as
a keyword but it's absolutely a concept
that like every program in the world
knows about and in fact in other
languages in Python for instance there
will actually be a proper string
although it's not going to be called
string it's going to be called stir St
Str for short questions on these strings
here well let me propose there's one
other feature of this syntax that we can
now leverage as follows let me propose
that if we go back to the previous
version of my code here wherein let me
switch back to vs code in just a moment
I'm going to rewind in vs code to the
integer version of my code from before
and most recently it looked looked like
this before when we were using integers
only and not in fact strings at all let
me propose that there's this other
feature of C that we can use that
actually allows us to go to an address
so at the moment let me just rewind and
do make addresses to remind you what
this program do did when it was using
integers alone and there's that address
why because on line seven notice I'm
printing out the value of P which is a
pointer so of course it's going to look
like an address but let me zoom out now
and make one change and instead of
printing out P how can I use today's
second new operator not the Ampersand
but the star to actually go to that
address well what I can actually do on
this line of code is this if I want to
print out the actual integer 50 that's
in that variable or equivalently at that
address I can go to P here and not print
P literally because that's just an
address I can now say star p and star p
means go there more technically
dreference p that is follow the treasure
map to the actual address and do what
Carter did open the mailbox and print
whatever was in the mailbox which recall
was the actual number 50 so let me try
this let me recompile the code so make
addresses okay let me clear my terminal
window do/ addresses this time I
shouldn't see the ox anything I should
see just the number 50 in this case and
here to is kind of a unfortunate design
decision certainly pedagogically I would
say in C if I zoom in on this code star
is unfortunately being used in two
different ways in an Ideal World they
would have used three different symbols
to make this more semantically clear but
this is what we're stuck with so in line
six when you declare a pointer that is a
variable that stores an address you put
the type of variable that you want to
point at then a star just because and
then the name of the variable and on the
right hand side you actually get the
address of whatever using Ampersand but
when you want to go to an address you
want to dreference a pointer you don't
use int again and we've never done that
right once you declare a variable you
never again mention the data type but in
the world of pointers now if you want to
not print out P but go to whatever
address p is storing you use star P here
so a good visual indicator would be when
you declare a pointer that is make it
exist in your program you have to
declare the data type with the star but
when you use a pointer you just use the
star in an Ideal World this would be a
completely different symbol but again
this is what we have questions now on
that syntax
[Music]
yeah uh why can't we just do the Amper
sand here are you saying it was still a
little quiet so strictly speaking we do
not need line six so this is really for
pedagogical sake that I am um defining a
separate variable p and then printing it
out at this point though I'm just kind
of you know going in circles if you will
because more simple would have been what
I would have done in week one which
would be get rid of P alt together get
rid of P here and just print out n right
but today we're just giving you this new
building block these this new syntax via
which you can figure out the address of
something and then reverse the process
later and actually go to it as
well other questions on what we've done
here with these
pointers all right well let's context
switch back to the string now and see
what more we can do with this here in
the case of our strings here let me uh
refine this to zoom out let me delete
the integer related code here let me do
string s equals quote unquote high in
all caps let me go ahead and for the
moment include cs50.h at the top so that
indeed I can use the keyword s or string
rather and let me go ahead now and do
something more than I did last time last
time I did print F of percent s back sln
and then I printed out s and again I'll
recompile this just for clarity make
addresses addresses that just prints out
high so that's again week one stuff but
now that we have this other bit of
syntax we can do some interesting things
too so for instance suppose I want to
print out not s itself but what if I
want to print out the address of s like
at what memory location is s well I can
change my percent s to percent P which
now we know P is for pointer so percent
p means print out the value of a pointer
that is an address and here I can
actually print out s itself but why that
is we'll see in a moment let me do this
here go the training wheels string does
not technically EX exist but it does if
I'm using the cs-50 library but if I get
rid of the cs50 library as I'm
metaphorically doing by taking off the
training wheels I can't use the word
string anymore and in fact let me make
this mistake deliberately as you might
have accidentally in past weeks here is
the error message I get if I forget the
cs50 library use of Undeclared
identifier string did you mean standard
in it's trying to be helpful but it's
not because I didn't mean standard in so
indeed this is confirmation that c does
not know the word string exists at least
as a keyword exists as a concept but not
a keyword so I could fix this by adding
back the cs50 library but that's kind of
a step backwards educationally is
instead of a step forward what could I
do instead to fix this now if the
training wheels are now off
yeah exactly replace string quote
unquote with Char star instead so I'm
going to go ahead and change this to
char technically you can put the literal
star here the asterisk or you can put it
there or you can put it here by
convention is to do what I done from the
beginning put the star next to the name
of the variable as opposed to anywhere
else uh let me go ahead now and or sorry
I meant to add the spaces there you
could do this too but this would be the
most normal convention so now let's do
this make addresses compile is okay now
do slash addresses what should I see
high or something else feel free to just
call it
out so still high you say someone
else memory location a memory location
all right so could be one of the two
options right either I'm going to see
the string or I'm going to see a memory
address though I do in fact see a memory
address and this one's quite different
from the integer one but does anyone now
want to explain why you were correct why
am I seeing the address down here and
not hi it's subtle
yeah exactly because I left my percent P
there which means hey print F show me a
pointer but this is where printf is
smart and has been smart since week zero
humans who invented printf decades ago
uh wrote code that notices that okay
percent s means to treat the following
value not as just an address per se that
gets printed literally but printed as
with the mailbox demo is sort of a
treasure map that leads you to the
address of a character so simply by
changing one character percent P to
percent s and if I now do make addresses
again and slash addresses this now is
identical to week one but hopefully
makes sense because percent s is just a
clue to print f that means go to this
address in s print out every character
there and thereafter until you see what
the null character and then stop
printing anything more and this is why
hi has printed since week one today we
can see the address percent P but this
combination of having access to
addresses and the null Terminator is all
the information printf needs to actually
do something more useful by like
printing the actual
strings any questions now on this
approach to percent s yeah in
back oh so why is it traditionally being
used in this way honestly like the word
string has been around for decades it's
not a keyword you should be able to type
in C unless you're using a library like
cs50 um and so percent s just means
string so even though it doesn't exist
as a keyword percent s connotes string
and humans decades ago like today just
kind of know what that means so they
could have chosen any letter of the
alphabet but s sort of makes the most
sense all right well let's in back other
question good question before let me
zoom in I did not use a star before the
S why well it's subtle here but printf
is was invented years ago to know given
an address like in the variable s printf
knows to go there so if we looked at the
source code that some human wrote years
ago for C we would likely see the actual
uh asterisk that you're referring to
printf is taking on the responsibility
for going to S if you were to do uh star
s here instead an asterisk and then s
that would now be literally a character
because if I say p uh star s that means
go to the address in s and all you're
going to find there is a single
character what printf wants to know is
not what is the character there what is
the address of that character why
because printf needs to walk through the
rest of those characters looking for the
final null character and in fact let me
see with a bit more syntax if we can
highlight this a bit more let me do this
in addition to printing s let's try out
our syntax in another way let me print
out with percent s how about uh not s
here but let's print out some addresses
percent s back sln close quote and then
let's print out how about this the first
character in the string s would be
called s bracket Z but how do I get the
address of the first character in s well
I could technically just use today's new
primitive I can just add an ampon that
always gives me the address of some
value so when I end this thought and
clear my terminal window and run make
addresses still compiles when I run
addresses in just a moment any guesses
as to what I will see line by line this
will print out two
things and you don't have to remember
what the actual number was but at a high
level what will be printed now the same
thing twice why well when I run this
what I'm printing here and let me zoom
in at the bottom I ined see two really
long addresses but they're in fact the
same why well that's because again if s
is the address of a character as implied
Now by either the cs50 word string or
the actual phrase Char star well then s
is just an address by contrast per week
two s bracket 0 is a Char always has
been a Char a specific Char but if you
want the address of that Char you just
add the Ampersand well it turns out that
strings per the definition we keep
emphasizing is just the address of the
first character in a string so of course
if you do this you're going to see the
exact same thing and if I do this a bit
more generally you don't want to copy
paste but this is just for uh
visualization sake let me print out all
the characters so another another
another and let me change this to print
out the address of bracket 1 bracket two
and bracket three so all four characters
Hi exclamation point and the null
character notice I'm using percent P for
all of them so if I now do make
addresses and do/ addresses now notice
and this is kind of cool the first two
are indeed still the same but what's no
noteworthy about the other values on the
screen yeah they're consecutive each of
these is just one bite away even if
you're not good at hex yet and there's a
crazy number of digits here who cares
they're all the same except for the last
ones four four and then 5 six seven and
this confirms what I've been claiming
for weeks is that in an array all of the
characters are back to back to back
contiguous One Bites away so with just
this Ampersand with just this star like
it's actually a pretty cool tool in the
toolkit to have because you can start to
poke around what's actually going on
inside of the computer's memory and in
fact if we do this I can introduce one
other cool trick here if you will let me
propose that we can actually now do
arithmetic on pointers and you don't
have to you'll see a simpler way to do
this but now that you have perhaps this
underlying understanding of where things
are in memory and it's just addresses we
can actually do something kind of neat
we can do something like this uh let me
go back to how about uh the string
version of this with high and let me do
this instead let me um clean this up a
bit get rid of some of these lines of
code and let me do this let me print out
percent C percent C percent C let me get
rid of all these Amper Sands we're going
to roll back to like week two stuff just
to be clear when I compile and run this
version of the program and I'll zoom in
what should get printed on the screen
this is just week two stuff now no
pointers per se yeah
mhm just Hi exclamation point one per
line because I have all of these back
slash ends so let me do that let me go
down here make addresses enter okay
pretty good/ addresses and indeed Hi
exclamation point But now if you're
getting a little more comfortable and
it's fine if you're not yet today but
over the coming week or weeks as you get
a little more comfortable with the
equivalence of addresses with our
definition in the past of arrays and
strings and all of this you can start to
play around and I can do this instead if
I I want to print out the first
character in the string I could do like
week two s bracket zero like that will
always work and you can keep using that
that's not a cs50 thing it's just a
convenience in C but I could technically
print out not s because s is an address
but what would be the syntax I could use
to say print out the character at
s any
Instinct how can I say go to the address
in
s it's one of two possible answers
today so of our two new uh uh of our two
new operators today we have the
Ampersand and the star which one will
lead us to what is that an address so
the star so in fact if I want to print
out what is that address zero at the
address S I can just do star s and if
you really want to get fancy how do you
print out the second character that's
immediately to the right of it so to
speak well you can go to with the D
reference operator and do you want to
answer this
one s+ one Argo pointer arithmetic like
you can do math simple addition
subtraction whatever on pointers if you
want and you can do this here too so
star you want to pluck this one off too
how do I print out the last character
the
third s plus2 right because if you know
and understand that like a string is
just a sequence of characters every
character is just a bite and these bites
are back to back to back you can just go
wherever you want in the computer's
memory and here I can do make addresses
again/ addresses and voila we now have
high exclamation point so we haven't
printed out anything new but again just
by using these two new operators the
erson and the star you can figure out
the address of something and you can go
to the address of something okay
question in
back indeed it ends up being the exact
same and so I might have used this term
before the Amper sand technique where
sorry the square bracket technique where
you do s bracket 0o s bracket One S
bracket 2 that's actually what we would
really call syntactic Sugar like it
works and you can use it you should use
it it's nice and simple
but the square bracket notation
underneath the hood is essentially being
converted to this which this is not fun
right like this is when you want to show
off to your friends like you know how to
do cool stuff in code but this is not as
readable as just s bracket Z and one and
two but that's all that's happening
underneath the hood and so again this is
why in cs50 we spend time on some of
these lower level building blocks
because if you assume that indeed your
computer's memory is just this grid of
btes and you have now the code ability
in code to get an address and go to an
address you can start doing any anything
you want and you can poke around a
computer's memory at any location and
here in lies the danger like I'm kind of
on the honor System right now that if my
string is high exclamation point it's
kind of up to me to go to the first bite
the second and the third but I could get
kind of crazy now and if I want to see
what's going on in the computer's memory
I mean there's nothing stopping me from
doing like s+ 50 and let's see what's
there so make addresses do/ addresses Hi
and then okay nothing it seems well how
about 5,000 bytes away let's poke around
what's inside of the computer's memory
so make addresses again uh make
addresses addresses enter okay still
nothing there let's try
50,000 all right do make addresses do SL
addresses okay there we see it so you've
probably done this some of you by
accident because you probably went too
far to the left or to the right in an
array touching memory that you shouldn't
suffice it to say I should not go
blindly touching 50,000 bytes away cuz
who knows what's there and indeed in
your computer computer when a program is
running the computer uh segments it into
different segments of memory and if you
get a little too greedy and you touch
another segment of memory that
technically was not allocated to you by
Mac OS or Windows or Linux or the
operating system bad things happen and
you get a segmentation fault and that
means it's a bug in your code so you can
now do this and this means hackers too
can do things like this if they can
somehow inject code into your C program
maybe they can poke around the
computer's memory and indeed this is
kind of the technique whereby maybe a
really sophisticated hacker can jump to
this memory this memory this memory
looking for something like your password
or your financial information or
anything that's in the program but at
some other address there's nothing
stopping an adversary at least right now
from poking around if they can execute
code on your computer from doing this
kind of thing so there and again is the
power of C but also the danger and
you'll absolutely suffer more segals in
the coming days but ultimately the goal
is going to be to help you solve them
ultimately uh and fix things um but for
now I think that was that was quite a
bit so let me propose that we go ahead
and take our longer break here maybe 10
minutes and have ourselves some whoopy
pies in the transcept we'll be back in
10 all right so we're back and to recap
where we left off you now have this new
capability in code to do pointer
arithmetic like treat addresses as
numbers which they really are in heximal
or otherwise and like add them together
and kind of poke around a computer's
memory and it was asked during break
actually how we might further harness
this in the context of string so I
didn't change the code we wrote just
before break recall that we last broke
the program by checking out bytes 50,000
bytes away but let's not do that and
let's actually try printing out not
individual characters like I did per the
percent C but why don't we try printing
out strings and substrings if you will
so let me clear my terminal window let
me change all of these percent C's to
percent s percent s percent s and then
let me rewind to what we've been doing
since week one with strings which is
just print them out for instance with
that first line and the only difference
at the moment is that now I took off the
training wheels I got rid of cs50.h
wherein string is typ Def to char star
for you got rid of that so now on line
five I'm declaring S as being a Char
star which just means the address of a
character and print f is smart enough to
know that the end of a string is
wherever that null character is but now
that I can do pointer arithmetic notice
that I could do something like this if I
want to print out s i just print out s
suppose I do s+ one here and s+2 here
again after changing percent C to
percent s any intuition around what this
code will now print on the screen line
by
line yeah
thoughts okay reasonable conjecture
maybe the memory address of H that of I
that of exclamation point but other
[Music]
thoughts yeah I think it's going to do
the latter it's going to print high in
the usual way because honestly line five
is this rather line six is the same as
like week one stuff except we took off
the training wheel of string and we're
calling it Char star but I think line
seven is indeed going to print out I and
line eight is just going to print out
because it'll be just the exclamation
point prti will still be smart enough to
know where each of those substrings a
portions of the string End by the same
logic as always but let me go ahead and
zoom out run make addresses enter
compiles okay/ addresses and now indeed
this is all a string is it's a sequence
of characters identified by its first
bite if you then start poking around and
tell printf to print at what's at the
next bite or the next next bite it's
going to do its same thing printing out
that character and everything after it
up until that null character so again
even though there's like a lot going on
we've introduced these two new operators
like there's nothing that's happening
today that hasn't been happening for
weeks but hopefully through this week uh
this week's lecture this week's problem
set and Beyond you'll start to realize
that now you just have more tools via
which to harness those lower level
implementation details so last week too
recall one other implementation detail I
claimed that you could not compare two
strings quite as easily as you could
compare to uh integers for instance and
I told you to use a different function
instead that you probably used one or
more times with the past problem set how
are you supposed to compare strings
apparently yeah so string compare stir
comp that additional function that we
said H you just have to use it for now
but you might have a little intuition
already as to like why we have to use
Stir compare and we can't just use
equals equals to compare strings like
any intuition for this already why was
Stir compare necessary last week
equ perfect equals equals would compare
literally the two memory addresses
instead of the actual strings character
by character and unless the memory
addresses are literally the same so you
compare the that exact same memory
address two different strings probably
are not going to be considered equal
even if to us humans they indeed look
equal so let's see this let me go ahead
and close addresses. C and actually
before I do one last mention one of the
powerful things about Pointer arithmetic
as an aside is that c and really the
compiler is smart enough to know how
many bytes to keep adding and adding and
by that I mean this right now we got
lucky because a string is a sequence of
characters and by definition every
character is is a single bite you can
poke around and do s+ one to get the
next bite S Plus 2 to get the uh the
third bite however if we weren't dealing
with strings suppose we were dealing
with integers that were in an array back
to back to back if you wanted to get at
the next integer you could still do plus
one or plus two to get at the next or
the next next integer you would not
start to get into the weeds of doing
plus four and then plus eight you don't
have to know or care how big the data
types are in the computer C and the
compiler will figure that out for you
based on the data type in question so
keep that in mind if ever doing this on
a different data type uh than chars all
right so let me go ahead and open up a
file that I wrote in advance most of and
let me hide my terminal window and show
you this so here is a program called
compare. C whose purpose in life is to
compare two strings I'm back to using
the cs50 library because at least for
now in probably a couple more weeks it
is so much easier to get input from the
user using cs50's function get in but
we'll conclude today by taking off those
training wheels as well so you can see
how you can actually get user input with
nothing cs50 specific so line six and
seven pretty boring week one stuff get
an INT called I get an INT called J and
store them in two variables I and J
respectively if I equals equals J print
out the same else print out that they're
different let me just stipulate for time
sake I'm pretty sure this code is
correct this will get two integers from
the human it will compare them and tell
me correctly if they're the same or
different and I'll prove as much by
running make compare
slash compare and I'll type in 50 for I
50 for J and they're the same and now
I'll do how about 50 and say 13 and
those are different so let me just
stipulate this code is indeed correct
would have worked in week one also works
now in week four but let me now change
it to compare not two integers but as I
hinted maybe two strings instead so let
me go ahead and change this line of code
to maybe be string s equals get string
uh asking the user for s s uh then let's
change this second line here to be
string T just to keep the variable name
short for now and T is a good uh Choice
after s for something like this get
string prompt the human for T and then
let's change our I and J here to do the
wrong thing per the intuition earlier if
s equals equals T then print out the
same else print out that they're
different now if I want I could take off
at least some of the training wheels I
could change this to char star I could
change this to char star either is fine
I still need the Cs library though
because I'm using get string because
it's actually hard as we'll see today to
get strings manually without using a
library but I'll keep it using string
just for now with the library all right
make compare
again compare and now let me go ahead
and type in for instance Hi exclamation
point Enter and Hi exclamation point
Enter and they're different all they're
obviously not visually but they are
underneath the hood and you probably do
have the intuition for this already
whereby what's going on underneath the
hood is that we're comparing
accidentally the two memory addresses so
in fact let's go there let's consider
the memory and let me zoom out now so I
can just have more btes to play with so
the squares are a little smaller than
before just so we can fit more in them
and let me propose that when I declare s
on what was line six a moment ago it
ends up somewhere in memory like the top
leftand corner of my picture for
discussion sake and when I uh execute
that same line of code and get string is
called and I type in high exclamation
point we know from week one that get
string puts it somewhere in the
computer's memory and I'll propose that
it's in like the bottom left hand corner
of the screen here what happens after
that well I know even though I don't
generally care that Hi exclamation point
in the null character exist at some
address like ox123 12 4 125 126 for
discussion sake and what's in s same as
before break 0x1 23 so that's all that's
happening again on line six which is
pretty much the same as when we were
getting an S earlier but notice now with
line seven when I get a second variable
called T and I call get string again and
by coincidence as the human I type the
same thing well what happens here T gets
its own chunk of memory maybe at the top
right uh that second version of high
gets somewhere else in memory you know
the computer could be smart and notice
it's the same but C doesn't generally do
that for you it just plops it somewhere
else in memory and maybe it's at address
Ox 456 457 458 459 or wherever but you
can perhaps see where this is going
already T now of course contains the
address of that first bite and so in my
code on line nine when I compare s and t
for equality suffice it to say they are
not equal because of the way the uh
strings are laid out in the computer's
memory it's indeed looks the same the
same values are there but if we abstract
away further you can really see that s
and t are not the same themselves and so
how did we fix this or really how did we
avoid this last week without spilling
the beans and going down this Rabbit
Hole explaining like why you have to use
Stir compare well if I go back to my
code here let's do it now the right way
let me go ahead and include uh a line of
code that says string compare of s comma
T both as inputs and then if you recall
what does stir compare return when two
strings are equal there's three possible
return values so zero so one is for if
it comes alphabetically or atically
first or second but for now I just want
zero if I want to use S compare I do
need
string.h so string.h does exist that's
not a cs50 thing there's no keyword
string as a data type that's a cs50
thing but string.h does exist so I think
now with that change on line 10 if I do
make compare and slash compare and then
run again uh type again High exclamation
point High exclamation point I think now
they're the same and just as a uh second
check high in L caps maybe high in
lowercase those are in fact different
why well stir compare which was written
by some other human decades ago is just
smart enough to know that it should go
to S and go to T start comparing them
left to right stopping once it hits one
or both null characters and return zero
only if everything in s and and T are
exactly the same are any questions then
on this
here any questions on why we're using
stir compare all right if no yeah oh in
the
middle yes so so why does why is it not
the case with integers so it turns out
it's not the case with integers with
floats with bulls with uh doubles with
Longs like literally every other data
type works correctly strings though are
special they are useful enough in
programming and have been for decades
that the authors of printf and the
authors of stir compare and bunches of
other functions Sterling for that matter
just kind of treat strings special
because they're just useful right we
humans interact using language be it
English or anything else and so it's
just useful to have into the language C
just sort of uh first class support for
this notion of strings of human text so
the short answer is just because like it
just uh is necessar strings are
different they're implemented with this
address and the null character
everything else though is just a value
but a string again is a white lie it's
an address it's not a thing unto itself
good question yeah in front
oh really good question so in my code
here in vs code what if I do this
instead of stir compare and instead of
if s equals equals T what if I start
playing around using star s and star T
really interesting case to consider
let's go back to our sort of deductive
logic here so star the asteris operator
today means go there so when I've typed
in high once and then high again both
uppercase for instance what is at the
address s literally someone
else what is at the address s yeah uh so
not quite at the address not so not what
is the address what is at the address
ox123 H and what is at the address Ox
456 H also and so here you're kind of
cheating like you're comparing the first
character of both strings but not every
other one now you could be really
pedantic and here again this is like a
good use of uh codee but you could do
this if that and how about this
craziness so star
s+1 equals equals star t + one and and
you could do this for every character
manually but that's why stir compare
exists it does all of this for you but
that's why and that's the intuition so I
would encourage you too anytime there's
something kind of weird going on there's
I realize we might be um straining
credibility now we haven't told you that
many white lies and so most everything
that we've seen thus far can explain
pretty much all of the behavior up until
now from week one onward in C so let me
revert this back to the right way if s
compare of S&T equals equals z this now
is the right version of the code and now
here is again where you can play so let
me do this let me um clear my terminal
window just to tidy things up let me get
rid of all of this comparison stuff and
let's just see what's going on as you
are welcome to in your own code let's
print out for instance as we might have
in week one the value of s itself in a
new line comma s and then let's just
print out T just to make sure it
compiles and I'm not doing anything
wrong but this is not going to be that
interesting and frankly I don't need
string.h anymore because I'm not using
stir compare so make addresses addresses
there's my um oh sorry that's fun okay
not percent T percent s here too ignore
that let's do this again make a oh and
that's the wrong program okay dot SL
let's do make
compare compare and let's type in high
again and high again and and now we just
see the two strings I'm not comparing
but now we can kind of play around right
instead of printing out percent s which
prints the string how do I print the
address in S I just need to make a
slight change if I want to see not
what's at s but I want to see s the
address
yeah perfect so change percent s in both
places here to percent P so now printf
will treat it literally as an dress it's
not going to do any fanciness this with
a loop from left to right looking for
the null character it's just going to
print out S&T so let me clear my
terminal run make compare whoops let's
do make comparecompare enter type in
high type in high again and now you see
oh so this is interesting it's not quite
as straightforward as the other values
which were slight one bite away they're
almost the same but this one ends in b0
this one ends in F0 so they're indeed
separated by some number of bytes not
just one but a few because these strings
are indeed longer all right so once
you've seen this here how can we now
maybe leverage this to solve other
problems well let me propose that we do
this let me uh zoom out here let me
close compare and let me open up another
program I wrote part of in advance
called
copy.c so copy. C in theory makes a copy
of a string how on line eight I'm using
the same thing as before get string
storing in a string or char star and
asking the user for it then I'm not
asking get string again I'm just making
a copy super simply with line 10 here
string T equals s now intuitively I
think that's how I would copy a variable
right that's how we've copied variables
every week thus far and see but
something's going to go wrong in line 12
in English does someone want to explain
what you think line 12 does don't worry
about finding any bugs or mistakes but
what does line 12 seem to be doing using
two upper which which is thanks to the
ctype library which I've included the
header file for
yeah yeah right it's kind of like ugly
syntax but this would seem to be
capitalizing the first letter of T
specifically and just changing it so we
have t bracket Zer here because we want
to save the change and we're passing to
two upper the first character here so
this is how we did uppercase in the past
and now I print out s and t respectively
using percent s so this feels like it
should work I copied s and stored it in
t on line 10 and then I change T and
only t on line 12 but you can perhaps if
you're comfy thus far see where this is
going if I do make
copy copy and let me type in lowercase
Hi exclamation point this time just once
so I'm going to hit enter and watch what
we see for the value of s and
t huh the new value of SN T at the end
of my program seems to be what it seems
to be
the same high is capitalized both times
so what's the intuition then for this
why did this just
happen yeah and
back yeah I assigned S&T the same memory
address so it did copy s into T but C
takes this very literally what is s it's
an address what is T it's a copy of that
address if you want to copy the whole
string like a normal human would expect
hey you or someone has to do a lot more
work you have to go to that address copy
this character this one this one this
one and copy it to a new location in
memory that does not happen
automatically here for you in C it does
in some other languages those of you
who've programmed in certain higher
level languages this just works as you
would hope and that's one of the
benefits of python and other languages
that we'll soon see but for now it
literally takes at face value what this
is copy the address into this address
and I'll make that more clear by getting
rid of the string keyword which again is
just a type def this is technically an
address here this is technically an
address here so what's being being
copied is the value of that address not
all of the characters that might very
well follow it so I should make one note
to here I'm going to start getting more
in the habit of trying to avoid
segmentation faults because things could
go wrong here for instance online 12
previously I was kind of blindly naively
dangerously assuming that there will be
at least one character in s or t that
might not be the case if the user Just
Hits enter there's no characters to
uppercase and so this is reckless of me
and could theoretically create a sigall
so I should probably start to be smarter
and say something like this if the
length of T is greater than zero okay
now it's safe to actually capitalize the
first letter and that will decrease the
probability now of those segmentation
faults by just not making any
assumptions about what the human does
almost always the your programs will
crash when you've made a mistake yes but
the user gives you an input that you
yourself did not
expect so what does this all look like
in memory well let's go back to the Big
Grid this time focusing on the copying
of values and let's do this here's S as
in this new program just declared to be
a Char star uh here is where my
lowercase High maybe ended up in the
computer's memory that's probably at
ox123 12 4 125 whatever something like
that and that's of course what ends up
in s as a value when I declare T I do
get a second variable called T just like
before but when I copy s into T what
happens it's really just literally ox1 2
3 whatever the value of s is is now also
the value of T and so if we abstract
this away at a high level get rid of all
of those extra squares this is what s
and t now are they're indeed copies but
copies of each other not copies of the
underlying characters and so if you
follow those arrows um and try to print
them both out after capitalizing one or
the other you're going to unfortunately
end up capitalizing not just one of them
s but both of them s and T because
literally it's the same address any
questions then on this
visualization
yeah good question is this pass by
reference we haven't um we have not seen
in detail an example like that um right
now you're copying by value but
references will come into play and
remind me in a bit if I haven't used
that term yet but this is just copying
things by could have ended poorly value
other
questions no all right so with this in
mind like how do we actually copy things
properly for this we actually need
another building block so today we give
you two functions one of which is called
Malo one of which is called free and
these are used all of the time by like
every piece of software you and I use on
our Macs PCS and phones whether it's
written in C or some equivalent other
language Malo is for memory allocation
it's a function that you can use to ask
the operating system Mac OS Linux
Windows anything for some number of of
bytes one bite 100 bytes a gigabyte of
memory you can ask malog for however
much memory you want in advance it will
return to you the address of the first
bite of memory that it found free for
you unlike a string it is not null
terminated and so the danger with malok
is that it's on the honor System if you
ask it for one bite or 10 bytes you the
programmer in like a variable have to
remember how many byes you requested one
or 10 or the like strings do that for
you not when we're getting now to this
low level Mal just going to give you
some memory and it's up to you to manage
it free does the opposite when you're
done with some chunk of memory you can
free it by passing in that same address
and just hand it back to Mac OS windows
or Linux and say I'm done with this you
can let me use this for something else
later um as an aside if your computer
has ever like frozen or hung like the
whole thing maybe just spontaneously
reboots yet another reason for a bug
like that might be if you write a
program with a bug that keeps Mal
loocking Mal loocking Mal loocking that
is asking for more and more and more
memory but you make a mistake and you
never free it well eventually the
computer is going to literally run out
of memory and something's going to go
wrong and that's often when computers
freeze like they're just out of memory
it has the memory there but the program
was trying to use too much of it
endlessly so this too will be a mistake
that some of us will surely make in the
coming weeks but hopefully you'll now
see the solution so let me go back to uh
vs code here and let me propose that we
do the following I'll hide my terminal
window for a moment and I'm going to
introduce another header file up here
and I promise there's not going to be
too many more of these but this one is
called standard li. for standard library
and in this file are the Declarations
the prototypes for malok and free and a
bunch of other stuff as well it lets me
now manage my own memory so let's focus
now on line 11 line 11 is where I went
wrong before because conceptually I want
to copy the whole string but of course
I'm only copying modestly the individual
address so how do I copy the whole darn
thing well what I need to do is this
when when I declare T to be the address
of something in memory why don't I set T
to be the address of a free chunk of
memory so let me ask the operating
system give me this many bytes tell me
what the address is and I'm going to
store that in t initially just so I know
where there's free space for me so how
do I do that well quite simply I call
malok and then I pass in the number of
bytes that I need now for Hi exclamation
point I think I need three although wait
no I really need four because of the
null character but I don't think I
should be hardcoding numbers like this
cuz who knows what the human's going to
type in so I can actually use Sterling
of s and then plus one this will ask
malok then for however many btes
corresponds to the number of characters
the human typed in plus one for again
the null character so it's just being
smart and defensive rather than choosing
a number myself but now all T is is a
pointer if you will to some random chunk
of free space so there's nothing there
yet or there's you know bits there but
who knows what value they are they're
certainly not identical to what the
human type did in I now have to do this
so how can I copy one string into the
other well let me do this instead of uh
capitalizing something just yet let me
do this how about four in I gets zero I
is less than the length of
s uh and then i++ so I'm going to
iterate for the whole length of the
string and in here I'm just going to do
this the E character in t should be
identical to the E character in s so I'm
just literally copying from right to
left each and every character in s and I
can trust that there's enough memory in
t why cuz I asked for that many bytes
plus one now there's technically a bug
here I actually should probably do this
I should do plus one here or if you
prefer I should do less than or equal to
the Sterling but I think it's a little
clear to do the plus one why do I for
the first time want to go just beyond
the boundary of s and copy one more
bite yeah yeah I need the null character
like I could technically manually add it
with some additional line of code but I
might as well just copy it because back
sl0 is back sl0 so this time and
probably only this time it's reasonable
and correct to go just beyond the
boundary of your string so you copy the
null terminating character so that the
computer also knows where T ends and now
I think what I can do a little more
safely is this let me go down here and
say t braet 0 equals 2 upper of t uh two
upper of T bracket Z so same line of
code as before if I actually want to be
really safe I should probably do this so
if the stir L of T is greater than zero
so there's at least one bite there okay
now it's safe to blindly capitalize the
first character and I think that now
puts me in better shape so let me try
this now let me uh open up my terminal
make uh copy do slash copy I'm going to
type in Hi exclamation point in all
lowercase crossing my fingers this time
and now if I zoom in it indeed
capitalized only T and not s in this
case so pictorially let me switch over
here here is as before the variable s
pointing at high in all lowercase when I
call malok though that gives me a chunk
of memory that I'm going to store the
address in t of so if T is some other
variable as it is in my code and there's
some other available chunk of memory I
don't know where it is but let's assume
as always it's at Ox 456 4557 4558 N9 so
four bytes total what is now happening
well T is defined as pointing to that
because that's what Malo gives us the
address of the first bite of the free
memory and now with my for Loop I'm just
iterating over it copying the H then the
I then the exclamation point and then
for good measure the back slash Zer
instead questions then on this process
here a really good question um if I
omitted in my code the
uh plus one and I didn't do less than or
equal to so that I'm copying the fourth
bite odds are in this program because
it's so short you wouldn't notice that
there's an actual error but what could
happen is When I Call printf On T if
there's no null bite there it might
print h i exclamation point some random
value some random value some random
value some random value until it gets
lucky and there happens to be a zero
bite a null bite by chance for instance
so if you don't include the back sl0
some way that's going to happen and I
say some way I could even do this I
could technically just copy the length
of the string s and at the very bottom
here I could do something like T bracket
I uh sorry T bracket um
Sterling of T I could do this but this
is just not necessary like I could
manually add it at the end of the string
but again i' claim that it's just
simpler to borrow that is copy the one
that's already in s because it's the
same thing at the end of the day good
question other questions on this copying
correctly
[Music]
now all right is there any room for
improvement here well let me propose a
slight optimization this is kind of a
throwback now to week one turns out that
arguably my line 13 here wherein I have
this for Loop now that I'm doing things
in Loops again and again and using a
function like Sterling this is correct
it will iterate from zero on up to the
length of I a length of uh s plus one
but it's kind of stupid of me to write
this for Loop in this way why well
here's my initialization on the left
here's my condition in the middle and in
general calling a function inside of
your condition is probably not very good
design like why why is it bad for me to
be calling a function like Sterling in
this condition in the middle of my for
Loop
yeah yeah you're just calling it again
and again for no reason like the length
of s never changes so like why are you
wasting everyone's Time by calling
Sterling of s again again again again
just to check this inequality whether I
is less than that value so it turns out
if you haven't discovered this already
there's a slight optimization we can do
here that has nothing to do
fundamentally with strings or pointers
just with better design I can actually
Define two variables at once I could do
this let me remove this whole condition
and let me add a comma after I equals 0
set n or any variable equal to the stirl
of s + 1 and then after the semicolon
just ask the question while I is less
than n so it's almost the same but
notice now my condition in the very
middle of this Loop is at least
comparing two static values n never
change sorry one static value n never
changes all that changes is I but I'm
not foolishly calling sterling sterling
sterling again and again why well how
does Sterling work similar in spirit to
PR print F Sterling given the name of a
string looks at the first character and
then starts looking through the entire
string looking for the null character
and we saw this in week two counting up
how many characters are there so it's
just a waste of time again and
[Music]
again totally if you wanted to use n
multiple times you could absolutely take
it out of the for Loop put it right
after s is defined and reuse n and again
and again absolutely but in General
consider this when designing your for
Loops even though modern compilers like
cang can actually fix this problem this
inefficiency for you good practice would
be don't call functions unnecessarily
especially if the answer is always going
to be the same all right so what else
should I perhaps refine here well how
about I do one last thing and just
comment on what exactly could go wrong
here well a couple of things well
actually this is just silly too like
surely someone before me in the world
has had to copy a string before surely
there's a function like called stir copy
maybe like stir compare like stir Ling
and indeed there is so let me propose
that we actually get rid of this whole
for Loop and we actually just call a
function called stir copy no o just St
cpy and pass in the destination which is
T first and then the source that you
want to copy into the destination and
that takes the place entirely of that
whole Loop so again I demonstrated the
loop first just to be very pedantic
about it but that's wasting time you're
wasting time writing lines of code you
don't need to stir copy is what you can
use here instead and so this has now
always existed and what more can I do
well as one final point it turns out
that there's actually things that can go
wrong in this code even besides the
string being too short like if the human
Just Hits enter and there are no
characters I don't want to blindly
capitalize the first character that
doesn't exist that's why I added that if
condition but there's other things that
can go wrong and we introduced those to
you today it turns out that functions
like get string and functions like Malo
return potentially a special value and
wonderfully confusingly it's also called
null but with two L's all right so left
hand and right hand weren't talking so
well like decades ago NL is a back SL
zero it's a single character as it
always has been for a couple of weeks
now
n is technically a pointer it's an
address but it's address zero it's like
the top left hand corner if you will of
your computer's memory that just nothing
is ever supposed to go in by convention
so null is a synonym for zero but it's
specifically an address now why is this
useful well suppose that in my code here
something goes wrong with get string
suppose you're being a little crazy and
you type in way too long of a string
it's not just high but it's like an
entire essay of text and there's not
enough memory in the computer how does
get string signal to the programmer whoa
like that's way too big of a string I
can't fit it in memory well we never
told you this but all of this time it
turns out that that get string will
return this special value called null if
something goes wrong so to be really
careful now you should do something like
this if s equals equals literally null
then you better um exit the program
entirely and return like one or two or
three to signify that something went
wrong don't uh go any further similarly
with malok it's possible if you ask for
way too much memory that could fail
especially if you're asking now for
double the memory after the human typed
something in so if T equals equals null
then you know what but let's also return
one or some other value to just get out
before something crashes or freezes on
the human as well so honestly I tend not
to do this always in class because the
code just gets so bloated and
complicated but you absolutely in
practice need to start doing this
otherwise you will be responsible for
the freezes and the crashes and the
reboots that users in the real world
might actually encounter otherwise of
course if we get to the bottom of this
program now I should probably return
zero explicitly or implicitly to just
signify that everything is is
successful but there's one other thing I
haven't done we introduced malok but
what did I claim also
existed so free I'm also being a little
reckless now here I am not practicing
what I'm preaching I'm asking the
computer for memory via get string I'm
asking the computer for more memory my
via malok and I'm never technically
handing it back so really what I should
be doing at the very bottom of my
program to is freeing the memory I've
asked for so henceforth it is a rule a
law if you will in see whenever you
allocate memory with malok or certain
other functions as well you the
programmer must free it when you're all
done with it now this is a bit of an
overstatement because technically when
programs quit they'll free the memory
automatically so you're not going to
break someone's Mac or PC because you
necessarily have this bug but for
programs that are running all the time
like someone keeps a chrome their
browser open Microsoft Word or the like
bad things will happen if over time you
never never never call free and the
program keeps running so always get into
this habit here you you do not need to
free memory that comes from get string
because the cs50 library automatically
frees it for you but you anytime you use
malok henceforth as you did or I did
here you must free that by just passing
in the same address you got back
questions now on malok and
free questions
yeah oh really good question so free
just so what does free do so free um
just uh lets the computer know that you
are done with that chunk of memory which
means that if you have a another line of
code elsewhere that same memory might be
reused and can be used again and again
and that's going to be necessary
certainly for any long running program
you can't ask for memory constantly
you'll eventually run out so you need to
free it in this way other languages as
an aside python you get another
motivation in a couple of weeks for it
is going to be Python and certain other
languages manage all this headache for
you but in C the goal here is to really
harness these capabilities ourselves all
right so it turns out like almost
everyone in the room everyone in the
room myself included you're going to
screw up when it comes to anything
memory related if you haven't already
segals are in your future but hopefully
there's tools via which you can detect
these things and fix them proactively
and not just use print def uh or debug
50 or rubber duck we actually have
another tool we can equip you with now
that help you find some mistakes so let
me do this let me close copy.c let me
open a program I wrote In Advance called
memory. C that doesn't do anything
really interesting but it's going to
have two bugs in it notice that I've
included standard i.h as always I've
also included standard li. which is
necessary now for anything related to
malok Andor free and the like line six
it's a little weird what I've done here
but this is like the manual way of
asking for enough memory for an array in
week two how do we ask for memory for an
array you very simply say int X3 and
that gives you an array called X of size
three but if you do it manually Now
using Malo what you have to do is use
syntax like this you call malok you ask
for three things times however big an
INT is now we know it's four so you
could literally write 12 here but this
is more generic so three times the size
of an integer will give you 12
dynamically and what do Malo return the
address of the first bite you get back
what do I want to put that well I want
to put it in a variable now the variable
can't just be int X because that's a
number it's not an address per se if I
want to store this address in a variable
I could call it X I could call it P but
in Star X just means that X is now the
address of a chunk of memory
specifically a chunk of memory that's
big enough not for one but for three ins
in total all right now I'm just sort of
naively putting our old friends 72 73
and 33 at the first second and third
locations in memory but perhaps based on
week two or week four I'm clearly
screwing up up here in a couple of ways
someone want to identify at least one
bug what did I do
wrong yeah like this is now you know
amateur uh stuff like I should be zero
indexing not one indexing so this has
got to be 0 one2 ultimately and other
bugs that are maybe more week four
specific other bugs it's more subtle
yeah I'm not freeing the memory right so
I'm not practicing what I'm preaching by
freeing this memory now suppose these
are non obvious and honestly after like
an hour or two of this like this
shouldn't be obvious yet it will be over
time how could I find these bugs with uh
software as opposed to just staring at
the thing or asking someone for help
well let me propose this let me first go
ahead and run make memory to compile the
program and it seems to work look fine
there's no syntax errors at least
dotmemory notice seems to work fine too
now this program doesn't do anything
interesting there's no printf or
anything like that but it didn't crash
there's no segmentation fault but that
doesn't mean there aren't bugs latent in
the software and this is true sadly of
all of today's software like Chrome and
Microsoft Word and other programs surely
have memory related bugs that people at
Google and Microsoft haven't yet found
but there are tools at least to find the
most obvious of those bugs and we're
going to introduce you now to a program
called valren so valren it's a fairly
fancy program but we'll use it for very
simple ways we'll look at your code and
find memory errors as it's executing and
try to help you understand where they
are so let me go back to vs code here
memory seems to be fine you know I feel
like okay I'm going to submit this
homework all is good no error messages
that's no longer the case now you need
to poke a little more at your code to
see if maybe there's still some bug
there so let me do this
valren and then space dotmemory so just
like debug 50 you run it on a program
you already compiled valren I'm going to
run it on a program I already compiled
let me uh zoom in on my terminal window
so we can see more at once and enter all
right the output is crazy cryp IC for no
good reason there's lots of numbers and
equal signs it's a lot of clutter but
there is some juicy information here and
let me start from the top down invalid
write of size four so write means to
change a value read means to like access
a value and this is again esoteric like
a lot of our error messages are but it
looks like uh after a block of size 12
allock and then there's these weird hex
notation there's some mention of malok
but honestly the juicy part here is
memory. C line six that's probably my
fault so let's look at line six per that
output let me shrink the terminal window
look at line six okay 12 is now Germain
right if you did the mental math of the
size of an INT times three 12 is somehow
involved here but line six is now uh
happening next year that's where the
memory came from what is this let me
Zoom back in where is there invalid
right of size four like what's perhaps
going wrong here invalid right of size
four what does that mean it's like a
very technical way of explaining the bug
is actually one line later on line seven
as we already identified
yeah indeed and I I misspoke a moment
ago the bug actually arises here with
line nine so after the allocation of
memory I'm somehow writing four bytes
incorrectly and unfortunately the onus
is kind of on you to sort of think
through deductively like what could that
mean but I'm clearly touching four bytes
of memory in these few lines of code
that I shouldn't be and hopefully here
is the light bulb already went off ear
oh I'm not zero indexing okay that must
mean that X bracket 3 as you note is
just too far past the chunk of memory so
I'm invalidly writing to four bytes that
I shouldn't be so again it's not super
obvious this is not super userfriendly
but at least it does give you a clue as
to where that bug is so the fix there is
going to be quite simply to change the
one to a zero the two to a one and the
three to a two that'll fix that but
there's still a second error and let me
look at the cryptic output again Heap
summary some stuff there okay this does
not sound good down here 12 bytes in one
blocks are definitely lost in Lost
record one of one very Arcane output two
but clearly related to line six again
our allocation of memory now here too
it's not obvious what the solution is
but memory is lost AKA this is a memory
leak and now the deductions kind of up
to you why what is leak oh wait I didn't
call free and so the second solution
here is probably to free x at the very
end of the program and if you really
want to be you should probably check
like I proposed earlier if x is null
just get out now while you still can and
don't even touch those other lines of
code but if you get to the bottom return
zero but really the takeaways are I
fixed my zero indexing of the array to
avoid the invalid right of size four and
now I'm freeing the memory that I asked
for so there should be no leak lost all
right let's try this again make
memorymemory no visible errors yet but
let me now increase my terminal window
again do valren of dotmemory crossing my
fingers and now all Heap blocks were
freed no leaks are possible I don't see
any invalid rights there's still a crazy
amount of output but none of it is
erroneous it's not bad now I fixed my
memory bugs and so now my my ta my TF
they're not going to find them either
because at least valr has proactively
done that for me questions then on
valgren generally it's those two types
of Errors you might trip over there's
not twoo much else in the way of Arcane
output questions then on
this no all right well what else might
be going on so someone alluded to this
earlier what happens when you for
instance forget the null Terminator or
you generally start poking around memory
that you yourself didn't ask for or uh
looking at values you didn't put there
well let me go ahead and open this code
of garbage. C in honor of Oscar the
Grouch here of sorts and here is a
simple program if I hide my terminal
window that just does something kind of
arbitrary I first declare an array uh
called scores uh but I made it crazy big
like 1024 like that's a lot of uh
integers but so be it and then I iterate
over those integers and I print each of
those scores out so I'm using week two
syntax here but based on this program
what have I clearly not done that I did
do back in week two I've allocated the
array I'm printing the array but but
Bute yeah I didn't initialize any values
for that array back in week two we
didn't do 1024 we did like three and I
typed in like three test scores or
something like that he here I'm
allocating memory even more than that
just because I really want to be
dramatic with what I'm demonstrating but
I'm not initializing those values to
anything and so here it turns out in C
generally if you do not initialize a
variable or you do not initialize an
array with explicit values there are
going to be garbage values there so to
speak remnants of that memory having
been used before probably by some other
function of yours some Library function
or something else while your program is
running not a huge deal with a super
small program like this but for anything
sizable memory is going to be used and
unused and used and unused that is
macked and freed again and again there's
going to be lots of garbage values in
the computer's memory by default so if I
open my terminal window here uh let me
do make garbage uh let me zoom in on my
terminal so we can see the output when I
runt garbage theoretically I should see
1,24 integers but none of which have
been initialized now I'm going to get
lucky with some of them and it looks
like wow okay a lot of them are
initialized to zero and C does in some
context initialize memory for you to
zero at least at the beginning but not
again and again typically but if I start
scrolling backwards in time at this
array of size
1024 where did these values come from so
just random positive and negative
numbers interspersed among the zeros
well that's because I'm literally poking
around a random 1,24 bytes of the
computer's memory who knows what's there
so the lesson here is that garbage
values are indeed this like term of art
it means that a variable that you might
have uh defined that you might have
declared if you don't give it an
explicit value who knows what's going to
be there and the lesson here is just
don't do that always initialize
variables to something either yourself
or prompting the human for
it questions about garbage
values you'll see them sometimes if you
print things you shouldn't or touch
arrays beyond their
boundaries all right so maybe to make
this a little visual too it turns out
that a lot of things can go wrong
unfortunately with poers and we've seen
some of them and here's another program
that's a little contrived it's very
simple and it just is about manipulating
values it doesn't do anything useful per
se except demonstrate some of today's
Concepts so in main here let me propose
that we declare a pointer called X
that's going to store eventually the
address of an integer apparently here's
another one called y that's going to
store the address of an integer as well
here now I'm allocating enough memory to
fit one integer now technically it's
four we know that but size of in just
gives me that answer dynamically so it
will work on all systems
and I'm going to store the address that
Malo finds for me in X then I go to x
and put the number 42 there all right
why it's the sort of meaning of life the
universe and everything here but star X
again just means go to that address and
put a value there so why I don't know
but it's just uh correct at this point
but what about this line here star y
equals 13 unlucky in this case what's
bad about this line here star y It's a
combination now of today's Primitives
and that point here
yeah yeah we didn't ask the computer to
allocate any space so why was not
initialized with an equal sign at any
point to anything and so what is inside
y so to speak like a garbage value maybe
it's zero which isn't bad because at
least it's nice and simple but maybe
it's some crazy large uh positive number
some crazy large negative number either
way odds are if I go to this address or
that address randomly with star y bad
things are going to happen and so let me
go ahead and propose well let's not do
that let's let's actually do this
instead assign y equal to X and we've
done that before and then I can go to Y
now and change what was a 42 to a 13
again why this is just for educational
sake but for now this does not crash
because I only dreference y with star y
after actually giving it a value albe it
a duplicate value similar to our copy
example earlier so our friends at
Stanford have put together a wonderful
visual it's about 2 minutes long allow
me to dramatically dim the lights if we
could and play with what happens with
memory when you do bad things like
[Music]
this hey Binky wake up it's time for
pointer fun what's that learn about
pointers Oh goodie well to get started I
guess we're going to need a couple
pointers okay this code allocates two
pointers which can point to integers
okay well I see the two pointers but
they don't seem to be pointing to
anything that's right initially pointers
don't point to anything the things they
point to are called Pointes and setting
them up is a separate step oh right
right I knew that the Pointes are
separate or so how do you allocate a
point e okay well this code allocates a
new integer point and this part sets X
to point to it hey that looks better so
make it do something okay I'll
dereference the pointer X to store the
number 42 into its Point e for this
trick I'll need my magic wand of
dereferencing your magic wand of D
referencing uh that that's great this is
what the code looks like I'll just set
up the number
and hey look there it goes so doing a d
reference on X follows the arrow to
access its Point T in this case to store
42 in there hey try using it to store
the number 13 through the other pointer
why okay I'll just go over here to Y and
get the number 13 set up and then take
the wand of d referencing and
just oh hey that didn't work say uh
Binky I don't think de referencing Y is
a good idea cuz uh you know setting up
the point T is a separate step and uh I
don't think we ever did it good point
yeah we we allocated the pointer y but
we never set it to point to a point
T very observant hey you're looking good
there Binky can you fix it so that y
points to the same point as X sure I'll
use my magic wand of pointer assignment
is that going to be a problem like
before no this doesn't touch the Pointes
it just changes one pointer to point to
the same thing is another oh I see now y
points to the same place as X so so wait
now Y is fixed it has a point e so you
can try the wand of D referencing again
to send the 13 over uh okay here it
goes hey look at that now D referencing
works on why and because the pointers
are sharing that one point e they both
see the 13 yeah sharing uh whatever so
are we going to switch places now oh
look we're out of time but L thanks to
Professor Nick parlante of Stanford for
spending a huge amount of time doing
stop motion animation for that but
hopefully now you have a sense of what
two can go wrong when you misuse memory
in this way but at the end of the day we
really only have these four new building
blocks today like the star operator the
Ampersand operator malok and free and
really with that and the underlying
understanding of what your computer is
doing underneath the hood we have this
way now to really manipulate things in
memory For Better or For Worse and
eventually we'll see how we can build
things but we can also now use today's
Primitives to better explain some things
that we've been asking you to take for
granted over the past several weeks so
for instance let me propose that we uh
do one volunteer up here if we could
could we get one volunteer who's you
want to come straight up yep right in
the middle come on you'll have to take a
left right
there
all right so we have two empty glasses
here and two colors of liquid and we
have let me give you the mic if you'd
like to say hello to the
group hello um I'm Moen uh I'm in the
and first year all right welcome well
well welcome here I'm going to go ahead
and fill these two glasses with this
colored liquid um purple here on my
right let's fill up a glass
here yeah don't drink uh and now we'll
put some orange in here
and what we'd like you to do for the
audience if you don't mind is swap the
two values we've got a purple value and
orange value and I'd like the purple
liquid in this glass and the orange
liquid in that glass
please can I have another glass oh okay
good intuition but for the microphone uh
can I have another glass so you can and
just in fact I brought one here for you
why are you asking for this though cuz
if I just pour this into this and it'll
get mixed up right so obviously we need
like a temporary variable if you will so
here is your temporary
variable and you want yeah there's
yeah all right so pouring the value of
the orange glass into this temporary
variable if you
will all right and now pouring the value
of the purple glass into the former
orange
glass and
now the temporary value goes back into
the original purple glass and now I
think we give you a round of applause
for having done that very well
okay thank you all right so so it should
go without saying that in the real world
like that's how you do this and in fact
in code that's pretty much how you have
to do this although ask us some time for
a super fancy way of doing it without a
temporary variable turns out that is
possible using bits but for now let's
suppose that indeed this demonstrates
what is the reality in code if you want
to swap two values you need to have have
something like a temporary variable so
for instance on the screen here is a uh
the beginning of a function called swap
whose purpose in life is to as you just
did swap two values call it a and b so
orange and purple respectively are now
just a and b and integers to keep things
simple well here is the corresponding
code if I may to what you just enacted
as a human you declared a temporary
variable a called temp in this case
which was like me handing you The Empty
Glass and you stored the orange liquid
in it akaa you then changed the value of
the formerly orange glass to be equal to
the Purple by pouring one into the other
and then you did the opposite there now
at the end of this you still have a
temporary variable that's now empty so
it's temporary in literally that sense
like you just don't need it anymore but
it was necessary along the way so I dare
say this code is correct logically like
this will swap two values A and B thanks
to the use of that temporary variable
unfortunately though if I actually do
this in practice let me go over to VSS
code here and open a program I wrote in
advance called swap. C which does this
as follows in here notice I have my
prototype for a swap function at the
very top and let me scroll down to the
very bottom there is that exact same
code so I'm uh the same code for
swapping two values A and B which I'm
claiming for now is correct now if I go
back up here what is main going to do
for us main is really just meant to be a
demonstration of the correctness of your
algorithm so here I declare on line
seven and eight two variables X and Y
being 1 and two arbitrarily respectively
I then on line 10 just print out what
the value of x is and Y is just so I can
see it on the screen I then call the
swap function on line 11 and then I
literally print the exact same thing
again I print X and Y hopefully it'll
obviously be the opposite so I think
logically swap is indeed correct let me
do make Swap and then do/ Swap and I
should see X is one y is 2 and then
hopefully X is 2 Y is 1 enter but I
don't and it did work in the sense that
the code compiled the code ran so it's
not like some bug in that sense but
because I don't quite understand what's
going on underneath the hood at least as
of right now or prior weeks this code
here is indeed buggy in some way but
does anyone have an intuition perhaps
based on today's discussion is to like
why this code while logically correct
clearly works in reality apparently does
not work in
C any intuition
yeah perfect and to summarize here's
that term of art I prom
when you call a function and pass in two
arguments Like A and B you're passing
those arguments by value so copies of
those values effectively and so when
swap is actually called here sorry when
you pass in X and Y we call them A and B
but that's just a convention we could
call the parameters anything we want
what A and B are are indeed the values
of X and Y respectively but copies of
the values so this code here is very
successfully in vs code 2 swapping the
values of a A and B but as you note
because I'm passing them in by value
literally one literally two and not by
another term of art by reference AKA by
their addresses swap has no capability
in C to go to those locations swap the
actual locations just like we did
successfully in reality but I think we
really have the syntax already for
solving this if we consider that really
this is just an issue of scope and we've
talked a bit about scope in the past
whereby scope refers to the context in
which a variable lives and generally
I've claimed that a variable exists
between the most recent curly braces and
that's pretty much true for the swap
function because a and b i now claim
again exist only in the context of these
curly braces they have no effect on Main
up top which has different variables X
and Y but we can consider now what's
really going on underneath the hood and
here's that same picture of memory as
we've seen in the past if we zoom in and
see on these little black chips this is
a bunch of bites of memory if I create a
grid out of it just to kind of highlight
that we can address each of these bites
throw away the plastic circuit board and
focus only on those bites what's going
on underneath the hood when functions
are called in C which you've been doing
for weeks now well this rectangle of
memory if we kind of abstract it away
further is generally broken up into
different regions or segments like I
called them earlier and different things
get put in different parts of the
computer's memory and without getting
too into the weeds when you double click
a program on your macro PC or when you
do/ something on a Linux you are loading
your machine code into the computer's
memory from the computer's hard drive so
all the zeros and ones that compose
Microsoft Word or Chrome or whatever are
loaded into the computer's memory or RAM
and by convention it's put up top in the
so-called machine code area and that's
how the CPU has access to them quickly
at that below that are what are be going
to be our globals so Global variables
which we haven't used very much in C but
you can declare them outside of main at
the very top of your files if you have
globals they end up up there as well
just FYI and then there's this big chunk
of memory that we saw valgren mention
indirectly earlier called the Heap and
it's kind of like Heap literally like
it's a heap of memory that you can use
as you see fit and the Heap is where
malok grabs memory from so initially
there's nothing in the Heap it's just a
big chunk of free space anytime you call
malok Malo kind of carves out from the
Heap area more and more bites and Malo
keeps track of essentially which bites
have already been allocated so initially
it looks empty but different bites
squares if you will keep getting
requested again and again as a program
runs thanks to functions like malok and
it grows if you will conceptually down
so the more and more memory you request
from malok it starts up here but then
the next chunk you get is down here
conceptually the next chunk is down here
down here so it kind of fills the
available space in the computer's
overall memory but there's this other
chunk of memory called the stack and
just like a stack of trays in like
annenburg or a cafeteria kind of grow
upward so does the stack of memory and
it turns out the stack is where
functions have variables and have
arguments stored temporarily so whenever
you call a function and it has variables
inside of it or it has arguments there
too this is the chunk of memory and the
computer's overall block of memory that
are used for functions but anytime you
call malok it's memory up here right at
the end of the day they just had to pick
a direction top bottom and technically
it's an artist rendition you could
Circle this thing around any orientation
you want but you're just using a finite
amount of memory in this conventional
way Malo Starts Here functions start
here now you can kind of see where like
bad things can happen and indeed one of
the other reasons programs computers can
crash is if you ask for way too much
memory from the Heap by calling malok
many many many times or if you call way
too many functions or accidentally per
last week you recurse infinitely many
times you might have a segmentation
fault and that's because you're using
too much stack memory so this is bound
to be a problem eventually and the onus
is on the programmer to just minimize
the probability of doing that and really
avoid the possibility of doing that by
just checking return values like
checking if malok or get string return
null because you can proactively with
conditionals make sure that these two
things do not Collide by just making
sure that you get back non-null values
so let's consider the stack in the
context of Swap and what's really
happening here and Carter if you
wouldn't mind helping me animate the
screen here when I call the main
function of any program it is allocated
a slice of memory called a frame at the
bottom of this stack so if Carter you
want to go ahead and uh Advance here
here's like the First Slice of memory
that will always be used by main whether
it has commandline arguments or local
variables it just ends up here in memory
suppose now per our swap. C program that
main calls swap well where does the
memory for swap end up like right up
here so swap had two variable two
arguments uh A and B and it also had a
temporary variable so all of those end
up in here in memory and if you want to
go ahead and Advance again Carter once
swap is done executing whether it just
returns because there's no more lines of
code or you explicitly return this
memory is just freed up automatically
you don't call free you don't undo malok
this just all happens automatically and
has been since week one now technically
it's still there even though we've
removed it from the picture and there's
your first hint of garbage values right
like there's still zeros and ones there
and they're left in the original the
previous configuration and so the reason
you get random values in the memory is
because even though we hav't drawn swap
here there was stuff there a moment ago
it's going to be there the next time you
use that same memory now let's go ahead
and step through this a little more
methodically main has two variables
called X and Y one and two so let's
advance and represent X is one y is two
taking up these two chunks of memory
when we call swamp now swamp gets a new
slice of memory that then gives us three
variables A and B technically the
arguments and temp so what happens well
because functions automatically pass in
values by value or rather pass in
arguments by value X gets copied into a
y gets copied into B and then once we
start executing the algorithm all the
watered glasses well what happens here
so if I execute the first line of code
temp equals a temp gets a copy of a what
happens next a equals B so a takes on a
copy of B and now we do the final swap
in the glasses b equals temp b gets a
copy of temp now we don't have to change
temp because it's essentially empty
although there's the garbage value one
is always now going to be there until we
reuse that memory the important thing
though is that a and b have been swapped
but what obviously has not been swapped
as is Manifest is when swap returns X
and Y are untouched because copies
thereof were passed in so we need a
solution to this problem and if we
advance one more time if you don't mind
let me step over here but then call you
back in a second this code here is
logically correct this is what you did
but this is now a detail of C you can't
just swap the things by value because
you're only changing it in the scope of
the swap function function but I think
if we change it to this and add some
annoying syntax we can solve the problem
just like you can declare variables as
storing addresses you can declare
arguments to functions AKA parameters as
taking addresses this new version of
swap means that a shall be the address
of an integer B shall be the address of
an integer and now it gets a little
cryptic here temp is the same because
it's just an integer like it was in week
one nothing special about temp but if
you want to get the value at a you do
star a and that goes to the address
grabs the number one presumably if you
want to change the value of a you go to
that address you follow the treasure map
to the other mailbox and you set it
equal to whatever is at the value of B
you go to B as well last line you go to
B now and change it to be whatever the
temporary variable was which happened to
be the same as a so that's where the
final value gets swapped but here
there's a lot more like crisscrossing
metaphorically across the stage where
you're going to all of these different
addresses in the swap function to make
these changes so if we advance now to
the pictoral version of this here's the
same story as before with Maine and X
and Y are 1 and two respectively when
swap gets called now notice and I'll do
it with arrows here a is effectively
pointing to X B is effectively pointing
to Y if we really get into the weeds
these are actually like addresses but
who cares about the specifics it's
really just the concept here so now what
happens in temp gets star a star a means
start at a and go there Follow the arrow
if you will sort of shoots in ladder
Style and then that's one so we put one
and 10th all right star a equals star B
so let's do it from right to left star b
means Follow the arrow it's two and then
what do you do Follow the arrow it's now
two because you copy one to the other
from right to left and then lastly star
b gets temp so start at B go to B and
now store whatever the value is in temp
so just by having this basic new syntax
of like ampersands and stars and so
forth we can actually now go to places
and circumvent what is otherwise a
feature of C that these variables are
locally scoped but you can still access
things in other functions as well so
thank you so much for helping step
through this so we now have a
application of this that explains why
now in this version of the C code this
would actually now work so in fact let
me go back to my swap code here and let
me change the function ever so slightly
in vs code so let me scroll down leaving
main the same and let me change swaps
prototype to taking in addresses let me
go to a here let me go to a here let me
go to B here and let me go to B here as
well but nothing else changes this
change here in particular is enough of a
clue to see that means when you call
Swap and pass into values I'm expecting
addresses now not integers but now that
I've made this change I do need to go up
to Main and make one change does anyone
have the intuition for what now need
change in main so that I pass in X and Y
by reference that is by address rather
than than by value or copy oh yeah and
[Music]
back so close so on the swap line it's
not star that I want in front of the X
and the Y it's
instead what's the other one it's the
Amper sand why because if I want to
enable swap to go somewhere just like
Carter and I played this game with the
mailboxes I need to inform swap of the
address of X and the address of Y and
again per the beginning of today's class
Ampersand is the text via which we do
that so I add an ampersand here to get
the address of X Ampersand here to get
the address of Y and now this code lines
up with the picture that Carter just
helped us walk through and so when I run
make swap here I have a mistake oh what
did I do wrong not intentional but I
guess worth pointing out I screwed up
here it doesn't like Ampersand
X because of something on line three
which is way early in the code what did
I screw up yeah in the middle
yeah so this is why we you should not
copy paste even though it's necessary
for things like function prototypes if I
change swap at the bottom I need to
change its prototype so let me add the
star there add the star there or just
recopy paste it at the top of the file
now let me do make swap again let me now
do do/ Swap and I should now see X is
one y is 2 and hopefully X is 2 Y is 1
which I now do so the logic is the same
the algorithm is the same all the weak
zero stuff is the same except now and
four you just have a bit more
expressiveness via which you can tell
the computer exactly what you want to
manipulate and how any questions then on
this technique
here no all right well when we fix this
there's still going to be problems and
just so you've seen some terms of art
here this is bad whenever you have two
arrows pointing at one another certainly
if you might use and reuse more and more
memory and it turns out there's some
terms of art that might suddenly now
make sense especially if you've
programmed before bad things Can Happen
by this design but there's really only
this kind of design because it's a
finite amount of memory so at some point
bad things are going to happen no matter
what if a computer runs out of memory so
it's not that this was a poor decision
it's just sort of a necessary one given
finite amounts of memory in a computer
but a heap overflow so to speak is when
you actually overflow the Heap and touch
memory that you shouldn't up there stack
Overflow is when you somehow overflow
the stack and touch memory that you
shouldn't down there so with that said
these are really just problems that can
happen and there specific incarnations
of what are generally called buffer
overflows a buffer like in the YouTube
sense is just like a chunk of memory
that in the case of YouTube stores like
the next few seconds or minutes of video
but generally speaking a buffer is just
a chunk of memory that the computer is
using for some purpose be it the stack
be it the Heap be it an array in the
computer and so buffer overflows are
what happens when you just have logical
bugs in your code but with these
Primitives now in mind we wanted to
conclude with a final Revelations and
that's how some functions like these
here work the other thing in the cs50
library besides the type def for quote
unquote string is of course all of these
functions and we give you these
functions because honestly in C it is
hard it's annoying it's painful it's
difficult to get user input correctly
it's very easy when you don't know how
much how much the humans going to type
to write buggy code when it comes to it
and indeed it's really hard to store it
correctly without accidentally having
some kind of buffer overflow so for
instance let me show you a program here
I'm going to go ahead and write this one
from scratch so let me go ahead and open
a file called get. C where I'm going to
go ahead and mimic the idea of getting
integers manually without the cs50
library so I'm going to include standard
io. only I'm going to Define main as not
taking any command line arguments and
then I'm going to do something like this
give me a variable x with no value yet
and normally I would do something like
get int but let me take that away no
more training wheels for get int either
so let me just Define the int X let me
then just print out something like uh a
prompt and I'll just do x c just to make
it obvious to the human what we're
waiting for and now I'm going to use a
builtin c function to get user input I'm
going to call a function called scan F
which sort of scans the user's keyboard
for input I'm going to scan it for an
integer so just like print F I'm going
to use percent I because I expect an INT
and then I want to tell scanf where to
put the human's integer from the
keyboard it is not correct though to say
x because if I say x I run into the same
swap problem scanf no function can
change the value of X unless I pass it
not by value but
by reference so we're back to our
Ampersand friend and now it has like a a
treasure map to the actual location of X
and can therefore change it and so now
at the very end of this program let me
do something simple like let's just go
ahead and print out with print F uh the
value of x using percent I as always
plugging in X not Ampersand X this is
now week one stuff I want to print the
actual integer value of x so the only
change here is that instead of using get
in I'm now using this new function that
as of today exists called scanf so let
me go ahead and run get make get to
create this program doget and let's go
ahead and type in a value for x 50 enter
and it just works so it turns out get in
is pretty simple to implement however
notice what does not work if I type in
cat for instance cat gets converted to
zero and meanwhile get in recall will
reprompt the user if a human not type an
actual integer you get automatically
reprompt so that's one of the features
we for cs50 added to get in just to make
your programs more user friendly but
otherwise get in is pretty
straightforward to re-implement using
scanf unfortunately that's not true for
Strings because how do you know when you
write your code what word the human's
going to eventually type in how long
they're greeting like high is if it's uh
if their name is David or Carter or
anything else you just don't know in
advance how much memory you need so how
might we do this in with string well let
me go ahead and declare a string s
although you know what there's no cs50
Library so we do Char star s today
instead and that gives me not a string
per se but a pointer that will Point
presumably to a string ideally I would
use this get string but again we've
taken that training wheel away so now
that I have a pointer s suppose I prompt
the human for a value for S just like
before let me use scan F now and tell
the user that I expect to read a string
percent s from the keyboard
uh and store it in s now this is subtle
I don't technically need an Amper sand
here even though I did for an INT and I
would for a float and a double and a
long and a bull and a Char why do I not
need an Amper sand in this story to pass
by
reference because s is it's already an
address again strings are just special
strings now are always addresses so you
don't need to additionally add an Amper
sand here that's the only subtle
difference here but now if I go ahead
and print out at the very end what the
value of s is using percent S as before
this program looks like it's almost the
same as the int version but let's do
make get and okay so this is not good
all right so it doesn't like an
initialized value so let me make it
happy I said earlier to always
initialize my variable so let's
initialize it to null so that at least
something is there that's your good
default value nowadays now if I do doget
now we're good and let me type in
something like cat
okay cat is not X well let me try
another word maybe it's just cat is
wrong dog okay let me try David it just
doesn't seem to be working moreover it's
printing it as a zero what logically
though is the bug here scanf worked a
moment ago for integers but it's not
working for Strings and it seems to be
forgetting C A it's forgetting dog it's
forgetting
David
why what's Happening
Here think back to our yellow pictures
of
memory when I
yeah it might be reading just the null
itself because s is being initialized to
null and what step have I forgotten from
just like a few minutes ago what did I
not actually request of the computer
like actual memory to store the C A the
dog the d v d right there's nowhere have
I asked the computer for some amount of
memory and so technically it might be
reading it into some garbage location
and that's really the problem here S is
initialized to null now and so in fact
it is printing zero as null but I'm not
seeing any of the other letters because
there was nowhere to put them C A do D
ID because I didn't ask for three bytes
four bytes five bytes 100 bytes there's
no use of malok there's no use of an
array there's no memory allocated for
anything other than the pointer itself
and this is where honestly life gets
hard with scanf like I could solve this
problem in a couple of ways let me go
ahead and do this instead of declaring s
to be a pointer let me declare s to
actually be a an array of four chars and
now let me go ahead and recompile the
code so make get doget and I'll type in
cat now that now works why well I'm
allocating an explicit array of size
four enough for a one two three letters
plus a null character here's where to
someone's question earlier it turns out
then in some context you can treat
arrays as though they are Pointers
themselves see we'll sort of do the
conversion for you but for now just
assume that s is just an array of size
four and if you pass it into to scanf
that's like a treasure map that leads to
those four bytes so scanf can now
successfully fill it with c a d o but
but let's try this again let's type in
David and here okay we got lucky but I
technically touched memory that I should
not and in fact if I typed in a long
enough string and I don't think I could
do it very easily like by without typing
this thousands or hundreds of times
still okay but you'll notice that it's
forgotten the rest of it now right so
somewhere we went beyond the boundary of
the array and we just don't have enough
storage space for that entire thing so
what do you do in your program if you
don't know how long the person's name or
the the the animal name is going to be
what do you do 40 400 4,000 40,000 like
at some point you have to draw a line in
the sand and that's why like getting
user input is so annoying in a language
like C and that's why get string exists
what we do if you're curious is we look
at the user's input and we take baby
steps we look at it one character at a
time and every time we see another
character we actually call malok again
and say no I need more than one bite I
need two oh wait they typed in three
letters I need three instead of two oh I
need four instead of two and we have
this crazy loop essentially that keeps
asking for more and more memory but by
taking baby steps and honestly if you
all had to do that in week one my God
like we couldn't even write hello world
anymore and so that's why these training
wheels exist at least early on and
that's why in higher level languages
like in uh python you don't have to do
this at all it just works as you'd
expect so what more can we do well
you'll see in problems set for this
coming week if I open up an example like
this phone book. C you'll see that you
can manipulate files now that you have a
vocabulary for pointers it's going to be
new quickly but here we have an example
of how I have a program using some
familiar libraries here but as I claim
in my comment this saves names and
numbers to a CSV file all of my examples
thus far I type in some words I type in
some names and some phone numbers and
they disappear because we only store
them in memory but if you want to store
data in like a CSV file comma separated
values which is like a simple
spreadsheet like Excel and apple numbers
and Google Sheets can open you can
actually do this yourself so just as a
teaser for this week here on line n I'm
using a new data type not a cs50 thing
this is a c thing called file but if you
want to manipulate files you need to use
addresses that is pointers so here is me
creating a variable called file that's
going to point to an actual file on the
hard drive on the server or your Mac or
PC fop is going to be a new function
you'll use that will open open a file
and it will return effectively a pointer
there to in memory the file name I want
to open is phonebook .csv and in this
example it's going to be uh a pen mode
it will keep allowing me to add more and
more names and numbers to this file
here's some old get string stuff because
I'm not going to reinvent get string
with scan F but down here is a slightly
new function it's not print F but
fprintf and it turns out it's very easy
to print things not to the screen but to
a file with fprintf and it takes an
additional argument instead of starting
with the quoted string you'll have to
like say what file you want to write to
and fr print F we'll figure out how to
get the uh the bits into that file
passing in something like name comma
number so if I run this somewhat quickly
here let me do this let me pre-create a
file called uh phonebook do CSV and in
phone book. CSV I'm going to create a
temporary row here name comma number
just so that there's something in this
file and now let me go ahead and do this
and split my screen here if I have
phonebook.com
and phone book. C on the left let me
compile make phonebook which is the C
version phonebook and now I'm prompted
for a name and a number so I'll type in
David and then for instance + one
949 uh what is it 468 275 o enter oh
damn it bug uh pretend that didn't
happen I forgot to hit enter in the file
so let's do this again if I run the
program Again David and plus one 94 9
468 2750 enter it's been saved now to
the file and if I close this file and I
reopen code of phonebook.com
or the like and I've actually created an
actual CSV file uh if you're smiling
because I keep repeating my phone number
out loud I would encourage you to call
or text that number sometime it might
very well well be a an Easter egg of
source but via these functions here do
we have now the ability to write files
uh input and output and among the goals
then for this week as we'll see are to
actually play with images in the spirit
of something like Instagram filters or
the like and we'll introduce you for
instance to a file format called bmps
which to come full circle to the start
of class are just maps of bits but more
than just single bits for white and
black but rather colorful patterns as
well and we'll give you images like this
of the week's Bridge here across the
river at Harvard and you've run
after writing your own code in C and
understanding how the data stored in the
computer's memory you'll be able to
apply your own Instagram like filters to
make things uh grayscale instead or
sepia in this case you can even flip the
bits around so that the thing is a
mirror image you can blur things further
or if you really are feeling more
comfortable you can even write code that
finds the edges of the image and creates
works of art like these so all that in
more in problem set four we will see you
next
time
[Music]
all right this is cs50 and this is week
five which is going to be our last week
in see uh but what that means is that
we'll have
okay
but with this week with last week and
really all of the weeks prior have you
been hopefully acquiring if slowly and
with some challenge like some
fundamental building blocks that are
still going to underly everything we
continue doing in the semester even as
we transition to so-called higher level
languages next week indeed we'll
introduce python a very popular language
that does not have pointers does not
have memory management at this very low
level but that's really just because
someone else wrote the code that will do
that for you and it's going to make our
lives easier because it means when you
want to solve a problem concept up here
to just get real work done or build
something amazing you don't have to
really get into the same weeds as we
have been deliberately this week and now
last but the goal ultimately is that you
better understand and can better harness
than all that a computer can do even in
those higher level languages So today
we're going to focus particularly on
data structures how you might structure
your data in memory which really amounts
to building things digitally stitching
together ideas and Concepts in memory
using this new building block from last
week which of course are these pointers
pointers allow you to store addresses in
memory like in variables but with those
simple addresses we can sort of leave
these breadcrumbs we can point from here
to there and we can conceptually stitch
pieces of data together but there's
going to be different ways of doing that
and today we'll focus first on what's
generally known as an abstract data type
and similar to a type in C more
generally it does actually have some
properties in it but the underlying
implementation details of an abstract
data type are ultimately up to you that
is to say an abstract data type can
represent one thing and can do something
but how you implement it allows you some
discretion underneath the hood so for
instance in the world of computer
science a q is actually a technical term
this is a type of data structure that we
could theoretically build in code in C
or really any other language but a q has
properties just like cu's in the real
world for instance if you've ever lined
up for something to get food in a uh and
get food in a restaurant or go into a
store or wait for the airport to clear
you well you've lined up in a queue Q
being some sort of line but what's
noteworthy about Q's are specific
properties they are first in first out
data structures either virtually or in
the human world which is to say the
first person in the line should ideally
be served first at the restaurant or the
first person in the line should get
through airport security first by
contrast if it weren't first in first
out you can imagine how frustrated you
would be if you have this sort of
inherent unfairness in fact if you've
ever been in line at a store a
supermarket or the like and all of a
sudden they maybe open a new line and
now the person behind you gets to kind
of cut ahead and go forward that's
because they've broken the concept of
the cube so it has this inherent
potential for unfairness unless you
maintain this first in first out
property this would be true too for like
a to-do list just for productivity sake
if you're in the habit on paper or
virtually making a to-do list ideally
you probably want to go through that
list top to bottom so that you actually
get the first stuff you thought of done
first rather than always focusing on
your most recent thought now within the
world of Q's there's generally two
operations two functions if you will
that any Q would have either in the real
world or in the virtual NQ is usually
the technical term to mean adding
something to a q but specifically it
means adding it to the end of the que so
that someone isn't cutting in line for
instance to go up front and then DQ is
just the opposite when it's time for the
first person in line to be served the
time for the first person in line to go
through security they are dced so to
speak so technical concept ultimately as
it's implemented in code but it's really
just a real world concept and these are
in contrast to another abstract data
type that we might call a stack and a
stack much like a stack of trays in the
cafeteria has sort of fundamentally
different properties you can still add
and remove things from them but consider
what happens whenever they clean all the
trays in the cafeteria or the dining
hall they put one of the trays down here
and then the next one on top of it and
then the next one on top of it it it and
so forth but of course which tray do you
presume presumably take as a user of
that physical
stack the top one presumably right like
you're not going to fuss down here and
try to pull one out and so that would
seem to have an opposite property lifo
last in first out is what characterizes
something like a stack and that just
makes sense certainly in the physical
world of stacking all of those cafeteria
trays because it just makes more sense
to grab the most recently added one the
last added one first and at least in
that context the trays don't necessarily
care what order they're using used in
but even then you could imagine that
maybe there's some old dirty nasty tray
at the very bottom that like never gets
used because you're constantly
replenishing the stack so there might
very well be side effects of these kinds
of features um you might be familiar
with using Gmail for instance or really
any email program what you're looking at
in your inbox is technically a stack at
least if you've left the defaults
configured why you get a new email where
does it end up not like five pages of
emails later presumably right at the top
and the next one's right at the top
right at the the top right at the top
and so if you're like me you're guilty
of eventually losing track of some
emails why because you've pushed so many
more emails onto the stack that you sort
of lose track of the things you got
earliest last in first out though is
maintained the most recent email you get
might very well be the first one you
reply to but that's not necessarily good
for responsiveness to everyone else out
there uh similarly if you store like all
of your sweaters in a stack like this uh
the uh like a pile of black ones below
which is a red and then a blue stack
might be perfectly fine for keeping
things organized it's sort of the sane
way to do it if you just have a shelf in
your dorm room or home but what's going
to be a side effect of using a stack to
store your sweaters if they're these in
this way as opposed to a queue
yeah it's harder to get the red and blue
one so presumably you're going to much
more often wear for instance if you will
black instead there now the operations
for adding things to a stack are similar
in spirit but just different vocabulary
you push something on top of a stack um
even though it's more like in the tray
world you sort of place it or rest it
but pushing means adding something to
the top of the stack and popping means
some removing something also from the
top of the stack so it's not a matter of
enqing at the end and deqing at the
beginning with a stack everything's
happening on top you're pushing onto the
top and then popping off of the top now
when it comes to actual code how might
we Implement something like this well
let's just focus on really how you might
implement the data structure itself and
we won't Implement any functions you
might implement the notion of a stack
like this we've seen type def before it
just means Define a new type of my own
struct means here comes a structure AKA
a data structure of one or more
variables within and let's suppose like
last time we've had we defined already
like a person data type using a separate
type Def and every person has like a
name and a number or whatever let me
just stipulate that person exists
already so here you might have to
implement a stack an array called people
of some capacity maybe it's an an array
of size 10 or 100 or whatever this is a
constant here in this context capacity
and every element in that array is a
person structure and I now have this to
size now this almost seems like a
synonym for capacity but maybe
intuitively anyone want to propose why
I'm apparently maintaining separately
the capacity of the stack but also the
size of the stack why these two
distinctions
here yeah
perfect the capacity is how high the
stack could be like how much room is
there for those sweatshirts in my closet
for instance whereas size is just
literally at this moment in time how
many sweatshirts are in the stack it's
either capacity or fewer presumably in
total there so what is capacity well we
could implement this in you know perhaps
a familiar way I might just Define a
const somewhere else in my code of type
int that just defines it to be capacity
50 but what perhaps is going to be the
downside of implementing a stack in this
way of how using an array inside here
like what's a downside now of
implementing a stack using an array and
this size variable
within what's a caveat here
perhaps any hands
yeah okay so it's going to be harder to
reach elements that aren't the last one
that is the most recently added one so
there could be some sweatshirts so to
speak way down below so we've seen that
before too but at some point too a
limitation of this design is is what
it's going to be finite right I can
maximally fit in this example 50
sweatshirts or 50 emails or 50 cafeteria
Trace which is fine but at least it's
indeed finite and at least in the
computer's memory it might be nice to
use more and more and more maybe as more
things are getting added to the computer
so maybe I make this 500 or heck why
don't I make it 5,000 or 50,000 well
what's the tradeoff there if I want to
have enough room to grow seems like I
should just crank up the value of
capacity endlessly but why might I not
want to change the 50 to 500 or 5,000 or
50,000 what's the trade-off there
perhaps just intuitively
yeah okay you don't want to touch memory
that you're not supposed to be touching
and in this case it wouldn't be that
wouldn't be a risk per se unless you
indeed overflow the stack but there's a
related issue in asking for that much
memory what would another downside
be yeah okay exactly so if you've got a
capacity of 5,000 but you're only using
one of those elements it's it's awkward
to say it non-technically which is just
to say very very wasteful right that's
just bad design it's correct it will
work for up to 5,000 elements but my
gosh you're wasting
4,999 extra spots and that's not going
to end well especially if you're using
more data structures in memory like your
Mac your PC your phone is surely going
to run out of memory if you ask for that
much so it' be nice if there is a bit
more dynamism there whether it's a stack
or a CU both of which might be
implemented a little similarly in spirit
but let's conclude this abstraction by
comparing thanks to a friend of ours
Professor Shannon Duval of Elon
University who kindly put together this
graphical animation that's just under 2
minutes long that paints a picture of
these two types of abstract data
structures and then we'll dive in
underneath to how we might Implement uh
problems like these if we could dim the
lights
[Music]
dramatically once upon a time there was
a guy named Jack when it came to making
friends Jack did not have the Knack so
Jack went to talk to the most popular
guy he knew he went up to Lou and asked
what do I do Lou saw that his friend was
really distressed well Lou began just
look how you're dressed don't you have
any clothes with a different look yeah
yes said Jack I sure do come to my house
and I'll show them to you so they went
off to Jacks and Jack showed Lou the box
where he kept all his shirts and his
pants and his socks L said I see you
have all your clothes in a pile why
don't you wear some others once in a
while Jack said well when I remove
clothes and socks I wash them and put
them away in the box then comes the next
morning and up I hop I go to the box and
get my clothes off the top Lou quickly
realized the problem with Jack he kept
clothes CDs and books in a stack when he
reached for something to read or to wear
he chose the top book or underwear then
when he was done he would put it right
back back it would go on top of the
stack I know the solution said a
triumphant Lou you need to learn to
start using a queue Lou took Jack's
clothes and hung them in a closet and
when he had emptied the box he just
tossed it then he said now Jack at the
end of the day put your clothes on the
left when you put them away then
tomorrow morning morning when you see
the sun shine get your clothes from the
right from the end of the line don't you
see said Lou it will be so nice you'll
wear everything once before you wear
something twice and with everything in
cues in his closet and shelf Jack
started to feel quite sure of himself
all thanks to Lou and his wonderful
Q all right so sure so that paints a
picture of these two abstract data
structures but if we really were to dive
underneath the hood we could Implement
them in a number of different ways but
we really I think need some building
blocks via which we could solve problems
like those and we'll see today to some
others as well so let's rewind back to
week two where we imple we introduced
you to your very first data structure
that is an array and an array of recall
was just a chunk of memory whereby
elements were stored by Design back to
back to back it's an array of contiguous
memory specifically so with an array we
could certainly store not just one thing
but two or three or even more and so for
instance if we treat uh my computer's
memory as this sort of abstraction here
and pictured here are three bytes or
some uh uh multiplication thereof
suppose we're storing in the computer's
memory an array of size three storing
the digits one two and three well
remember that if we zoom out per last
week there's other stuff going on in
memory so even if we want to add another
number to this array that we didn't
think of when we first started the
program like the number four ideally we
would put it right here next to it
otherwise it's no longer an array so by
definition if we're using an array it's
got to end up right there after the
three but what else is going on inside
of your computer's memory well assuming
your program is of any length and you've
got other variables other functions
you've been running it for a while
there's a lot going on in your memory is
being used and reused so for instance
somewhere in memory might be immediately
adjacent to this like hello comma world
back0 the null character just because
maybe you have another variable
somewhere in there that is storing that
particular string alongside your
existing array of size three and all of
these Oscar the grouches here really
just represent what we called last week
garbage values like there's obviously
bits there because they don't disappear
they're always going to be inside of the
computer somehow implemented but we
don't really know or care what they are
they're the remnants of those bytes
having been used for other older
variables previous function calls or the
like but the problem clearly here is
that okay 1 two 3 is there but the H is
here and unless I want to start uh
taking a bite out of my string by
overriding the H with a four like we
just can't fit it right there and yet
even though there's Oscars all over the
place those are indeed garbage values
and therefore we could use that space
because it's technically unused we just
don't know or care what the values are
so where could I put 1 2 3 4 well my
gosh like I have all this memory down
here that's unused I could certainly
change those garbage values to be 1 2 3
4 but to do that I might need to do a
bit of work here right it's not just a
matter of just saying boom and it
happens now with c and with code I'd
have to do this a little more
methodically so let me abstract away
everything else that's a distraction let
me assume that there is indeed at least
four bytes available for four numbers
just down here though we could have put
them in a bunch of different spots
what's involved now in moving the one
two three to this new chunk of memory so
we can add the four well I think
conceptually we're going to have to copy
the one from old to new copy the two
from old to new copy the three from old
to new and then ultimately we can get
rid of the old memory those three
original bites could now look like Oscar
the Grouch and just be garbage values
for all intents and purposes but now I
have room for a fourth bite wherein I
can put the number four so this is nice
but what's a downside of this
approach what's a downside of solving
the problem in this way where the
problem at hand is just to grow the
array so to speak to increase its size
to fit one or more
numbers seems pretty
straightforward but
yeah okay maybe it's out of order but I
think that's okay because the order is
just matters that it's relative so so
long it's it's still contiguous back to
back to back in a different chunk of
memory I think we're okay there it's not
like I changed it for 4 3 2 one but a
reasonable hunch
yeah yeah like I don't really plan ahead
here like if I have to add another
number like five or anything else well I
might have to jump through these hoops
again maybe I get lucky and maybe
there's space there but not if I have
other variables and other things going
on that too might be used at some point
other thoughts yeah slow efficiency slow
effic in slow efficiency why have
to again yeah I mean it's just in it's
just inefficient it's sort of bad design
arguably why because I had to copy all
of my original work down here and as you
note if I want to add a fifth number I'm
going to have to copy it again and again
and again and do things end times again
and again now maybe that's necessary
we'll soon see for sure but it feels
like this is not going to end well
especially if the array isn't of size
three or four but 300 400 your computer
ends up spending so much time just
spinning its Wheels I mean honestly
better might be this like if this is my
same array physically incarnated Now 1
two 3 it's literally on the edge of the
shelf so there's no room for the number
four you know maybe where we could take
this story is well let's just find room
for the four like let's just put the
four for instance over here replacing
some available garbage value some spare
bite over here but now wait a minute
I've broken the definition of an array
right it's I can't have one two three
and then four over here so maybe there
maybe there could be a mechanism if I
put this thing on again where when you
get to the end of the existing elements
maybe I just somehow digitally point to
the fourth array and maybe we can kind
of stitch together all of these
different values in memory so that if
you follow the arrows so to speak we can
reconstruct exactly what the order is
even without having to find or make room
here or pick up all of these numbers and
move all of them over there so that's
perhaps the direction in which we'll go
here so let's see how we might get to
that spot as follows let me go ahead and
open up say VSS code here let me open up
a program called list. C in my terminal
and let me go ahead and whip up a
relatively simple program that just
demonstrates what we did back in week
two when we introduced arrays as follows
let me include uh standard io. so we can
print stuff out let me do int main void
no command line Arguments for now let me
give myself a an array uh called list of
size three and I'll just hardcode it to
keep it simple for lecture sake Each of
which is going to be an integer and now
just so we have some specifics to talk
about let me put it list bracket zero
the number one list bracket one the
number two and list bracket two the
number three so I'm just translating
into codee what we just had uh
pictorially on the screen and also
physically here with these numbers on
the desk now let's just do something
mildly useful for this how about we do
four in I gets zero I is less than three
I ++ let's just print each of these
numbers out just to make sure they're
indeed in memory as I intended so
percent I back sln comma I and then a
semicolon and I think that's it for now
so nothing interesting no problem solved
just yet just a proof of concept so that
now when I clear my terminal and run
make
list no apparent errors at the terminal
and so when I now do do/ list I should
see hopefully from left to right 1 two 3
but of course if I want to add a fourth
number now there's no mechanism for such
certainly in the code that I just wrote
I could go back in here and change this
to a four I could go down here and
change lists bracket 3 equals 4 I could
just manually change the code recompile
the code but of course that doesn't give
me any additional run way for the fifth
or sixth number so let me try to take a
different approach drawing some
inspiration from last week if I want to
allocate memory dynamically maybe
because I don't know when I wrote the
program how many bytes I want we have
another function as of last week that
does not require that you commit in
advance to a certain number of bytes via
what function can you just ask the
operating system for a chunk of memory
okay so Malo to allocate memory now an
array is just a chunk of memory and even
though since week two 've been using
this syntactic sugar this convenience of
just using square brackets and indexing
into it it's just making it easier to
manipulate a chunk of memory that's
contiguous all together back to back to
back so today just like last week we can
take those sort of training wheels off
and maybe be a little more deliberate in
how we allocate memory let me go for
instance and do this let me delete my
contents of my main function here go
back into Main and let me propose now
that I declare for instance how about my
list no longer as an array but as a
pointer so int star list and I'm going
to go ahead and initialize this to be
how about a chunk of three integers for
now so I'm still going to hardcode it
but I'm taking a step toward more
dynamism for now so let me allocate
three times whatever the size is of an
INT but it's usually going to be four
bytes as we know so this is really going
to be 3 * 4al 12 but it's a little more
Dynamic and now what can I do down here
well this is just a chunk of memory
so I can do literally list bracket 0 uh
equal 1 list bracket 1 = 2 list bracket
2 equals 3 and voila achieve the exact
same effect because again an array is
just a chunk of contiguous memory but
malok gives you any old chunk of
contiguous memory so you can rather
treat one like the other here now if you
really want to be cool you could do
something like this instead you could
dreference the address in list and go
there you could go down here and
dreference list + one and go there but
honestly no one really writes code like
this it's just too cryptic it's a little
too far over the line at least for most
people and so I think the syntactic
sugar as I keep describing it just the
more user friendly square bracket
notation does the exact same thing
figures out the pointer arithmetic and
puts each of these integers in the right
chunks therein now just to be super
pedantic let me make sure if something
went wrong so if list equals equals n
that means that something went wrong
like my computer is out of memory which
we should check for typically so let me
just immediately return one signaling
anything other than zero which means
success typically just to get out of
this program because something's wrong
but now let me propose that I've had a
uh well let's do this for in I gets zero
I less than three i++ though a better
design would always be to use a con but
I'm just doing this for demonstration
sake let's print out each of these ins
too and just make sure I didn't mess
anything up and let me open my terminal
window again let me do make list
again okay huh implicitly declaring
Library function Malo with type void
star something something implicitly de
declaring is the operative words there
what did I mess up
yeah yeah I forgot the header file in
which malok is declared I remember now
okay that's in standard li. and it's
fine to look stuff like that up if you
forget so let me include standard libh
now let me clear my terminal run make
list again okay now we're good /list and
now what did I do
[Music]
wrong oh okay not intended but teachable
moment what did I do wrong
yeah yeah I'm printing the values of i
instead of what is at location I in the
array so what I actually meant to do was
print this out thank you you so now let
me recompile make
listlist and now okay those are the
three values I was expecting not the
indices thereof now let me propose that
for the sake of discussion that I I
regret having only allocated space for
three integers and maybe I really should
have allocated enough space for four now
this is not how you would do this in
practice because presumably if you have
a change of thought just go back in and
correct the code but let me propose that
somewhere in here is a more complicated
program and time passes dot dot dot
there's a lot of other interesting code
there but at some point I might want to
give myself more memory so how can I do
this well let me just ask the operating
system now for four new bytes of memory
so that we can at least in version one
implement the ID on the board where I
just copied the three bytes into the new
four bytes and then added a fourth value
so I'm going to use malok again and I'm
going to say here's a new pointer I'll
call it temp TMP for short which is
quite common when you just need it
briefly I'm going to then call malok
again I'm going to say give me four
integers using size of let me again make
sure so if temp equals equals null
something went wrong so let me just
immediately return one and for good
measure before I return one one let me
free the original list so that I don't
leak memory so I'm not just immediately
returning one I'm being a good citizen
and remembering well if this Malo call
did succeed and indeed I got as far as
line 18 but then line 18 failed I should
free the memory that I previously macked
so again that's the rule of thumb if you
allocate it you should be the one to
free it even before you're about to quit
now once I've done that I think I need
to do what we did pictorially on the
screen where I need to copy the One the
two the three from the old array into
the new so how might I do this well let
me give myself a loop so for in I gets
zero I less than three i++ because the
size of the original is still the same
let me go ahead and treat the new chunk
of memory called 10 temp as an array
itself and so I can absolutely use these
square brackets just like before it's
just a chunk of memory I'm treating it
like an array and let me add to that
value whatever is at the original list
at location I as well so this again is
just this exercise of copying from right
uh from old to new step by step the one
the two and the three but I still need
one additional step if my goal at hand
now is to have ultimately a fourth value
here well I'm just going to hard coose
this for demonstration sake and I'm
going to go to the very last location of
temp which is of size four which means
the last element in temp is temp
bracket three because it's zero indexed
but there's four total spaces there and
I'm just going to arbitrarily for the
sake of discussion put the number four
there and that is what happened when we
proposed uh changing the final garbage
value there to that four but now I need
to do what the slide did for us sort of
magically on the screen I should now do
a couple of final things I should free
the original list which I've not done
yet CU I only called free earlier in
cases of error and that was just to be
safe I can now free the list and now if
I want to inform the computer that I
want list quote unquote my variable
called list to point at not the old
chunk like it originally did but the new
chunk I think I can just do this list
equals
TMP and again that's just saying that if
list is a pointer which it was cuz look
at the very top line here on line eight
on line six I declared list to be a
pointer uh to a chunk of memory temp
meanwhile is a separate pointer to a
chunk of memory so down here this line
33 is just a matter of my saying okay
now henceforth because I've already
freed the old chunk of memory my list
variable should Point not at this chunk
of three bytes but this chunk of four
bytes or really 12 in total now uh or
rather 16 now because we have four such
bytes questions now on this code the
point of which was quite simply to
demonstrate how we could Implement and
code this idea of Fairly correctly but
inefficiently allocating a new array of
sufficient size and then populating it
with a new fourth
value questions on what we've just done
here no
yeah
[Music]
good question at this point in the story
with line 33 do I not have two different
variables pointing at the same chunk of
memory short answer yes but here's where
the semantics are perhaps compelling
list is the variable that I intend to
use longer term and keep around in
memory and again assume that there's
even more code going on here that we
just didn't write yet so it's useful to
have that that variable temp was just
kind of a necessary evil because up here
it would not have been correct to do
this it would not have been correct to
say list on line 18 equals the new chunk
of memory because this would have
represented a memory leak if I pre uh
prematurely change temp to point not at
the old chunk but the new chunk at that
point no one's pointing at the old chunk
and so I've lost those three bites vren
for instance would yell at you for
having lost as many btes in memory so in
this case here I do leave this as temp
yes it's duplicative at this point but
it's it's not a huge deal if it was just
meant semantically to be a temporary
value but down here at the risk of one
more line of code I still want to to be
a good citizen free list and maybe just
for good measure return zero explicitly
but notice it's not doing it twice per
se on line 31 what am I freeing the
original address of list the three
integer version then I change what list
points at so it's pointing at a
completely different chunk of memory
this one of size four So eventually when
I'm all done using this memory for this
demonstration I still need to free list
but at this point in the story line 40
it's pointing at the new chunk of memory
which I similarly need to hand back to
the operating system by free
yeah when would temp equal null so let
me scroll back up slightly this is being
a good citizen and a good programmer
whenever it comes to using malok malok
can return null if the computer's out of
memory so this is maybe a much bigger
program you've got other things going on
in it and so you just don't have enough
memory available to be handed malok
needs to signal to you that there's some
error and so it will by convention per
the documentation per the manual pages
return null so this is just me being a
good citizen otherwise here's another
error that might cause your program to
crash with a segmentation fault if you
get back null but you assume that it's
good memory uh going to address zero AKA
null will crash your program
intentionally
[Music]
yeah correct if I were to change my
final line 40 here to be free temp this
would also work as well and here this is
really a matter of design it's a very
nitpicky thing we could probably debate
it but because at this point in the
story my main variable for remembering
where the list is is called list this is
sort of the more responsible way to do
it freeing the list just so that my
colleagues my ta doesn't sort of wonder
why are you freeing temporary ver memory
that you already freed like it just is a
semantic thing at this point but good
Instinct it would also work correct
maybe just not good design all right so
it turns out that this gets annoying
quickly as it did in the picture of
doing all of this duplication and even
though technically it's necessary to
copy those values if you need a newer
bigger chunk of memory
there is at least a function in C that
simplifies a lot of this for us and in
fact let me go ahead and do this instead
of using malok this second time on line
18 in addition to the first time I used
it on line six I'm actually going to try
and introduce another function called
realloc which as the name suggests tries
to reallocate memory for you and it
works a little differently from malok
realloc expects two arguments the first
one is what is the chunk of memory that
you want to try to grow or Shrink that
is reallocate to be a different size and
then you specify what size you would
want and indeed in this case I want four
times size of int and that will now give
me hopefully a new address of a chunk of
memory that's big enough to fit all four
numbers but what's wonderful about
realloc is that it will handle all of
the copying for me so in fact I'm going
to go down here I'm going to get rid of
all of this this extra for Loop and what
I'm simply going to do instead is this
once I can
trust after lines 18 through 23 that
rioc worked and it didn't return null
because I'm out of memory I can just say
okay just immediately remember that the
new list points at this new chunk of
memory instead and then I can still now
do this line but I can tweak the
semantics here and just say list bracket
3 the new Final a in uh um the new list
is for I don't need to free this here I
don't need to do this all I need now at
the bottom is the final for Loop to just
print out these values so in short even
though that was somewhat quick using
realloc just moves the entire copying
process that I implemented myself a
moment ago using a for Loop it just
moves it to realloc and lets it deal
with the copying for me it's no more
efficient but at least means uh I'm
writing less code which is more pleasant
and hopefully the people who wrote aloc
or realloc are smarter than me and they
just will introduce bugs with lower
probability
too all right that was a lot any
[Music]
questions good question why do you still
need to make list equal temp as I did on
line 24 so ideally I would do this
ideally I would just change this line 18
to be list that is to say call re or
actually even better ideally I would
just say realloc this list to be of this
new size but again things can go wrong
when allocating memory you need to check
a return value to see if it was
successful or not and so we need to use
a return value okay so let's not
introduce temp let's just use list but
here's where a memory leak might happen
in the off chance realloc fails and
doesn't have enough memory for your four
bytes therefore it returns by definition
null you can't overwrite the original
value of list with null
to then check it why because now who
remembers where the original Three byes
were if you prematurely change the value
of list you've lost you've uh leaked
memory in that sense and so that's why
let me undo this change I declare a
temporary pointer for the sole purpose
of making sure I can check the return
value and then once it's good now I'll
update the value of list so it's sort of
doing a Switcheroo by making sure first
that you have a new value to swap with
the old other question
on this code
yeah indeed realloc automatically frees
the previous memory for you and better
yet it's even smarter than that if you
get lucky and they happens to be space
right after your existing chunk of
memory so one two three garbage value
instead of one two three hello world
realloc won't even bother copying things
from old to new it will just say okay
I'm going to now reserve for you more
bites than you originally asked for so
it doesn't have to waste time doing that
copying and so in that sense this
version is now not only still correct
it's even better designed because we're
not wasting time with that for Loop we
might have to resort to it if there is
in fact hello world or something else in
the way but hopefully we'll get lucky
and save those steps other questions on
this this manipulation of code
here yeah in the
middle
what if you want to resize a
two-dimensional array so very similar in
Spirit uh whereby you can use the same
trickery let me wave my hand at that for
now just because I think that's going to
sort of significantly increase the
complexity but very same Primitives
ultimately a two-dimensional array is
essentially just a doubly long or
quadratically longer list of memory that
using square bracket notation is doing
some of that mental math for you but
it's fundamentally no different of
what's going on underneath the
hood all right so with that said and
that code under our belt even though
that's not going to be something you'll
frequently need to code yourself let's
propose now how we might go about
building some actual data structures
ourselves the new ingredient here being
this reality that if you want to resize
a chunk of memory so is to make room for
things we now have that ability memory
addresses and pointers just give us the
ability to like Point around at things
and move things around in memory but now
that we have malok and even realloc you
can imagine maybe rewinding and you
could Implement that stack that Q using
not an array per se because you have to
commit to an array size in advance but
if you implement your stack or your que
using a pointer and then malok and
realloc and maybe someone else writes
all that code for you perhaps now you
can imagine that okay now the stack can
grow or Shrink by using realloc
accordingly you don't have to preact pre
um preemptively say give me five bytes
or 50 or 500 or 5,000 you can say just
give me one initially and if I need more
I'll realloc realloc reloc and if you
keep popping things off the stack you
can realloc in the other direction and
ask for fewer and fewer bytes and the
operating system can take that memory
back as well so we now have this
building block let's see what we can do
with it so we've had a few pieces of
syntax in recent weeks all of which
we're going to combine now in just a
slightly more clever way so struct is
this keyword in C that lets us build our
own structure in memory like a
collection of two or three or more
variables like a person that we've seen
before the dot operator recall we've
used when you do have a struct like a a
person and you want to go inside of it
so like uh person. name or person.
number we did this a few weeks ago now
but the dot Operator just allows you to
go inside of a structure and get the
individual variables within and then the
star operator unfortunately has a lot of
uses now one was multiplication like my
God that was easy back in the day now
it's used to declare pointers it's also
used to dreference pointers so to make
one exist and then go to that address
unfortunately it's the same symbol for
all of those but it's all related but
with these three symbols it turns out
you're going to get one last one today
and my God it finally looks like the
concept it turns out there's a clever
way anytime you want to use the dot and
the star together that is to go
somewhere and go to an address and then
look inside of a structure you can
actually literally use an arrow symbol
on your keyboard it's not a single
keystroke it's a hyphen and then an open
angle bracket but at least it looks like
an arrow and we'll see indeed in code
today the things I was drawing
pictorially on the screen last time with
yellow arrows you can actually now
Express as well in code and so here we
have our next data structure called a
linked list and this is one of the most
useful powerful Concepts in C it's the
kind of thing that you can take for
granted in Java and Python and higher
level languages but today we'll see how
we or others can actually build these
things just using these same Primitives
so a linked list is going to allow us to
actually do what we you know used a foam
finger for last week allow us to link
together for instance these three values
maybe with that fourth value over there
and then if there's a fifth you know
maybe this other foam finger points even
farther overway to that fifth value the
key being that you can stitch together
fancier data structures without having
to like pick all of these up and find
new space you just have to at least
connect the dots somehow we just need to
somehow point from one to the other and
that's going to make things much more
efficient it would seem so how do we get
there so here's my computer's memory as
always suppose that I'm storing the
value one somewhere in there and it's at
ox123 address whatever and I'm storing
the number two somewhere else in memory
Ox 456 and number three at address Ox
789 this is not an array by definition
why even though it's the only three
things on the screen what makes this not
an array it's not contiguous so this
violates the definition of an array but
you know especially since they're
sequential it kind of looks to a human
like a list so it would be nice if there
were a data type called list and there
isn't in C there will be in Python but
you know what if I could somehow like
Stitch together these three values so I
can get from one to the next to the next
then I think we could achieve the idea
the concept of a list without this
really annoying constraint that they all
be contiguous as in an array so how do I
do that well at the end of the day I
only have memory at my disposal right
there's no more training wheels to take
off here this is what we've got
underneath the hood of a computer so if
all I have is memory I think the
solution to this problem of stitching
together those values in a list must be
to spend a bit more memory that's
literally the only resource we have
right now so let me propose that if we
want to create a list conceptually out
of three values that are in random
although pictorially pretty positions in
memory let me just add a little bit more
memory to the picture so in addition to
storing the one I'm going to leave my
space myself some room a little scratch
pad if you will to use some other bits
as well same for the two same for the
three and you can perhaps see where this
is going based on last week if I want to
somehow connect the one to the two any
instincts as to what I should write in
this box here that would lead me
effectively from one to the two
what could go here
yeah we could store the address of Two
And so specifically what would you have
me write
here perfect ideally I would just put in
this box another integer one that
happens to be represented in heximal but
that's just a base system it's just a
human thing for us to look at I'm going
to put the value Ox 456 here so let me
go ahead and reveal that Ox 456 goes
there you can perhaps see further where
this is going well if I want to get from
the two to the three I think I need to
put below the two the address of the
three which gives me Ox 789 now if three
is the end of the list I don't want to
let it be some garbage value because
that would imply that it who knows where
it's pointing I need some definitive
value and just what would your instincts
be if I want to make clear with some
special Sentinel value that the buck
stops here what do I put what my my
options be yeah so null not n per se but
n l which was the new keyword we
introduced last week which just
represents an empty pointer if you will
technically the address o x0 so
literally the zero address and what
humans did years ago they just decided
you know what nothing should ever live
at address zero in memory we're just
going to reserve that one special bite
to be a special signal a sentinel value
such that if you ever see a zero address
in a pointer it just means it's it's
invalid it does not exist now now we
write that though a little more
pleasantly for the eyes as just n l in
all caps and that's a key word in C as
well but of course last week I claimed
that who cares where things are in
memory and honestly like this quickly
gets tedious even worrying about these
values so let me abstract this away and
propose that if we want to remember
where all of these numbers are in memory
let's give oursel one final piece of
memory that just allows us to start the
whole process let me allocate on the
left hand side here not room for a
number like 1 two 3 just room for a
pointer that henceforth I think I'll
call list by convention and then store
in that one additional pointer a value
that just kickstarts the whole process
this is the sort of treasure map if you
will that you get handed and this has
the address of the very first actual
node in memory now technically we could
just start with this but it turns out
we'll see it's just a little cleaner to
use a simple single pointer that leads
to the things you care about as opposed
to just starting with the first element
why well if you ever want to get rid of
this element it'd be nice if you could
at least still hang on to an empty sheet
of paper that indicates that the list is
empty would be one argument for that so
again who cares about these addresses
now now with the wave of the hand let's
just abstract it away and there are our
pointers each of those addresses in the
rec uh the squares at the bottom are
simply pointing to the next element in
the list the jargon to introduce here
would be that now that we have these
integers 1 2 3 but they're in these like
wrappers if you will these structures
that have metadata that is additional
data that is related to but not the data
you actually care about this is data
this is metadata this thing here
rectangularly we'll call a node n o and
it's just a term of art that means it's
like a container in code for storing
some
values this then is a linked list and
this then is the sort of graphical
incarnation of like one node pointing to
the other in this case case they happen
to be by chance and by design of this
desk contiguous initially but there's no
requirement that they be such the one
could be over there the two over there
the three over there I would just need
more foam fingers to point at one to the
next questions on this concept of a
linked
list yeah and
[Music]
back can you say that
again a good question do traditional
arrays start with a pointer that's
outside of the structure short answer no
arrays are special in C and certain
other languages and the name of an array
is technically a symbol if you will that
the computer the program knows maps to a
specific location in memory it's just a
label a synonym for a memory address it
does not take up space so to be clear
the name of an array does not take up
space like that extra Square on the left
but you do need that extra Square on the
left when implementing a link list so
that you can determine if the list is of
size zero there's nothing being pointed
at or size three in this case we're sort
of taking on more responsibility
ourselves
yeah how do you point to the next
element can you
[Music]
elaborate ah good question if each of
these elements is pointing to the next
how is three point to the others short
answer it doesn't at least in this
design we have more technically what's
called a singly linked list and as the
arrows imply it only goes in One
Direction so if you somehow find incode
maybe a for Loop maybe a while loop
somehow you're sort of encode over here
you have no way in code to go backwards
unless we changed this to a doubly link
list where I add another box that lets
me have arrows in both directions or
maybe I just kind of make it uh uh
circular and I connect the three back to
the one which you can totally do but
that tends to you know make life harder
because now you have to figure out when
you're stuck in a loop in your data
structure but it's doable as well but as
is it's a dead end by Design other
questions on this design
here all right well how might we
implement this structure in code well
let me just connect the dots to
something like we've seen before here
like this is how a couple of weeks ago
we introduced the notion of a a person
and we claimed a person might have a
name and a number last week of course we
took off some of these training wheels
and a string is really technically a
Char star in both cases but really
there's no conceptual difference beyond
that but let's use this same Paradigm to
implement a node as I described it in
that picture so let me get rid of the
name and the number because that's
related only to a person and let me
rename this structure for discussion
sake to node that then invites the
question well what needs to go inside of
a node well minimally an
integer but this is now where we need to
think a little harder just conceptually
even if you have no idea how to type it
at the keyboard what else needs to be
part of a node based on these
rectangular pictures that we've
drawn what more do we need
yeah yeah we need a pointer to another
node so if I don't know how to implement
this yet you know it could be something
like you know pointer to another node
how do I do that well you know what but
it turns out you would ideally say this
if you know that the next node is itself
a node by definition well anytime we've
needed a pointer we just use the data
type and a star and I'm going to
arbitrarily but I think reasonably call
this second square at the bottom of
those rectangles next as the name of my
attribute here but node star just
connotes that the next variable is going
to be not a node per se but the address
of a node and that's exactly what we did
you had me put Ox 456 Ox 789 in that box
which is the address of another node so
the way we would Express this in code
would be node star next but we could
call the variable anything we want now
this is a bit of a white lie but we'll
fix this right now this code won't
actually compile C takes you pretty
literally recall and if you use some
term at the top of your file that you
don't Define until later in your file
you're going to see some error message
right we've seen this when I've messed
up and forgot to include the function
prototypes at the top of my code this is
related in spirit I seem here on my 1
two 3 fourth line of code I'm trying to
use this new term of art that I invented
here in my code called node even though
it's a CS term as well but nowhere Above
This it would seem did I even Define
what a node is it's not a data type and
C every computer scientist know what a
node is but it doesn't come for free
with the language so I need to do
something else like I need this word
here to come first so that I can use it
here and so we have this sort of Catch
22 like how can a structure be
self-referential that is point to
another version of itself if the word
doesn't yet exist so the solution to
this in C which we didn't need for a
person because there was no notion of
listing connecting as a list we need one
more keyword here that we didn't need
for a person and we reuse that keyword
here so kind of an annoying detail but
if we preemptively call this whole thing
struct node you can now refer to the
thing on the inside as a struct node
star but then you can shorten the name
of the whole thing from struct node to
just node sort of an annoying sequence
of steps but in short anytime you're
building a node a linked list in memory
this is just the Paradigm you use type
def struct the name of the thing you
want to Define like node you use that
name on the inside if you want to point
from one to another and then you can
shorten it down here to just be called
node questions then on this code
here questions on what we just did well
if I rewind just a moment to that final
picture what would be the upside to be
clear of having jumped through these
hoops and added this complexity if you
will what problem did we just solve by
linking together these three values to
be clear
[Music]
yeah making lists that
are that are not contiguous if you will
so making lists that are not contiguous
in memory the upside of which is that if
I want to add the number four to this
list it looks like I could choose from
any chunks of available memory on the
screen I just need to sort of point from
the end of the current list to wherever
that other one is in memory what I don't
need to do to be clear is copy the One
the two or the three everything can just
stay put which means TimeWise I can do
this much more quickly it would seem
without copying things again and again
and even without using realloc to let it
do all of the copying potentially for me
all right but as we'll start seeing even
more in the coming weeks every time we
benefit and solve some problem we pay a
price there's a tradeoff what is a
downside as you might perceive now of
using a linked list instead of an array
yeah as much memory yeah I mean we use
twice as much memory because now in
addition to storing the integers one two
three I also need to store a pointer for
each of those and honestly even this
picture is a bit of uh simplification
technically in most systems today each
int would be four bytes technically
today most pointers though would be
eight bytes I just didn't want to draw
this weird shape on the board where the
bottom square is even bigger than the
top square but technically we're using
even more than twice as much space for
these pointers so there's that trade-off
now thankfully decades after SE was
invented memory is generally much
cheaper nowadays and so it's okay to
sort of spend more of it if you need to
and it depends on what you want to
optimize for but that's absolutely here
a downside what's another downside of
having transitioned to in a uh link list
you can't index into it now I haven't
even tried in code but when you have a
linked list you can no longer use square
bracket notation because why well square
bracket notation just assumes the
contiguousness of memory location zero
is here location one is literally one to
the right location two is literally one
to the right one to the right these
things even though I've drawn it from
right to left to just keep things pretty
there are gaps here and this is just my
interpretation of this these gaps could
be big they could be narrow they could
be down here up here they could be
anywhere so long as we're linking things
together in this list the computer can't
just use bracket zero bracket 1 bracket
two anymore because it can't do simple
arithmetic and jump to like the middle
and now here's perhaps the worst price
we've paid if you don't have square
bracket notation or really you don't
have
contiguousness what algorithm did we
just sacrifice for this
dynamism if you rewind even back to week
zero and we gave it a name in week
three what algorithm can we not use now
if we can't assume that the memory is
back to back to back to
back binary search why because binary
search just like the phone book back in
the first week requires being able to
arithmetically jump right to the middle
right take the total length of it divide
by two and boom you're right there in
the Middle with some simple arithmetic
here they might be laid out again with
these big or small gaps there's no
simple math I can do to just jump
immediately to the one in the middle and
in fact again if this TV were bigger the
two could technically be in memory be
way down here or even way over here the
foam finger could be pointing in any
number of directions depending on where
malok put the thing there's just no way
to do binary search and so it would seem
that we've paid another price indeed in
terms of it performance we're now
talking about linear time again so
that's a regression now that's also a
lot things like feels like a good time
for some muffins and fruit out in the
lobby and when we come back we'll try to
solve the problem we just created so see
you in 10 so we are back and let's see
if we can't now take some of these
higher level concepts of like stitching
together these nodes in memory and
translate it to some actual code but
we'll do it step by step first before I
actually start writing it in vs code so
if Carter you wouldn't mind helping me
step through with some visuals let me
propose that line by line we solve some
of the problems that we've just created
for ourselves in building this thing in
memory so let's go ahead and first
consider how we could build a length
list containing the numbers indeed one
then two then three and let's translate
each of those steps to code and then
we'll put it all together into something
that actually runs so how about first
step here will just be this to declare a
pointer called list that's initially has
no value at least at this point in the
story list is the name of the variable
node star just means that this is
essentially going to be our little
square over here that points to the
beginning of the list of course it's
ideal If It ultimately has a value
because when we initially I'll call this
line of code it just gives us indeed
that square over here on the left but
it's got a garbage value because there's
no equal sign on the other side there so
let's propose that we do one more step
here and actually initialize it to null
so that if only we know that it's not
garbage it at least has some known value
and null is a good way of signifying
that at this point in the story The List
is empty indeed null indicates there's
no nodes in the list so that picture
would now look like this whereby let's
just draw instead of writing null
everywhere I'll just leave the squares
blank when it's not a garbage value per
se it's literally Ox Z or null all right
so that's it for building a link list of
size zero like we're sort of done then
but we want to now add a one and then a
two then a three so next step here might
be this if I want to allocate the first
of my rectangles on our previous picture
I'm going to call malok and I'm going to
ask for enough memory to fit a whole
node now technically I think that's
going to be like four bytes for the int
and eight bytes for the pointer even
though I did not draw it to scale on the
board so that's technically going to be
what 12 bytes but again size of node
just figures out how many bytes I
actually need dynamically that's going
to return to me the address of that
chunk of memory which apparently I'm
going to store inside of a temporary
variable called n for short for node but
let's see what this does pictorially so
when this line of code is executed I
first get on the left that variable n
it's got a garbage value by default
because I haven't executed the whole
thing from right to left meanwhile on
the right hand side of the expression
I've got now a node somewhere in memory
it happened to be free here this is
where malok put it for me but it does
have two garbage values initially but
because it's a node per my type def
earlier every node I proposed is going
to have a number and a next pointer so
we can see those labeled here but
they've got two garbage values initially
but all I care about initially is that
ultimately n is pointing at that chunk
of code so initially if we could back up
two
steps we have two steps so we have initi
one step forward we have this line of
code gives us this variable here which
has garbage when this side of the
expression is executed that allocates
the memory and then when we copy from
right to left the address of that chunk
of memory that's what gives us
conceptually this arrow and the garbage
goes away because it's a valid pointer
now of course there's still two garbage
values there because we haven't set this
node to store a number like the number
one so let's go ahead and execute one
other line of code like this which while
cryptic looking is just an application
of ideas we've seen in week four and
prior star N means to start at this
variable and go there Follow the arrow
is what the star or the D reference
operator does for us and then the dot
operator recall when we first introduce
structs like for a person struct allows
us to go at the number field or the next
field so if I do star n and then in
parentheses to make sure order of
operations is preserved do number and
then assign it the actual number one
which puts the one in the top of that
rectangle now admittedly this syntax is
not very user friendly it's annoying to
remember you have to the parentheses so
there's another Syntax for this whenever
you're doing two things like this in
code dereferencing a pointer that is
going to an address and then further
using the dot notation to go inside of
the structure you find that wonderfully
C gives us this syntax whereby you can
just change the star and the parentheses
and the dot to just be an arrow and
again it's not a single character on
your keyboard it's a hyphen and then an
open angle bracket but I kind of like
the semantics of this because this code
now pretty much matches the picture n
arrow leads you to the value that you
want to access or ultimately change in
this way there's one step though we've
forgotten of course which is that we
can't leave this garbage value here
because the garbage value is some
unknown value that effectively is
pointing who knows where and we don't
want to accidentally misinterpret that
garbage value as being a valid address
and risk going there so of course what
value should we put here instead our old
friend null just to signify that this is
indeed the end of the list and we could
do that with a line of code like this
and again we'll canote as much by just
leaving that empty box blank so now we
have a list of size one let's go ahead
and add the second number to it as with
these lines here list equals n allows us
to remember that indeed we have this
list here so if we can step one step
forward here's what the picture now
looks like and technically let's go one
step further here this is now really
what's going on in memory once my list
of size exists my main variable called
list is pointing at exactly that first
node at this point in the story I don't
need to know or care about the temporary
variable that I called n even though it
might very well still be there but
indeed this now represents that link
list let's now indeed add the number two
so with the same line of code as before
I'm going to allocate another node size
of node ideally I would be checking for
null here but we're doing the juicy
Parts only on the slides let's now go
ahead and depict that so what happens
with this this brings back our n pointer
which might have been there the whole
time but we're doing this step by step
it's a garbage value though because we
haven't yet copied from right to left
Malo of course gives us a second chunk
of memory which maybe ends up there with
two garbage values by default I've
omitted the labels now just because
they're still going to be number and
next respectively once we copy from
right to left the garbage value indeed
becomes an arrow Oscar disappears
because it's now indeed a valid pointer
pointing here now the values themselves
number and next are invalid garbage
values so here is where we can now start
using our new syntax like the arrow
notation or the star and the dot if you
prefer and we can change the value of n
Follow the arrow to number and that
becomes two similarly we can do this
again and set n arrow next so start at n
Follow the arrow access the next field
and set that equal to null now we're not
quite done yet because we haven't
actually linked things together so
here's now where things get interesting
how do I combine these two well let me
me propose this let me propose on our
next line here we actually update for
Now list equal to n that is to say
whatever address this is whatever it's
pointing at change list to be the same
address that is point at the same thing
so if n is pointing here let's change
list to point here and go ahead and do
that Carter if you could I don't like
this can you go one further step this is
bad what is wrong about my sequence of
operations here where I updated list to
point my new
node
yeah yeah we lost the pointer to the
other node so I don't even care about
the ordering 21 or one two the bigger
problem now as the lack of arrows over
there suggests is that I have a memory
leak I have orphaned my original node in
the sense that nothing is pointing at it
anymore now absolutely I could fix this
by adding some temporary variables I
could add it to the mix but at this
point in the story I have not done any
such uh recollection thereof so let me
back this up and let's go forward in the
slides this is where we left off a
moment ago I think I need to take into
account order of operations and I'm
going to keep this simple I'm not going
to care about the order of the numbers
for now I'm fine with a list that is two
and then one so with that said let me go
ahead and update I think this box here
to point at my original node so let's
see how we can do this in code okay n
arrow next so n arrow next should equal
the current list and this is a little
weird again but recall what list is list
is this pointer here that just contains
the address of the original address of
the list or equivalently it contains
this Arrow whatever it's pointing at so
what this means in this line of code n
bracket next means start at n Follow the
arrow access the next pointer and set it
equal to whatever list equals so if list
is pointing here then next should point
there as well this I think is safe
because now we have redundancy now we've
got two pointers pointing at the
original list and now I think we can do
another step whereby we update list to
equal n same line of code before that
got us into trouble but I'm doing it
second now instead of first when I
execute list equals n this now sets list
equal to the same thing that n equals
and so now I have successfully inserted
my new node containing two into the list
and in fact if we advance one more we
can just clear up the Clutter assume
that the temporary variable is gone from
the story now we have a linked list
where admittedly ordering is wrong it's
21 instead of one two but at least it's
linked correctly and I didn't orphan or
leak any
memory questions on this sequence of
steps
here yeah in
[Music]
back yeah spot on so this would fall
under that category of a stack if you
will although I've not called it that by
name because I just pushed the number
two onto this data structure if you will
and indeed it ended up at the beginning
of the list instead of the end and so
here's where we see a distinction
between an abstract data structure which
is where we began a stack is a thing
like the pile of sweaters that just has
push and pop properties and lifo access
like uh last in first out how do you
implement something like that in memory
well it would seem that you could
implement the notion of a stack here not
for sweaters but for numbers using a
linked list so long as you implement
insertion AKA pushing by prepending new
values to the list by prepending again
and again and if Carter you don't mind
hitting the keyboard one more time if I
wanted to add the number three now you
would could imagine prepending it to the
list why well honestly especially as
this list gets longer and longer I kind
of like the appeal of prepending these
elements why because even if this list
gets crazy long and way way out here you
didn't notice me following all of the
arrows earlier to do the insert if I
want to insert a fourth number a fifth
number a sixth number all I have to do
is like insert it here if you will point
it at the original uh start of the list
then update this pointer and done and I
would say that's like two steps give or
take it's not going to be end steps as
it would be if I had to upend the new
nodes to the end of the list now of
course we've sacrificed ordering of
these numbers they're literally in the
opposite order or whatever order they
were inserted in but that might very
well be okay depending on the goal at
hand all right thank you to Carter for
stepping through this what if now we
wanted to translate this oh sure thank
you it's all for you none for me in this
example so here we have perhaps a way of
translating this now to some actual code
and this will be the last of like the
sort of intense code here just to give
you a sense of how we can translate this
idea now to actual step so this is list.
C and VSS code here let me go ahead and
make a couple of changes up top let me
go ahead and how about uh declaring a
node using typ def uh struct node using
our new framing as before I'm going to
give every node a number as I proposed
and every node a pointer to the next
element which is going to be implemented
just as before and I'm going to simplify
the whole name as just node so all of
that is is the exact same type depth
that we proposed earlier now let me go
ahead and get rid of all of this code
which we wrote earlier and recall that
this was the most recent version that
was not a linked list this was just in
Array that we allocated and then
reallocated so this is sort of the old
way of doing things but it was
inefficient because we might have to
lean on a for Loop or lean on realloc to
copy everything around we're now going
to reimplement the notion of a list as
an actual linked list not as an array so
my main function now might do something
like this and I'm going to really just
copy the lines of code that we just
stepped through on the board so let me
give myself a uh special variable called
list that's going to be initialized to
null and this is just my pointer the
square on the left hand side of the
screen that represents the start of the
list and if it's null it means the list
is empty so done I'm done implementing a
linked list of size zero well now how do
I want to run this code well let me
propose for the sake of discussion that
this version of the program will take
command line arguments so I want to be
able to do something like this I want to
run this program ultimately and type in
three command line arguments like this 1
2 3 and I want my program in a couple
minutes to allocate one two three nodes
and Stitch them together just like the
visualization on the board uh I could
use get int but it's just going to be
faster if we use command line arguments
so again I'm just borrowing some
Concepts from week two but none of
that's possible yet until I change my
code here so let's do this in argc uh
string uh argv but you know what we know
that strings are not actually a thing
anymore so I can change my command line
argument definition to be what it really
is it's really charar but it's the exact
same thing as in week two just strings
are no more at least without the
training wheels on anymore like last
week and now let me do this uh for in I
equal 1 uh I is less than ARG C i++ so
what I'm doing with this Loop is I just
want to iterate over the command line
argument so I have one number at a time
from The Prompt um what else do I want
to do here uh well let's go ahead and
how about do this um let's get
a number so in number equals arv braet I
so a couple of notes Here one I'm
starting my for loop at one instead of
zero but I'm going up to RC RC is
argument count how many words are at the
prompt why am I starting at one instead
of zero though given my
goal why am I starting at one
yeah yeah so the first value in RV is is
actually the name of the program that's
obviously not a number so I want the
second value so I'm going to start
iterating over those command line
arguments at I equals 1 so that's all I
just want to get the actual numbers at
the prompt um unfortunately argv bracket
I is a string AKA Char star that is not
an INT so this line of code won't work
but can anyone think back to like week
two where we had a function for
converting strings to
integers anyone yeah so a to I is a
function that converts asky to an
integer assuming what you give it as an
argument looks like a number like one or
two or three so let me fix this let me
actually do the conversion if I were
really being careful I would error check
this make sure that there's no digits
just like you might have in problem set
two but for today's purposes I'm just
going to assume the honor System that
the user me is going to run the program
correctly all right so now that I have a
variable containing the number from the
command line let's just allocate a node
for it so let me do node star n just
like we did in the visualization and
let's malok enough space for the size of
one such node here I now need to just be
super safe so if n equals equals null
like if I'm out of memory you know what
let me go ahead and just immediately
return one here otherwise if that's not
the case let me go ahead and update the
number field of this new node which it
line 24 does exist because it did not
return null so I did not exit early with
return and let me just store whatever
number that human typed in first so the
return value of a to I which per line 17
is in my variable called number and then
let me go ahead and just prepend this to
the list let me go ahead and say that um
this next field first has a known value
null just so that we get rid of that
second garbage value and let me go ahead
and now prepend it to the list so if I
want to prepend it that means this new
node must have a next field field that
points to the current beginning of the
list and again the goal here is to preen
Preen Preen so whatever the current list
is let's change it so that this new node
points to that existing list and now
step two as before was to update the
actual list to point at this node so
recall in red on the screen before I
screwed up originally and I only did
this line by moving the pointer too
early if you will but I fixed that once
Carter helped me rewind and we got rid
of the red line which indicated error
and I just do n arrow next to change the
next field of this new node to point to
the existing list so I'm not orphaning
anything all right at this point in the
story I think my code is
correct not batting very well though
today but I think my code is correct but
the program doesn't do anything
interesting so it would be nice to kind
of now iterate over this link list in
memory whatever its order is and print
things out well how do we do that well
it turns out if you want to iterate over
a linked List the general Paradigm is to
do something like this to define a
temporary variable I could call it temp
but another convention that you might as
well see is called pointer PTR for short
but you can call it anything you want
and you can have a temporary variable
first point at the first node in the
list and then in some kind of loop like
a while loop you point it at the second
node in the list and then you keep
iterating you point it at the last node
in the list and then eventually you
iterate too far effectively pointing at
null at which point your while loop can
presumably terminate so how do I
Implement that idea of allocating a
temporary pointer that just points at
each node in the list and lets me print
out ultimately each of those numbers
well let's go back to my code here and
let me do this let me go ahead and
declare this temporary pointer which is
going to be a node star also why because
it's the address of a node the first the
second the third and I'm going to set
that equal to whatever the beginning of
the list is so that is going to be
equivalent to this version of the
picture here where pointer is just
temporarily pointing at the first node
in the list it's not pointing at list
per se it's pointing at the first node
in the list which list is also pointing
at itself all right once I've done this
I think I can translate this to code
that's a little new but it's
conceptually familiar perhaps now while
that pointer does not equal null so
while I have a valid pointer like my
finger or that arrow is pointing at an
actual node in memory well let me go
ahead and print it out so let me print
out with percent I back sln whatever is
in the current node at the number field
within and again this is going to have
the effect hopefully of first printing
the three and I think I just need to Now
update the pointer so that on the next
iteration it's pointing at the next
value so if this is where the story is
how do I update pointer to point at the
second element of the list well I want
pointer to point at the two and I want
pointer to eventually point at the three
well how do I do that well the way in
code I can follow these arrows is as
follows if I currently have pointer
pointing at this node but I want to
point it at the next node I can borrow
this pointer here so whatever this
address is in the first node aka the
next field I can copy that into pointer
because then pointer will point at
whatever this is pointing at by just
setting one equal to the other so once
I've done that the picture will
become this and how do I translate that
to code it while new syntax is
surprisingly straightforward all I need
do is say pointer after printing it
equals whatever pointer currently is but
grab its next field
instead and this is a very common
Paradigm when iterating over a link list
and you're using some temporary variable
like pointer you can simply set pointer
equal to pointer next and what that
means here is as follows if this is
pointer pointing from here down to here
pointer next is Follow the arrow grab
the next field so if you set pointer
equal to this thing that's the same
thing as pointing this at this same box
and indeed if I advance to the next
slide even though the arrows are
technically pointing at different parts
of the rectangles that's just for
graphic sake pointer is now pointing at
the second node and when I do this again
on my next iteration it points at this
and then this last step notice when I
keep doing pointer equals pointer next
this will become eventually this value
but what's this value in this link list
it's null technically so this Arrow will
eventually take on this value when I set
pointer equal to pointer next and at
that point PTR my temporary pointer is
going to be null so it might as well
look like this pictorially and what does
that mean for my Loop once pointer is
null because you've walked off the end
of the length list what's going to be
true of this Loop here started in line
32 any OB observations
here what's going to be true what will
happen now as soon as we hit the end of
the list yeah
sorry the loop is going to break out why
because line 32 which is constantly
asking well pointer does not equal null
well if pointer finally equals null
three steps later the four the while
loop is now done and so what I can do at
the end of this program once I've
printed out those values well first
let's go ahead and open my terminal
window let's make list okay a compile
do/ list and let me try the same values
one and two and three that's going to
again allocate one node two node three
nodes by prepending prepending
prepending each of those values and it's
then going to iterate over them from
left to right and so when I hit enter
now what should I see on the screen if
my code is
correct what will I see feel fre to just
call it
out 321 because I've prepended
presumably and here we go I indeed see
321 so the list is is backwards but all
of the elements are there now
technically if I ran valgrind on this
valgren would not be happy because I
have never freed any of my memory so I
should probably now have a second Loop
here that does something like this let
me again set pointer equal to list I
don't need to redeclare it because I've
already created this thing on line 31 I
just want to reset it to be the
beginning of the list again and now I
can do the same kind of thing while PTR
not equals null go ahead and do this
well I don't want to just do free
pointer and then do pointer gets pointer
next y my goal is to free all of my