cryptic and uninteresting URL notice at
the very end of it and I'll zoom in in a
moment what do you see slh hello.html
which follows the convention I claimed
before break is how a browser would
allow you to to access a specific file
on a server by doing slash and then the
name of the file name everything before
it is very cryptic it would be better if
I you know uh buy a domain name that's a
little more easy to remember and set
that up some other time but for now
let's just focus on only the file names
that I'm actually creating all right so
the code is up and running underwhelming
though it might be with the body in the
middle of the page and let me zoom in up
here too hello comma title is indeed in
the tab just as promised so what's
actually going on with code like this
that we just created well let's go back
to the slide version of the same and let
me just highlight a few of these lines
the very first line is what's called
your document type declaration doesn't
really matter to remember that by
phrasing and this is just something you
copy paste or do from memory at the top
of any HTML file that you create when
making your own web page it's a implicit
indicator to the browser that you're
using the very latest version of HTML
which is version five you don't mention
the number five just browsers now
nowadays are program to look for this to
know that you're using the very latest
version of the language languages just
like human languages evolve over time
we're up to version five of HTML but new
features get added every few years so
indeed this lecture this class has been
evolving over time too so let's now
focus on the next line as well as the
bottom line and you'll notice some
deliberate symmetry here this here is
what we're going to call a tag and it's
technically different from this this is
a document type declaration it's got the
weird exclamation point that's the only
anomaly everything else follows pattern
this is a tag in HTML and it's the HTML
tag and a tag generally both starts and
stops or opens and closes at some point
so this is the so-called start tag or
open tag and this just means essentially
to the browser hey browser here comes
some HTML the language in which web
pages are written this here with the
forward slash after the angled bracket
means hey browser that's it for the HTML
of this page so that's what I mean by
symmetry I started a thought here
finished it down here what's in between
those two thoughts well here browser or
rather let me clarify one thing this
thing here is that other uh keyword an
attribute an attribute is something that
modifies the behavior of a tag so it's
similar to an argument in C or in Python
like a parameter to a function these
aren't functions but it's the same idea
it just modifies the default behavior of
something instead Lang equals you can
probably guess just means that hey
browser assume that everything Hereafter
is in English and that might be useful
for like Google translate or just search
engine optimization so that just the
server the browser know like what human
language you have actual content in like
hello title hello body even though a
good computer can probably infer from
Context often all right so that's an
attribute that's a tag and the whole
thing here everything in between the
start tag and end tag we would also call
an HTML element that just means
everything related to that open and
close tag all right now notice indented
inside of so to speak the HTML open and
close tag are another pair of tags the
head tag and the body tag or the head
element collectively and the body
element collectively and same idea hey
browser here comes the head of my page
hey browser that's it for the head hey
browser here comes the body of my page
hey browser that's it for the body the
head is essentially the tiny little
strip at the very top including the tab
itself the body is like 95% of
everything else the big rectangular
region what's inside of your title at
the at of your head of the web page at
the moment just the title so this
indicates hey browser Here Comes My
Title hey browser that's it for the
title the title of course is literally
quote unquote hello comma title
meanwhile if we bounce back out here is
the uh second element inside of the HTML
tag uh this says Hey browser here comes
the body hey browser that's it for the
body and hey browser this is the
contents these are the contents of the
body itself now the indentation is a
stylistic thing I did it just to be sort
of neat and en TIY because it suggests
what is inside of what but it also
suggests a sort of hierarchy and in fact
we'll use terminology from like the
world of family trees if this is like a
parent so to speak head and body would
be the child elements of the HTML tag
meanwhile title is a child of the head
tag or equivalently tital is a
grandchild of HTML so you can use the
same sort of vernacular as in the human
world when it comes to uh familial
relationships too and that just H set
again the same hierarchy so we have tags
and they include HTML head title body
and that's it for now we have attributes
we've seen one example of them Lang but
we'll see many other examples of the
same idea but these building blocks are
exactly the same generally you start a
thought you finish a thought and you
might do something in between questions
on this basic structure of any web
page any questions at
all no all right so let's now now allow
things to ramp up a little more
interestingly and do something with
these building blocks but so that you
have a mental model for everything
that's going on here on after think of
this same HTML being related in spirit
to week five when we talked all about
data structures if I really wanted to I
could take to heart this idea of
children and parents and grandparents
and really depict this thing graphically
and in fact this tree here if you will
and it's not a binary tree it's not a
binary search tree it's just a tree uh
used week five's terminology if this
special node here represents the whole
document well the root element as I
called it is HTML HTML has two children
head and body the head tag has in turn a
title uh child and in turn has some text
just as the body has some text and so
this is what your browser is doing you
and I the programmers write this stuff
the browser reads this code top to
bottom left to right whenever you visit
a website and inside of the computer's
memory Chrome Edge Firefox Safari what
what not they build this data structure
in the computer's memory so as to know
what it is you have told them to do and
we'll see over time at the end of today
you can write code in an actual
programming language JavaScript to maybe
dynamically add or remove things from
this tree and this is how things like
Gmail work when you open up your Gmail
inbox if you're a Gmail user if you just
stay there long enough you'll probably
get more and more mail and what happens
you don't have to like reload the page
or rebuild the tree per se it just all
of a sudden appears at the top
at the top at the top what's happening
there is that Google wrote some code
that just keeps adding more nodes to
this tree every time they realize you've
got a new message again and again so
that's the relationship now even with
this world of HTML with all of the
programmatic ideas we looked at in the
past all right so let's go ahead and do
something with this that's a little more
interesting than just hello itself I'm
going to go ahead and hide my terminal
window because the server is now running
and all I want to do now is experiment
with uh hello and other examples as well
let me go ahead and actually before I do
that let me go ahead and run uh code of
paragraphs. HTML just so I can keep my
code separate and now I'll hide the
terminal window again um paragraphs.
HTML I'm going to do almost exactly the
same let me go ahead and start with
something familiar and eventually I'll
start copying and pasting just to save
time so doc type HTML is always there
open the HTML tag and now notice I
didn't type the rest of that just like
with C just like with python we try to
save you some keystrokes by closing
parentheses adding quotes the HTML
support in VSS code is pretty good too
and it tries to finish your thought when
it comes to tags as well it can screw
things up if you if it does something
you don't want it to do so sometimes you
have to delete but it's just
autocomplete as we've seen before uh
let's go ahead and let me add Lang
equals as all of my examples today will
be let's add the head tag let's go and
proactively add the body tag and now
let's go ahead and give this a title tag
uh which has a I'll just call this
paragraphs just so I remember which
example is what now notice all of this
white space and all of this neat and
tidy indentation the browser ultimately
is not going to care about this is just
for us humans to kind of keep ourselves
saying when we look at the code it's
just easier to read but strictly
speaking I could minimally delete all of
this white space and I could just move
all of this tag up to the same line both
I think are fine I'll just going to
follow a certain convention but this too
would have the exact same meaning but
we'll see where that detail about whites
space could potentially get us into
trouble later in my paragraphs tag let's
do this in advance I've written up some
Latin like text a really long paragraph
of Latin like text like this it's
actually random nonsense it's not real
Latin even though a couple of the words
might look familiar and so here we have
three paragraphs of text and I've
deliberately hit enter in between them
so that just like an essay in Google
Docs or Microsoft Word hopefully I'll
see three separate paragraphs let me now
change tabs and I'll close hello.html
from before I'm going to go back to my
other tab here I'm going to click back
to go back to that index of all of my
files which I started at earlier and
you'll see now that I have two files
because I obviously just created a
second file called paragraphs. HTML so
let's click on this to see our three
paragraphs of Latin like text and voila
I'll zoom out all right first bug if you
will this just looks like one massive
blob of text not three Blobs of text and
why might that be borrowing the the hint
I offered a moment
ago why are we not seeing break yeah so
we need some kind of line breaks here
because the browser turns out is only
going to take us literally and if you
just give it text text text it's just
going to show you text and anytime
there's more than a single white space
whether it's two or 20 or 200 it's going
to just assume that you did that just to
be neat and tidy and it's going to
collapse them into just one space
visually like this so there are in fact
a couple of solutions one is this here I
could add some explicit line breaks and
it turns out that there's a br tag like
this and just for uh visibility sake let
me do two of them so like hitting enter
enter on my keyboard I'll do it here too
BR for break break and now let me go
back to my other tab nothing's changed
yet but that's because I have to reload
I've changed it on the server but now I
need to change it in the browser by
reloading and now it looks a little
better albeit nonsensical but you'll
know is a curiosity per this BR tag this
is kind of poorly designed it's a little
hackish to just say enter enter and make
the browser do this breaks line breaks
don't actually require Clos tags or end
tags so not all tags need to be closed
at least those that it just makes no
semantic sense to close them right like
the break is there or it's not you can't
imagine like starting to move to the
next line and then eventually getting
around to finishing like it's either
there or it's not so some tags do not
have closed tags as necessary but
there's a more elegant way here I dare
say not just sort of hackish putting in
these line breaks let me do this instead
I'll delete those and let me go ahead
and as the name of this file suggests
let me add a paragraph tag now here I
need to fight with vs codes autocomplete
because I don't want to finish the
sentence uh the thought there let me go
ahead and open the paragraph tag and
close a paragraph tag and just to keep
things tidy I'll go ahead and indent two
even though the indentation itself
doesn't matter let me go ahead and
create another tag for opening this
paragraph and I'll close this one here
and now let me see sometimes it's
fighting with my auto complete but
that's fine because I did this sort of
the wrong way at first and now let me go
ahead and finish this thought by closing
this paragraph tag here and I've
manually fixed all of my indentation so
now on line 10 I have the equivalent of
hey browser start a paragraph and then
it does the Latin like text then on line
12 hey browser that's it for this
paragraph and repeat repeat repeat if I
now go back to my other Tab and reload
again shouldn't be all that different
but semantically it's a little bit
better why because just saying break
break doesn't really mean anything but
by saying paragraph paragraph paragraph
now there's some more semantic
information there now if like Google is
analyzing your page or if the programmer
is trying to understand what it is you
did in the past when writing this code
you just know semantically oh this is a
paragraph This is a paragraph This is a
paragraph just like in a book or or an
essay so it's a little more clear
focusing more on what it is not how you
want to display it any questions then on
these
paragraphs now all right so a few more
tags and indeed these first few examples
will really just be like sort of bang
bang bang just a bunch of different
vocabulary words in the form of these
new tags but we won't go through the
entire laundry list of tags this is
indeed the thing for which web
references and books and the like are
ultimately helpful just like a
dictionary in the real world so I'm
going to go ahead and do this let me go
ahead and copy this let me create a new
file called headings. HTML just so we
have a new file for this to save time
I'm just going to paste that exact same
code just to get me started I'm going to
change the title of it for clarity for
the code online to headings and now just
like a book or an essay or a thesis let
me actually put some actual headings
here now if my first heading like
chapter one I could do something like
this up here I could have a paragraph
like I just learned and I could say
something like chapter one here but
that's not really a paragraph and so
it's sort of better designed to tell the
browser and really tell the world what
it is so it turns out there's another
tag I can use like H1 for heading and
like most important heading and in here
I'm just going to keep it simple and I'm
going to say something like one and in
fact this is so short here's a good
candidate for just keeping this all on
the same line but this has no functional
difference but it'll just make it a
little tur more tur on the screen now
let me go ahead down here and I could
have multiple headings so H1 2 and down
here I could have another one H1
three and if I go back to my other tab I
reload it now we should see just like a
book or an essay now we have some
proper now we have some oops I have to
go to the right file sorry if I go back
to the index now we see the new third
file called headings. HTML and now we
indeed see some fairly pretty if simple
headings as well now if these aren't
three chapters 1 two three but maybe
it's a chapter then a section then a
subsection such that just visually you
want things to get smaller and smaller
well those exist too and in fact you can
do H1 through H6 H1 a little
paradoxically is the biggest and boldest
H6 is the smallest but still bold so it
might make sense to make this H2 both
open and close and maybe this H3 open
and close if again this is a section or
a subsection inside of that chapter if I
reload now notice just gets a little
smaller so it's more similar to what
you'd see on the printed page but this
now is just another three tags that I
might use in my own code all right well
how about lists of things I have three
paragraphs here but let's do this let me
go back to vs code I'm going to copy
this code so I have a starting point I'm
going to create a new file called say
list. HTML here I'm going to copy paste
I'm going to change my title to be list
just for clarity and in here I'm going
to go ahead and get rid of this whole
body because let's move away from these
massive paragraphs and keep it simpler
for now if I want to have a list of
things uh for instance uh if you haven't
seen these already a computer scientist
when they're fishing for just some
arbitrary meaningless words uh they
often use Foo bar and baz just as their
go-to just like a mathematician might
use XY Z for variables so Fu bar and baz
are on three separate lines and maybe
this is like my to-do list or my
shopping list but you can probably
imagine if I go back to my other tab go
back to the index I now see my new file
list.
HTML but it's probably going to look
wrong I think I'm just going to say yeah
Fubar baz all in one breath if you will
the not on new line and you can try to
fight this like you can be like really
want to put some line breaks there go
back and reload it's still not going to
make any change how do I want to fix
this well I can do this in a few ways I
could make them paragraphs but they're
not really paragraphs they're a list so
I'm going to use a different tag instead
I'm going to create for instance an
unordered list using the UL tag open and
close inside of that I'm going to use
the list item tag Li I and I'm going to
say Foo inside of another tag I'm going
to say bar inside of a third tag open
and close I'm going to say baz so it's
getting a little verbose but it's still
relatively succinct Li is all you need
type for list item UL is all you need
type for unordered list so there's some
shorthand syntax here that's adopted if
I now reload you're going to see a
so-called unordered list like not sorted
which means by convention to show it as
bullets though it could be displayed in
different ways visually as well if you
actually change your mind and you
realize oh I'd really like to number
this well you could obviously like just
add one and two and three but that's
going to get annoying especially if the
list grows you want to change something
insert something in the middle then you
have to reorder it I mean we using
computers here they can do this for us
so we can change the UL to any
guesses o maybe for ordered list which
is sort of the opposite here so let's
try changing that to O let me go back to
my browser and I'm just hitting command
r or controlr to reload the page instead
of clicking the button every time now I
automatically get 1 2 and three and you
can even override the Aesthetics using
different numera bles or symbology
instead but that would be perhaps the
most common there as well all right it's
a lot of tags quickly but any questions
on lists paragraphs headings or the like
no all right so let me go ahead and
propose this here um let's go ahead and
create what we'll call a table so let me
copy and paste this into a new file code
of table. HTML and in table. HTML let me
again rename the title to table let me
get rid of that ordered list from before
and let me now use a table tag open and
close this one's a little weird but
inside of a table you typically have a
head of the table so uh I'll say well
let's say the first row we'll keep this
one simple a table row or TR inside of a
table row you would ideally have columns
but that's not the nomenclature instead
you have data so TD for table data and
let me go ahead and just have the first
datm be one I'm just going to
arbitrarily do 1 two three just so we
have something to play with and you know
what just for demonstration sake I am
going to deliberately copy paste this
twice and I'm just going to manually
change the numbers just so we can see
what I'm creating 789 and then maybe
just for good measure if you're seeing
where this is going let me copy this one
more time and give myself a final row
with an asterisk a zero and a pound sign
if maybe you see where this is going let
me go back to my other tab let me go
back to the index there's my new file
table. HTML I'll click that and while
it's not very pretty I'll zoom in it's
indeed a table of data I happen to mimic
like a key uh a telephone keypad but you
could imagine this being much juicier
much more interesting scientific or
financial data or the like laid out into
these rows TRS and these columns AKA
table data as well so we have that
ability as well for structured data now
of course the internet um has lots of
images on it and in fact this is all
just text how can we introduce images
well let me go ahead and do this let me
first uh sort of semi secretly copy an
image file that I brought from uh
earlier just so we have something to
play with and I have in my account here
now an image called harbor. JPEG and I
uploaded this semi- secretly a second
ago into my account so that I can
reference a second file let me go ahead
and copy this HTML just to save myself
some keystrokes
let me go ahead and do code of image.
HTML and let me paste that code and hide
my terminal window I'm going to get rid
of all of this table as just
uninteresting now we're going to make
this even simpler by changing my title
to image to keep all these
demonstrations uh separate and now if I
want to make a web page that when
visited shows us a picture of Harvard
well there's an image tag abbreviated
IMG for short I can specify what the
source of that image is and if my file a
JPEG in this case is literally in the
same folder I can just say quote unquote
harvard. jpeg if it's in a folder I
should mention the folder name in a
slash or something like that if the
image is on the internet somewhere with
a URL I could also have a whole URL
https colon and then the URL of the
image but I upload it in in advance now
this is just going to visually display
on the screen but not everyone of course
can see images screen readers might need
a bit of assistance and even search
engines might want to analyze the page
and know what this is an image of now
machine learning and artificial
intelligence are maybe getting better to
be fair at figuring out just by
analyzing images what they are but
they're certainly imperfect I am a human
I know pretty well what I took a photo
of for instance so maybe what I should
do proactively which would be good for
accessibility is have this alt tag for
alternative text and then literally say
like Harvard University so that someone
who can't see or so that a a server can
actually know with higher probability
what it is uh they're looking at and I
could be even more detailed than just a
phrase I could describe the image as
well all right let me go back to my
index in the second tab let me go back
and zoom back out there's my new file
and there's my new JPEG that I quickly
uploaded before I can click now on
image. HTML and albeit a little
overwhelming that is a really big image
of harvor now apparently it's too big to
fit on the screen so this isn't the best
user experience to have to scroll up
okay so there's the image horrible
horrible design if you will at least in
terms of my code but there's going to be
ways where I can sort of rein that in
and affect the height or the width as
well but for now it's just deliberately
a little overwhelming instead now we can
do something a little more fun and
topical today uh which might be to use
an IM a video instead so let me go ahead
here and very quickly grab another file
today which is uh I brought in advance
and that you might have seen briefly
earlier which is an MP4 an actual video
file and what I'm going to do here by
revealing vs code again is I'm going to
code a file called video. HTML get
another demonstration here I'm going to
change my title to video just to keep
these things straight and instead of the
image tag you might imagine using now
indeed a video tag and this is a
relatively newer tag that has increasing
support among browsers so it's good now
to use and inside of this the syntax is
a little different you specify and this
is weirdly annoyingly in consistent not
SRC for Source you literally say source
and then in Source you use a source
attribute horrible design semantically
but like this is what we're stuck with
halloween. MP4 is the name of the video
we uploaded in advance made by some of
harder Harvard's digital artists and the
type of this video so that the browser
knows for sure is video/ MP4 that's a
so-called content type that you just
know or you look up to figure it out and
just so that this is as animated as
possible I'm going to tell the video tag
with a few attributes to autoplay and it
turns out that attributes often have key
value pairs whereby it's the key the
attribute name equals quote unquote some
value just like Lang equals quote
unquote for English but not all
attributes need values in fact if you
read the documentation for html's video
tag there's an autoplay attribute where
you can literally just say the key and
it needs no value it's just going to
mean autoplay and if you don't want to
autoplay you just omit it alt together
so so you don't necessarily need a value
on or off uh I want the thing to Loop
just so it keeps going I want it to be
muted so that we don't hear any sound in
fact there is no sound but browsers
nowadays for anti-spam and advertising
reasons often will not play a video if
it has sound because it's just kind of
obnoxious if you visit a page and all of
a sudden your speakers start blaring so
I know this from having read up on this
that I should mute it so if I want it to
actually autoplay for real and then I'll
set the width manually for now to be
like 128 pixels across just from some
trial and error earlier and that with
attribute does have a value now I'm
being a little um a little uptight here
by alphabetizing all of my attributes
not at all necessary I do it just so I
can skim things faster and know if
something is there or not so for me it's
just a matter of style let me go back to
my other tab go back to my index and
you'll see two new files again the mp4
file and video. HTML I'll click on the
ladder and if I did this well here we
have thank thanks to our friends in
Harvard U our artistic friends at
Harvard very like an oo would help with
the drama here but okay but we have a
very dramatic nice Halloween type view
here as well so we have videos embedded
as well and suffice it to say there's
ways to embed YouTube videos or Vimeo or
other services as well using yet more
tags too but the web is of course all
about hyperlink Hyper text markup
language where you click on something
and you end up somewhere else and this
is how the web is so powerfully
interconnected
so how do we start creating links from
one website or web page to another
either that I made or someone else well
let me go ahead and open back up my
terminal window and let's create a file
called link. HTML just to demonstrate
what you and I know as a link I'll hide
my terminal window now let me copy paste
just to save myself some keystrokes and
let me get rid of the video tag so we
can focus now on links suppose that I
want you to visit Harvard virtually well
I could say something like visit uh
Harvard period this is uninteresting
because it's just going to be text I
probably want you to actually visit
harvard.edu instead more specifically
and I'll lower case it just to be
consistent with what browsers do in the
address bar all right let me go now to
the video uh back to this video Tab and
go back where we now see my index I'll
Zoom back in and there's link. HTML
unfortunately when I click this and I'll
zoom in you literally just see the text
that I wrote and yet on every social
media platform nowadays except like
Instagram when you type a URL or what
looks like a URL even if you didn't
bother with the HTTP or https it usually
automatically links it for you on
Facebook on Twitter and other sites as
well that's just a convenience Discord
and slack do that too but they're just
doing it to make things more
userfriendly but they have to generate
HTML with the proper tags and attributes
so to get this to actually work it's not
even good enough to say
https www.harvard.edu because if I go
back now and reload now you'll literally
just see all of that as text if you want
the browser to treat this as a link you
need to use the anchor tag it'd be great
if it were called the link tag but it's
not it's called The Anchor tag or a for
short and the way you reference the URL
to which you want to lead the user is
via href for hyper reference this is one
of the earliest tags perhaps among the
most Arcane now but if I then put that
whole URL in quotes and close my tag I
now have to opportunity to finish my
thought in between the start tag and the
end tag for this anchor and what I put
in between the start and end tag is
whatever the human's going to see so
here I can say Harvard I can go back to
my other tab I can reload the page and
now you see the familiar blue underline
this now is an actual link and if I
click it I'll be whisked away to the
actual Harvard websites but there's a
risk here can anyone imagine pretty
simply after like what 60 seconds of the
link tag of the anchor tag how could
someone an adversary misuse this tag
alone How could a website run by an
adversary How could a spammer misuse
this tag do you think
yeah yeah absolutely you could have it
say one thing but lead another lead
elsewhere so I could say Yale in here
nothing stopping me as the developer go
back to the page reload now it says
visit Yale you click on Yale and voila
you end up applying to the wrong place
instead now there's some hints of this I
could hover over this and super small
like this isn't very good for your
anti-hacking techniques but way down
here you can actually see the URL that
it's going to go to in most browsers
indeed do this at least on desktops and
laptops so it's a little bit of a hint
but what you're seeing here even though
this is kind of a silly um uh playful
example this is exactly how fishing
attacks work p i sh iing work whereby an
adversary tells you to log into your
PayPal account but it doesn't go to
paypal.com it goes to some other random
website that they bought and built that
then tries to collect your username and
password and stored in their database so
now they can log into your PayPal
account as you and it boils down to that
simple primitive and you can be even
more manipulative to you can even say
the whole URL for Yale like yale.edu or
Worse htps www.yale.edu reload that and
now who I mean who among you and people
in your lives are necessarily going to
be so paranoid as to not just blindly
click on that URL this is why just being
a defensive real world person nowadays
digitally is just ever more so important
so these same things that can be used
for good or uh benign use cases can also
be used for ill purposes too and it is
literally that simple questions now on
any of these tags thus
far just a few more to offer up any
questions on this
here no well let me open up a couple
that I brought in advance just so we
don't have to type all of them here um
if you for instance have a web page
that's got quite a bit of code let me go
ahead and grab from the website a couple
of examples real fast here namely one
that we'll call how about uh meta
HTML and in this example here give me
just a moment to full screen it we're
going to
have a file So codem Meta HTML I'll open
this up next no relationship to what we
now know as meta the company but rather
this is going to be a page that I copied
and pasted the same chunk of Latin like
text from earlier so it's going to be a
really big paragraph of text and this is
an example where if you were to open
this web page not on my own Mac or your
PC but on your phone the font might
actually be really annoying and
difficult to read why because your
phone's going to try to squeeze all of
the content onto the tiny viewport the
rectangular region of your phone instead
so it turns out there are ways pretty
easy ways to make your website mobile
friendly as well Otherwise Known
technically as responsive and the
easiest way to do this is to include
this tag here a meta tag again no
relationship to Facebook this has been
here much longer and this case here this
meta tag online five has its own sort of
approach to key value pairs this is a
good example of where it'd be nice if it
looked just like everything else but
this is what we have historically
you can have a meta tag with an
attribute called name that refers to the
name of some feature of the browser in
this case viewport is the technical term
for like the big rectangular region to
which I keep referring the body really
of your page the content for the
viewport you can say some AR esoteric
details like this the initial scale
should be one that is no matter who
visits your site it shouldn't start
zoomed in it shouldn't start zoomed out
it should start at just the default
sizing and then this here with equals
device width is a very arcane way of
saying if the user has a small screen
show the text proportional to that size
don't just try to cram it all into a
tiny little window so it's super simple
but if for the next problem set or
future projects as well you find that
just things look really bad on mobile
like this kind of tag is the place to
start meta there aren't terribly many of
these that you'll use but they're useful
for other mechanisms as well in fact let
me go ahead and semi secretly pull up
one other example as well whereby I'm
going to grab another example that uses
more of these tags and in just a moment
I'll reveal it here give me just one
second here I'll have I'll propose that
in this
example of
meta we now add these properties instead
so I copy pasted this from an existing
file just so as to not waste time typing
all of these out if you've ever shared a
URL on Facebook or Twitter or slack or
Discord order any number of websites
nowadays that automatically show a nice
preview where you sudden instantly see
like the default image of the page maybe
a few sentences or words of text or
something like that sometimes those
applications those websites will just
choose like the first image it finds on
the website or the first sentence it
sees and show that but that might not be
very user friendly or search engine
friendly and so a prog a developer might
want to control what it is that slack
Discord Facebook Twitter and other such
sites show by default for that can use
nowadays what are called open graph tags
which is to say there's other uses of
the meta tag and you just look these
things up even I had to look this up to
remember what the key value pairs are
the meta tag can also have a property
attribute that can be these very
specific strings OG title OG description
OG image which denotes open graph which
again is this standard that's evolved in
recent years and what you can do here is
tell browsers and in turn servers what
you want them to show as the default
title of the page P the description of
the page and even the default image just
so you can exercise more control when
sharing things socially nowadays as well
again it just boils down to these key
value pairs this is absolutely the kind
of thing you look up as needed to cross
check but those capabilities are there
and so literally the next time you paste
a link into slack or Discord or any
online site that then displays it in
embedded fashion just know that all this
time a little bit of textual code like
this in HTML has been there by whoever
authored the site
all right let's do one final example in
HTML alone before we transition to just
cleaning up the Aesthetics and improving
the visuals of everything we've been
creating let me go ahead here and close
meta HTML let me code up a new file
called how about search. HTML and see if
we can't draw some inspiration from our
cursory understanding earlier of how
URLs work to see if we can't reinvent
google.com itself so recall that a
canonical URL might look like this here
and in particular if you want to pass in
user input to that URL again you can
potentially have a question mark and
then a key equals value pair or for that
matter you can even have multiple key
value pairs that by convention are
separated by ampers sense these things
are everywhere like later today when you
pull up almost any website in your
browser look at the URL and you'll just
see a lot of this a lot of noise too and
distractions but there's going to be
some equal signs most likely Andor some
ampersands as well and those are just
separating key value pairs now what can
I do here well if you think back to how
we manually searched for cats earlier
let me quickly do this I'll do this one
manually doc type HTML as my very first
line HTML tag with how about my Lang
attribute for English up here and then
inside of this I'll have a head tag
inside of this I'll have a title I'll
call this example uh search and then
down here I'll have my beginning of a
body tag and now let me introduce you to
really a final tag for now uh a form tag
which will create a web form the thing
with text boxes and buttons that you and
I use every day on any number of
websites inside of this form I'm going
to have an input like a text box whose
name is going to be Q for query because
I'm trying to re-implement Google here
uh the uh type of that I want to be a
text box or if I know I'm using this for
search I can actually change this to a
search box and it's going to let me it's
going to generally put a little X there
so you can clear it quickly that's a
nice little enhancement as well and then
I'm going to give myself a submit button
by doing input whoops I'm going to give
myself a submit button by doing input
type equals submit and then I'll leave
that as such here all right now I need
to do a little bit more but let's see
how this looks let me go over to my
other tab let me go back to my index and
if I zoom
out there is search. HTML I'll click it
and there's not much going on here even
if I zoom in but I do indeed have a
really big text box and a submit button
but I haven't in my HTML told anyone
anywhere that I want this input whether
I type cat or dog to go to google.com so
for that I need a couple of more
attributes and I know this from having
done this before and any online
reference will say the same you can add
an action attribute like what do you
want the action of this form to be and
you can put the URL to which you want
this form to be submitted and I know
from tinkering that it should be hdps
www.google.com search I don't need to
put any question marks here myself but I
do want the uh browser to do that for me
so let me go back to my other tab let me
reload and nothing visually has happened
but watch this when I now type in cats
but before I hit enter notice that I'm
currently at some long crazy URL search.
HTML is expected if I now go down to the
submit button and click submit watch
what happens to the URL and the page
itself I'm whisked away to the actual
google.com and indeed there are those
same cats and if I zoom in here you'll
see that my URL has changed to be indeed
SL search question mark Q equals cats so
this is just how web forms work when you
submit any form on the web in this way
the browser automatically goes to that
action URL adds a question mark puts any
key value pairs that you manually typed
into the text boxes and lets the server
do its thing now here's where Chrome is
starting to simplify things Safari does
this too if you double click on your url
now you see the full URL but if any
parts are missing that's just a UI thing
to eliminate visual distractions
nowadays meanwhile if I go back to my
own form if I search this time for dogs
and hit enter now again the URL changes
to be Q equals dogs and it all reduces
to this basic building block of using an
a form tag now I can be more explicit if
I know I want to use get it which is
actually the default I can literally say
quote unquote get in all lowercase even
though the verb earlier was by Design in
uppercase but here now I'm just being
ever more explicit if I don't want the
label of this button to be very
generically submit maybe I want it to be
Google search quote unquote well if you
read the documentation for forms you can
actually change the value of the button
to be quote unquote Google search and if
I now go back here and reload I get a
fresh form and now I get a button that
literally says Google Search and if I
tinker with this further because this
isn't very user friendly there's even
more attributes I can do I can add on my
t uh search input a uh autoc complete
equals uh off if I don't want to see my
own history for whatever reason I don't
want people knowing I'm searching for
cats and dogs on this page I can
autofocus on the text box so that it
shows the cursor blinking in that box by
default and I can even do something like
this I can have a placeholder attribute
that says something like query or some
other documentation for the user and if
I now go back and reload you'll see
notice it says query and it's subtle but
my cursor is already positioned there it
gave it focus and I can type cats now
without having to click in the Box
manually which is just marginally better
for the user's experience any questions
now on all of this
here any
questions all right that too was a lot
why don't we take a casual five minute
break and when we resume we'll take a
look at CSS add in some JavaScript and
then wrap up so 5 minutes only for now
all right we are back so that's
technically it for HTML like here on out
it'll be up to like online resources and
references we point you to just to fill
in your vocabulary for more tags and
attributes but like conceptually that's
it there's attributes uh there are tags
and there are attributes and the rest of
it really is just kind of a laundry list
of capable uh possible features but it
turns out too you'll see over time that
you can even see the HTML for websit so
for instance if I go over to harvard.edu
in my browser which I'll go ahead in
just a moment here here and do here and
do
https
www.harvard.edu
enter it again will pull up today's
version of Harvard's website and if I
rightclick or control click on it again
and go to inspect you'll see those
so-called developer tools and earlier we
focused on the network tab just so we
could see the HTTP stuff going on but
what I glossed over earlier was the
so-called elements tab which actually
shows you the HTML underlying any web
page on the internet and so for instance
here is the underlying HTML for
Harvard's homepage as of right now and
aesthetically some of it's been
collapsed so if I click on these various
triangles I'll see what's actually
inside of that is the children of some
of these HTML tags but here on out if
you're ever curious as to like how a web
page uh made some feature visually you
can just literally use these developer
tools built into your own browser just
to see what the uh web developer
actually did and you can do things too
like this like if you really like maybe
uh let's see if you really like this
menu in the top right hand corner of
Harvard's website you can even
rightclick that or control click that
specifically choose inspect and what
browsers will do is jump to the HTML
corresponding to that visual element on
the page and here you can see though
we've not talked about this tag before
there's a button tag there's an ID
attribute and there's some other
attributes as well that Define that
button um you can do other things too in
the web page let me scroll down for
instance here and let's go actually
let's go to another one like yale.edu
here in today's theme and suppose we
want to do something like uh change the
Aesthetics of this website well let's do
how about this over here life at Yale
let's rightclick on this choose inspect
that's going to jump to that part of the
page and notice what you can do here in
this elements tab we can be a little a
little playful in return today life at
Harvard and voila we've now changed
Yale's website it would seem so have we
really like hopefully hacking is not
actually this
easy what did we actually do based on
today's mental
model like I have changed the page
but yeah just changed how it is for me
right because my browser just like with
Phyllis and Brian from the GetGo
requested Yale's web page I got back a
virtual envelope containing that HTML as
we've now called it my browser has a
local copy it's got its own tree
otherwise known as a Dom document object
model built up in its memory and yeah I
went to town and changed my copy of it
but of course hopefully I've not changed
the actual server and in fact if I
reload Yale's website now hopefully it
will revert back to indeed yep what it
should be instead life at Yale but this
ability in your own browser be it Chrome
or Firefox or Edge or Safari to have
these built-in developer tools are very
powerful because it's going to enable
you to not only diagnose problems that
will invariably arise in the coming
weeks with your own code but is also
going to allow you to learn from other
sites like how you can do things and
Tinker as well but up until now we
focused only on tags and attributes and
on the structure of a web page let's now
focus more on the Aesthetics and
fine-tuning that it turns out that HTML
has very limited support for anything
aesthetic like font sizes and colors and
so forth and in recent years people have
used necessarily a second language
called CSS not a programming language
again a markup language if you will to
just fine-tune the Aesthetics of a page
font sizes colors margins and all of
that so CSS is going to allow us to
define a whole bunch of properties which
is just another group of people's
terminology for key value pairs indeed
ever since week five like key value
pairs are everywhere in the world not
just at like sweet green and restaurants
but indeed under in line code and
languages and Technologies like these so
properties is the new word in CSS for
what a moment ago we called attributes
in H but it's the same idea just
different vocabulary that you get used
to over time a few phrases I might use
now and you'll hear in the coming days
would be these type selector class
selector ID selector attribute selector
which just refer to different techniques
we're about to see that are going to
allow you to control more precisely the
Aesthetics of specific things on the
page and the way we're going to do this
is we're going to take our basic HTML
like we saw earlier and we're going to
introduce in the next few minutes just a
couple of more tags and or attributes
one we're going to introduce you to a
tag called style which nicely named
allows you to um allows you to control
the style the Aesthetics the visuals of
the web page or we're going to introduce
you to a link tag which very confusingly
does not give you a link that you can
click on it just links to another file
that then gets automatically included or
imported to borrow our language from C
or in Python but same idea this will
allow us to include secondary files and
we're going to ultimately show you how
you can leverage third third party
Frameworks libraries that other people
wrote so as to not get stuck in the
weeds of all the fine tuning of
Aesthetics and just make pretty things
fast so you can focus really on the
intellectually interesting part if
that's your choice of building the
content the site out the application out
yourself all right so with that said let
me go back to vs code here and let me go
ahead and create a simple example called
home.html like a very simple homepage
for John Harvard for instance let me
give myself three paragraphs initially
the first of which is just going to have
uh the person name the second paragraph
is going to say something like welcome
to my
homepage uh to greet visitors and the
third is going to be like a little
footer like copyright uh how about John
Harvard 1636 or something like that all
right let me go back to my other tab as
before reload my index there's my new
file home.html and I'll click that and
you'll see okay I mean this is sort of
1636 style web page super simple all
text nothing really interesting going on
there
but we can start to style it a little
differently like if the title of the
page is John Harvard and then it's
welcome to my homepage and then this
less important footer why don't we have
the text be large then medium then small
so something arbitrary but a little more
nuanced so let me go back to vs code
here and in my home.html file let me
introduce not yet the style tag but what
I'm going to call temporarily the style
attribute both indeed exist this one's
simpler and it's going to be correct but
we'll see in a moment not as well
designed arguably as is often our
narrative so inside of the style tag you
can put this language called CSS key
value pairs otherwise known as
properties the only way you know what
properties exist what keys exist is by
taking a class reading a book looking at
an online reference and we're going to
give you just a sampling of what's out
there so suppose I want to control the
font size of this first paragraph I can
literally say font Das size in all lower
case colon and then a word like large or
I can specify 12p point or 18 point or
something more precise like that like
from Google Docs or Microsoft Word and
suppose I want to make this text down
here uh medium well uh I'll do quote
unquote font size colon medium and down
here I'll do style equals uh font Das
size small so I'm going to start with
just these three key value pairs same
key but different values I'll go back to
my page and in a moment I'll reload and
it's going to be somewhat subtle but
watch how the font size do change when I
reload now all right so got a little
bigger middle one's about the same and
the last one is a little smaller what if
I want to center it just like many web
pages have the text like this centered
well I can separate these key value
pairs with semicolons and I'm sorry
semicolons are kind of sort of back with
CSS but I can do text-align Colon Center
strictly speaking I don't need the last
semicolon if there's no more key value
pairs but I'll just do it to be
consistent uh text align Colon Center
and then down here after another
semicolon text align Colon Center all
right let's go back reload now it's
going to be much more obvious the change
and we now have the beginnings of a
homepage still pretty basic but at least
it's a little more interesting turns out
we can do a little better with the
copyright symbol like most computers
actually have support for a circle with
a c in it but you can't just do that
with uh text like this there's different
ways to do this you could copy paste it
from like a website that already has it
so you don't have to figure out the mag
iCal keystroke on your Mac or PC but
there's also in HTML what are called
entities and you can actually specify
using heximal or decimal codes numbers
like this H1 169 semicolon after an
Amper sand and this is a special symbol
that you can look up in any online
reference for like special characters
that are hard or impossible to type
manually at your keyboard and this let
me zoom in just so it's obvious if I
reload now instead of being two
parentheses and a c character
now it's a proper Copyright symbol so
you'll see these out there they're not
necessarily that frequently used
nowadays but it's good to know that they
exist but let me go back now to my code
and propose that while correct uh this
is arguably not very welld designed and
even if you've never seen HTML never
seen CSS before what Instinct might you
have for why this is poorly
designed
yeah there's repetition right in general
in the past several weeks see python SQL
like repetition generally bad and and
sloppy and it's not going to scale well
so the repetition I think you're
probably alluding to is textalign Center
textalign Center textalign Center well
we can factor that out in CSS the C in
CSS means cascading and this means that
if you move some properties to like a
parent or a grandparent uh the children
or grandchildren will inherit those
properties that is they will Cascade
down the family tree so to speak and so
so let me go ahead and remove all of
these since I claim they're indeed
redundant and let me preserve just one
of them by well let me do this it's not
quite right to put a a paragraph inside
of a paragraph like that's just not a
thing in English writing or in writing
more generally so I'm going to do one
thing first it turns out that these two
are arguably not paragraphs right this
is like a header the body the essence of
the page and then the footer so if a
paragraph isn't quite the right English
semantics you can actually use more
generically a tag that's all over the
internet called div for division of the
page and this is just a very generic
term for like a big rectangular region
that divides the page again and again
just so that you can think about
different regions now that I have div
which really has no more meaning than
that it's a division of the page
interpret as you will now I can have
multiple ones of these and let me go
ahead and open a div tag here let me
close a new div tag here and then just
to keep everything tidy I'm going to
highlight everything in between and hit
Tab and that just automatically indents
everything for me now I have a three
divs inside of another div and that's
totally fine this is very commonly done
now I'm going to do this style equals
quote unquote text align Colon Center
semicolon or not and now I have some
cascading capabilities now the parent of
those three children John Harvard welome
to my homepage and the copyright will
now all inherit that property so when I
hit reload nothing aesthetically has
changed whoops sorry
um I should have done reload slightly
earlier when you use a div instead of a
paragraph it actually gets rid of the
par uh the space between those
paragraphs it just sandwiches them a
little closer together I can fix this in
another way but that aside everything is
still centered and the text is still
large medium and small but I should have
called out that change in the paragraph
spacing but we could bring that back
before long if we wanted now what more
could I do to maybe improve this well
strictly speaking I don't really need
that parent div right because these
three divs inside already had a parent
so let me actually get rid of that new
div just undo what I did I'll highlight
this and if you haven't seen this trick
shift tab will unindent nicely which is
perhaps helpful I could just put that
text align Center on the body tag so
text align Colon Center quote unquote
this two would work as well so long as
you go up the family tree so to speak
reload and now indeed there's nothing
aesthetically that has changed this time
but it turns out nowadays the web is
getting a little more sophisticated and
even though you will see so many
examples online and tutorials and books
using div div div div all over the place
there are newer semantic tags semantic
just means they have more meaning than
this generic notion of a division and if
you look up the a documentation for HTML
you'll see that if you want to have a
header on a page not a heading like H1
H2 but a header there's literally
nowadays a header tag and this is
marginally better because it now says
what it is search engines like Google
and Bing can detect oh that's the header
of the page maybe we should use this and
give it more prominence in the search
results you can then have a main part of
the page so literally a tag called main
nowadays you can literally have a footer
of the page and again these are often
useful for screen readers to help recite
things verbally for folks who might
otherwise not be able to read them and
probably these screen readers might
highlight the header and the main part
but maybe not might not spend time for
the user on the footer which is arguably
a little less important semantically
usually um or search engines again now
know what's the header what's the footer
what's the main part of the page so they
know what to search and analyze so this
would arguably be a a better design
nowadays as
well but what else remains as a problem
well this is now getting a little bit
more subtle and takes some experience
but this practice of putting HTML and
CSS all in the same file it's a little
sloppy why because it means I'm
co-mingling my data with the
presentation thereof like the juicy
stuff I care about like John Harvard and
the phrase welcome to my homepage and
all of the Aesthetics that I might want
to change over time and honestly because
everything is currently in one big file
it's going to make it really hard for me
to collaborate with a classmate or a
colleague at work so that maybe I do the
HTML they do the CSS like uhuh not if
you're all working in the same file it
would be a nightmare even if you use vs
code sharing feature like Google Docs
and both are typing at the same time
like you're going to mess up somehow
it'd be nice if we could separate these
two languages well one way to do that
would be as follows let me get rid of
all of the style tags sorry style
attributes that I've added up until
now on all four now of these tags and
let me introduce the style tag that we
saw on the slide earlier instead I'm
going to go up here into the head of the
page which is where technically these
style tags must go so that they're
already loaded into memory before the
body is even analyzed by the browser and
inside of the the style tag I'm actually
going to select the HTML elements that I
want to stylize if you will so if I want
to change the body's Aesthetics I'm
going to literally type the name of that
tag body and then I'm sorry curly braces
are back also from c u inside of these
curly braces I'm going to put text align
Center so the key value pairs are the
same the only new thing I've done is
I've moved some of the syntax up to this
new style tag in the head if I want to
now control the header tag as well I can
use the same curly braces this is
convention to put the open curly brace
on the same line the closed curly brace
on another the browser doesn't really
care but this is a common CSS style
convention I'm going to do font size
large semicolon then for the main tag
I'm going to do font size medium and
then for the footer tag I'm going to do
font size small so same exact thing and
it's admittedly a little bit more
verbose it's taking up more lines of
code it doesn't all quite fit on the
screen but if you scroll back down now
and you'll acquire an eye for this this
is just better like it's just more
compact it's more readable the the
content the data jumps out and there's
no visual distractions like the CSS
properties as before upside here too is
that we don't actually need to uh this
doesn't actually change the Aesthetics
if I reload the same page it still looks
the same but I've taken a step toward
some slightly better design but let me
propose that there's other ways to do
this too we just selected things by way
of their uh type so that was a so-called
type selector when I literally just
specifi the type of tag body header main
footer but there's other ways that now
we can lay the foundation for making
reusable CSS that you and colleagues and
classmates can use and reuse in multiple
files and even in multiple projects so
let me actually go ahead and do this
instead of just very explicitly saying I
want the body to be centered let me
invent an adjective if you will and let
me change this to do centered and this
new uh this new vocabulary word centered
will literally mean texal Center let me
go ahead here and I'm just going to
create a new adjective called large a
new adjective called medium and a new
adjective called small they are
deliberately consistent with what the
properties do but these are now my own
vocabulary words and they are called
classes so a class is just a collection
of key value
a collection of properties that you get
to invent for yourself and what it lets
you do now is this now if I want the
whole body to be centered I can add this
tag which we actually saw briefly in
Yale's HTML class equals centered down
here in the header if I want this to be
large I can say class equals quote
unquote large down here on Main I can
say class equals quote unquote medium
and down here I can have class equals
quote unquote small now I have taken one
step backward by read addding some of
the Aesthetics to the page but it's not
the actual properties it's not the key
value pairs it's now more semantically
nice because now I just know from
reading the HTML what these things are
going to look like whereas the
implementation details for all four of
those adjectives is now relegated up
above and these are literally my words I
could change it to Fu and use class
equals quote unquote Foo but obviously
that would not be the best choice of
words in this case all right any
questions on this this now is what we
would call a class selector by using
literally the dot even though the dot
does not appear elsewhere but dot means
this is a
class these are not always the best
syntactic design decisions that the
world makes all right well one last
trick then notice that this is a little
Annoying that I'm still working in the
same file and if my classmate wants to
clean up my Aesthetics make my homepage
look way better if my colleague wants to
do the same wouldn't it be nice if we
could actually move all of this code to
a different function file like a python
library or a c header file well you can
let me go ahead and delete that whole
style tag let me add a confusingly named
link tag the href of which let's call a
new file styles.css and let's say that
the relationship of that file is that of
stylesheet so this is a term of Art in
the world of web development a
stylesheet is a text file that contains
lots of styles lots of CSS properties
let me open my terminal real fast
and let me do code of
styles.css
enter and in this file I'm going to
paste all of those same lines as earlier
but now they're in a separate file and
indeed if I hide my terminal window and
I give this file to a colleague they can
now work on the Aesthetics of the page
and make things a lot prettier than this
maybe use specific font sizes maybe add
colors and the like whereas I can focus
entirely on the HTML because this file
now will reference that other and if I
go back to my other Tab and reload Cod
the content's going to be exactly the
same but now I'm using some separate
file
instead any questions now about these
techniques
here no all right so with that said let
me show just one example now of what I
called a moment ago Frameworks and this
is where web development gets kind of
fun at least if you like this especially
if you like the sort of logical design
the presentation of information you care
about but you really don't want to
struggle with like font sizes and colors
and getting everything Pixel Perfect so
to speak let me propose that I open up
here an example in just a moment in vs
code that I prepared in advance and this
one is going to be an opportunity to
consider how you might take some of the
data from last week which we had wherein
we collected everyone's favorites and
lay it out in a really big HTML table so
I wrote this out in advance because it
was a huge amount of data but it's the
same data from the Google form from last
week and you'll see already the hints of
a table tag and these TRS and I added a
few other tags for Aesthetics it turns
out when you have a more visually
interesting header for your table
there's another tag called T head
there's another tag called T body these
are not all that intellectually
interesting I just read the
documentation and realized oh to make
things prettier I need a t head a t body
and so forth but what's interesting here
is that if I go to my index here and
open this file called favorites. HTML
here is all of the data from last week's
Google spreadsheet which we exported as
CS and I manually before class converted
to just HTML it's indeed a table but
it's really not pretty like the columns
are really close together it's kind of
hard to distinguish one row from another
but this is just raw HTML written by me
now I could use CSS and some of the
tricks we just saw to maybe change font
size there's ways to change color
background color and a lot of things
like that but honestly other surely
other people in the world have presented
tabular data in pretty ways right I've
been to many websites that have prettier
tables than M can I maybe use someone
else's framework someone else's CSS
include it in my page but then stand on
their shoulders and just make my stuff
look prettier well I dare say I can let
me go ahead here and semi secretly open
up vs code again and let me grab a
slightly different version of favorites.
HTML that I also opened in advance
wherein I add this line of code instead
give me just a moment to foreground this
version and the data is is all the same
as before but I've added one of these
link tags and I'm not linking to my own
styles.css I'm using a popular Library
called bootstrap and bootstrap is just
one of many popular libraries out there
free at that that has a whole bunch of
CSS files and soon JavaScript files that
you can just use for free in your own
projects personally or professionally
that just make things look and behave
better without you having to reinvent
Wheels now to access their CSS I had to
read their documentation and grab this
very long URL here but it's the same
idea link a forre equals quote unquote
something and I read their documentation
and they told me to add this they told
me that if I want my tables to be
prettier I have to add a class attribute
to my own table tag and specify a little
weirdly but this is what bootstrap told
me to do a class called table and that
will make it a prettier bootstrap table
and if I want to stripe it like every
other row is gray instead of white just
to make it pop a little more visually I
can also add a second class separated by
a space called table striped that's all
I did I added line five and I changed
line nine and that is it the rest of the
hundreds of lines in favorites. HTML are
the same but if I go back here now and
reload the browser now thanks to
bootstrap voila like it's much prettier
now I can zoom out and that changes the
font size just locally for me and even
if you don't love their Aesthetics I
mean this is easily better than my own
there and it turns out we can can do
even better by adding interactivity to
this too but to do that we're going to
need one final language for today and
this one is an actual programming
language and we won't use it all that
much in cs50 but we introduce it here as
we begin web stuff because there's just
so many free libraries and professional
libraries that you can use just to make
your web applications fancier and more
interactive mobile applications as well
increasingly use HTML CSS and JavaScript
to power our iPhones and Android devices
as well so a quick tour some syntax and
then we'll conclude with just some
hopefully inspiring examples to give you
a taste of what JavaScript can do so
JavaScript supports conditionals just
like C and python before it if we rewind
to our scratch days here of course is a
conditional here is the corresponding
JavaScript code as of today it's pretty
much identical to see with the syntax
here uh if we had an if an if else in
scratch it looked like this in
JavaScript it's going to look like this
instead so it's a bit of a regression V
ofv python like the the parentheses are
back the curly braces are back the
semicolons I mentioned in CSS are also
back in JavaScript potentially but it's
familiar is the point here and it's a
different language that's frequently
used for the web whereas you can't use
python in the ways we're about to use
JavaScript it just wasn't designed for
that purpose meanwhile if you have an if
El it's else if else in scratch well in
JavaScript just like in C it's going to
look like this instead variables in
JavaScript of course are a thing too and
in scratch we might have initialized a
counter variable to Z in JavaScript a
few different ways to do this and just
the for now the keyword is let it's sort
of a polite way of asking for a variable
let uh counter equal zero semicolon so
you don't mention the type but you do
use a keyword here in this case called
let if you want to increment counter by
one few different ways in JavaScript you
can do this just like in C in JavaScript
you can do this just like in C and in
Python in JavaScript you can also get
this so plus plus is back so maybe that
counterbalances the other syntax as well
that was was not the case in Python
Loops are back of course in JavaScript
whereas in scratch you could repeat
three times like this in JavaScript it's
pretty much just like C the only
difference here is that you say let
instead of int for an example like this
meanwhile if you want to do something
forever in scratch in JavaScript just
like in C you say while true in this
case so this is to say we're sort of
comfortable spending relatively little
time on JavaScript at least for today's
purposes because syntactically it's
really the same as we've seen before
with maybe a slight variance here or
there but what's interesting today
arguably is just what kinds of things
you can do with it so with that said
what kinds of things can we do it's all
comes back to this picture if this is a
simple web page on the left and this is
the corresponding tree or Dom document
object model on the right that is the
tree the browser automatically creates
in memory or RAM for you JavaScript is
now a proper programming language that
lets us dynamically manipul ulate like
read data from this change this and this
is how Google for instance implements
your inbox they might have uh in your
inbox it's like a table so TR TR TR TR
probably something like that or heck
maybe div div div div using JavaScript
anytime they realize someone sent you
new mail they can create a new node a
new rectangle in memory and you the
human see a new div or a new TR again
and again and again so with JavaScript
you just have the ability to control the
user's experience and instead of like
I've been doing constantly hitting
reload in the page to see some new
content to see some new content
JavaScript can be running 247 so that
you can actually see all of these
changes live all right let's go about
writing some JavaScript code now instead
of writing it on the server and
executing it on the server we're going
to actually use a very common Paradigm
whereas JavaScript is actually executed
in the browser client side that is to
say we can actually start writing some
JavaScript code inside of our own HTML
file so that when a user visits that web
page with their browser not only is the
HTML and any CSS downloaded to the
user's browser so is that JavaScript
code so that it's executed indeed client
side on the browser rather than server
side as has been the case with python in
previous weeks well where do we go about
writing some JavaScript code let's go
ahead and revisit hello.html which
previously was a completely static
example that literally just said hello
title hello body indeed if I open this
up using HTTP server and view it now in
a separate tab all it said was exactly
that hello title in the tab and hello
body in the main part of the viewport so
to speak well let's make this example a
little more Dynamic so it doesn't just
say hello body but maybe says hello to
an actual person so let's go ahead and
do this let's go ahead and remove the
hardcoded hello body and let's actually
go ahead here and use a form tag but
we're not going to use this form in the
usual way whereby the data gets sent all
the way back to the server we're going
to Leverage control over this form
client side instead so I'm going to go
ahead and create this open form tag
close form tag inside of that let me
give myself a text input that's going to
have autocomplete equals quote unquote
off just to ensure that what I
previously type in my examples doesn't
reappear accidentally we're going to
autofocus it so that the cursor is
blinking right there in that text box
and this time I'm going to go ahead and
give it how about a uh placeholder of
quote unquote name to make clear that
prompting the user for their name and
then the type of this text box will be
the default or more explicitly here text
and then I'm going to have as we've seen
before a button the type of which is
submit also our typical default and then
inside of this button is going to be the
label how about something like uh how
about we'll call this greet so that's
what the button will actually say well
let me actually go back into my browser
tab let me reload this page and we
should now see a relatively simple form
whereby I have the cursor blinking on a
text inp input prompting the user for
their name and then a greet button that
I can click but if I click this button
now it's not going to do anything useful
because I haven't written any code to
tell the browser what to do when I click
that button but it turns out there's all
sorts of events in the world of
JavaScript that you can listen for so to
speak in fact here's just a list of some
of them anytime something changes in a
form field anytime the user clicks or
drags on something anytime the user
presses a key and maybe lifts their
finger up anytime the mouse goes down or
over or up on top of something or
anytime a form is submitted those are
events in the same way that we talked
about events back in week zero in
scratch and in JavaScript just like in
scratch where you can do something when
green flag clicked in JavaScript you can
write code that actually listens for any
of these events or more so with that
said let's go back to vs code here and
let's make a couple of changes instead
let's go ahead and add to this form a
new attribute that's not the best way to
do it but it's perhaps the simplest for
version one here and let's say onsubmit
do the following so onsubmit is an HTML
attribute and curiously its value inside
of the quotes there can actually be some
JavaScript code and let's go ahead now
and let's assume there exists a function
in the world called greet and what I
want to do is call that function right
then and there well now in JavaScript
how do I go about making that function
exist it doesn't come out of the box
just like print might or say might in
python or scratch respectively but I can
do this let me go up into the head of
this page inside of a script tag here
both open and close let me actually
write some JavaScript code and just so
it stands out I'm going to give myself a
couple of blank lines though not
strictly necessary and let me Define a
new function in JavaScript called greet
and this is the syntax in JavaScript for
creating your own function similar in
Python instead of saying defa in
JavaScript you just say function then
the name of the function and any
arguments within the parentheses
thereafter but I'm not going to pass in
any here then inside of curly braces
what I'm going to do is use a built-in
JavaScript function that comes with any
browser called alert it's not the best
or prettiest user interface but for now
it's going to get the job done what do I
want to say to the user well let's first
just say something simple like hello
comma World close quote semicolon
thereby alerting the user with precisely
that message now what I'm going to do
down here is make one other change I
don't want this form to actually get
submitted to the server just like we've
seen in the past when you submit a form
it often goes to something like
google.com/ search I actually want my
JavaScript code to take control over the
entire user experience of this form so
that I'm just using the form as a user
input mechanism not to actually send via
get or post this data to some other
server including my own so this is going
to look a little ugly but after calling
greet I'm actually going to do this
which I've read the documentation about
and I know that if you actually hardcode
return false here that just tells the
browser please don't actually submit the
form only call the Greet function all
right well let me go back to my browser
here let me reload this because I need
to download the latest version of the
JavaScript code and I'm just going to go
ahead without even typing my name I'm
going to click on the Greet button and
you'll see that Al be it a little
cryptically at the top we see an alert
that says hello world there's my ugly
URL of my code space there at the moment
but we do indeed see that string but
what I haven't of course done is taken
any actual name from the user so how can
we go about doing that well ideally I
want to alert the user with hello comma
David or hello comma Carter whatever a
name I type into that box so how can I
go about doing that well let me create a
variable called name and let me set it
equal to this function call
document. query
selector that comes with JavaScript
itself let me then in parenthesis pass
in an argument that is going to be huh
the ID the unique I need a unique
identifier for the thing I want to
select so let me actually go back to my
HTML code here and instead of giving
this form field a name like Q for query
let me actually use another HTML
attribute called ID where now I can call
this anything I want and for clarity I'm
just going to call this input element
uniquely name now up here in query
selector just like in CSS where you can
use hashes and dots and other symbology
in order to select certain nodes in your
Dom that is rectangles in that memory
tree well I can go ahead and select hash
name which again is just the Syntax for
uniquely selecting the element whose ID
is in this case name so you have the
hash up here you don't need the hash as
the value of the attribute down here on
line 20 and now if I want to actually
get the value of that text box I
literally just say do value so document
refers to the whole web page itself
query selector is a function that's
built into that object so to speak and
the value accessible via value just like
a c stru or even a python class allows
me to go inside of that text field and
get whatever the value the user has
typed in now as I've uh been able to do
in languages like python pretty Le
fairly readily I can concatenate this
name onto the string hello comma space
so as to form a complete phrase and
you'll notice here that I'm actually
using single quotes in my JavaScript
double quotes in my HTML this is perhaps
a common convention in JavaScript the
language does not care if you use double
quotes or single quotes but I dare say
single quotes are just more common and
so that's what I've done here all right
now as always I'm going to cross my
fingers go back to this page I'm going
to reload because I've changed the
JavaScript and I need my browser to
download it and now I'm going to type in
my name for instance David click greets
with fingers crossed and voila now I see
hello comma David all right so it turns
out that while functional this isn't the
best design and co-mingling your uh HTML
with your JavaScript script code AS with
this onsubmit attribute isn't
particularly clean it's better as with
CSS to keep your HTML over here your CSS
over here and your JavaScript now over
here so to speak and better still
perhaps even in some separate files so
how can I go about changing this a
little bit well let me go ahead and
actually let's go ahead and delete all
of this code for just a moment and let
me go and get rid of this on submit
Handler down here and really just
distill my HTML only into the HTML and
the attributes therefore and what I'm
instead going to do now is do this I can
use JavaScript to achieve the listening
for that submit event or that onsubmit
event I don't need to actually use HTML
for that I can use JavaScript entirely
so it turns out I can access some other
uh member of this document by doing
document. query selector again but this
time let's select the actual form tag
and it doesn't have an ID because it has
no ID in its HTML but it does have a tag
name so just like in CSS when you can
Target Elements by way of their name I'm
just going to select the one and only
form on this page by using that same
query selector function and now I'm
going to use another function that just
comes with JavaScript in the context of
browsers whereby once you select an
element like that form I can call add
event listener which is similar in
spirit to scratches when green flag
clicked or any block like that you can
then tell the browser what event you
want to listen for I want to listen for
the submit event so you don't say
onsubmit here now that we're in pure
JavaScript you just say submit and now I
can do something like this I can go
ahead and say call the following
function and I'm not even going to
bother giving this function a name and
that is allowed to in JavaScript as we
saw briefly in Python and what I'm going
to do now inside of curly braces after
that keyword function is the same kind
of code as before I'm going to do let
name equals document. query selector I'm
going to select that same IDE uh same
Name ID as before and get its value and
then I'm going to do alert and then pass
in hello comma a single quote again
after that concatenate with that the
name and then semicolon but I need to do
one other thing it turns out that this
function and if you read the
documentation for this technique
actually takes automatically a special
argument called by convention event and
this is just an a variable if you will
that refers to whatever event just
happened in this case it's of course
going to be submit but in other contexts
it might be a click event a mouse down
event or something else entirely so this
allows me now to do this which is a
little cryptic but you get used to these
conventions I can use that event
whatever it is and then prevent whatever
the default behavior is by calling a
special function called prevent default
with a capital D this is the alternative
to that Messier return fall semicolon
that I had inside of my HTML before so
all I've done here now is I've left all
of my HTML as pure HTML down here and
I've put all of my JavaScript code as
pure JavaScript up here this sort of
separation of concerns similar to what
we started doing with CSS just a bit ago
in order to keep those two languages
separate too well let me go back to my
browser here reload the page and
unfortunately there's a subtle mistake
I've made here let me go ahead and type
in David and click greet and
unfortunately nothing actually seems to
happen well maybe it's just my name
Carter greet and nothing seems to happen
that alert does not come up well why is
that well let me go back to vs code here
and point out that order of operations
in zscript matters similar in spirit to
C because on line seven I'm selecting
the form and trying to add an event
listener for submitting that form
unfortunately the form had better exist
at that moment in time but it doesn't
because just like in C and in some cases
python where the compiler or The
Interpreter reads the code top to bottom
notice that the form doesn't actually
exist and therefore get loaded into the
computer's memory until line 19 so we've
got to kind of reorder these somehow now
maybe the simplest way to do this would
just be to perhaps do something like
this let me scroll back up to my script
tag and perhaps a little more explicitly
move it into the order in which I want
it to be executed so I'm going to go
below my form and inside of my body
which is actually okay for JavaScript
here and just use that same code and
assuming I didn't make any typos let's
go back to the browser click reload
again to get the latest typee in my name
again using that purely JavaScript
solution and the only change I made was
I move the code from up here to down
here clicking greet now and wow it's now
back we get the alert with hello comma
David so those kinds of things those
kinds of principles matter at least when
we're back in this world but there's
other Solutions too and just so that
you've seen it because it's a common
convention in libraries as well let me
undo that change and put that script tag
back in the head or really anywhere else
in the page where it might be
and let me propose that there's one
other way to solve this problem to
postpone that code on line 7 through 11
getting executed until really the whole
Dom the tree is ready to go and the
Syntax for this might be as follows I
can do document and I can add to the
document a an event listener that's
going to listen for something a little
special and I always have to look this
up myself to remember the spelling and
the capitalization but it turns out that
the browser itself once it's done
loading all of your HTML top to bottom
left right it will raise an event called
Dom content loaded capitalized exactly
as such and if you want to call some
function and I don't even need an event
argument in this case you can open curly
braces just as before and put inside of
those curly braces the code that you
want to execute only once the dumbs
content has been loaded top to bottom
and now let me just finish my thought
with a closed curly brace Clos
parenthesis and semicolon it gets a
little Annoying to visually line all of
this up but I think I'm still good and
now even though this code is at the top
of my file or really above the form tag
itself I think we're okay so let's go
back to the browser here reload the page
type in David and click greet and we
still get the same correct behavior and
so this is just a very common Paradigm
to use these kinds of events to listen
and listen and listen for something to
happen and then only do something once
that thing has transpired all right well
let's take one more step with JavaScript
code before we take a look at what's
really fun about this language and what
you can do with browsers in particular
by just cleaning things up a little bit
further I'm going to go back into the
code here and I'm actually going to
remove uh or cut all of this code out of
the hello.html file itself and I'm going
to change my script tag to have nothing
in between the open and close tag but I
am going to give it a source attribute
and let's go ahead and call this for
instance hello.js sojs would be the
convention for the file extension for a
Javascript file and even though this is
a little weird that we have the script
tag and a source attribute then nothing
in between the open and close tag this
is indeed the convention when you want
to put all of your code in a separate
file and let me go ahead and do that let
me go ahead and open my terminal window
create a new file called
hello.js and then in that file I'm just
going to paste the very code that I just
cut from the previous file so no changes
to the code all I'm doing is factoring
it out and now I'm doing something just
like our CSS factorization before which
confusingly use the link tag this uses
the script tag this just now allows me
to collaborate with someone like Carter
or someone else so that they can do the
JavaScript code I can do the HTML maybe
a third person can do the CSS and indeed
maybe we can build even grander things
by uh designing things in this way all
right well let me go back to my browser
again reload the page I shouldn't see
any visual changes but if I type in my
name again David and click greet this
still now works and what my browser has
just done underneath the hood is not
only download the uh hello.html file as
always because there's now this script
tag that's referencing the source of
another file just like an image tag
might reference the source of an image
the browser is automatically helping me
out by loading that into its memory as
well and now how about one final example
and for this one I'm going to go ahead
and not write it live but open it up as
prepared in advance just to show you
what you can do by listening for some of
these other events as well like the key
up the finger going down the finger
going up and listening for exactly that
so as the user is typing something you
can do something interesting as well I'm
going to go back into my directory
listing here and I click on this Source
a directory which has all of the
examples that I wrote here in advance
and I'm going to scroll down to one
called hello 5. HTML and in hello 5 now
we've gotten rid of the button and we
just have this text box but notice now
what happens if I start typing my name
as d a v i d D I'm not typing enter at
all and in fact if I start deleting and
I change my mind and start typing
Carter's name notice now that the web
page the Dom inside of the computer's
memory is now automatically updating
itself so it's not even listening it
would seem for a submit event anymore
but maybe for a key up event instead so
let me go back to VSS code here open my
terminal window and in my source a
directory let me open up hello 5. HTML
inside of the script tag you'll see some
code that's similar in spirit to before
whereby I'm adding an event listener to
the document waiting for the whole Dom's
content to be loaded but then inside of
that function I'm now doing this I'm
creating a variable called input and
selecting from the document the one and
only input tag that we saw just a moment
ago I'm then adding on line 11 in event
listener for key up which is exactly
that gesture so that I can execute some
additional code anytime the human lists
their finger from the keyboard after
typing a key what do I then do well I'm
going to go ahead it seems and declare
another variable called name and I'm
just going to select some P tag on the
page and now we didn't really see a P
tag so I think it's time to look at the
HTML if I scroll down to the bottom of
the page where my actual HTML is you'll
see that there's just a form tag and no
onsubmit Handler anymore as before
there's just an input tag and no button
at all but there is on line 29 here an
open and close P tag just so I have an
empty placeholder in which to put
something like hello David or hello
Carter so that's why now on line 12 I
can define a variable called name and I
can select that P tag so that what do I
want to do well if inside of the input
there's a value so this is essentially
checking for null or the absence of a
string so if input. value does not equal
nothing that is there is a value in that
text box well this syntax here on line
14 is a very clever way of doing the
following go into that name tag that is
to say the empty par paragraph change
the inner HTML of it the HTML inside of
it to be literally this hello comma and
then just so you've seen an additional
piece of syntax this is similar to
Python's F strings the syntax is a
little weird in JavaScript you actually
use not single quotes not double quotes
but back ticks which on a US English
keyboard are typically the top leftand
key of your keyboard or thereabouts and
using dollar sign curly braces just like
the curly braces alone in Python allows
us to plug in whatever the value is of
that input however if there's no value
there it looks like I'm just going to
say hello whoever you are and in fact we
can see that behavior now is I delete
delete delete delete delete delete and
nothing's there now that if condition is
no longer true and so we see this
default value instead so this is only to
say that by harnessing these various
events that are constantly happening on
most any web page we can now register
code just like we did way back in
scratch to actually listen for those
events and do something with them now it
turns out we can do some interesting
things even using third party coat and
just as we used bootstrap a bit ago to
make our table prettier allow me to
propose that we also take a look at this
version of favorites as well let me go
back into my source a directory and open
up favorites 2 which I made in advance
which looks almost the same though I've
zoomed in here a bit but you'll notice
somewhat subtly over the leftmost column
in this table you'll see now this arrow
in Gray pointing up and pointing down
previously those were not there all I
had was a static HTML table with all of
this data sorted in whatever order it
was inputed the other day in that form
but now notice what I can do if I want
to sort in uh one order I can click this
Arrow or the other order I can sort in
this Arrow so essentially doing it
chronologically forward or backward now
how is that sorting happening it's
presumably based on all of the
timestamps that were registered when we
submitted that Google form just a bit
ago um uh when it was live but now using
JavaScript it turns out that we can use
some logic somehow and sort this data by
the same and you don't get that
automatically just by using HTML alone
now how did I achieve that well it turns
out if I go ahead and close these hello
files and in vs code let's open up uh
favorites 2. HTML you'll see that all of
the HTML is actually the same if I
scroll down and down through this file
but I added a little something
interesting at top I copied and pasted
the appropriate URLs and HTML tags from
bootstraps documentation and you'll see
here that I have a file called not only
bootstrap.css but also
bootstrap.min.js as well as a couple of
other things as well that allows me
ultimately using third-party libraries
to add some special HTML attributes that
those libraries told me to add and then
as soon as those libraries detect the
presence of these attributes now on my
own raw data they do their thing and
javascrip defy not a technical term the
entire table and now make it interactive
and not static so you'll see here that
the Aesthetics of the table are as
before table and table striped but I'm
adding now another HTML attribute called
Data toggle whose value is table and I
know that only from the documentation of
these libraries indicating that's that's
how I can now enable this table to be
interactive as I can too by adding data
sortable equals quote unquote true on
specifically the timestamp column and
the only thing unfamiliar here perhaps
is I'm using t P for table heading as
opposed to TD as I do elsewhere but
that's all that it takes to now focus on
the raw data you want to present and let
someone else do the heavy lifting of
actually implementing the logic well
let's end with just a look at what more
you can do with Java script and just how
powerful it is when you combine a
language like this with the data and the
uh user interface you want to convey
let's go ahead and open up within Source
a directory something called background.
HTML now this interface here is quite
simple it just has three buttons RG and
B and the background of course noticed
by default is just white but when I
click on the r the background turns red
when the I click on the G it turns green
and the blue it turns blue and again and
again so how is this working well if you
think back again to the available events
perhaps I'm just listening for a click
on those buttons and then doing
something with maybe the CSS of the page
to allow me to see those different
colors so in fact let's go back to vs
code here and let's open up background.
HTML and in here you'll see some simple
HTML at the top just three buttons but
I've given each a unique ID so that I
can reference it in code and then inside
of a script tag here below because I
didn't bother with the uh Dom content
loaded event here notice that I'm doing
the following I'm creating a variable
called body that lets me select the body
tag I then have in these three line some
code that handles red what am I doing
well I'm selecting from the document
whatever h HTML tag has unique ID of red
and then I'm adding an event listener
for any click on that button and anytime
someone clicks on that red button I call
this function anonymously it doesn't
even have or need a name and this syntax
here is powerful because now in
JavaScript I can alter the CSS of my
page by doing body which is the tag that
I selected two lines ago accessing its
style accessing its background color
property and setting it equal to quote
unquote red and I do the same down below
for green I do the same down below for
blue and the only thing worth noting
here is that in CSS it turns out it's
the case that the CSS property for the
background color of a page is actually
background Das color in all lower case
with a hyphen in between unfortunately
in the world of JavaScript a hyphen
would be mistaken for subtraction like
background minus color which would be
wrong so the convention in JavaScript is
when you're trying to manipulate CSS you
take whatever the property name is uh
font size background color and you
change it into so-called camel case here
you get rid of The Hyphen and you
capitalize the subsequent words like
color in this case here all right how
about another well it turns out back in
the day back in my day there was a HTML
tag that would actually allow you to do
this create blinking text on a screen
it's rather unpleasant at this rate
certainly but how might this work well
it turns out in JavaScript if we take a
look at the blink. HTML file here we'll
see that you can in your HTML do
something literally as simple as hello
world in the body but then you can call
this function here turns out just like
document there's another Global special
variable you can use in JavaScript and
browsers called window which refers to
all things related to the window itself
the window comes with a set interval
function which lets you do exactly that
set an interval in milliseconds and
after every expiration of that interval
some function will be called for you so
in this case it's saying every 50
milliseconds but let's actually slow
that down now to 500 milliseconds or for
one half a second call a function called
blink notice I do not have parentheses
after the blink name because I don't
want to call blink now I want to tell
JavaScript to call the function called
blink every 500 milliseconds now we'll
see in a moment what that code looks
like but let's go back to the page and
reload and you'll see now that it's a
more pleasant blinking if that's even
the case every half second because I'm
now firing that event that is I'm uh
calling that function now every 500
milliseconds instead how am I doing that
well this same script tag I've invented
my own blink function this is has the
distinction back in the day of actually
being an HTML tag and among the few tags
that the world removed and got rid of so
that it's no longer used because it's
not all that user friendly but down here
what am I doing I'm getting the body of
the document itself with this variable
and then I'm checking two CSS properties
that we didn't talk about before but it
turns out that you can check and set the
visibility of an element in JavaScript
by going into that tag checking its
style and getting its visibility uh
property and if it happens to equal
hidden the next line of code here 13
sets it equal to visible instead else if
it's not hidden it must already be
visible and so line 17 flips it the
other way and changes it to Hidden here
left hand right hand clearly not talking
no idea why the opposite of visible Is
Not Invisible it's indeed visible and
hidden but this just allows you every
time this function is called to change
the property from one value to another
achieving that blinking effect you can
do even more powerful things that you
and I take for granted every day let's
go into Source 8 and go to autocom
complete. HTML which I wrote in advance
and this is a page that also loads into
memory a really big dictionary that you
might recall from problem set five and
if I go ahead and type in something like
c a t you'll notice dynamically an
unordered bulleted list appearing below
the text box that shows you all of the
words in that dictionary from pet 5 that
start with c and then CA and then T just
like the autocomplete you see every day
on your phone in Google or websites like
it how is that working well probably I'm
listening for the key press going up as
soon as that key is pressed I'm probably
searching through a big array uh really
of all of those words maybe using linear
search maybe binary search if uh faster
than that and then looking for any
string in that array that starts with C
or CA or c a t and then I'm generating
automattic IC Ally the HTML therefore
but perhaps most familiar nowadays is
just how much your phone and your laptop
know about you and let me go into a
final example here in Source 8 called
geolocation HTML which is a term of art
that just refers to figuring out your
geography for instance your GPS
coordinates now here we have a third and
final Global variable that your browser
provides you with called Navigator and
in Navigator there's a special object
called geolocation that comes with a
function called get current position
so if you call Navigator geolocation dog
getcurrent position and then pass in a
function of your own that doesn't need a
name but does take an argument in this
case I called it position as soon as the
browser or as soon as the phone has
figured out where in the world that user
is with that browser at some latitude
and longitude the browser will
automatically call that function for you
and you can do anything you want with
the position that comes back the
latitude and longitude respectively so
I'm going to use a function that's not
often that help but for our purposes
today it's just going to write to the
document itself to my big rectangular
region whatever the latitude is then a
comma and then the longitude as well so
if we go back with this final flourish
into Source 8 open up geolocation HTML
you'll see that my browser first wants
my permission to let this website my own
know my location I'm going to go ahead
and click allow crossing my fingers
because it might take a moment for the
phone or the laptop to figure it out and
it looks like according to Google I am
right this moment with my Mac at
latitude longitude 42375 comma
7111 let's go ahead and highlight and
copy that let's go to a website like
Googl maps.com crossing our fingers if
you've never done this you can search
for GPS coordinates too let's hit enter
and amazing we are indeed in Sanders
Theater roughly there standing on this
stage on Halloween and that then is week
eight we will see you next time happy
Halloween
nothing
go buffering
okay Josh
[Music]
nice it's Moy no oh
wait that was amazing
Josh uh um Sophie
[Music]
amazing that was
perfect I think I
hey to
you
[Music]
oh that was amazing thank you all so
good
[Music]
all right this is cs50 and this is
already week nine which is our second to
last indeed this is really the last week
where you'll learn in this class how to
program but indeed it's this week that's
really meant to be the the pedagogical
climax of like all of these various
languages we've been looking at all of
these various techniques all of this
syntax so that at the end of cs50 in
just a few weeks you indeed feel that
you didn't take a class on C and you
didn't take a class on python but you
really more generally took a class on
programming because indeed we know
already about half of you uh will go on
to study computer science further but
half of you will not and indeed all of
your programming chops here on out
theoretically will have a foundation in
what we been doing these past many weeks
but here on out it's really going to be
up to you to learn some new fangled
language when it comes out or to follow
some new trend when some language
eclipses the ones we've been using as
more popular as more appropriate for
problems you want to solve and so today
really is about synthesizing so many of
the past few weeks but doing it in the
context of web programming which For
Better or For Worse is so very much
invogue nowadays both on our laptops and
phones and indeed the languages we
looked at in recent weeks are used not
only to make websites but also full
fledged applications and app stores and
the like so this really will be the
culmination of those past several weeks
and indeed we'll even talk about some
familiar Concepts like shopping carts
when you're on Amazon and these things
called cookies when you're visiting
websites all of those topics too will
come into play and you'll have an
understanding of what all that means
from the ground up so how did we get
here well just last week we focused on
HTML and CSS primarily which are not
programming languages they're just about
Aesthetics structuring your data
presenting your data and so forth um and
we served the web pages we wrote using
this program HTTP server this is just
one such program there's dozens hundreds
of different web servers that you can
use out there this is just a super
simple one we pre-installed in your
codes space for you in vs code so that
you can just serve up web pages at the
end of last week two though we teased
JavaScript a full-fledged programming
language that you can use to manipulate
the users experience for the better to
make things more Dynamic and interactive
by actually running code in the user
users's browser on their Mac their PC
their phone as opposed to server side
which up until now is where all of our
code in C and python has been written so
you're writing code on a server you're
serving code from a server but now with
HTML CSS and JavaScript it's getting
executed in a browser but today we're
going to give you one final feature of
python or really languages like it that
you can also use code on the server to
generate automatically dynamically the
HTML uh the JavaScript the CSS that you
actually want the user to rece receive
you don't have to hardcode everything as
you have when making your own homepage
well let's consider what what some of
the building blocks were last week so
here's a sample URL and over here slash
is sort of the default page on any web
server it might be index.html it might
be something else that's just a
convention but it refers to whatever the
default actually is you can visit of
course when any browser like a URL that
ends in file. HTML or something else.
HTML and that literally means your
browser wants this file on this server
or of course we saw that it can be a
folder and inside of that folder is
presumably some default file name like
again index.html or you can be more
explicit like folder file. HTML and
these more generally we just called
paths and indeed a path is just a
location on your Mac your PC or on a
server of some piece of information but
today we're just going to rename this
only to use other common terminology but
they're really just synonyms today we're
going to refer to those same things as
routes because now today we're going to
ultimately replace HT PTP server which
just serves up static content that you
all write with your own web server like
now you will be the ones controlling
what it is the server does in response
to the user in uh requests so that you
can respond interactively and
dynamically but we're still going to see
techniques like this these were our
so-called HTTP parameters they're
everything that comes after a question
mark in a URL and it can be like key
equals value and an example was what
when we played with Google what was the
key and what was the value
that I first tried any
recollection I was searching for cats
and so the key I figured that was Q
because that's what Larry and Sergey who
created Google years ago decided the
name would be of the HTML text box that
you type your query into and if I type
cat for cat the value of that would end
up in the URL for Google as being
question mark cat equals value and I
mentioned that it's often the case that
you want to send two different inputs to
a server and this is why I propose that
you just keep an eye out for Amper Sands
and and Ampersand separate these key
value pairs but again this is the same
darn Paradigm as before and we've seen
this so many times right key value pairs
in dictionaries in Python we've seen uh
HTML attributes and their values we've
seen CSS properties and their values
it's all the same thing associating
something with something else even
though every language every person seems
to have their own uh vernacular for it
it really is just the same idea this
associating of something with something
else we'll continue to see and here to
be concrete were the
HTTP lines of text that were in those
virtual envelopes if you will if I were
indeed selecting trying to search for
something like cats on Google this
recall was the message that got sent to
the server by my browser in order to
tell Google to please search for not
dogs but in this case cats now what is
HTTP server been doing for us well it's
just been serving up HTML files CSS
files maybe some js or JavaScript files
but it has been ignoring any HTTP
parameters like HTTP server does not
take user input why well what's it going
to do with it because you already wrote
the HTML you already wrote the CSS like
there's no decisions to be made until we
introduce a proper programming language
on the server and so we're going to move
away now from this simple HTTP server
program and introduce you to your own
server that's going to handle the
parsing that is the extraction of these
key value pairs so that you and I don't
have to write python code all of a
sudden that like analyzes this stuff
figures out what pages requested the key
value pairs all of that were still going
to get for free by just using the right
framework and so today we revisit python
uh which we've now used in some form the
past few weeks and indeed it's kind of
been the glue that allows us to stitch
together some of our own logic we saw it
with SQL we're going to now see it with
HTML CSS and even JavaScript if we want
and we're also going to see another
language today not a programming
language called Ginga and this is going
to be a common Paradigm in the real
world whereby different languages
different libraries different Frameworks
often like borrow from each other or
they use uh technologies that someone
else wrote just so they don't have to
reinvent that wheel so flask is just a
framework that is a third party Library
it's pretty popular nowadays it's
relatively simple which is why we use it
in cs50 if you've programmed before cs50
Jango is another popular framework or
library in the python sta space but it's
a little more complicated so we focus on
flask and Ginga we'll see is not a
programming language it's just going to
be some syntax thankfully familiar with
curly braces that allow us to use
placeholders in our actual web pages so
again you'll wrap your minds all
eventually around where the lines are
among these various Technologies but
these are not the interesting ideas the
interesting ideas are the ones we'll
focus on in code but starting today
instead of running HTTP server to serve
up a static website we'll have you start
running literally flask space run in
your terminal window to run your own web
server that's implemented in Python
using this flask framework so bootstrap
was a library for making your CSS and
JavaScript prettier and more interactive
flask is a framework or library for just
making your python code more pleasant to
use since you're borrowing features from
someone else all right so how can we go
about doing this well if you are to
write your very own web application your
own amazon.com your own google.com in
Python using flask minimally you need to
have a file called app.py by convention
which is where all your python code goes
and then a folder called templates which
is where all of your templates go and
for now your templates are just your
HTML files so if we're going to now
start building more interesting
interactive things like google.com or
amazon.com we need to be able to execute
code on the server and so this is the
convention it's not index.html anymore
necessarily it's these two things at the
top level with that said we'll quickly
see that there's some other conventions
and in my examples online and in the uh
problem set nine you'll see another file
called requirements.txt which is just a
text file that allows you to enumerate
all of the thirdparty libraries your
application might want to use it's a
convention so that the server can like
automatically install things for you
without you having to do it manually and
then static is going to be where
literally your static content goes so if
you've got images for your web
application if you've got JavaScript
files CSS files by convention that goes
in static these are just conventions
like all of this can be changed but this
is like the way to do things so we'll
introduce you to the defaults all right
so what does this mean how for instance
could I go about implementing my own web
application using python that somehow
spits out a message like Hello World all
right well turns out just this now we'll
tease this apart in just a moment but
this is the content of a sample app.py
file that apparently uses some Library
stuff like familiar syntax from
something import something else we've
seen that before with csvs and other
libraries this is somewhat new syntax
but it's kind of copy paste for now this
is definitely new syntax and kind of
weird with the at sign here but we'll
see this again and again today and it's
just copy paste initially until you
understand what it's doing for you but
at least there's some familiar stuff
here like index.html is still going to
be with us but it's going to be up to us
when and how to show it to the user so
let's make this more real let me go over
to vs code here and let me go ahead and
create a how about we'll do this in
hello let me do makeer hello to make a
new folder called hello and I'm going to
CD into it just to isolate all of these
files to the same directory so that we
have different apps today and different
folders and now I'm going to do code of
let's do this actually let's do our
maker templates. HTM ah sorry not
templates. HTML let me rename that to
templates using the MV command this has
nothing to do with web programming this
is me making typos so if I type LS now
I've got a folder called templates all
right in there let's create a file
called index.html that is going to be
super simple and pretty much copy paste
from last week let me hide my terminal
window and let me just very quickly whip
up a simp simple hello world page using
my HTML tag Lang will equal English then
inside of this I'm going to have a head
tag inside of this I'm going to have a
title tag and I'm just going to call
this thing hello uh I'm going to then
have a body and in this I'm only going
to say something simple like hello comma
world and just so this is mobile
friendly recall that we touched on these
meta tags so just in case you after
class play with your mobile device
instead of your laptop I'll do name
equals quote unquote
viewport uh viewport and and content
equals and I never remember this I'm
literally reading it off of a cheat
sheet initial scale equals 1 width
equals device width and this is just
this magical incantation that says to
the browser like size things
appropriately for the size of the device
it blows up the font sizes a bit all
right so that's what I would have done
last week and I would have served this
web page by running HTTP server in the
same directory and boom I would see that
HTML but let's now start to take some
control over the user's experience and
for now it's going to be underwhelming
it's just going to always say hello
world but in a moment version two is
going to say hello David or hello Carter
a bit more dynamically and we'll quickly
escalate from there to just more
interesting applications as well
culminating with things like cookies and
shopping carts and the like so let me go
back into my terminal window and as
promised let me create another file
called
app.py and this is where now I need to
implement the web server I'm going to
run using this flask framework and for
now I'm just going to kind of do some
copy paste from uh what we saw on the
slide a moment ago from the flask
Library which we've pre-installed for
you I'm going to import a uh function
called flask capital F it's subtle but
it's important there and I'm also going
to import a few other things a function
called render template and another
variable called request and the only way
I know this is from having taught this
before read the documentation followed a
tutorial like you wouldn't know this
unless someone told you or you read how
to do this this but what this means is
that this Library called flask has three
things in it a function called flask
capital f a function called render
template and a variable built into it
called request and this is going to be
all the building blocks I need to
implement my own web server the
convention in flask when you want to
create a web app in Python is you create
a variable by convention called app and
then you assign it the return value of
that flask function capital F and pass
into it underscore uncore name uncore
underscore which is weird but we have
seen this before a few weeks ago anyone
recall when and why we mentioned uncore
uncore name uncore
uncore yeah I think was
it name or something yeah if we wanted
to check if the name of the file was
itself main so that we avoided a
situation where if you're writing your
own Library code you don't want your
code to be executed automatically you
want to potentially execute the main
function and that was a solution to that
problem here for today's purposes this
is just the way you do it underscore
underscore name underscore uncore refers
to the current file and so this is just
a little trick that says turn this file
into a flask application that's all it
is and for now uh that line suffices all
right what do I want to do after that
well now I'm in charge of the web server
I need to write the code that decides
based on the browsers request what file
or files I'm going to send from the
server to the browser last week http
server did all of this for us just based
on the file name but today I'm going to
take over control over that process and
the way I do that is as follows I say
app. route with weirdly an at sign in
front of it this is known in python as a
decorator and it's a feature of python
not a flask that we just didn't
introduce in weeks past but it's a
special it's a handy trick to do what
we're about to do the route I want to
Define is quote unquote slash so that is
here is code I want the server to
execute whenever I user visits forward
slash the default page of the website
well what code do I want them to execute
well I want them to execute a function
and I can therefore Define in Python a
function I can technically call this
thing anything I want X or Y or Z but
because they're accessing the default
page otherwise known as the index of the
site I'm going to just more reasonably
call this function index but just a
convention you could call it anything
you want but X Y or Z is probably a bad
stylistic choice it doesn't need to take
any arguments in this case and the only
thing this code this function is going
to do is for now let's go ahead and have
it return hello world quote unquote and
that's it all right now let me go into
my terminal window let me go ahead and
do flask run in the same directory that
has appy and hit enter I'm going to see
some cryptic output but including a URL
of my code space and if I open that URL
after hovering over it I'll indeed see
hello world as you might hope but let me
do this let me go ahead and rightclick
on the page and click view page source
which if you haven't done before shows
you all of the HTML for a page however
pretty or messy it is and that's it
there's no HTML that I've spit out it's
just quote unquote hello world well if I
actually want to spit out a full web
page which is not a big deal here
because who cares it's just the text
anyway but if I want to spit out a whole
file let me do this I want to return
essentially the contents of index.html
which have all of the tags I want the
mobile friend stuff and all of that well
I can't just return index.html but I can
return this render template quote
unquote
index.html and per the documentation for
flask this render template function will
go find that file for me in my templates
folder by convention it will open it up
and then it will spit the whole thing
out to the browser for me so I can keep
all my HTML in one place and all my
python code in this one place so now if
I go back to my browser and reload I
don't think I'll really see a difference
because it's the same text ultimately
but if I view page Source now notice
that ah there is all of the HTML that
was just sent to the browser so this is
only to say we have the building blocks
the puzzle pieces if you will via which
to now store all of our HTML in one
place and presumably CSS JavaScript and
so forth but then serve up whatever we
want even though I'm just blindly
spitting out
index.html so before we proceed any
questions on this which again I claim is
like my manual version of what HTTP
server was doing for us automatically
last week but this is how you do it
yourself any
questions all right well let's make it
more interesting which we could not do
with HTTP server and HTML alone why
don't we go ahead and do this let me
visit the same URL and I'm going to zoom
in and your url will differ from my code
space but it's going to end similarly
here I'm going to do slash question mark
name equals David for instance or Q
equals cats or name equals Carter any
key value pair I want I'm going to
append after a slash and a question mark
thereby providing user input to the
server albe it in a very user unfriendly
way no one's going to normally do this
in their browser enter nothing changes
here it just says hello world but
wouldn't it be nice if it says hello
David or equivalently if I zoom in here
again and change David to Carter and hit
enter wouldn't it be nice if it says
hello Carter instead so we need some
dynamism there and here's now python is
going to be our friend if I want to
access the HTTP parameters that the user
has provided via the URL be it Q equals
cats or name equals David I can use this
special variable I already preemptively
imported earlier and I can do this if
there is an HTTP parameter called name
in what I'm going to call request. args
then I'm going to go ahead and create a
variable called name and I'm going to
set it equal to request. args bracket
name else if there is no quote unquote
name key in this special variable called
request. args I'm going to just assume
that the user's name is World by default
now what's going on here well it turns
out that flask provides us with this
special variable called request. ARs and
in there is all of the key value pairs
that might have come in via the URL so
if you had to guess what type of data or
what data type is request. args that's
its name and here is in context line n
might provide a clue in Python what data
type might request. args
be
yeah uh it's not going to be an array or
a list because those are always in every
language we've seen numerically indexed
but you're
close someone else it's a dictionary so
a dictionary is similar syntactically to
a list in Python but instead of numeric
indices like 012 you can literally use
strings like quote unquote name now
that's a bit of a white lie it is a
dictionary but it's flask's special
fancy version of a dictionary but the
syntax via which you can access it is
exactly the same and I actually this is
a typo I didn't mean to say names there
I meant to say name singular but
otherwise I think the code is correct
this is going to on line eight check if
there's a key called name in request.
ARs and if so it's going to set it equal
to that value otherwise it's going to
default to world I deliberately did not
do this I added this IFL
and did not do this why what error might
happen if I just blindly grab
name exactly if there was nothing at the
end of the URL that was of the form
question mark name equals someone then
there would be no name key and this is
uh you know a couple weeks back but this
would give you one of those annoying key
errors when you get a trace back because
you screwed up because you used a string
that doesn't exist that's why I'm just
proactively trying to avoid that
situation just like I'm might have a
couple of weeks ago so even though it's
more verbose this is just much more
defensive so that I don't accidentally
index into a dictionary where there is
no key but we'll see how we can tighten
this up to be not four lines but one but
I think now I can do this wouldn't it be
nice if now in my index.html file which
recall is in my templates folder
wouldn't it be nice if I could do the
equivalent in C of like a percent s here
for instance or in Python something like
this name well it's close and this is
just because different humans invent
different languages invent different uh
Frameworks the Syntax for this in flask
is to actually do whoops two curly
braces and then name of the variable
inside of it why it's just probably
someone figured what are the odds that a
normal person is ever going to use two
curly braces at once versus just one so
this is probably decreasing the
probability that people actually want to
Output literal curly braces like this so
it's similar in spirit to Python's F
strings it's similar in spirit to C's
percent s it's similar in spirit to
sql's question marks same idea slightly
different syntax and this there is
ginger so it's not programming code per
se it's just a template and indeed
that's why this folder is called
templates it is sort of like a a
blueprint for what I want to be spit out
to the user but I've got these
placeholders like this variable that I
want to plug into that value now this
alone is not enough watch what happens
if I go back to my other browser and I
reload the page after changing up here
let's do name equals David again enter
nothing outputs after the hello comma so
it seems that the name variable doesn't
exist yet and that's why indeed if I do
view page Source you can see what was
sent to the browser something's wrong
with my placeholder but I just need to
be a little more explicit as to what I
want to send where so it turns out that
the render template function takes not
just one argument the name of the
template you want to spit out but it
takes after that with commas all of the
placeholders you want to plug in so for
instance if you want the placeholder to
be this literally placeholder inside of
those curly braces you can then specify
as the second argument to rep uh render
template a placeholder named argument
equals whatever the name is so name is
the variable in the lines above
placeholder is the name of my literal
placeholder in the curly braces and so
now if I go back to my browser and
reload this with still quote unquote
with still question mark name equals
David in the URL now I indeed see hello
comma David and if I zoom in here and
let me move over here let me type in
Carter and hit enter now I see Hello
Carter instead now this is a little
unnecessary to explicitly call the
placeholder placeholder especially if
you want to have two or three of them so
you can actually call this anything you
want and I'm going to change it back to
name which is a little more
straightforward the only weird thing
here is that now you'll see that you're
writing code like this and this is
correct and this is the norm it just
looks weird but the thing on the left of
the equal sign is the placeholder you're
using in the template the thing on the
right can be any value you want
including a variable so even though I'm
naming them exactly the same which looks
stupid admittedly like this is what
people tend to do just because it's uh
simpler than introducing another word
like placeholder any questions now on
this
any questions on these
placeholders no all right well let's
tighten this up a little bit and see if
we can't get things to be more Dynamic
still let me propose now that instead of
outputting instead of using this
condition which made a very simple idea
like very verbose with four different
lines it turns out there's an easier way
to do this you can actually still create
a variable called name and you can set
it equal to request. args but instead of
just blindly indexing into to that
dictionary it turns out that request.
ARS comes with a function as well called
get you can pass it an argument that
tells you what value you want to get and
by default if there is no key called
name in that dictionary this function
will not throw a key error it's just
going to return none an O the special V
the Special Value in Python so it avoids
a bug in your code but it tightens up
four lines into one but even nicer if
you read the documentation
the get function can also take a
explicit default value so if you don't
want none to be on the screen like hello
comma blank or I mean that would be
weird too you can just put in a default
value per the documentation of this
function like world so now we've gone
from four lines to just one so arguably
it's better designed and if I go back to
the browser now still with Carter in the
URL and hit reload same thing happens
but we notice this suppose I uh get rid
of the name parameter altogether and hit
enter now it goes to the default instead
world so it's just a little better a
little better designed than doing it the
other way instead all right how about we
take things up one more Notch and how
about we introduce multiple routes and
actually introduce perhaps a form to the
mix because again no normal person is
going to like visit a URL and add a
slash and a question mark and their name
like that's not how browsers work uh
well that's how browsers work that's not
how humans interact with browsers you
and I use a form to quickly instead so
now things can get a little more
interesting when making our own web
application cuz maybe we could do
something like this let me go and zoom
out again let me go back to my code here
and let me move this around and focus
now on the index.html file instead of
just this placeholder why don't we go
ahead and give ourselves a form like
we've played with a little bit in the
past be it for Google or something else
and let's do this uh form and inside of
this form let's have an input and the
name of this input will be quote unquote
name so that too is confusing but inputs
have name attributes but this is a
person's name so I'm saying name equals
name here so just a messy world of
semantics and let me go ahead and make
this a text box by default and then let
me give myself a button whose default
type will be submit and the name of this
button will be greet for instance so
let's see what happens here but let me
change app.py to just be the original
simpler I'm not passing in any
placeholders now and I'm going to even
get rid of this I'm just going to rewind
to the first version of this for
Simplicity let's now change the url to
get rid of Carter and myself so we just
go to slash and hit enter and now we
have a super simple form again all right
this is not super userfriendly but
there's some nice enhancements we can
make for instance like we can uh for
instance turn off autocomplete
especially if I want to type David and
Carter manually and I don't want it
finishing my thought during class uh we
can do autofocus which puts the cursor
there BL linking by default which is
nice cuz then the human doesn't have to
deal with that um and then we can even
have a placeholder attribute placeholder
equals name so that it's like built in
instructions for this thing and so now
if I go back to the other tab nothing's
changed yet because I have to download
the HTML again reload okay now it's a
little more user friendly it says name
and light gray the cursor is blinking
and I'm sort of ready to go but this
form hasn't been wired up to go anywhere
yet and so let's do this let's for
instance say that the action of this
form
is not going to be something like
google.com which we did last time with
for cats I am now going to be both the
front end and the back end of this
website the front end is what the human
sees the web page the graphics the forms
the back end is the stuff the human
typically doesn't see the python code
the SQL code the server itself but now
I'm in control of both sides of the
experience the HTML and also the routes
so let's just propose that we invent our
own route and instead of calling it SL
search like Google does let's call it
SLG greet and let me specify that the
method this form will use which is
technically the default will be get and
confusingly it is lowercase get even
though in the envelope we keep talking
about virtually it's actually capitals
again left hand wasn't talking to right
hand when these things were decided all
right so all I've done is create a web
form that's going to submit whatever the
text box value is to a route called SLG
greet by default because there's no HTTP
or htps or no domain name SLG greet is
going to be assumed to be not at
google.com but whatever my own serers
URL is so whatever my code spaces URL is
that's going to be the implicit prefix
this SLG greet is just the route so now
let's go back to VSS codes app.py file
how do I now Stitch this together well I
think we're good to go with index.html
if index. html's purpose in life is just
to spit out this form we're done with
one of my routes but if I want to have a
second route greet that actually spits
out some greeting to the user well let's
prepare that template too let me go
ahead and highlight all of this HTML let
me go back into my terminal window and
into my hello directory and then into my
templates directory and let me create
another template called greet HTML whose
purpose in life will not be to show a
form but to greet the user with hello so
and so so in this file I'm going to
paste all that same HTML but I'm going
to get rid of the form and essentially
revert to our previous version hello
comma and then using the ginger syntax
name so one template index.html is for
the form the second template now is for
the greeting of hello comma so and so
but otherwise these files notice are
almost the same except one has the form
one has just the hello so now let's
finish this up in app doop High let me
go down here after a couple of blank
lines stylistically let me do app. route
quote unquote SLG greet but I could call
this route anything I want I'm just
using a a reasonable verb then let's
define another function I could call the
function anything I want X Y or Z I'm
going to call it more reasonably greet
no arguments and then now is the code
where I want to render the template so I
do return render template greet HTML but
but I need to do one more
thing what else do I want to do if I
want greet HTML to have access to the
human's name just to
recap I think we solved this already but
I deleted it but what do I have to add
back
yeahh yeah so I got to pass in the
placeholder somehow so I can do this a
couple of different ways I I'm going to
keep it a little more elegant this time
I'm just going to put my name uh
argument there and I'm going to set it
equal to request. ar. get quote unquote
name comma world before I used a
separate variable but I only used it in
one place so that's not strictly
necessary so this is fine too but if
this gets a little overwhelming notice
that I can alternatively do this I can
create an actual variable called name
and then I can pass in an argument
called name with a value that is that
variable but again what's really the
point here it was kind of prettier all
on one line so these are the exact same
things I'm just trying to tighten things
up further here all right so what just
happened if I go back to my form this is
still index.html if I reload it nothing
has changed if I type in my name to this
form notice again the URL I'm currently
at this is Chrome hiding things it's
technically slash by default even though
many browsers are just hiding
unnecessary uh characters these days but
Watch What Happens now if I scroll over
here and I click greet on this new
form notice my URL my route changed to
SL greet question mark name equals David
and the body of the page at top left
says hello comma David so this is
exactly how google.com works and it's
how we implemented search. HTML last
time but instead of submitting the form
to Google via the form I'm submitting it
to myself my very own route so I'm
implementing my own backend for this
same front end all right any questions
just yet much less interesting than
Google certainly but we kind of have all
of the wiring
now any
questions no
all right so what can we do to further
uh tighten this up and adhere to some
conventions well let me propose that in
this version we solve one problem and
even if you've never done this sort of
thing before I dare say we have enough
weeks of cs-50 where if I show you
index.html again and greet HTML again
odds are to someone's mind there's a
opportunity for
improvement why is this web app super
simple though it is arguably poorly
designed at the
moment and the answer lies somewhere in
these two templates index.html and
greet.tolowercase
probably did necessarily for your
homepage why because when you have HTML
only maybe CSS and even JavaScript
that's all you can do is copy paste copy
paste and just make sure that you have
the same structure maybe you have the
same CSS file the same Javascript file
the same third party libraries but it
makes it very very annoying as you might
have realized already to just m make a
change that affects everything so
wouldn't it be nice to like factor out
all of this and all of this and just let
the body change so here too is something
that flask and really other equivalent
Frameworks let us do it allows us to
create what we're going to call
conventionally a layout instead so I'm
going to go ahead and do this I'm going
to copy one last time all of the same
HTML I'm going to go into uh my terminal
window and I'm going to create by
convention a file called layout. HTML
this is truly going to be a blueprint of
sorts and in layout. HTML I'm going to
paste all of that same code but I'm
going to use now some ginger syntax to
indicate that I don't want to plug in
just a variable like name here I want to
actually plug the contents of a whole
other file so instead of just using
curly braces two of them left and right
I have to use slightly different syntax
to say I want a whole block of HTML here
from some other file and the way to do
this even though the syntax is a little
non-obvious is you use open curly brace
percent sign block then you can call the
next word anything you want it just has
to be a special type of placeholder for
an actual file not for just a variable
I'm going to call it body only because
I'm in the body so I'm want a
placeholder to be the entire body and
then outside of this you then say in one
word no space end block so it looks kind
of stupid honestly and why do we have
yet more ugly syntax again just
different software developers in the
world are all choosing their own Syntax
for their own libraries so they all kind
of look different but are all kind of
similar in spirit and you just get used
to seeing the different syntax this now
is not nearly as pretty as the pair of
curly braces for variables but this is
how I can say plug the contents of an
entire file Here and Now what does this
let me do I can now go back into my
index.html file which at the moment
still looks like this but almost all of
this is copy paste the only lines that
are interesting and different are these
four lines here in the body so what I
can actually do now is I'm going to
highlight that and cut it and then I'm
going to highlight everything else and
just delete the entire file and I'm
going to use some of that same syntax
and say curly brace percent sign extends
quote unquote layout. HTML and then I
close my thought with a percent sign and
close curly brace so this syntax as you
might just be inferring is now saying
please extend whatever layout. HTML
looks like that's the original blueprint
the mold out of which I want to make
this web page and now here the syntax is
a little weird too but similar at least
from before I can now say the block the
body block that I want you to plug into
that layout is going to be everything
between these two tags which we already
saw earlier but in layout. HTML they're
sort of giving a placeholder in
index.html this is what I'm going to
plug in to those other placeholders as
well so I'm just going to give myself
some extra white space I'm going to
paste the HTML that was there if I want
to make clear what's going on I can
indent it although this has no no
functional impact but it just makes
clear that just like in HTML you can
open a ginger tag and close it but in
ginger here we have this here hey uh Hey
python here comes the body of this page
hey python that's it for the body of
this page and all of this stuff should
be plugged into this main parent layout
if you will so super ugly admittedly but
now at least things get way less
redundant because I'm going to do the
exact same thing over here in greet HTML
it looks like this but now I'm going to
do this extends layout. HTML also just
as before uh the body the uh the body
that I want to plug in is going to be
everything inside of these tags here and
this body is just going to be hello
comma name in curly braces like that so
again ugly syntax got really ugly fast
but it's really just following these
patterns now and we have two types of
placeholders two curly braces for
variables and now this kind of syntax
with the percent signs and the single
curly braces for like contents of actual
files and so now in this world or in the
world of a homepage if you were using
flask and python to make your personal
homepage with all of those various Pages
you would probably design one main
layout with all of your pretty logos and
colors and fonts and like what you want
the site to look like and then each of
your smaller Pages would now be
distilled into just these smaller
fragments and whether you're using
python or Java or Javas script or other
languages too all different programming
languages have popular Frameworks that
do things like this the idea is the same
across all of them all right let's see
if it works let's go back into the
browser let me go back to my slash route
there's that same form let me type in
David and type and click greet and
indeed I see hello comma David I see
that greet was automatically added to
the URL by the browser when I submitted
the form followed by the key value Pairs
and if I view the page source as I did
earlier you'll see that you have the
entirety of that layout with hello David
plugged in meanwhile if I go back to the
form and view this page Source you'll
see the exact same layout but with the
form tag plugged in and here's where you
can be a little less uh nitpicky with
styling okay yes this isn't technically
indented inside of the body but it was
relative to the original file so at this
point in the game you don't need to
worry about your outputed HTML looking
super pretty you want your source code
that the see to be pretty not the
browser this is not a stylistic
concern okay questions on these
capabilities then a
flask or problems that we've just solved
and why
yeah uh okay so if the files in question
are in different folders for instance if
I go back into my uh index page which
has the form um the routes here are
entirely dependent on what is an app.py
there's no notion of a folder when it
comes to implementing a web application
anymore they are more generically routes
however and we've not done this yet you
can put your static content your images
your video files your CSS files in a
folder called Static and there can be
subfolders therein and that would affect
what you use as your Source attributes
for images or your Source uh tags for
video or any of those kinds of assets
and we'll see that eventually in the
home in the uh the problem set next
other questions on what we've just done
here
yeah good question how do I how did I
ensure that the web app starts on the
form and then goes to the hello page so
whatever you decide your default index
route is like the implicit slash that is
what is going to be pulled up when a
user visits the domain name where your
website is hosted so if I go back over
here to app Pi because my slash route is
designed to return index.html that's
exactly why that response came back good
question all right so beyond this let's
consider now issues of privacy and we'll
touch on this too as we get to issues
like shopping carts and cookies if I
zoom in on the URL here even though the
URL itself is a little long and ugly and
cryptic but when I type in my name and
hit uh greet of course we keep seeing
name equals David in the URL in what
sense might this be bad
design or in what kinds of web apps
might you not want the name to show up
in the URL like that because this is
what Google does this is what my app
does
yeah yeah so if I'm logging in with a
username and password I I could imagine
that they show up in the URL after the
question mark where username equals
mailin and password equals 1 2 3 4 5 but
then all my you know like nosy siblings
need to do is go through through my
browser history and boom like it's right
there for them to copy paste so that
doesn't seem particularly uh secure or
if someone's walking past you in a cafe
they can just look at your url if it's
revealed by the browser and they see it
too so get is not necessarily the best
verb to use even though it's the default
when submitting forms typically when
you've got anything remotely sensitive
or anything large so be it a password or
credit card number or like an image or a
video that you're uploading to uh
Instagram or to YouTube or any such site
like that you don't want the data going
into the URL and thankfully there's
actually an easy way to fix this I can
go into my form which is currently in
index.html and I can just change the
method from get to post in lower case
here but the verb in the virtual
envelope we discussed last week would
itself be capital p o St now
unfortunately Watch What Happens here
let me go over to my original form by
going back to the Slash rout and I'm
reloading the page to make sure I get
the latest freshest HTML and just as a
um just to confirm here yep if I view
Source method is now post so let me go
ahead and type in David now and click
greet and before we saw hello David but
now I get method not allowed and this is
somewhat subtle but in the title of the
tab notice that it's a 405 error which
is not familiar probably almost all of
us have seen 404 file not found turns
out 405 a little more Arcane is the
method the HTTP verb is not allowed why
because by default my app.py only
currently supports get by default how do
I support post well I just need a little
bit more syntax so let me go back into
vs code here let me go into app.py now
and after changing the form I just need
to inform flask that you know what the
method I want this GRE route to use
should not be the default which is only
get I want it to use these methods and
it takes a second argument called
Methods the value of which is a list the
default of which is quote unquote get so
that's the default this has not made any
changes but if I want to support post
instead I can explicitly pass a list
with one string in it P instead and now
what does this mean we didn't talk about
this in any detail last week but inside
of this virtual envelope typically is
that line like get slash search Q equals
cat after the ex after the question mark
if you want to hide that kind of
information for privacy sake or because
you want to upload like an image which
just doesn't make sense to put in the
URL essentially the part of the story
would be well the computer looks deeper
inside of that virtual envelope and
anything submitted via post goes below
the htdp headers like deeper in that
envelope so they're still there they're
just not obviously visible uh for prying
eyes in the user's own browser so just
by making that change in the HTML
telling the browser to submit the data
via post and changing app.py to tell the
route to expect the data via post I can
now go back to my other tab let me go
back to the original page let me reload
just so I've got the latest HTML and
indeed view page Source it's still yep
it's still post but now when I type in
DAV ID and click greet now it works but
but but notice the Privacy implication
I'm at the SLG greet route but where's
my name it's not actually there it's
still went to the server but it's not in
your autocomplete or your history now
for privacy sake questions now on
post yeah oh No Just scratching all
right can you the programmer see this
well let me show you a couple of other
features of Chrome's uh Chrome and
Safari and other browsers as well I keep
going to view page source which just
shows you like a readon version of your
HTML but recall that last time I
actually right-clicked and went to
inspect or viewed developer tool tools
and this brings up a much fancier
version of the developer tools and under
elements here you see everything and
it's nice and pretty printed it's
hierarchical it collapses things into
these clickable triangles but it's the
exact same thing it's just more
interactive but notice what I can do
today is this if I go to the network tab
here and let me zoom out a little bit
let me go ahead and re uh load the form
here and type in David again and click
greet notice now in the network tab of
Chrome's developer tools I see a few
things as we saw before one I see that
the request method is post two I see
that the server automatically without me
writing any code for this returns 200
when it's successful but I can scroll
down down down down down and you'll see
that eventually after all these cookies
more on those later if I click on
payload the second tab next to headers
you can see as the developer what was
actually sent to the server so indeed
this is going to be super useful like
when doing problem set 9 maybe your
final projects if you want to see what's
going from browser to server you have
complete control over all of that
information even if you're using htps
because your browser and you the
developer can certainly see all of this
so again these developer tools even
though there's a lot of tabs and buttons
you probably won't need anytime soon
some of them like elements and network
and with JavaScript console are going to
be super useful to start to get familiar
with all right any questions now on this
implication of
post anything at
all no okay how about one final hello
example that ties a few of these things
together how about now we try to tighten
things up further only in anticipation
of something like problem set 9 or
really more complicated web apps where
you might have not two but 20 or maybe
even more different routes it might
might be ideal to just minimize how many
total routes we have so we don't get a
little too overwhelmed and I dare say
that these two routes are so short maybe
I can combine them into one and maybe I
can keep the user at what seems to be
the same URL but just a kind of Tidy
things up so let me propose that we do
this instead let me get rid of my greet
route and let me go into my form in
index.html and let me go ahead and just
have the action of this form still slash
so I want the form to be visible at
slash the index of the site but I also
want the form to submit to itself if
only because I don't want to introduce
another route like SLG greet which
eventually indeed will be compelling so
you don't have one route for everything
you want your website to do so
technically this is the default to and
if I omit action the exact same thing
would happen as well but let me rewind
and let me now go into app.py to see how
we can make this happen well if I want
my one and now only route to support
both methods I can say methods equals
and then a list with both get and post
in any order but I'll keep them
alphabetical like this this now tells
python hey this route should handle both
get and post requests at the same place
let's now go into this function I kind
of want to say the equivalent of this if
get then I want to return the form else
if post I want to then return render
template of greet Doh HTML with the
user's name but this is not yet complete
code but I think I can do this I'm going
to go ahead and say the following I'm
going to go ahead and say if
request. method equals equals get then
indeed return
index.html L if request. method equals
equals post then go ahead and return
greet HTML this isn't quite enough
though because I still want to pass in
that placeholder so let me again add
back name equals request. args doget
quote unquote name and then a default
value of world what does this Now do for
me well let me go back to my other tab
here let me close the developer tools
let me go back to the form here let me
reload to make sure I have the latest
let me view page Source just to make
sure I have the latest and yep I have
the latest because it still says post
but it now says slash and let's see what
happens now if I type in my name David
previously this submitted bya post so I
didn't see any name or value thereof in
the URL but I did end up at SLG greet
but if the action is now slash and I
click greet notice that it still kind of
works I see hello comma World although
that didn't quite work so we'll come
back to that issue in a moment but
notice the URL ends in just slash and
again Chrome is hiding the slash because
that's all that's there but it does not
end in name equals David in this case or
name and equals world now notice this
too if I reload I'm going to get this
warning do you want to confirm form
resubmission the page you're looking for
used information that you entered
returning to that page might cause any
action you took to be repeated do you
want to continue you might have seen
this on websites you've actually visited
where you hit reload and you're prompted
wait a minute do you want to do that
odds are you've been prompted to reload
explicitly because why whatever you just
did was post instead of get and by
convention besides post being used for
privacy to like hide your username your
password your credit card number or the
like besides being used to upload bigger
files like images or videos post is also
used by convention to make changes to
the server to add something to your
shopping cart to add something to the
database whereas get is the name
suggests is all about getting
information not posting or sending
information instead so this is Chrome
being a little careful because you know
if you just checked out on Amazon and
then you hit reload you don't want to
accidentally like buy the same book
again so to speak even though Amazon and
fancy websites have other defenses for
this too to avoid this issue now there
is a bug though here it says hello comma
World instead of hello comma David and
it actually would have said the same a
moment ago and I just didn't retest the
code and reveal as much to you or if I
did I didn't even notice it said hello
world instead of hello David it turns
out that request. RGS is only used for
get when using get request. args is a
dictionary that contains all of your key
value pairs but somewhat confusingly
when using post with flask you have to
go into request. form I have no idea why
these are not sort of more obvious
opposites like request.get or request.
form and sorry request.get and request.
poost would be sort of sensible names in
this case though we have request. args
for get and request. form for post all
right that's an easy fix though if I go
back to vs code here let's change
request. ARS to request. form let's go
back to my other tab let me just reload
and you know what I'm going to say okay
continue to resubmit the same form
because the form was okay it was my
python code that was buggy hitting enter
now it's accessing David okay but watch
this again if I hit reload command r or
control r i get the same warning are you
sure you want to submit the form yes if
I do it manually with the reload icon I
get the same warning as before but if I
want to manually induce a get request
well that's fine don't hit reload and
send the same request instead go up to
your URL and just put the cursor up
there and hit enter and now notice same
URL is a get by default so anytime you
and I have typed URLs into browsers get
is always the default only when you
click on a button typically that the
programmer has configured to use post
are you actually adding things to your
shopping cart or the like all right so
we are back and if I go way back in time
myself like this is actually like the
first web application I made back in
1997 I believe uh so at the time this
was would have been what my sophomore or
so year I had taken cs50 I took a
follow- on class called cs51 which is a
different type of programming and then I
pretty much taught myself a language
called Pearl which is somewhat less
popular nowadays but it's another
language like python like Java like
JavaScript like others that can be used
to make web-based applications and the
web was very young at the time and the
process via which students my classmates
could register uh for the first year
intral sports program AKA Frost's was to
grab a piece of paper and like write
your name and email address on it and
walk it across across the yard to
Wigglesworth I believe where the Proctor
lived and you'd Slide the piece of paper
under the door and like that was how we
submitted forms in my day um so this was
an opportunity even back in 1997 is to
like move things online and the website
went on to live on until I think like
2007 I found this online and then it's
become something else since um but this
was a website via which people could
register for sports and people could log
in the scores for various games and
whatnot and so underneath the hood I
didn't even know anything anything about
databases at the time it was just like
CSV files that I was storing the data in
but there were HTML forms and there was
with pearl the language at the time the
way to do the exact kind of stuff that
we've just been doing already with flask
and so what I thought we'd do is
Implement a slightly less ugly version
of this um repeating uh graphical
backgrounds were invogue in like 1997 as
you can see here um but this is where
these were the Aesthetics of the day uh
including the the so-called blink tag so
let's at least focus on the
functionality of this website and not so
much the Aesthetics and see if we can't
Implement some of the plumbing for
actually solving like a real world
representative problem be it for
freshman inal sports or something else
like it where you're getting data from
users and processing it somehow so let
me go over here to VSS code let me
create a new directory called fros IMS
just so we can keep all of this code in
its own directory let me CD into fros
IMS let me proactively make another
directory called templates in which our
templates our HTML files do need to live
and eventually I'm going to go ahead and
create a two files minimally app.py and
index.html so let's do the first of
those app.py will live in my Frost im's
directory and I'm just going to recreate
something very simple like we have
previously so from flask in lowercase
import flask capitalized render template
and also request so same first line is
before let me then give myself a
variable called app set it equal to
calling the flask function capital f
with underscore uncore name underscore
uncore and then let me give myself a
route for slash as before with an index
function though again I could call that
anything I want and just for now let's
return render template of quote unquote
index.html as though that exists so this
is not really a web application as much
as it is at the moment just a recreation
of HTTP server for one file let's now in
another tab create a templates file uh
called called
index.html and I'm going to save myself
a few keystrokes I let me copy paste
from earlier almost all of the layout
from before I've change the title in
advance to frosts instead of hello but
this is essentially the same template
and for now though because I'm in an
index.html I'm not going to use extends
or any of that fancy block stuff yet I'm
just going to go ahead and create a
relatively simple form via which back in
the day my classmates could have
registered for interal Sports so let's
go ahead here and I'll propose that we
do this um in this page we'll have a
form the action of which will be a route
called SL register though I could call
that anything I want it'll be somewhat
private so I'm going to use post instead
of get just so that people don't
accidentally maybe register twice by
hitting reload uh without warning uh
inside of this form let's go ahead and
give them an input uh where autocomplete
will be off as always for demonstration
sake autofocus so the cursor goes there
initially the name of this field will be
literally named because I want my
classmates's name if they want to
register for some sport the placeholder
will again be quote unquote Nam just so
they see some gray instructions and the
type of this field will indeed be text
as before and then I need to give them
the ability to register for a few Sports
why don't we keep it simple like back in
the day basketball soccer and Ultimate
Frisbee were three of the sports that we
supported and so let me do this and you
might not have seen this before uh
unless you dabbled further on with forms
on your own but I can create a select
menu otherwise known as a drop-down menu
in HTML inside of which are a whole
bunch of options and each option
typically follows this Paradigm the
value of the option and then the actual
text that the human sees so the value of
these options will be how about we do uh
basketball as one and I want the human
to see literally the same thing though
just like with a link in HTML they could
be different but I'm going to keep them
the same another option will be
uh let's say
soccer and whoops let me fix my quotes
and this human will see the exact same
thing though it could say something else
and then lastly the value will be quote
unquote Ultimate Frisbee and the humans
will see the same thing there ultimate
frisbe all right so this is going to
create as we'll soon see just a drop-
down menu with three separate options if
I want the students to be able to submit
this now let me give them a button the
type of which is submit and this button
will be like the word register on it so
I think we're pretty much good to go
like this is all just HTML no python no
flask per se except for the rendering of
the same template so let me go into my
terminal window let me do flask run
inside of this directory because I need
to serve this app instead I'm going to
see some ugly output including my own
URL and if I hover over that and then
open that URL I should now see a more
interesting form it's got not only a
field for their name but also this
drop-down menu with all three Sports now
this isn't maybe the best user uh
experience thus far because I feel like
I'm biasing people to registering for
basketball maybe because it's checked by
default I mean a lot of forms nowadays
have like a blank placeholder for the
form so this is just an aesthetic thing
but I can do this let me go back to the
same form and let me give myself just a
a blank option at the top that in fact
I'm going to disable so you technically
can't select it proactively but I am
going to select it by default and so we
probably haven't seen those HTML
attributes before but if I want to
create the equivalent of like a a a
title for this dropdown I'm going to
literally create a disabled option
that's automatically selected called
sport so that you can't select it per se
but it is there at the top so if I go
back now to my other tab reload you know
it's just marginally prettier than
before and I'm not biasing people toward
accidentally registering for basketball
alone and if I click on this you'll see
that sport is great out and therefore
not manually selectable but I can select
any of these other three still all right
well un unfortunately if I type in David
and I try registering for instance for
soccer and click register I do end up
atreg and there's no question mark or
name or sport so it's probably indeed
post instead of get those are hints but
not found notice the tab here very uh uh
uh succinctly says 404 not found well
why is that just to be clear why did SL
register give me a
404 what's the logic
here perhaps just State the obvious
or it doesn't exist right we haven't
done that step yet all right so
something as simple as that and so I
actually U sort of belabor that point
because as you're learning like a lot of
these conventions and some of this new
syntax like honestly you're just going
to make stupid mistakes something's not
going to work but again go back to First
principles why is it not found all
right/ register should be a template
maybe called register. HTML oh I forgot
my app. route so that should be the kind
of of thinking as you try to diagnose
these problems moving forward all right
so let me go into app. and let me give
myself a second route here uh so app.
route quote unquote SL route then let me
Define a function called anything I want
but I'm going to call it oh sorry not SL
route SL register let me call the
function just to be consistent register
so but I could call that anything I want
and just for now let's not do anything
too interesting let's just return the
rendering of a template called success
.html let's just pretend for now that
registration is successful no matter who
you are or what you do now I need that
template and I only have index.html at
this point so let me actually now do my
best practices let me copy all of that
let me in a separate terminal window let
me do code uh let me go into my Frost
im's directory and let me create a new
template called layout. HTML just like
before let me paste all that same code
let me delete the form and just put in
that big placehold folder so block body
and then end block is all I did earlier
this is just kind of boiler plate now
convention everything else I'm going to
leave the same but if I wanted to make
it prettier I could add my CSS up top if
I wanted to add like this crazy
repeating background I could probably do
that up top too so I could make every
page look as ugly as it did back in my
day but we'll focus just today on the
text all right so now that I have
layout. HTML let me clean up index.html
I don't need all this redundancy I don't
need all of these tags at the top
instead recall I think I just need
extends quote unquote layout. HTML with
the appropriate percent signs and curly
braces I then have the appropriate block
body though I could call Body anything I
want but I'm going to stick with my
convention earlier and I'm going to
delete the tags down here that I no
longer need why because if I go into
layout. HTML I already have all my open
tags all my Clos tags the only stuff I
want in index.html is is going to be
which belongs in the body so end block
down here and just to be pedantic let me
go ahead and highlight all that hit
shift Tab and that will like unindent it
just to line things up just to be tidy
all right so better even though it looks
a little cryptic now but now I've laid
the foundation for making a third page a
fourth page that don't have all of that
same copy paste all right so now let's
go back into app.py success. HTML is
where I left off so okay let me open my
terminal window let me code up a
template called success. HTML whose
purpose in life is literally just going
to be like to say you are registered
just so that we see some informative
message on the screen so this part I do
still need extends layout. HTML so
there's a little bit of copy paste still
which is a little ugly but so be it
block body for this template and I'm
just going to say you are registered
exclamation point all right and then end
block so super simple it's just an
informative message claiming that the
Stu the student is registered all right
let's go back to the original form which
is this let me reload to make sure my
HTML has reloaded type in David I'm
going to register again for soccer and
click register and oh interesting method
not allowed so I'm not getting a 404
anymore I'm getting
405 at SL
register what's the deduction here how
did I screw up this
time 405 is progress yeah the
placeholder uh so it's not the
placeholder I think is okay this is now
about the underlying HTTP stuff the
method was disallow was not
allowed say again so get purposes post
thing too so by default all of these
routes in flask just by default assume
get because it's safe it doesn't allow
you to send information to the server in
quite the same way but if I do want to
support post recall that we changed this
to be methods equals and then a list
with quote quote Post in it so I just
need to enable support for that method
that that is that HTTP verb all right
let's go back to the form reload just to
make sure I haven't screwed up type in
my name David select soccer from the
dropdown click register and now I'm not
only at SL register in the URL it claims
that I am indeed registered now of
course I'm not I've done nothing
interesting there's no database there's
no CSV file we'll get to that in a bit
but at least I now have the plumbing in
place to do something Dynamic based on
that sport all right well how can I now
improve upon this how about we go ahead
and implement store the actual
registrant in a dictionary in the
computer's memory so instead of just
claiming that they're registered let's
actually make a notation and the
simplest way as we did weeks ago in
Python is just store things in like a
variable in memory like a list or a
dictionary a set anything like that all
right well let me go back into vs code
and in app.py and I think what I'm going
to have to do here is change my register
route to actually do some useful
information but before I register the
user let's consider where I want to
actually put them and so let me propose
that how about we do this at the top of
my file let me go ahead and declare a
global variable called registrant uh and
set that equal to an empty dictionary so
we've done this before when we were
playing around previously with using
dictionaries to store key value Pairs
and I'm going to propose that we store
the registrant as a dictionary why cuz
I'm going to keep it simple like the
name is going to be the student's name
sorry the key is going to be the
student's name and the value is going to
be whatever sport they registered for so
David and soccer and Carter and
basketball and so it kind of makes sense
for like a two column dictionary so to
speak as we often depict it on screen so
how can I use this dictionary well let
me go ahead and do this down here under
SL register let me go ahead and
initially do this how about we get the
user's name from request. form. Get and
set it equal to whatever the value of
name is and I'm not going to give a
default value now because I don't want
to call the student world or something
strange like that I'm just going to
assume for now that it's there let's
then create another variable called
Sport and do request. form doget quote
unquote sport to get these students
Sport and then let's go ahead and do
this in the
registrant dictionary let's index into
it using the student's name and let's
set it equal to whatever the sport is so
I've got these variables just to keep my
code tidy and I'm now putting a key
value pair in that uh into that
dictionary all right well what do I want
to now do and I'll I'll go ahead and say
success. HTML sure let's go ahead and do
that but now I think success. HTML means
that so let me go back to the form
reload let me type in David and soccer
register okay let me go back and say
Carter and basketball registered okay
now let's see what I want to do next how
about I go
into um Let me give myself another route
and let's play around here so app. route
let's give myself another third route
called registrant whose purpose in life
is just to show me who all of those
registrants are just like you would
expect from a website like this and then
let me Define a function called
registrants or anything else and then
let me return the rendering of a
template called
registrant H ML and let me pass in this
is kind of neat I can do registrant
equals registrant which again looks
weird but what am I doing I'm presuming
to pass in a placeholder called
registrant the value of which is this
dictionary that I've been collecting all
of the registrations in so similar to
the name placeholder before but it's a
little more powerful because now it's a
whole dictionary not just a single
string so I think now let me be creative
here let me go into my
templates under uh my templates folder
and let's do this uh let's go into uh my
terminal window let's create another
template called registrant HTML that's
actually going to do this displaying of
all of the registrant for us so extends
layout. HTML just so I can borrow all of
the same HTML as
before and let's define block body just
like before and inside of this and block
I want to put I don't know like a
bulleted list or an ordered list list of
all of the registrant so how can I do
this well let's do uh an unordered list
ul and here's where Ginger and flask
more generally get kind of interesting
like I want there to be something like
this An
Li uh and then like the students's name
and then an L uh maybe Li yeah like that
and then maybe like sport something like
this but I didn't pass in a name I
didn't pass in a sport I passed in the
entire dictionary of registrants now in
Python if we were just doing something
at the black and white terminal window
and doing a command line program you
know I'd probably have some kind of for
Loop in Python Ginger does allow you to
do this so a templating language tends
to come with very lightweight mechanisms
for doing placeholders doing Simple
Loops doing Simple conditions so python
like syntax and it's almost identical so
watch what I can do inside of this
unordered list let me not start to
manually output a single Li let me use
this syntax the same Ginger syntax that
I used for Block so curly brace percent
sign and I'm going to say this for name
in registrant so this is just like
python Syntax for iterating over a
dictionary and now this is going to look
stupid but the opposite of that is end4
so in HTML you use the slash in ginger
you literally use the word end no space
and then the name of the keyword so end4
is how you close this but this is where
templating gets really cool you can now
do Li and in here I can do something
like that student's name and that's it
I'm going to leave it like that and what
I'm doing here is using really a
template as templates are intended I've
got like the basic building blocks of
what I want this output to look like but
thanks to this little for Loop here
thanks to Ginger syntax the curly brace
and the percent sign I'm going to
iterate over every dictionary printing
out name name name name and so if I've
got two kids registered now I'm going to
see two liis David and Carter
respectively so let's see let me go back
to uh my Frost IM tab here and I don't
have a link yet so I got to do this
manually uh like a developer would let
me go to slash registrant and I'll zoom
out and hit
enter and you'll see what you'll
probably see two when making mistakes
for the first time in this world so
where is the error message unfortunately
internal Ser server error is not all
that useful but we do tell you you see
terminal window so if I go to the
terminal window I haven't been paying
attention to this for quite some time
and in fact I have two terminal windows
open so that I can still use commands at
the prompt but if I go back to my first
terminal window AKA bash there you'll
see in your terminal window When
developing web applications like all of
the mistakes you made in the terminal
itself this is one of those python
tracebacks that's related to me screwing
up here now let me go ahead here and
let's see uh type error function is not
iterable
and block for name function is not
iterable all right so what mistake did I
make well this is what happens when I
don't follow my notes and make changes
on the fly so I have this variable on
line five called registrant in all lower
case but what did I then do on the Fly
here in line
22 I defined a function called
registrant so like newbie mistake like I
shouldn't have done this I can't have a
variable and a function of the same name
name because the symbols are literally
identical so just to make clear that
this variable up here is actually Global
we'll use our convention like we did in
C often when we had a global variable
we'll capitalize it all just to make it
stand out like a a constant value up
there and so down here what I'm going to
do is pass in registrants in all cap so
that was stupid didn't mean to confuse
there but the reason for that error to
be clear is that you can't have a
function that's the same name as a
variable I could just change the
variable name alt together I'm going to
go ahead and just capitalize it to make
it really stand out that this is in fact
a global variable up top all right now
I'm going to go back to my browser let's
do David and
socer all right but there's going to be
some other mistakes here so on line 17
let me go ahead and change this variable
to be capitalized there because indeed I
want to put the key and the value in
this newly named variable as all
capitals registrant let me now go back
to vs code here let me go back to the
form and let me start adding some data
fresh let me register David for soccer
clicking register now and we should see
you are registered but hopefully now
it's indeed in the computer's memory let
me go back and register now Carter for
basketball clicking register again and
hopefully it's now registered if I now
change my route manually to B SL
registrant which is this newly added
route that I made and hit enter now I
see thank God now I see the unordered
list containing everything in the
computer's memory so when I say you are
registered I kind of mean it now because
the server is still running and in the
computer's memory is in this registrant
Global variable a dictionary of key
value pairs of course we're only seeing
the keys at the moment so it might be
nice to actually see the values in as
well so let me go back to VSS code and
let me go into registr trans. HTML and
I'll just do something a little messy
I'll just say uh how about let just make
it a sentence is registered
four and now another placeholder I'm
going to say registrant bracket name so
just like in Python if registr is itself
a dictionary registr bracket and then
the key you want to index into is
perfectly valid syntax as well so now
let me go back to SL registrant let me
click reload again so why isn't it
working everyone what's the bug that I
introduced earlier if David is
registered for none and Carter is
registered for none but David and Carter
are in the dictionary like that's a good
thing so some of the data is in there so
why are there no Sports Associated well
the first thing I literally just did in
front of you all was I went to app.py
and I stared at line 17 thinking like
how did I screw this up I'm putting
sport as the value of the key which is
the student's name all right line 17
looked fine to me a few seconds ago so I
looked then with my eyes at line 16 and
this too looked okay my first thought
was oh did I use request. args instead
of request. form instead because that
would have assumed get instead of post
but no like that looks okay too so then
my final Instinct was oh my god did I
screw up the HTML form and so that's why
I went back over to my tab here I went
to the original form here I then view
page source and this might not be as
obvious to you if you've never seen the
select menu before what is apparently
missing here that might explain my
mistake yeah
yeah I didn't name this form field quote
unquote sport now to be fair you haven't
seen me do this as a select menu before
and it's different from this input when
you have an input tag you literally say
name equals whatever on the input tag it
turns out I don't know why I skipped
this earlier I probably meant to come
back to it the select tag also can take
a name parameter so if I go back to the
name
parameter here and go back and add the
name parameter let me go into that
template which is
index.html let me add name equals quote
unquote sport in all lowercase which is
different from the visual aesthetic of
this temporary disabled option that's
just there to make things prettier for
the human now let me go ahead here and
first I'm going to go into my terminal
window and I'm actually going to hit
control C to stop the server alt
together because I want to throw away
the contents of memory and therefore get
rid of that dictionary that had David
and Carter and those nun values so this
is sort of me clearing the computer's
memory I'm going to rerun flask run I
get that same URL as before so I'm going
to hover over that and open the new tab
and just to be sure I'm going to do view
page source and here I see now okay now
the form has both a name and a sport in
it all right now I'm really going to
cross my fingers because I intend for
this now to work David will register
again for soccer register claims we are
registered I'm going to go back and do
it again for Carter and basketball
register we still don't have a link so
I'm going to manually go up to the URL
and change/ register to registrant as
before zooming out and hit enter and
thank God now I'm actually registered
properly for this so oh thank
you so what is it like 20 years later
I'm still struggling to implement this
site okay so um so here now we have for
the first time in Python and web stuff
like now we have a proper web
application and it's not just echoing
back hello David hello Carter this could
now work for any of you and it's
currently served privately but if I made
this URL public I could put this on the
web now and let anyone in the world
register but there's kind of some issues
here there's some security flaws
potentially and so for instance let me
go back to the web form here and let me
open up the inspect tab the developer
tools and just remind you that anyone on
the internet not only you the developer
but a an adversary can see all of your
HTML see all of your CSS see all of your
JavaScript but more importantly because
this is all client side in the browser
there is literally nothing technically
stopping them from changing the HTML or
at least their copy of it and I did that
last week with Yale I changed their
website but no I changed my copy of
their website but when forms get
involved you could maybe be actually
malicious now because even though this
drop-down menu only has basketball
soccer and Ultimate Frisbee suppose I
really want to register for how about uh
let's say uh name your favorite sport
volleyball we really want to register
for volleyball but like this website
won't let me well there's nothing
stopping me from going under the
elements tab in my browser going into
this select menu here and you know what
no one ultimate for me let's change this
to volleyball and let's change this to
volleyball enter I'm going to close the
inspector now and as requested now we
support volleyball in the form now now
it's not changed on the server to be
fair but think about how HTTP works when
I fill out this with uh say let's see
Bernie's name Bernie really wants to
register for volleyball as well at the
moment my code is just going to trust
that what's in request. form is what was
in the original form itself no matter
whether the human adversarially actually
changed it so if I actually submit this
form and click register for Bernie and
volleyball even though that's not one of
the supported available Sports if I now
go to registrant my website nonetheless
has trusted that uh Bernie and perhaps
you are registered for volleyball so
what's the implication of this this has
surely happened in the past when like
really poorly implemented websites um
allow you to uh specify the price of an
item for instance in your shopping cart
and they just trust that when you click
submit or add to cart it adds the price
to the backend server if you're not
validating the price and making sure as
with a database that wait a minute that
price is valid valid or wait a minute
those sports are valid like who knows
what people are going to do to your site
and it's that simple to actually hack a
website accordingly now we can very
easily fix this with some um some week
six style python we really just need to
do a bit of logic here and so let me
propose this let me go into app.py here
and at the very top let me also create
how about a uh Global variable called
Sports in all caps and I'm going to set
that equal to in square brackets the
list of Sports I actually want to
support so I'm going to put in
basketball here I'm going to put in
soccer here and I'm sorry no volleyball
officially I'm going to put in ultimate
frisbee here so I've got this Global
list of supported Sports now think about
how I made this form a while ago I just
hardcoded these Sports here well I don't
have to do that I can sort of draw upon
my own official list of sports instead
so let me scroll down to my
index.html rendering template here let
me say that the sports I want to support
are are these so just using the same
placeholder trick as before but I'm now
telling the template what sports we
currently support now if I go back into
index.html I don't have to manually do
any of this let me get rid of all three
of those options which I manually
inputed earlier let me use my new trick
with ginger syntax and say for sport in
sports then let me proactively say end
for just to finish that thought and then
in here let me do option value equals in
curly BRAC is Sport and then so that the
human also sees the same words I'm going
to say sport out here so I've completely
changed what was hardcoded manually
typed to something now that's completely
Dynamic so now it's not going to stop
someone adversar like me from changing
the HTML but watch this the behavior on
the form if we go back is still now the
same drop down as before so
aesthetically it looks the same but you
know what why don't we be clever now and
let's go into app.py and the/ register
route and why don't we say this uh if
how about sport not in sports then let's
return render template uh failure. HTML
now this template doesn't exist yet so
let me just quickly make this real fast
I'm going to copy that code from before
let me create a code file in uh failure.
HTML I'm just going to paste this here
so I have a super simple error message
and I'm going to say you are not
registered just to that's what we mean
by failure and now in app.py consider
what logic I've added Sports in all caps
on line 22 is that same Global list as
before by asking pythonic if sport not
in sports well then you hacked me like
you tried to inject volleyball or some
other sport into request. form so I'm
just going to say no failure not letting
you register and I can do this a little
more uh verbosely too why don't I also
say this if if not name so if the name
is blank let's similarly return a render
template of failure. HTML in other words
if you didn't give me a name you left it
blank that's not useful for me running
the sports program let's also consider
that to be a failure so if I go back to
this tab now I'm going to reload just to
make sure I have the latest client side
let me be lazy and just click register
enter you are not registered because I
didn't give it an actual name all right
well let's go back how about I now type
David but no no I'm not going to choose
a sport I just want register myself nope
that did not work now let me go ahead
here and choose soccer this I think does
work let me go back now and try this
hacker trick whereby I go into the drop-
down menu I go into the select menu I
change as before Ultimate Frisbee to
volleyball and I'll change this one here
to
volleyball let me close the tab now this
looks like it's available now but when I
click register this this time it says
you are not registered and this is much
better than relying on other techniques
you might see or have seen online with
regard to HTML because there's also this
trick let me go back to the screen here
let me go back to index.html and you
might have seen online or you might
eventually see online that there's other
attributes you can use like required you
can literally tell the browser uhuh this
field is required you cannot leave it
blank if I go back to the browser now
reload and I again presume to be lazy
and I don't type in any name and click
register okay so that's kind of nice
like now the browser is being a little
more helpful for me saying no no no this
is required you have to fill this out
but again if you know what you're doing
okay well I disagree with your requiring
a name of me let me go in here let me go
over to this tag let me delete the
required attribute and now I slip
through but I didn't slip through on the
server and so there's a difference here
and an important distinction and so many
people in the real world still screw
this up there's client side validation
like actually checking that the data is
as you expect on the client side the
browser and there server side validation
and even though client side validation
like adding that required attribute
makes things more user friendly right
like that was a pretty little popup it
tells me that it's required it just
looks better than the previous version
it is not trustable you cannot trust any
input that ever comes from the user
because clearly with like a an hour or
so of cs50 like they can learn how to
turn all of these defenses off so even
if you like the user interface better
client side you have to have to have to
do server side validation always users
are not to be trusted and as soon as any
app or website you make becomes popular
unfortunately then you have to deal with
all of the adversarial possibilities as
well oh good question could the
adversary potentially access things
sensitive like app.py theoretically no
like if flask itself is buggy then sure
maybe if you're running some other
software on your server on your laptop
then sure uh it it's possible however if
your server is properly configured
theoretically they should not be able to
get access to that with that said we'll
soon see or You might with your final
project if you do something web based
you're never going to want to write like
usernames and passwords in your actual
code you can put them in what are called
environment variables so sort of in the
computer's memory but not in your code
just in case you or someone screws up
there are uh still ways to defend
against those kinds of possibilities
however slim
yeah a good question and this comes back
to First principles just like in C and
in python as soon as you return from a
function that's it nothing below that
line of code executes and so to
summarize the question even though I'm
returning this failure. HTML template
how am I making sure we still don't
accidentally put volleyball in that
Global dictionary it's because for
instance if you don't give me a name on
line 22 at the moment I'm returning the
failure template and that's it lines 23
24 25 26 27 never execute in particular
26 never executes and that's where I
would have been saving the name
similarly if we do we get a invalid
sport that is either blank or not in the
original authoritative list we return
failure. HTML is a template in line 25
we never get to line 26 so it just boils
down to return and what that means in
Python 2 good question other questions
as
well no all right how about we make one
more enhancement here or so because the
problem with storing everything in this
Global dictionary might be what we've
got it all working finally but why is
probably a global dictionary not the
place to store Frost's registration
data what's the implication of
this okay might slow the whole process
down but that actually Ram is actually
good memory is actually generally a good
thing so not going to be a deal breaker
here why might I not want to store that
data though in that
variable you can perhaps infer how I fix
something
earlier yeah and
back yeah it gets it's the memory gets
deleted garbage collected if you will as
soon as flask stops running so if you so
much as hit control C like you've just
lost all of your freshmen who registered
for the sport probably not a good thing
I did this deliberately a moment ago and
I hit control C because I did want to
clear the dictionary but trusting that
your server will never crash and your
code will always work and the power will
never go out like that's not the right
way to build any kind of web application
with persistent data so what we probably
want to do is reintroduce csvs and we've
played with those in C and in Python
could totally use csvs but we also now
have p uh SQL at our disposal and let me
propose that we do this in SQL in
instead and for this let me go ahead and
open up a version of the program that I
wrote in advance so let me go ahead and
close these templates which will look
very similar but a little different from
the ones I wrote in advance and let me
go ahead and open up uh in today's let
me go into Source 9 let me go into Frost
im's how about version four technically
in the versions online and let me go
ahead and open up app.py as follows so
here is an already made version that
does just a little something different
at the very top I'm importing cs50 SQL
Library which you might recall we used a
couple of weeks past just to write
python that talks to a SQL database and
this feels like an opportune moment to
bring that idea back down here on line
eight I'm creating a DB variable that
opens up a file called frost. DB using
syntax that we've seen before I did
create this FRS DB file in advance of
class just so that we have a couple of
columns in which to store names and
sports and such here's that same Global
array a global list called Sports and
let's just see what's going on down
below if I scroll down to Index this is
the same as before as we wrote together
on the Fly let's skip deregister for a
moment and go now into register so this
one's a little different but let's see
what I've done I've got some comments in
here because I wrote it in advance and I
think this logic is pretty much the same
though I tightened it up and I'm asking
two questions at once using on line 38
the or keyword here just to say if
there's not a name or the sport is not
in sports that is what we'll call now a
failure but what's fun now is that on
line 42
I'm using the cs50 SQL library to
execute some actual SQL and I'm going to
insert into a table called registrant
two columns name and Sport what names
and Sport well these two values with
placeholders plugging in name and Sport
notice I'm using the question marks
absolutely necessary so we don't get one
of those SQL injection attacks because
that too could be possible if someone
typed in some dangerous words or
keywords like delete or single quotes or
semicolons in the form here I'm letting
the library sanitize the data and then
this is a trick we haven't yet seen and
it's really going to start tying things
together I can also use a redirect
function in flask that has the effect of
doing the the if you will uh
safetyschool.org trick again whereby
after the user registers if I want to
automatically show them now everyone who
is registered atreg I don't have to
manually expect that they'll change the
url like I've been doing for the past
few minutes I can just redirect them
anywhere I want on my app or heck I
could redirect them to any URL on the
internet using this function call and
it's just a nice way to send them to a
different route if you want them to see
in this case those registrant so let me
do this in the same directory let me
increase my terminal window size let me
do SQL light three of frost. DB and let
me type schema and you can indeed see it
wraps on to two lines here that each
registrant has an ID which will be
automatically assigned one two three on
up a name which is not null text and a
sport which is also the same and the
primary key is just going to be this
unique identifier so that I made in
advance but if I do select star from
registrant semicolon there's no one
currently registered for any sports but
let's try now running this let me go
ahead and close my old version which we
wrote together and I'll close that tab
let me do flask run in this version four
here all right I'm going to see some
similar output I'm going to open the URL
now and you'll see that I made a couple
of Chang changes before instead of using
a select menu I used what are called
radio buttons now which is a reference
to Old School radio buttons that were
mutually exclusive in cars back in the
day and we'll see how to do this but
it's just an alternative to a select
menu and I'm going to go ahead and type
in my name again here so I'll do David
I'll do soccer by selecting this radio
button and I'm going to click register
now and notice what happened it's a
little ugly the formatting but so again
was this 20 years ago here I have now
now at the slash registrant route
instead of an unordered list I'm just
using a simple HTML table so I'll show
you what this looks like in just a
moment too and I'll show you this
deregister button which is sort of
unnecessarily large I also have
functionality we'll soon see for how you
can unregister someone from a sport as
well so take your name out of contention
well let me go back to my terminal
window here and I'm going to click the
plus to give myself s a second terminal
so I can go back into Source 9 Frost IMS
4 I'm going to do SQL light of frost. DB
I'm going to do select star from
registrant now and now you'll see that
indeed there's David registered for
soccer and in fact if I quit the flask
program with control C and rerun it
again no big deal because that next
version of flask will just use the
database as well so I'm persisting
keeping the data in SQL light whereas
I'm actually grabbing it using my python
code in flask all right let's put one
more person in here so we can delete one
of us too Carter for basketball register
and now we see both of us here all right
so let's see how we did this let's go
back over to VSS code let me shrink down
my terminal window let me go into the
actually let's go into the templates
directory and let's look at for instance
index.html so previously we were using a
select menu turns out radio buttons use
the input tag but instead of having
input of uh type equals text like for
the human's name you have type equals
radio and so long as each of your radio
buttons has the same name the same name
the same name that's what makes them
mutually exclusive so checking one radio
button turns off the others because they
have the same name the value I want to
assign to each of these radio buttons is
just the sport placeholder this is what
the human sees on the screen so it's
almost the same as the select menu it
just looks aesthetically different but
there's my same button so that's all the
difference I made there and I added a
heading tag H1 just to say register to
make clear what it is but let's take a
look at another file uh this one now
being how about the SL registrant route
so if I open up registr trans. HTML here
now it's way more verbose than my
unordered list but this is just kind of
boring HTML here's my table tag table
head table row table heading this makes
things bold as the first row of the
table name sport are my two columns I've
got a third empty column just so I can
fit that button as we'll soon see again
T body for table body here's the same
for Loop trick again so that I can
output for every registrant a whole
table row and there's this weird form in
there but we'll come back to that but
there's the registrant's name there's
the registrant sport but notice the
slightly different syntax here recall
that cs50's select uh cs50's execute
function when it returns to you a list
of dictionaries you can then get at the
individual columns by way of those keys
so let's go to the/ registrant Route let
me go back to app.py scroll down here
and it's actually super simple here I
have a SL registr route that first
executes select star from registrant so
just old SQL stuff give me everyone from
the registr table let me then render the
template called registr trans. HTML and
just pass in this list of dictionaries
and we haven't quite done this yet but
if you go back to register. HTML how do
you iterate over each dictionary in that
list well the syntax is just for
registrant in registrants that makes
this a dictionary one at a time in the
list just like in Python so registrant
name and registrants sport is just
another Syntax for using the square
bracket notation it's just a little
cleaner and slightly more succinct than
having quotes and square brackets
everywhere and then the rest of this is
just
HTML so what happens now if I want to uh
like Carter has been cut from the
basketball team if you will so how do we
do that well we want to click this
button deregister next to Carter's name
but how does this work and think about
now any website you visited that has
something like a shopping cart uh where
you can remove things from your cart or
update quantities or add more quantities
to your shopping cart on Amazon or
anything else well let's actually look
at the HTML that my app has spit out
let's actually look at this here and
we'll see the following we'll see that
we have here in the HTML that reached
the user not only is David in the first
column socer in the second notice that
my register. HTML form is also spitting
out a tiny little web form of its own
it's ugly but I only care about its
functionality for now and notice what
I'm doing here every registrant in this
database gets their very own deregister
button and that form has a button that
says deregister but notice what else
each of those forms have there's no text
box there's no drop down menu there's no
radio buttons rather you have a hidden
input field here so there is a way with
HTML to have a form that will submit
information but you don't have to give
the user the ability to change that
information you can just go ahead and
tuck it inside of the form invisibly if
you will hidden in fashion and so what's
going to happen is if I click the D
register button next to Carter his
primary key is two
mine is instead one so what's going to
happen if I click his deregister button
it submits a form with a
ID parameter whose value is two and it
submits it to the deregister route so
what do that mean well if I go to VSS
code and I go to app.py let's look at
the deregister route that I skipped over
so if you access the deregister route
via post this code gets called I grab
from request form the ID that was
submitted in Hidden fashion if there's
indeed an ID that is it's not blank it's
not zero it's an actual number like one
2 three or more I execute delete from
registrant where ID equals that value
with a question mark Place holder and
then I redirect the user back to
registrant now if I go back to this form
here I click deregister we'll see that
in action gone is now Carter and in fact
if I go back to my terminal window here
I open open up uh SQL light 3 of frost.
DB and rerun select star from registrant
Carter is now gone so again using very
simple HTML forms you can get buttons
and links and other such UI mechanisms
to like do things on the server that you
want but there is a danger here this now
is really meant this example is like an
administrative website like it was some
20 years ago just for us internal staff
to be doing things technically this is
dangerous what I've just done
two even though Carter's ID is two and
hidden and mine is one in Hidden what
could this allow an adversary to do if
they had admin access to the same
site any
thoughts
yeah
yeah yeah they could change the value of
that hidden attri by opening up chrom's
like developer tools change the number
in the HTML they could delete anyone
deregister anyone want from the database
now in this case I claim this is fine
because this is only meant for us staff
who were running Sports back in the day
but it's indeed a risk so wouldn't it be
nice if we could actually ensure that
only those users who are authorized are
allowed to execute certain actions I
think for this capability we're actually
going to need to introduce something a
bit more and so here of course is an
opportunity to talk briefly about really
what you and I do all day long every day
we log into one or more websites or apps
or at least until uh you're logged out
automatically and you have to do it
again so here for instance is a
screenshot of Gmail when you type in
your username you type in your password
maybe your to factor code that gets
texted or sent to your phone then you're
logged in and thankfully you're not
prompted to log in again typically for
number of hours or days or weeks
depending on the website like Gmail
keeps you logged in for ages your bank
probably logs you out within an hour or
so for safety sake so that is completely
configurable on the server but how does
g Emil know how does Google know that
even as you're checking different mails
again and again and again how do they
know that you're still the same person
who logged in well it turns out that
using these same building blocks as
today HTTP and HTML and more you can
actually implement the notion of a login
feature by doing the equivalent of
something with something called cookies
essentially what happens when you first
log into a website for the very first
time successfully with your username and
password a cookie so to speak is planted
on your computer and metaphorically this
is kind of like taking a hand stamp and
your hand is now stamped in this case a
smiley face so that every other time you
click on a link on that same website
google.com gmail.com whatever
unbeknownst to you your browser is
constantly presenting that handstamp
just like going into a club or an
amusement park or something like that
where they don't want to check your ID
again they don't want to check your
ticket again they just want to quickly
see the same hand stamp and so that is
one of the things that a browser is
always doing for you once you're logged
in any cookies that have been planted so
to speak in your Mac or PC or phone are
constantly represented to the site every
time you click a link or make another
request to that website and mechanically
how this works not just metaphorically
and ink essentially this is what happens
here is a example of an HTTP request to
something like Gmail and suppose for
instance that you've logged in typically
as of last week we said that coming back
from the server would be another virtual
envelope containing like a 200 okay
message and then like the actual web
page or the picture of a cat or whatever
it may be but Google can also if they
verified that you have some username and
password correctly inputed they can do
the equivalent of stamping your hand and
the way they do this is they send an
additional line of text in that virtual
envelope from the server to your browser
literally using another HTTP header not
content type which just mundanely tells
you what kind of content has come back
they literally send an http header
called set-cookie and then they set a
key value pair on your Mac or PC this is
the technical equivalent of this smiley
face handstamp and what your computer is
designed to do because your computer and
intern browser are supposed to implement
HTTP anytime you click another link on
Gmail or click on another mail or the
like your browser unbeknownst to you
presents that handstamp and how it does
it technically is in the envelope it
sends to Google from your browser it
doesn't send set cookie it just sends
cookie colon and the exact same thing
and so long as Google is smart and they
have a database or something of all of
the session Valu session is the
technical term for this maintenance of
information across HTTP so long as
Google has a big database that knows
that my cookie value is one 123 and your
cookie value is 456 they can infer from
this virtual handstamp whose emails they
should be showing mine or yours or the
like so this is just scratching the
surface but if I really wanted to enable
only Carter to deregister himself I just
have to make sure that I log him in
somehow username password and all of
that I stamp his hand or really put a
cookie on his computer and only if his
cookie lines up with the user ID he's
trying to deregister should he be
allowed to in fact do so so all of this
is quite possible and indeed the
technical term for this is session and
what we thought we'd do in our remaining
time Today show you some examples of
exactly how some of the most familiar
web functionality is implemented today
some of which you'll use in your own uh
problem set 9 uh which itself will be a
web app or perhaps even your final
project so let me go ahead and do this
let me close my previous tabs and all
things for ashs and let's move on to
implementing some notion of login so in
just a moment I'll switch over here to
VSS code and what I'm going to do is
indeed in my source 9 directory I'm
going to go into a login directory and
if I type LS here you'll see app.py
requirements. text which just refers to
libraries I want to automatically
install and a templates folder as well
I'm going to go ahead and stop the
previous server and close that terminal
window and I'm going to open up this
version of
app.py so there's a few new lines here
and we'll give you these lines for
problems at nine but I've got some of
the familiar stuff up here including
this new redirect function we just used
and I have a session variable that comes
with flask 2 so what's nice again about
flask is that it deals with all of this
cookie stuff for you it sets the cookie
it checks the cookie and what flask does
for you is it gives you the abstraction
of a variable called session so that
anything you put in the session variable
which itself is a dictionary will be
there again and again and again whenever
that same user comes back a session is
how you implement essentially like the
proverbial shopping cart uh if I'm
logged into Amazon you're logged into
Amazon Amazon knows which of us is which
by way of that cookie and Amazon if
they're using flask provides the
programmer with a dictionary called
session and flasks make sure that when
Carter is visiting the site the code
uses his session object when I'm
visiting the site it uses my session
object but it's all implemented with
those same cookies this is the same as
before these lines are new and you'll
see these in problem Set n this is how
we enable sessions in a web application
and I'll just wave my hands at the
detail there's different ways to
implement sessions whether you use
cookies on the server cookies on the
browser or other things these just
ensure that we're storing the the
session information the shopping cart on
the server itself now down here let's go
ahead and do this let's go ahead and run
flask run so I can see what this app
does if I do this and visit the URL that
gets outputed you'll see a very simple
web page here and if I type in for
instance my name I'm not going to bother
with a password and click log in you'll
see that you are logged in as David and
now I can log out so I'm going to go
ahead and click log out and now it seems
to know that I'm not logged in again I
can log in as Carter because I didn't
bother implementing passwords for
Simplicity but now the site knows I'm
logged in as Carter better yet if I
reload reload reload or click this
button again and again notice it still
knows that I'm Carter uh until such time
as I log out all right well how is this
working well let's go back to vs code
here and let me scroll down to first
this route this is a very common
Paradigm here whereby I'm checking for
the index route if there is not a name
in the session redirect the user to SL
login now what does that mean well let
me go back to vs code here let me go to
the slash route so again your url will
be different but I'm just going to go to
slash and hit enter notice that I got
automatically redirected to login and so
many websites do this if you go to a
website and you're not logged in you're
very often redirected to SL login or SL
account or something like that where
you're prompted the code for doing that
is right here if there's no name in the
session if there's no name in the
shopping cart if you will go ahead and
return the user to login that route
otherwise implicitly if they are logged
in show them index.html so let's go down
that rabbit hole let me open up in VSS
code a second terminal window let me go
into Source 9 and go into this same
login demonstration and let me open up
the template called
index.html and here's all this is
there's some layout but who cares at
this point it's just the boiler plate
generic HTML here's the body block I
have this and this two is ginger because
of the curly brace and the percent sign
if there's a name in the session this is
just python syntax then say this
sentence you are logged in as whatever
name is in the session in the shopping
cart if you will and then I just have
this HTML link for logging the user out
else if there is no name in the session
logically just say you are not logged in
and give them a manual link for logging
in instead so that's all this particular
template does but how does the slash
login work well let's go into this other
template code of login. HTML to which
I'm redirected super simple this is just
copy paste from HTML before I've got a
login form that's going to have an
action of Slash login submits for
privacy sake just via post and then the
rest of this is just a simple form and
I'm using using an input type equals
submit instead of button equals type
equals submit but same idea here too and
if I go back to app.py well let's see
how login works all right it's a lot all
at once but they're relatively simple
reapplications of the same idea so if
the user visits SL login via get or post
call this function login if the user has
submitted via post and we saw this
technique before go ahead and do this on
line 23 store in this special session
variable that comes with flask a name
key and store in it the user's own name
so quote unquote name will have a value
of David or Carter or the like and as
soon as you do that redirect the user
back to slash just so they see the
homepage again and this is how Amazon
and all these other websites work too
otherwise if they visit this page
implicitly via get and even though I
didn't say equals equals get anywhere
that's sort of the implication because
if you can only get here via get or post
and we already handled post logically
All That Remains is get well then just
show them the login screen instead but
there's half a dozen ways we could
express that same logic and then for log
out this is kind of straightforward if
the user clicks that log out link and
ends up at SL logout this route well
just change the value of that key in the
session to be none effectively no Carter
is gone David's gone there's no one
logged in so that is all that's required
to actually implement the notion of
logging in and logging out of website
plus the password thing which should
probably involve a database but one
thing at a time and really session is
sort of like the code version of a
shopping cart whereby if I visit the
same code I get my own session object if
Carter visits the website he gets his
own session object and the way flask
Keeps Us straight is they put one cookie
on my computer a different cookie on his
computer and uses those to line up with
making sure the right session gets shown
to the right actual
user questions on this notion of
sessions no all right how about a couple
final examples just to tie this all
together let me go back into vs code
here let me quit my previous version of
flask let's go into Source 9 and go into
store which is a separate app Al
together and let's start by just running
flask to see what it does let's hover
over the URL and open it in another Tab
and this is pretty ugly too let me zoom
in but it's a very simple bookstore like
an early amazon.com for each of these
seven books here Each of which seems to
be like maybe this is H1 this is H2 H2
H2 H2 and then there's a button
underneath each well now let's use this
as an opportunity to kind of infer like
for any website how this thing works let
me go ahead and do view page source and
you can do this for any website on the
internet let's try to figure out how
this bookstore adds things to a cart
well here's the H1 tag uninteresting H2
H2 H2 so the juicy part is in these
forms each of these forms has an action
of SL cart so that's the route that's
going to be interesting in a moment and
it uses post for privacy sake each of
these forms like the deregister feature
for Carter has an ID attribute an ID
parameter that's hidden visually that
has a value of one or two or three so
like the unique uh uh like barcodes for
the books if you will but super small
numbers in our case and then each of
these other forms just had each of these
other books has an identical form except
for the value of this year now in this
case this isn't such a big deal that a
user could technically hack the HTML of
this bookstore amazon.com and change the
IDS because whoa what's the worst
they're going to do like buy more books
by adding more IDs to their shopping
cart like that's not a problem there's
no prices here it's just the unique
ideas of books so whereas the deregister
was maybe worrisome because you're
changing the server I think it's okay
because the user can only at worst buy
more books than then uh they might via
the buttons alone so how does this now
work well let's go into vs code again
here let me give myself another terminal
window and in Source 9/ store let me
open up app.py which is where all the
logic is so I'll flip through most of
this quickly because we've seen this
before these Imports are pretty much the
same as before this line is the same
this line is almost the same but the
database now is called store. DB instead
of frost. DB this is the boilerplate
code for just enabling sessions this
notion of a shopping cart and so let's
see how the index Works how is that I'm
seeing all seven books at once well in
this index function I'm using on line 19
select star from books to get all the
books from the database and then I'm
rendering a template called books. HTML
passing in as a placeholder all of those
books all right let's go down that
rabbit hole for a second let me open up
books. HTML in my templates directory
and here again even though it's you know
new today it's probably increasingly
familiar syntactically here's the H1
here is my Loop here's the H2 which is
going to Output the current book's title
in that Loop here's the form here's the
ID of that book that's going to be
outputed in the form so I didn't
manually type out seven long forms I
just did one in this template so that it
gets generated automatically literally
what a website CL Amazon would do to
show you 10 books at a time or 10 search
results or more at a time all right well
let's go to SLC cart which was the juicy
one and this one's longer but let's see
if we can reason through it if the user
submits via get or post to/ cart well we
first do this and this is just necessary
in some boilerplate rewrote we're going
to use the session object to store a
variable called cart that in this case
is going to be a list so session again
is just a dictionary you can put
anything in it you want previously we
put students names and sports now uh
what I want to do is actually sorry prev
previously we put uh the student name
the user's name in it now I'm going to
actually store a cart key whose value is
a list why because I want to aggregate
more and more books in this list all
right so that just makes sure that I
have at least an empty shopping cart the
very first time the user does this if
they visit this form via post let's go
ahead and get the ID of the book that
they posted if it is not empty if there
is a number like one or two or three
let's go ahead and go into the shopping
C cart which is a list per this line and
just append that ID so this list of
books in your shopping cart is going to
contain like one comma 2 comma four
comma six whatever books you're actually
buying and then the user gets redirected
to cart what if though the user got here
via get and not post well this one's
relatively straightforward if you just
visit slart we select star from books
where ID is in okay so this is
interesting this list and and this is a
syntax you might not have seen before
but if you read the documentation for
cs50's Library if you select something
and use a question mark placeholder and
the placeholder itself is a list we
output a comma separated list of values
just like you would use maybe in problem
Set uh seven for doing SQL queries on
your own so this just means show me only
those books in my shopping cart not
Carters not someone else's not in the
whole database only show me the books in
my shopping cart and then
render it as such so we only saw what
the catalog here looks like at slash
books Let's go ahead and in slash let's
go ahead and add maybe the first book to
my cart and now I see at SLC cart only
that first book whose ID is one let me
now go back to the bookstore here scroll
down to maybe the seventh book and add
that to my cart and now I see this here
too meanwhile all of this information is
stored in my session and so when I
reload this cart again and again the
reason I'm only seeing my two is because
we're checking only the list in my
session and flasks make sure again that
my session is different from your
session is different from Carter's
session as well but you write the code
once and it works for thousands millions
of people in
parallel any questions on
this this yes in the
back sorry say a little louder
uh so to recap so users will never have
the same session values theoretically
the cookie that gets planted does not
look like a smiley face for everyone
each of us gets a big random number
that's assigned to us so it' be like
each of us gets a completely unique hand
stamp that no one else can see the
reason no one else can see it is because
if the website's using https every time
this hand stamp is shown every time this
cookie is sent back and forth It's all
encrypted as well so each of us can even
if we have the same contents by
coincidence because we like the same
books they will be separate cookies
separate memory separate sessions behind
you
yeah really good question when does the
session end totally configurable
typically it ends when you close the tab
or when you quit the browser or you can
also configure cookies to themselves be
persistent for a day for a week for
longer so for instance when you log into
um uh say Gmail they plant a cookie on
your computer probably for a week a
month a year something like that because
it would be annoying and probably drive
you to like Outlook or something else if
you kept having to log into your account
whereas your bank account might actually
wait for you to just close the tab and
then for your own Financial safety they
just automatically delete the session
far sooner but totally configurable by
default as I'm using it it will
typically be thrown away when the
browser itself quits and here too is
another reason to develop websites using
incognito mode because if you want to
just throw throw away all of your
cookies you close the incognito window
mode open a new one and now you're
starting from scratch you don't have to
manually delete all your cookies which
could log you out of websites you
actually care about
yeah a good question when using sessions
if someone maliciously changes the value
of sub forms could it affect other
people theoretically no because the
worst you can do is like add books to
your own shopping cart that you don't
want there so at that point even though
it's on the server it doesn't affect you
or Carter or anyone else unless there is
something more globally happening like
registering or deregistering for a sport
or removing books from the Amazon
database that would be problematic but
in this case we're removing things only
from my own session that the website is
giving me all right the last topic for
today is this thing here which is sort
of everywhere nowadays these things
called apis or application programming
interfaces and this is a very generic
term in fact because any function you've
used in C in scratch in Python in SQL
are all apis like there is a standard
way of interfacing with those functions
they all have names they sometimes have
return values they sometimes have
arguments and an API is just how you use
a function or more generally an API just
specifies how you interact with some
service and so nowadays there's a lot of
web-based services that you can use to
get back data like the weather or the
current time or the database of Amazon
books for instance all might have apis
often web-based that allow you using
URLs or some other technology to just
get data from someone else as though
it's a function you're calling remotely
but HTTP is very often the mechanism
that's used to actually get data from
servers and the way the data can come
back can be as follows let me end with
one final example using some of our
familiar shows from uh weeks past let me
go ahead and close the old flask version
version go back into Source 9 and go
into how about an example called shows
and the first version of this zero I'm
just going to go ahead and run with
flask run I'll hover over my URL and
open it here and you'll see now that I
have a very simple form as we keep doing
today I'm going to type in like o f f i
c office into this search box and click
search and you'll see now that I ended
up at a URL ending in/ search question
mark Q equals office so this is like my
own baby version of google.com but I
implemented it myself and for any title
of a TV show from a couple of weeks past
that matches o i I spit it out into an
unordered list how is this working you
can maybe imagine even if you might not
be able to program this off the top of
your head certainly so soon let me go
into Source 9 let me go into uh show
zero let me open up
app.py and in this file you'll see that
that I'm grabbing a uh file called
shows. DB which is like a simpler
version of the one from a couple of
weeks past uh here is why I see the web
form my first route my index is super
simple it just spits out that form and
my search route like you can think of
this as google.com there only like four
lines of code so if the user sends data
to SL search this function called search
is called I declare a variable called
shows I execute a SQL command that is
Select star from shows where title like
question mark and the syntax here is a
little crazy but I want to prefix to the
user's input percent sign and suffix it
with a percent sign as well putting in
the between those two values the actual
input why in SQL what is it mean if you
have a percent sign to the left and to
the right nothing to do with Ginger
today yeah it's a it's a wild card so it
means match zero or more characters on
the left or match zero or more
characters on the right you have to do
the concatenation
as the second argument to this function
you can't do something clever like put
it here around the like the is the
placeholder that you plug these values
into but this just means hey SQL show me
all of the titles that have o f i
somewhere in them that gives me back an
a list of dictionaries I pass that in as
a placeholder for a variable called
shows and if we look at search. HTML
let's look at that in my templates
directory there's something called
search. HTML super simple I mean this is
like the essence of google.com search
results I'm using an unordered list to
keep things simple but I iterate over
every show in the shows list that came
back and I output An Li with each of
those shows titles and that's it now
Google has like Blue Links and like
little previews and other text the first
sentence or so from each page but like
that's the idea like this is really
similar in spirit to what google.com
search does for you now how is this
working there's no API involved here yet
this is just very basic HTTP I submit
the the form I go to another route and I
get back the results but check out this
version Let me close these tabs here and
open my first terminal window let me go
into shows one from today's Source 9
directory and do flask run this time let
me go ahead and hover over that URL and
open it here and gone now is the submit
button now I'm going to make an user
interface that uses a technique called
Ajax for asynchronous uh JavaScript and
XML which is somewhat of a data term
because we're not using something called
ml anymore but Ajax is a technique
whereby you don't have to submit forms
anymore to get more data from the server
you can use JavaScript per last week
listen for an event like the key press
coming down or up and as soon as you
hear such an event you can secretly in
JavaScript code send a request to the
server to get back more data and then
plug it into the Dom the tree in the
computer's memory and this just makes
for more seamless experiences like
autocomplete on any website so now let
me try typing o okay we got auto
complete super fast f f i c e and you'll
see every time I add more keys to my
input I'm doing another search another
search another search and the data is
changing now how is this working well
let me go back to vs code here and in my
other terminal window let me open up uh
app.py and in app.py you'll see that
there's still a
search route down below that turns a
search template but watch this let me go
into templates search. HTML and notice
here that we're indeed getting back an
unordered list of shows again and again
and again and this HTML that's coming
back let me go here let me open my
terminal oh sorry this is the wrong
version uh sorry I was in the wrong
folder let's fix this and shows one code
of app.py it's almost the same thing
inserch
here okay well I changed this slightly
let me show you this version of search
if I open up app.py here's my search
route I'm getting a variable called Q
giving it the value of whatever request.
RX has from the user like Q equals
office and then I'm checking if the user
actually typed something in execute this
SQL query select star from shows where
title is like that using the same and
this time just to keep things efficient
I limited the total results to 50
instead of an infinite number otherwise
if the user type nothing just to be
super safe here I'm setting shows equal
to an empty list so if you don't type
anything there's nothing to show and no
matter what I render this template
called search. HTML well let's look at
that if I open up templat search. HTML
this time there's no layout there's no
inheritance of that layout. HTML I am
literally generating just a whole bunch
of Li fragments why well let's see what
what's happening in the browser and this
is the beginning of an API if I wanted
to make this API available this
application programming interface I
could tell the world that if you want to
search for TV shows in my database go to
URL that's something something/ search
question mark Q equals office or cat or
dog or anything else and what I will
return to you is this enter I will just
give you a whole bunch of Li tags which
almost looks the same but let me view
the page source only am I going to hand
you back a fragment of HTML I'm not
giving you an HTML tag a body tag a
title tag a head tag I'm not giving you
a web page I'm giving you a fragment of
HTML that you can now do whatever you
want including insert this into your own
unordered list so notice what happens in
this actual app if I go back to vs code
here let me open up my index template
here and you'll see some JavaScript
magic so in JavaScript here in my form
that only had the text box and no button
what am I doing in a script tag here I
am creating a variable called input and
I'm using this function called query
selector that just gets me a reference
to the input text box on the form so I
can see what the human typed this is a
little different today but I'm using
input. atevent listener which is a way
in JavaScript to tell it just like in
scratch listen for something to happen
like the green flag being clicked but in
this case listen for an event that
involves input that is like typing on
the keyboard whether it's by a copy
paste manual input or anything else then
whenever that happens call this function
and async stands for asynchronous this
is a term of art which means that this
this function might take like a split
second maybe even a second or two to
execute so it's going to do it behind
the scenes like in the background so to
speak and what is it going to do well
it's going to call a JavaScript function
that all browsers now Support called
Fetch which is a function that uses HTTP
to go fetch more data via the from the
server it's going to fetch data from a
route called SL search question mark Q
equals and whatever the value is that
the user typed in so I'm just sort of
manually creating my own mini URL and
telling JavaScript go fetch me that HTML
when it comes back via this line of text
here called response. text and let me
wave my hand at await await just means
this might not come back immediately
let's await the response and when it
does come and then let's execute this
code I'm going to do this I'm going to
search the document the whole web page
for this UL tag which is somewhere in
this page that we'll see in a moment
change its inner HTML to be that
fragment of Li Li Li of all of those
matching shows and where does this all
go well if we scroll up here you'll
notice that there's my usual HTML up at
top head tag body tag and all of that
there's the text box that we've talked
about already there's no button for
submitting cuz it all happens
automatically but there is by default
this empty UL that has nothing by
default until we start using that API
and the final flourish here is this this
is kind of a uh ugly sloppy way to get
data from a server to just get back like
a fragment of HTML like what if I'm not
using HTML I want to store these uh TV
shows in a PDF or in some other wet tag
in a table or something like that it
doesn't really make sense for the server
to be presuming that I want Li tags
surrounding each of my data better would
be to get a more generic format back and
that format is almost always nowadays
called this our final acronym Json
JavaScript object notation and let me do
this let me close these two tabs here
and open my terminal window and C cancel
the previous version of flask that was
running let me close this version and
look at our final version called shows
two and do flask run on I'm going to
hover over that URL and open it in a
browser and I'm going to manually visit
after zooming in let's do again slash uh
search question mark uh Q equals Office
enter and this is what Json looks like
now at a glance this does not seem like
an improvement like this looks crazy
that it's just this Big Blob of text but
it's just enough text for the computer
to be able to process it reliably notice
that there's a cur a square bracket here
and if I actually scroll to the Bott
botom there' be a closed square bracket
like way down there inside of that
square bracket is a curly brace then ID
colon and then a number then a title
quote unquote colon and then the title
and then the closed curly brace so what
you're seeing in JavaScript object
notation is a very standard super
popular format that's just text that
still uses square brackets for lists AKA
arrays that still uses curly braces for
dictionaries key value pairs so what you
see here is a massive list up to 50 I
think think shows that came back from
this API Each of which has a dictionary
if you will an object of key value pairs
what keys and values an ID key and a
title key Each of which has a value
respectively and this is the same data
from IMDb some of which you might be
recalling visually this is just a very
raw computer friendly way of returning a
whole bunch of data that we humans don't
need to see but I can use this data by
going back into vs code let me open
another terminal window and go into
Source
9/ shows 2 and in here let me go ahead
and open up how about uh templates
index.html which previously just used
that inner HTML trick and this is not
going to impress you're not going to be
pleased with this syntax but let me just
at least explain what we're doing it
turns out that Json is just the better
way in general the more generic
multi-purpose user agnostic language
agnostic way of returning data from a
server because it's just text so it
doesn't matter if you're using python or
C or C++ or JavaScript or Ruby or PHP or
something else like all of those
languages can process Json information
and indeed here is some JavaScript that
does just that same code as before
initially I declare a variable called
input that gives me access to the user's
text box I listen for input like key
strokes going up and down and when they
happen I call this Anonymous function uh
I fetch data from the server using the
exact same code as before search
question mark Q equals office or
anything else and then this is just now
new code that I use to convert that Json
data into my own HTML format be it an
unordered list an ordered list a table
or anything else what am I doing I've
got a variable called HTML initialized
to nothing so I've got no HTML initially
I then iterate over every ID in those
shows so every one of IMDB's unique
identifiers I iterate over them one at a
time and then I go into the show at its
ID location and I grab its title and
this
is forget this for just a moment I then
take this HTML variable concatenate or
join onto it my own Li tag plus the
title plus the close Li tag and I
skipped this because it got scary pretty
fast but it turns out that if some TV
shows have actually angled brackets in
that could break my HTML entirely so it
turns out you might recall super briefly
last week we had the copyright symbol
using an HTML entity using the Ampersand
and the hash symbol and 169 semicolon it
turns out there are other such cryptic
sequences of characters that represent
otherwise dangerous or untypable
characters like this which could confuse
the computer into thinking it's at the
beginning of a tag and an Amper sand
which could similarly trick the computer
into thinking that it's a entity which
it isn't but long story short there are
libraries thankfully that handle much of
this for you for our purposes the
takeaway is that now that you understand
a bit of
HTTP uh now that you understand a bit of
HTML CSS and JavaScript all of which
they have their roles you can use them
ultimately to start assembling your own
web applications as you will for problem
set nine um stitching together all of
those languages and building
full-fledged web applications mobile
applications or anything more and for
that I think we are all set and if the
first one up here uh can have these
cookies as well we'll see you next time
for our very last cs50
[Music]
lecture
good afternoon my name is Sarah and my
name is Grant and we are the Harvard
crocodillos and pitches now Sarah and I
understand that today is the final
lecture of cs50 it's been a tough
semester we made it through pets four
five and even Finance now I know this is
an unpopular opinion but I particularly
enjoyed Finance I spent a lot of time
with my
flask the P set there was a p
set well um at least things are looking
up um today is our last lecture and look
how far we've come if I were an emoji
right now I'd be the face with tears of
joy sorry about that we're just trying
to work some cs50 references into the uh
intro I I mean uh boy I sure hope this
uh tide man doesn't run off my Mario
filter you could say that for Loop x
equals Open Bracket one comma 2 close
bracket boy I sure wish we had checked
to see if these jokes were funny when we
wrote
them any who we hope that you'll enjoy
this brief
[Music]
serenade your
boot
[Music]
KN House of well there's
friers Andy truck barbecue ribs Tri
[Music]
the boy
boy bo boy bo bo boy boy down at the
house the house of well your root and
you walk on down to a knock down Shack
on the edge of town There's a l
there just quit you see
fall down the house the house
[Applause]
of up your boots and you walk on down
at the
house the House of Blue
Light to your down at the of
light
[Applause]
good afternoon everyone we are the
Harvard crocodillos and it is such an
honor to be here with the Radcliff
pitches performing for cs50's final
lecture congratulations to everyone and
we hope you'll enjoy this our tribute to
cs50 one two one 1 2 3
4 C is for the language I once knew O is
for all notation I must do D is for
dynamic flask run and finance it is even
more than David May in canor so code is
all that I can give to you to youe
debugging it since
PE soon deadlines I'll make it hit
compile and please don't break it code
was made by
[Music]
foru
I for notation I must do
is
Dam even
more is
[Music]
I is for the language 0 1 0 1 0 oh is
for otation 0 1 1 D is for dynamic flas
run and finance e is even more than
David mail in canor so C is all that I
can give to
you debugging it since
PE soon deadlines I'll make it hit
compile and please don't break it code
was made by me for COD was made by me
for COD was
[Music]
by all
right
all right this is cs50 and cs50 this was
the Harvard crocodillos and the Radcliff
pitches if one more time we could thank
them for joining us
today so this is already week 10 our
last and indeed among the goals for
today are to hopefully give you all the
more of appreciation of truly just how
far you've come recall that in week zero
we began with this this visual here
whereby it was described this class as a
bit of a fire hose whereby drinking from
that fire hose or really a fire hose
from a water fountain uh is not unlike
getting an education down the road too
and so this is to say that if you're
feeling like you didn't quite get it all
down like that's actually okay and
that's to be expected and even if you
felt that with each passing week 0 1 two
all the way up now till 10 it never
really ever got easier perhaps just
consider that what was once hard like
Mario and like getting hello world to
compile is indeed the right measure of
the Delta between week Zer and now in
week 10 in fact you might recall that
again in week zero 2third of your
classmates had never taken a CS course
before now of course you all have and
indeed if you think back too to this
final sentiment from week zero that
indeed what ultimately matters in this
course is not where you end up relative
to your classmates but where you end up
relative to where you yourself began so
I would take some pride take some
satisfaction take some relief even
though a little bit more work does
remain at really just how far you've
come since that week zero and recall
that in week zero we literally started
with just zeros and ones and by now many
of you might have gleaned that these 64
zeros and ones have been spelling
something week by week in fact today is
our very last message here in binary uh
encoded on stage but then quickly we
introduced scratch and we started to
assemble some building blocks of
programming Loops conditions uh uh Loops
conditions functions and the like but
without all the distractions of
semicolons and curly braces and all of
that which admittedly we introduce the
next week when we introduce you to C but
even now that we've transitioned to
python hopefully even those kinds of
Curiosities or confusions are hopefully
starting to just get more familiar and
so you finally start to see the missing
semicolon as opposed to spending time on
that kind of struggle recall too that in
week two we started talking already
about memory and like how you can manage
things in arrays that later became of
course in Python lists uh the week after
we talked not only about uh debugging uh
bugs in code but how to debug those same
programs um thereafter we started
talking talking about algorithms and we
took a step back from code and looked at
the bubble sorts and the selection sorts
and the merge sorts and all of the
searches as well that go hand in hand
with that and indeed this ultimately is
what a lot of problem solving moving
forward is going to be about just
solving problems with some form of
algorithm and you have so many different
languages um in your toolkit now with
which to approach problems like those we
talk thereafter about pointers which are
not likely to come back in any modern
languages that you now use but hopefully
you have an all the better of a sense
underneath the hood of like what's going
on inside of the computer so that when
you're designing something you're using
something something crashes you at least
have a mental model for what's going on
and it's no longer that week zero black
box as it once was I mean you built
things like this think back to week five
when you built your own hash table and
those things are everywhere key value
pairs whether it's in python or in C or
if it's now in CSS and JavaScript and
even HTML like that principle of key
value pairs is really everywhere and so
of course now code doesn't necessarily
have to look like this it now
wonderfully looks a little something
more like this but eventually you're
probably not I'm not going to use Python
anymore something new and better is
going to come along but odds are like a
lot of the building blocks from these
past 11 weeks are still going to be
useful for wrapping your mind around
those new worlds and indeed SQL we
introduced you a little bit too and even
if you don't feel yourself yet an expert
hopefully have a sense of like what you
can do with it and what problems you can
solve uh it's of course a better
alternative to something like something
simple like a spreadsheet and now of
course like web stuff is everywhere
whether it's on your laptop or desktop
or a lot of the mobile apps that you use
on your phone even though they're native
applications like you install them from
Google Play or the Apple App Store like
they're implemented increasingly with
HTML CSS and JavaScript but they're put
in a little rectangular window so you
don't even notice that that's actually
really just an embedded browser and then
of course you can build things as you
might for your final project that to
might very well be web based if you go
that route I mean I'm still clinging to
like the very first like web app I ever
made years ago um but honestly I do that
in part because I was just so darn proud
that like I taught myself how to do
something and it actually worked and was
used by other people so whether it's
just used by you or your classmates or
your roommates or your family or your
company down the line there's a great
sense of satisfaction that comes despite
all of the the pain that might be along
the way when you just can't see or fix
that bug now of course we'll transition
as you'll see in the coming days to try
empowering you to code client side as
well up until now you've been using our
own vs code installation in the cloud
which is nice cuz you got up in running
super fast in week one focusing only on
code challenges not on technical
difficulties but among the goals now if
you so choose and want to program after
this class even if you never take
another CS course before you can use
these same real world deao standard
tools on your own Mac or PC and so
pictured here is a screenshot of like vs
code on the Mac and even though yes
you're going to have to like jump
through a couple of more Hoops to just
get python or some other language
working on your own Mac or PC like
that's what programming is ultimately
going to be about and we deliberately
transition you to this at terms end so
that now you have 11 weeks of more
Comfort under your belt with which to
solve sort of silly technical support
headaches that might have been deal
breakers so many weeks ago so there's
still more to be done uh in the coming
weeks and indeed a support structure
there for the cs50 hackathon of course
will be this 700 p.m. till 7 a.m.
opportunity to dive into your final
project well really continue diving into
your final project ideally at that point
uh alongside classmates perhaps your
project Partners if you're working
collaboratively
uh and awaiting you will be such
memories and excitement hopefully as
these even as you then turn your
attention back to your final project
there of course will be several meals
during the day culminating with 500 a.m.
uh shuttles to IHOP the local Pancake
Place uh if you are so awake at that
point or even if you get there uh this
is not an uncommon site as you might
recall from week zero and then lastly is
the cs-50 fair which is finally back
after a couple of years now of it not
being on campus and this will be an
opportunity for everyone to present
their final projects to passers by
classmates faculty and staff and really
just Delight in what it is you created
on your Mac your PC your phone in the
cloud or anywhere else and indeed it's
just going to be an opportunity to bring
your laptop to a shared space or your
phone and introduce your project to
passers by such as might appear and
ultimately celebrate what you all uh
accomplished and indeed will you be
handed at the cs50 fair your very own I
took cs50 t-shirt which I dare say I'm
still wearing all of these years later
and so you
to
we'll have that uh ahead of you as well
so for what's on the agenda today we
thought we would not only look back but
look forward but first we wanted to
thank so many of the team members that
have been helping both on stage and off
who've made this course and these
sections and so much more about cs50
possible of course um the building that
we are now in there's a whole team
downstairs in Memorial Hall who helps us
get set up and organized each day our
thanks to them there's the education
Support Services team who makes
everything look and sound so well down
here especially when we have all of the
more microphones as well our friends the
harbard crocodillos and the redcliff
pitches most recently and then of course
cs50's own team uh but butter cs50's own
favorite restaurant Chang show down the
road indeed if you find yourself in
Cambridge for the next one two 3 four
years or visiting from out of town uh do
pay a visit to our friends just down the
road and in fact we'll have our very
last cs50 lunch this Friday if you're
able locally to partake and then there
cs50's own team um both on stage and off
in thanks truly because not only do they
make the everything run so smoothly they
capture it for students here who might
not be physically present here for our
friends down in New Haven at Yale and
certainly for anyone online who might be
tuning in as well and then lastly wanted
to thank of course the huge team of your
classmates your peers that make cs50
possible in sections and office hours
tutorials and more allow me to share
with you the outtakes so that even we
the teaching staff sometimes struggle
with computer science here are some of
the clips that we captured when just
passing packets via tcpip a while back
you saw the finally the the nicely
polished version but here are if I may
if we could dim the lights are some of
the
outakes nothing
go buffering
okay Josh
nice
[Music]
Helen no oh wait
that was amazing
Josh uh um
[Music]
Sophie
amazing that was
perfect
B I think
I what
you oh nice
[Music]
guy that was amazing thank you all so
good indeed and that moment if we could
just one round of applause for everyone
who's helped out this
semester so back in week zero uh we
introduced you of course to this idea of
computational thinking which is to think
a a little more methodically a little
more algorithmically and by way of these
various languages hopefully that is
something you notice maybe not in the
moment but in the months and the years
to come that you do find that your
thoughts are indeed a little more
cleaned up and you're just able to
express yourself a little more precisely
and even spot illogic in someone else's
document or statements as well but at
the end of the day really a course like
this is also about critical thinking and
indeed rewind again to week zero when we
frame the entirety of computer science
is really just this like problem solving
and any problem in the world be it CS or
otherwise has some input and we decided
how to represent those inputs it needs
some output the solution there too and
then all of what you focused on doing
and learning and applying these past
several weeks is in that proverbial
black box which hopefully is not such an
abstraction anymore but is indeed
something that you know how to harness
and know what could be going on
underneath the hood even if it's in some
technology or some language that maybe
we ourselves didn't cover because a lot
of those first principles remain the
same now along the way we talked about
the quality of solutions to those
problems we happen to focus on
correctness just does it work design
which is a bit more qualitative and
subjective and then style the Aesthetics
of it all and these two are
characteristic maybe not with these same
words of just how you might write or
evaluate other creations in life be it
physical or written or the like so think
about too as you solve problems just how
you can sort of frame for yourself like
am I doing a good job or not by
quantizing it along these or perhaps
other axes as well and we thought we'd
highlight just two topics from that week
zero that have really been manifest for
the past several weeks namely
abstraction like taking complicated
things and ideas and trying to simplify
them so that we can sort of operate at
this level and like solve problems we
care about without getting into the
weeds of implementation detail so to
speak but there's this tension because
you know now from all of these different
languages that code is fairly
unforgiving I mean even omitting a
stupid semicolon sometimes breaks
everything and so Precision is sort of
at odd sometimes with this idea of
leveraging abstraction and so we thought
we would try to tease this apart
especially all these Weeks Later here uh
with a bit of a uh live demonstration so
on the way in you probably all received
a sheet of paper if not but someone near
you did just tear theirs in half and
borrow half a sheet if you can or any
piece of loose leaf paper or the like
will suffice so long as you have a pen
or pencil and for this allow me to
propose that we invite up maybe two
final cs50 volunteers this semester and
like a lot of hands are going up in this
okay a lot of hands how about I saw the
first hand there uh yes yes who's yes
who's pointing at herself now come on
down we just need the one hand for now
but oh wait oh wait uh you'll be our
number two well okay we have way too
many volunteers now no no please please
come down yes in the black shirt and if
you guys we will okay we'll do pair
programming in just a bit if you want to
hang out in the wings here we'll have
our second demonstration as well so okay
now maybe a round of applause for our
three
volunteers oh come on up first oh second
and third okay you come first we'll do
order no uh this is a q okay Q here okay
what's your name I'm Danny Danny okay
take this mic okay so we will DQ you
momentarily all right so Danny come on
over to the middle here and in a moment
I'm going to hand to Danny a sheet of
paper that has a picture on it and this
picture is going to be something that
I'd like you to verbally program the
audience to draw you can use any words
any abstractions any PR level of
precision that you want but you just
can't make hand gestures or sort of show
them what to draw But first you want to
tell us a little something about
yourself including everyone here I'm
daddy and I took ts50 okay wonderful
wonderful so I'm going to reveal the
picture only to Danny and if each of you
would like to take out that sheet of
paper and just make sure that no one
else can see this if you want to hold it
up this way everyone here is now holding
their pen or pencil and in some number
of steps give them a verbal algorithm
for drawing what you see and you can say
anything you want but no gestures okay
so you're going to want to
draw a square in the center of the paper
with the
diagonal pointing to
the center of the
edge wait no actually I scratched that
draw a rbus in the center of your
paper and for those who forget what a
rhombus is for um a d
Diamond a a square that's on its
side and then from the bottom vertex
draw a straight line down but not all
the way to the edge of the
paper okay and then keep your pencil or
pen at that point and you're going to
want to draw a line that's parallel to
the line of the original rumus to the
right and then keep your pencil or pen
at that point and draw a line straight
up connecting to the side
vertex yes and then go back to the line
that you drew from the bottom vertex to
the bottom of the paper and then draw a
line parallel to the left edge of the
rumus and then then keep your L your
paper your pencil at that point and draw
a line up to the vertex of the rumus
again the end the end all right well
thank you to Danny hang on to your paper
thank you so much and if you want to
step off to the stage there we will
reveal thank you a round of applause if
we could for Danny that is not an easy
task I'm sure and if Carter wouldn't
mind just grabbing a few samples here
let's actually take a look on the
overhead if we could I'm going to pop
down over here real fast we don't need
to collect them all but if you're
feeling either good or bad with what you
drew happy to collect a few of them
okay okay thank you thank
you okay hope you won't mind if I can't
reach everyone just a couple more okay
over here okay all right that's that's
okay this one's really funny okay I'm
going to go with this one if I may and
Carter has some
too
okay thank you so much okay so just a
random assortment here let me turn on a
camera so I can show you what I see here
for instance is one classmate drawing
which might resemble perhaps what you
drew here uh here is the beginnings of a
house it
seems nice this
one okay this one is larger
and how about a couple of others that
were getting closer I think okay so more
edges and vertices there this one seems
a little similar in
spirit if not
proportional this is uh Zach's the best
one but it turns out if I may Zach
you're not all that far off here Denny
is what you were reciting to everyone
algorithmically indeed it was this here
Cube and so Danny can you come on back
up for a
moment so if you'd like to share for
just a moment like what were some of the
thoughts going through your head and why
did you choose the words that you did
okay so what was going through my head
when I saw the cube um I didn't know if
I could say draw Cube so I decided to
start with the top and so draw a Remus
in the center of your paper and then
draw a line down and just like do the
first part then the second part then the
third part and then you would get a cube
like Zach yeah and so had you said and
you could have said draw a cube which
would be more of an abstraction even
that's not necessarily sufficiently
precise right because you don't
necessarily know what the orientation of
that cube is the size of it the
positioning on the paper so you instead
took a lower level approach which is not
unlike scratch if you think about
scratch being able to move up down left
right turn 90 degrees turn 15 degrees
and the like I mean that is ultimately
how a lot of graphical programs and
games even might be implemented by
really focusing at the level you do but
of course there's this tension with us
humans whereby we prefer often to think
at this level but even that might not be
sufficient which is to say here in week
10 like these are still going to be in
our hard problems uh but a hand if we
could one more time for Danny for
getting us that far along thank you so
much let me give you a stress ball here
all right and if we could have both of
our volunteers come up here we're going
to have yes come on up come on up and
let me uh have you guys introduce
yourselves in the middle
here hi I'm
hey there I'm sadik from Turkey nice to
meet you all wonderful welcome and this
time we're going to flip it around so as
to have the audience do what Danny just
did for us the only catch here is that
the only means we have for showing the
audience what they need to tell you to
draw is like literally right above the
chalkboard so on our system here that
your eyes must stay on the chalkboard
and not look up and in just a moment if
you guys want to both stand in front of
the chalkboard back to the audience and
as you're talking with each other other
verbalize it through the microphone if
you will I'm going to show everyone else
in the room a second and final drawing
and we'll just go rapid fire around the
room give us one step at a time
collectively and we'll see if these guys
can't draw exactly that same outcome so
is there another chunk what's that is
there another chunk or just just the one
so you'll have to collaborate and let's
give you a clean slate here
literally all right so no looking up
that's the only rule for you guys here
we go for the audience here is what we'd
like them ironically to
draw step one from anyone in the
audience yes draw a circle draw a circle
anywhere not anywhere not
anywhere okay that's step one step two
someone else yeah in the
middle
draw a line down from the bottom of the
circle about halfway down I think there
was a hand in front of you too number
three
[Music]
okay okay the overarching goal here for
those unable here is to draw a person
fig okay it may be a SI figure draw the
left leg of the person of this person
okay good job all right next step four
yeah
of line up Circle
okay the left oh sorry to the right draw
a v okay to the right of the vertex at
the bottom of the circle draw a v draw a
v um like what V nope not interactive
draw a v um no no
well yeah it seems Weir
weird let's get ready for maybe
something like step
five okay we'll go with that step five
someone else step five someone else
someone else
yeah draw the right side of the leg okay
nice step six step six happy face six
six yes erase the line
erase the line that you have on the left
on the
okay okay step seven yes instead of like
that line that was before going up make
it go down instead of that line before
going up make it go down mhm okay step
eight step eight step eight yes connect
that line to the hip connect that line
to the hip not like not touching not
touching something like this
maybe okay compromise not touching okay
not touching okay all right step nine
almost there I think step
nine step nine step nine yes in
back uh write the word high on the top
left of the circle
here okay
and step 10 almost there line draw a
line pointing to high so like a spee
bubble basically
yeah okay and step uh 10
yeah erase the exclamation point nice 12
do we want to give them one
more 12 or we good yeah last one erase
the erase erace the right arm okay I
think we're going to need a 13
then and
then yeah
repat repeat the left arm but rotate it
by
90 that feels
wrong wait how would you like as an
organic human being how put your
arms like would you put your would you
ever structure your arm like that that
would not be a stick
figure CU would you do this or would you
do that or a little hint maybe get a get
a give me a step 14 step 14 and final
step
14 I think we just got to tell them what
to do step 14
yes think of a walking man
and and have the left the right hand
walking to your right all right so like
it's like where could the hand go where
should the hand go on that
arm but yeah yeah okay yes
no yeah I mean look look look like right
here look right here look right I yes
sorry thank you 14
St that's pretty close so
congratulations to you guys and thank
you as well all right so I mean these
these things too are not yes Round of
Applause then sure
so so this is to say that these ideas of
abstraction and precision and really
every other term of art that we explored
this term are sort of omnipresent and
can be easier or harder to implement
depending on exactly what the problem is
but what we thought we' do now in our uh
final day is try to now similarly
prepare prepare you for life after cs50
and this is really going to be a list of
really potential to-dos so that you can
stand on your own after the class after
the class's infrastructure write actual
code and then we'll come full circle one
final time with our friend Jennifer 8
Lee to look at the world of emojis and
how they relate to all forms of
representation that we've talked to uh
talked about up until now so one how can
you go about programming after cs50 so
one you can actually install command
line tools on your own Mac or PC perhaps
unbeknownst to you Windows has what's
generally called a command prompt Mac OS
literally comes with a terminal program
in your applications utilities folder
and so even if you've never run those
programs you've actually had a sort of
blinking cursor black and white prompt
available to you might not have all of
the same software installed as your code
space in the cloud but you have that
command line interface even within
today's graphical tools and among the
tools you can install within that
command line interface would be
something called xcode on the Mac which
comes not only with a guey IDE
integrated development environment but
also those command line tools and
Microsoft for Windows has something
similar as well learning git so we've
used git only unbeknownst to you
underneath the hood for the most part
but git is a very very popular tool if
challenging to pick up for the first
time that makes it easy to push code to
a website called GitHub or any
equivalent and then collaborate more
effectively with classmates there's
definitely a bit of a learning curve but
thanks to cs50's own Brian youu you can
start for instance with a video like
this and this indeed is going to be one
of these deao standards in the real
world at least for the next several
years that you'll probably encounter if
you work in Tech or really any company
where you're doing some programming vs
code itself will walk you through this
process in the coming days but you can
indeed install it on your own Mac or PC
and what can you do when you write code
well you can certainly write software
for your Mac for your PC for your phone
or of course per week 10 uh week nine
you can host uh your own website be it
static as in week uh week eight um
hosting it at websites like these which
gener generally have free or
student-friendly accounts via which you
can put something statically on the web
at a real domain name that you might
choose or you can host a full-fledged
web app and using uh student tiers on
Amazon and Microsoft and Google's cloud
services or others you can sign up for
being a student certainly a whole lot of
free software free hosting so as to if
nothing else um experiment and uh
perhaps maximally get your own app or
website up and running so know that
those are resources available to you and
this is by uh certainly a non-exhaustive
list if you'd like to geek out in the
coming months in the coming years these
are just some of the places that people
who take computer science classes who
write code might tend to hang out and
ask and answer questions of each other
um so keep an eye for instance on these
here and then cs50 has its own
communities as you'll see if you go to
this URL here via the open coreware
version of cs50 which is open to the
world do uh is there a Vibrant Community
uh thanks to time zones that's pretty
much active 247 365 talking about not
only cs50 going on in problem sets and
projects but really technology more
generally as well so certainly feel
welcome to partake either asking or
answering questions now in speaking of
asking and answering questions a couple
of weeks ago you kindly gave us a whole
bunch of review questions which we
called through and picked out our
favorite 20 of them these of course were
multiple choice questions and in
preparation for this week uh in
preparation for life ahead we thought we
would choreograph a bit of a a quiz show
here and ceed as you came in at the
start of class you might recall being
invited to go to this URL here
cs50. either here in person or if you're
watching live from home at this URL here
you can use a phone or a laptop and if
it's easier on a phone you can point
your camera at this 2D barcode here
we'll give folks a moment to pull that
up and again that URL was cs50.
l/p
and once it looks like most folks have
it up and running our friend Carter here
will help us dive into this uh review
session if you will with a bit of fun
along the way all right Carter if you'd
like to take it away what do we have as
our first question you should see on
your phone or laptop this same question
being asked the first question is how do
you print quote un quote hello world in
Python so among the possible answers are
these here
buzz in on your phone or your
laptop we've got a few hundred responses
are
ready 7 Seconds to make your
decision this is question one of 20 go
to it with some confidence I think we're
down to zero on the clock and Carter it
looks like 98% of you uh indeed said
hello world and Carter per the check
mark That's indeed the correct answer
here now to make things interesting in
know that you'll see some number of
points and we've deliberately anonymized
it so only you know what number you are
so a whole lot of guests have a perfect
score of 1,000 at the moment hopefully
we'll see over the next several
questions things start to bridge out uh
but know that the speed with which you
buzz in will also factor into how many
points you now get So the faster you
move the more points you get question
two if we could what does DNS stand for
from just a couple of weeks back domain
number system domain name system data
numbering structure or there's no such
thing as
DNS few hundred responses are
in 8 seconds
remain fewer points now but still a
chance to buzz in and now as we hit zero
the responses are these domain name
system which is indeed correct and 84%
of you got that one correctly and indeed
exists we talked about it a couple of
weeks ago so we're still seeing a whole
lot lot of ties at 2,000 we'll see if
someone starts to pull away before long
question three what is the upper bound
of merge sorts
runtime so that escalated
quickly Big O of n log n Big O of log n
Theta or Omega of log n or Big O of
one what is the upper bound of merge
sorts
runtime that was the last of the
algorithms we solve for sorting and in 1
second we'll see that the correct answer
is is just edging out everyone else
indeed 46% it is n I know it's n log now
if I may as the teacher it can't be
login because login is strictly less
than n and you can't possibly sort n
elements unless you minimally look at or
touch each of them so it's got to be at
least greater than n intuitively we
still have a whole bunch of ties let's
move on to number four what is stored in
ARG
C back to the language C is it in Array
of arguments the maximum size of an
array the count of arguments given to a
program when first run or how much
memory is allocated to a
function again you wrote all of these
questions and we have 5 seconds for the
reveal ARG C
is indeed the count of arguments given
to a program when first run think back
to C when we did command line arguments
there was argc and arv argv was the
array but Arc was indeed the count the
CN AR save all right we still have a
whole bunch of ties at the top here but
let's move on then to number five what
is the duck debugger favorite hobby
according to one of your classmates
dressing up like Dracula swimming across
the stage filling up the entire bathroom
of a guy's house and sitting quietly on
stage the third of course is a reference
to a YouTube video that was on the
course's website that week but according
to your class mate number two seconds
remaining sitting quietly on stage is
its favorite pastime so a little harder
perhaps than the
others 5,000 now we're starting to see
some spread so we only have six six
guests in contention for first place and
the next question now is six what is the
function used to open a file in
C F open open file open
file
what is the function used to open a file
in
C 7
Seconds there's some differences between
C and python here and the reveal it is
indeed fop it's 77% correct too all
right let's see the rankings now if you
are guest 15 9715 6171 3753 or 3273
you're now in the lead as we move on on
to se question seven how does Sterling
compute the average sorry how does
Sterling compute the length of a string
in C it looks at how much memory the
string uses it counts the number of
characters until it reaches back0 it
counts the number of bits in the string
or it creates pointers for each
character and counts
them 10 seconds Sterling in
C recall that we implemented this
ourselves in class but then we used the
library thereafter and in indeed with
85% it simply counts the number of
characters until it reaches that
Sentinel back sl0 AKA null and in this
case we
have five four four of you tied now for
first all right question eight where
does Malo allocate memory
from the stack the Heap the pointers or
the
temp where does malok allocate memory
from responses are coming in 8
seconds a good review question at that
in two seconds we'll see that malok
allocates memory from woo close one the
Heap is correct the Heap is correct the
stack recall is where functions store
their local variables and their
arguments and that just happens
automatically the Heap represented in
our pictures up top is where malok draws
from now we have guest
15 has
made its way to the top here but others
can catch up if they don't buzz in fast
enough so number nine how many people
flew from 50v to New York on the day of
the
crime 16 29 8 or
three anyone with a laptop perhaps has
an advantage
here 5 Seconds
and the answers are but the answer is
16 let's see if guest 15 got
this they did not goodbye to guest 15 at
the top all right question 10 we're
about halfway there what are meta tags
used for in
HTML to describe a web page to Define
parameters for an element to group
elements together to translate content
into machine readable format
at what are meta tags used for in HTML
we saw a few of
them for different use
cases and with one second we see that
indeed the number one answer was to
describe the web page be it for a mobile
device be it for screen scrapers like
Facebook and Twitter and other such apps
that grab images and descriptions
thereof all right we're in the second
half now guest nine guest four 669 has
edged ahead guess 15 is now in sixth
place all right number 11 is how do you
find the address of a variable in C
think back a few weeks star dollar sign
Ampersand or
ask from one of your own classmates how
do you find the address of a variable in
C and the number one answer is ersan
which is indeed the address of operator
at 62% nicely done let's see who's the
top of the list now guess 4669 has
retained their lead so we move on to 12
what does the arrow operator mean in C a
hyphen and a greater than sign nothing
starts a comment replaces a star and Dot
operator declares a
pointer what does this Arrow operator
mean in
C
again from a few weeks back 3 seconds
harder assortment perhaps and it's oh
replaces a star and Dot operator the
number two answer was indeed correct
this was just a cleaner way syntactic
sugar for collapsing what would be a
star and then some parentheses and then
a DOT into quite simply something that
looks like an arrow itself all right
Carter who's in the lead now still that
same guest and let's see what 13 has for
us which of these is not a data type in
SQL light blob string integer
text we used a few of these more
commonly than others but not all of
these are for
real 5 Seconds to make your
decision and the results are blob is a
thing string is not in SQL light it's of
course called text as we've seen it blob
as goofy as it sounds is just binary
large object but indeed it's how you
might store a binary file in your
database all right the rankings now oh
guest 8444 has Eed ahead so we move on
to 14 which of the following is a valid
way to print Exclamation point
Exclamation point Exclamation point
Exclamation point in
Python I'll let you read these
yourselves
which is a valid
way everyone got quiet in is
thinking all right 6 seconds few hundred
responses in so
far all right and yes nicely done 78% is
correct you can use the star operator to
essentially multiply the character at
left all right who's in the lead Carter
we now have still G guest
8444 and so we move on now to 15 what
does the free function do D allocates
memory from A Primitive deallocates
memory at the given pointer terminates a
loop or returns a value from the
function what does the free function
do all right 5 Seconds what does the
free function do call it's the opposite
essentially of malok and it deallocates
the memory at the given pointer as well
and in C that's on you in Python you
don't need to worry about allocating or
freeing aik all right we now have at the
top still guest 8444 and seeing more and
more spread 16 which is not a step of
compiling think back now to week two
compiling pre-processing linking or
threading which is not a step of
compiling we use it as a catchall but it
technically means a few different things
collectively all right and threading is
indeed not on the list that is a
technical thing generally meaning a
program can do multiple things at once
but that is not related here to
compiling all right guest 8444 is still
at the top we have just a few questions
left and so 17 what was the surprise at
the beginning of the Halloween lecture
according to your classmates someone
scared me someone hid candy under every
chair someone dressed up as me the
entire staff dressed up as
Carter interesting litmus test of who
came to or watch lecture
perhaps let's see which guests got this
correct someone someone's really dressed
up as indeed me at 64% so I think we
have attendance here essentially from
that lecture so let's move on now to the
final few questions after seeing that
guest a 8444 8444 is still doing well
can anyone Dethrone them why is it
incorrect to use the equals equals
operator in C to compare
strings it's computationally inefficient
you comparing the locations of the
strings strings don't exist using equal
equals will lead to buffer
overflow why is it incorrect to use
equal equals in C to compare strings 3
seconds we saw this live and it
motivated like an entire week because
you're comparing the locations that is
the addresses in memory of those same
strings all right let's see if this
leaves the rankings the same guest 8444
is still at the top and pulling ahead
two final questions 19 what is the
difference between null one L and null 2
L's they null and null mean the same
thing nulls refers to back sl0 whereas
null to L's is the zero address null is
the zero address whereas null to L's
refers to back sl0 null is null but
lazier 5
Seconds subtle not the best design
perhaps to have in technical terms but
indeed 62% of you got that NL is the
first thing we talked about when we
talked about back sl0 and N is a pointer
it's the zero pointer same thing same
number but different context all right
Carter guest 8444 is the person to beat
with our final 20th questions what do
the binary bulbs on stage spell
today and these are your four choices
different from usual we usually use 8
bit asky today we are using utf8 which
is a form of Unicode which is the larger
subset that uses one or two or three or
even four bites to spell a single
character and the answer wow close close
is indeed a cupcake indeed a cupcake
well done and let's see the final
results 8444 is the winner are they here
in person perhaps
8444 you're 844 come on
[Applause]
down thank you here you go
congratulations oh you're all right so
today if we
may give me just one
moment all
right all right so today we are so
pleased to be joined by uh Jennifer 8
Lee who's an of the college a dear
friend and is actually really the reason
why there's evidence of Muppets in cs50
in fact some years ago I was visiting
her and she had on her shelf like this
custom Muppet it wasn't one that appears
on TV but she had somehow gone on a
website former toy store called FAO
Schwarz at the time and you're allowed
to configure your own Muppet whatnot
choose the eyes the nose the face and
the Torso and I just thought this was
the coolest thing and so in the taxi on
the way home I was like going on the
website trying to purchase our very
first Muppet I then woke up the next
morning thinking why did I just buy a
puppet in the back of a taxi and so it
sat on the shelf for really 2 years and
then a colleague of mine within cs50's
team decided after I brought it into the
office to sit on a shelf there to
actually bring it to life and indeed if
you Google around cs50 Muppet and
puppetry online you'll see in fact these
as characters not only over the past
couple of years in coid times when
really there was next to no one actually
here and so they were instead um but
indeed she's brought not only this this
educational element this pedagogical
element this playful element El to cs50
and we have her here today to speak to
exactly the sorts of encodings that are
here on stage Jenny is the former Vice
chair of the Unicode subcommittee on
emoji which is to say that she and her
colleagues have been influential in
taking emoji from what was a very
limited character set early on and by
far unrepresentative of much uh human
emotion in speech into really an
initiative now to capture digitally all
of the world's languages past present
and future as well as the range of
emotions that might see here in the form
of that pillow or even in the cake that
awaits so allow me to introduce Jennifer
8 Lee thank
[Music]
you I much drink okay clicker hi all
right hold on I have to hide my drinks I
might need more water all right um I'm
really excited to speak to speak here
last time last year I was here uh one I
was wearing a mask which is like a real
bummer if you're lecturing and then the
entire like front part was all Muppet so
I'm really happy to see humans actually
um and it's always an honor to speak at
Sanders and and then Dave and I were
actually classmates way back when so I
do remember him when he was an undergrad
much like you so I um I'm going to give
a talk on the world of emoji and how I
kind of became an emoji activist so it
kind of all starts um with my friend e
inl who is a designer who's well known
for doing the Twitter fail whale which
was kind of laid to rest except now this
week it seems like it may be like may be
necessary again um so she and I one day
were texting this is back in 2015 we're
texting about dumplings because we are
Chinese is women and we like like to
text about food and so I sent her this
picture of dumplings she was like yum
yum yum yum yum yum yum yum um and then
she was like oh Apple doesn't have a
dumpling emoji and I was like oh that's
kind of interesting and didn't really
think anything about it because like you
know people Point things out to you all
the time and then you just like forget
you just like move on but then half an
hour later um on my phone appears this
like dumpling with hard eyes and you
don't see it in in because it's a still
shot but it actually had like blinking
eyes so she liked to call it like bling
bling dumpling so she as a designer had
decided to like go in and like make her
own dumpling Emoji um because she was
like I'm a designer I can fix it but
that actually got me thinking I was like
where do Emoji come from and like how is
there not a dumpling Emoji cuz from my
perspective dumplings are this kind of
universal food right so and there are a
lot of Japanese Foods
on the emoji keyboard and I I was not
this was like back in 2015 I was like
not a big Emoji user like at all so I
mean you have things like Ramen you have
Bento boxes you have Curry you have
tempura you even have like kind of
obscure um kind of foods like this thing
things on a stick turns out to be fish
fish things on a stick then this pink
and white white swirly thing is also a
fish thing and there's even like that
triangle rice ball that looks like it's
had a bikini wax all well represented on
the Emoji Keyboard but no dumplings and
it's very strange cuz like all cultures
kind of have their dumpling right
whether or not it's um kinali or ravioli
or aanas like essentially everyone sort
of like discover the idea of like um
yummy goodness inside a carbo hydrate
carbohydrate shell whether not baked or
fried or um steamed so I was like okay I
literally Google I was like who controls
emoji and you discover that they're
actually regulated by a nonprofit called
the Unicode Consortium and um it is you
know and I just like went on their
website and I discovered that they had
12 full voting members as of 2015 so
this is 2015 and they were like mostly
us multinational tech companies it was
Oracle it was IBM Microsoft Adobe Google
Apple Facebook and Yahoo and of the
three that were not multinational US
tech companies they were let's see a
German company called sap a Chinese
Telecom company called Huawei and then
like the government of Oman like those
were basically the 12 full voting
members of the US multi-national tech
companies so they at that point paid um
$118,000 a year to have full voting
power on the you know Unicode committee
and I was like oh that's a that's a lot
of money and I kind of felt indignant
about this and uh but then like if you
kind of keep on digging on their website
you found like there was this kind of
interesting loophole which is you could
join as an individual for
$75 um you don't get voting power but it
gave you the right to put yourself on
the email list and also to like attend
the quarterly Unicode meeting so I was
like I'll do that I had no idea what I
was doing but I'm like I'm going to go
fight um for this dumpling Emoji because
from my perspective dumplings are
Universal Emoji are kind of universal so
uh the fact there was no dumpling Emoji
meant like something was wrong in the
universe and I was I was determined to
fix this so um you know I was on this
email list and then a couple of like
maybe even like a couple weeks later I
got you know they they they kind of sent
out this note that's like hey who's
coming to the quarterly meeting and I
was like um I looked at the calendar I
looked at my schedule I was like oh I'll
be in like you know Silicon Valley that
time so I basically like rsvpd and I was
like I will be there and took um cow
train to an Apple building it's a legal
building in I think it was sunny Veil so
I just like show up and I don't know
what I was sort of expecting like with
like you know the Unicode I think maybe
thought it was going to be like a baby
Congress like you know like with a
little you know very formal seats people
with gabbles um that is not what I found
uh basically it is a it was a conference
room full of people who skewed wider
skewed older skewed Mal skewed engineers
and this is basically the room where it
happen so this is 2015 these were the
people who decided your Emoji um all
very nice and um there was you know one
one even had a daughter who had a sense
of humor and made him a shirt that said
shadowy Emoji Overlord um so I just kind
of listen to them debate things like
milk emoji and beans emoji and it just
seemed like not quite right to me that
like it would be uh This Global visual
language that were basically decided
decided by like a a small group of
people inside a conference room in
Silicon Valley so I decided to former
group called Emoji nation whose motto is
like Emoji by the people for the people
and it basically advocates for more kind
of Representative inclusive Emoji um you
know we we we we start with a
Kickstarter campaign uh dumpling Emoji
process trying to like you know write
the wrong in this world and uh made this
little cute video sort of advocating
dink for one of the most universal
crosscultural Foods in the world Georgia
has Kali Japan has giosa Korea has Mandu
Italy has ravioli Poland has barog
Russia has pelman Argentina has
empanadas Jewish people have kler China
has pot stickers Nepal and Tibet have
Momos yet somehow despite their
popularity there is no dumpling Emoji in
the standard set why is that emoji
exists for pizza tempora Sushi spaghetti
hot dog and now tacos which Taco Bell
takes credit for we need to write this
disparity dumplings are Global Emoji a
global isn't it time we brought them
together
oh yeah and while we're at it how about
an emoji for Chinese
takeout so uh I did put together a
dumpling Emoji proposal I wrote this uh
I remember Thanksgiving Day 2015 on a
plane and uh actually and we got it past
basically dumpling takeout box
Chopsticks and uh fortune cookie I have
to say I don't think fortune cookie
would have made it on its own merits but
it kind of like slid in on the clo tails
of the other ones um and so these were
the proposals as we submitted them and
then these are the ones that kind of uh
exist now on the Apple keyboard and I
have to say the dumpling looks really
really realistic um oddly realistic and
whereas like the fortune cookie is think
it's like a big fail because first of
all there's like it has no it has no Gap
it looks like a dead 3D Pac-Man so I'm
very
disappointed in uh the manifestation of
that but that's okay that's okay um and
so it's kind of interesting like what is
the process of getting an emoji um ped
and I will sort of walk you through it
so first of all you come up with your
idea right and then you kind of write
this proposal and then you submit it to
the Unicode Emoji subcommittee who then
kind of gives you comments and then
sends it back to you and you kind of go
around and around in the circle um and
when so these are things that we
consider so somewhere in there I also
like fought my way on to the Emoji
committee and then also became a vice
chair became a vice chair sort of a
extracurricular that's like completely
run a muck in my life um um so things
that matter uh popular demand is a
frequently requested Emoji um multiple
usages usages and meaning so that's
actually kind of very important for
something like you know certain animals
have meaning so we did you know sloth a
while ago and that also has not only the
literal meaning but sort of like um like
um connotations there are visually
distinctiveness it can be recognized so
this was a blocker for one of the uh
emojis that I have worked on before
which is cave which is kind of hard to
do I think you know meaning wise is
pretty good but it's really hard to get
a cave down in emoji sizes and then it
filling a gap completeness so a good
example for that is like for some reason
for many years we had Red Heart yellow
heart green heart blue heart purple
heart and uh no orange heart so so
somewhat so you know you would do the
rainbow but people would substitute the
pumpkin in so You' like you know have a
have a rainbow heart thing with a little
pumpkin stuck in the middle so orange
heart obviously should be added and give
a sense of completeness um and then
something else is existing vendor cap
cap compatibility and so a good example
for that was um many years ago what's
app decided to uh add the gender
non-binary emoji and then once it did
that then all the other kind of vendors
um jumped on um so what kind of knocks
out an emoji so too specific or narrow
so we'll often see that with like very
specific animals or a very specific
group it's redundant so one
year oh my God who makes that Butterball
Butterball makes the turkeys Butterball
submitted um a an emoji proposal that
was like a cooked turkey but we already
had a live turkey so it seem kind of
redundant have both like a cooked turkey
for Thanksgiving and a live turkey so so
not visually discernible um this is a
struggle for things like I don't my
friends have kind of proposed
kimchi kimchi is is really hard on emoji
sizes for many reasons and part of that
but part of that tension is because it's
not visually discernable then there are
no logos Brands deities or celebrities
so no Nike swish no McDonald's M and
then this is one that we kind of decided
in the last uh year or so which is no
more flags flags are a very complicated
thing um and as a result Unico does not
want to be in the business of deciding
what is a country or not a country uh so
like you know when you get a proposal
from like Kurdistan you're like yeah so
right now the way that the Emoji flags
are decided is they kind of depend on
what the UN recognizes and then those
get passed down to the international
standards organization and then and then
Uno just does that like it does not want
to be in the business of kind of you
know geopolitical
Affairs um so once it comes out of the
subcommittee it goes to the full Unicode
technical committee UTC those were the
people that were in the room that I
showed you um and they vote once a year
basically to pass all the Emoji and
takes a while there's a lot of like
coordinating with the international
standards organization and like a lot of
working with the companies and
eventually it takes a long time but it
ends up on your on your devices and that
historically is taken about 18 to 24
months from when you put in the propose
to when you get it in it's going to be a
little bit longer um going forward
probably is my sense as we were're going
to Unicode has decided to sort of space
out some of the Unicode releases so yeah
Emoji Nation you know kind of has done
its thing so of the weird things is like
how did Unicode this like kind of
nonprofit organization based in Mountain
View California end up controlling this
like Global visual language um so a lot
of it has to start with has has to do
with the fact that emoji started in
Japan uh back in the late 1990s one of
the this set from dok 1999 is considered
is widely considered sort of like the
first like color Emoji set it has been
collected by the Museum of Modern Art
and um so these the Japanese telecom
companies would use
basically would have their own sets of
emoji and then they were different
companies so they would have different
sets so you could basically only send
these like visual characters with
someone who is on your same carrier so
it's like it's like basically equivalent
of if you were on like Verizon you can
only text people on Verizon with like
Emoji or if you were on um T-Mobile you
could only do that so at a certain point
they um decided they were they the Apple
and Google came into Japan they wanted
to start selling smartphones and they
realized that it was a hodgepodge of
systems and they wanted to unify it and
so in 2007 they went to unic code and
they're like okay help us unify the
Emoji um like kind of like basically all
the Emojis so that we have one standard
system and part of the reason is why
Unicode because Unicode basically has
this mission is to enable everyone
speaking every language on Earth to be
able to use your languages on computer
and smartphone so it basically unifies
um all written languages into one
ginormous set and that was not the case
actually when I was uh growing up there
was a point where like if you you were
Japanese on Apple that would be
different than Japanese on um dos or
like Chinese or Arabic so it drove
everyone crazy and they basically
decided um around the late 80s early
1990s that they were going to come up
with one standardized system that sort
of encoded all characters in in one
ginormous set so um there's three main
projects for Unicode if you care so one
is encoding characters including Emoji
now they're about 100,000 characters
aside assigned so that includes like
like Chinese Japanese Korean uh Arabic
cilic um actually all the hieroglyphics
all of the Emoji um a lot of things like
the Bitcoin symbol or like copy left or
whatever those all assigned were about
100,000 uh characters even those
languages that are basically out of use
so the other thing it does it creates
um localization resources so things
things so that you know like oh if
you're in this country this is this is
uh you're using the Euro or you're using
the pesos or something so there's a lot
of localization that is that data that
is needed depending on which um
geography you're using your device from
or like that you know you you know that
the time is used this way or the dates
are shown that way so that is called um
the common local data repository or cldr
as they call it and the other thing they
do is they kind of maintain libraries
for developers in order to do all um to
kind of so they are not building
everything from scratch and that is
called ICU so it's very funny cuz like
it's called cldr and then one day one of
our friends girlfriends made him this
thing which she called a seal deer
because whenever he talked about
cldr he thought he thought she thought
he was talking about seal deers so now
this is his little like mascot for like
Unicode related things so what is um how
does Unicode do this so it basically
asss code points and each code point is
a unique number assigned to each Unicode
character so uh face with tears of joy
can be written like this with a code
point or it can be written like this in
terms of decimal numbers and it can also
be written this in binary numbers so
these are all basically the same and the
key thing to know at least about Emoji
is that when your device if you're
talking your iPhone with um someone
who's on a laptop or an iPad or like um
an Android device it's not sending the
images back and forth it's sending just
a number back and forth and then locally
your phone or like your laptop decides
like oh this number correlates with
which image um in terms of our emoji
font and then pulls it up so this is
really key to know why different Emoji
look different on different
platforms so 2007 to 2010 it took about
three years but Unicode 6.0 came out
with a first our first little baby set
of emoji um and it just kind of hung out
there for a year like no one it wasn't
doing anything so 2011 though Apple
starts adding the emoji keyboard and it
it just like explodes like I feel like
in some ways Emoji are were not like
invented they were discovered they like
obviously touch something very very
Primal to um to like our human desire to
like communicate in like little colorful
glyphs on electronic devices and you
kind of have what's kind of really
interesting is like the ambiguity that
comes with what emoji kind of mean and
so one of the you know this one my
favorite emoji is sort of like an upside
down smiley face very very ambiguous
clearly very ambiguous because if you
start typing into Google like the top
hits are like what does it mean from a
guy what does it mean from a girl like
it's clearly something that a lot of
people are are using in like complex
situationships between each other so um
so so one of the fun things is who can
propose Emoji technically anyone can
anyone here can normal normal humans can
we have basically Google doc uh or
Google form that we throw up uh
historically between August sorry April
and August in the last two years um and
uh so this is one of our my our favorite
examples this is Ru aumed she was a
15-year-old Saudi Arabian girl who was
living in Vienna at the time that she
proposed the um hijab emoji and then you
know then she was like Time Magazine
like you know coolest teens she got like
a whole bunch of different things she
got into Harvard and Stanford and she
went to Stanford um and uh so this is a
PR we got then there was a group of
folks from Argentina who got the mate
Emoji kind of they you know similar
their national drink then we worked with
um there was a a nonprofit that really
wanted to like get a menstruation emoji
and so what they proposed to begin with
was like bloody underwear and I was just
like no no no so many different reasons
why this is a terrible Emoji uh but so
we did get blood drops so then you can
do Moon and blood drop or underwear and
blood drop there's a lot of different
ways actually it's really funny cuz I
was ping my friends beforehand what they
would use to indicate menstruation
before there you know there was a blood
drop so there was like red wine there
was like kind of that Rose um with the
like falling petal and then my favorite
is actually um my friend who used a
Japanese flag as a way to indicate that
she was having her
period so um one of the biggest
contributors this uh skin tone Emoji
appeared I think in 2015 it was amazing
it is and it was proposed by a mom
Katrina parrot she is a entrepreneur and
a mom who is just like at home one day
and her daughter comes home and is
like you know I wish there were emoji
that looked like me and her mom was like
that's great honey what's an emoji and
so she like me I guess Googled and just
figured out that uh Unicode controlled
emoji and she just came up with a
proposal saying we should not only have
the yellow you know skin tones at that
time everything was sort of Simpsons
yellow um it's really interesting to see
how race and like nationality are like
depicted in different parts of the world
so originally in Japan everyone was
yellow um but this these were the non
you know by default everyone was just
like like you know human or Japanese but
they had like a couple things that were
like not like one was you had a blonde
person so there's an emoji called like
blonde blonde woman or whatever that
represents all westerners okay so that
was one and then they have one that's
like an Indian guy with a turban so
that's supposed to represent Indian
people and then there's like a like a
guy with a little like um little hat
that's supposed to represent like
Chinese people so that was like that was
the view Japanese view of race which was
like default then you were I then you
were like blonde Western Chinese or
Indian and and that is all there was and
um obviously in the United States we
care a lot about race and then so she
came up with this system with five skin
tones um like just like normal people
some guy in Germany decided that he
wanted to do a a a face with one eyebrow
raised or as we call it the coar Emoji
um and oh this one's fun so woman's flat
shoe I have to say not highly used
statistically at this point but I really
kind of appreciate it because it was a
mom who was very offended that all
women's shoes had heels even the sandals
so this is her she had like three kids
at the time now is four she was very
fertile um and she also did um the women
women's flat okay she also did um um one
piece bathing suit because she was also
um offended by the fact that the only
kind of bathing suit you had was like
this like little itsy-bitsy polka dot
bikini thing which is not great if
you're like taking your six-year-old so
I have to say that got passed but like
it didn't go over like super well with
everyone um so you know unic Cod because
it's very public submits things for
comments and um we got this comment back
so one piece bathing suit why a person
want to indicate the use of swimwear
can't use existing bikini is this really
necessary what about a Victorian bathing
costume or a wet suit or water rings
this is like literally in in like uh the
records and like do not encode um and so
the person who did it's actually very
impressive he's actually the person who
created the middle finger emoji and
actually you ever seen the Vulcan Emoji
he he the Vulcan hand emoji he's
actually very active and I have to say
this is actually I think one of the more
impressive Emoji so so obviously
obviously we have a lot of active debate
um sometimes you get like whole
countries submitting so literally the
government of Finland as in like their
equivalent in the state department their
diplomacy kind of thing uh submitted a
proposal for SAA and um these were so
creepy and so
weird so much is wrong with this and but
I I I felt where they were coming from
first of all like they're naked they
have no they have club feet and so we
decided to help them we're like okay we
see where you're going with this let's
see if we can like help you like come up
you know like we had the spoon like
should there be like steam around them
like should they be naked or wearing a
tow towel it's like super like dicey but
we wanted to help them because it was
like literally a foreign government
coming from an Unicode advocating for
the sauna emoji on behalf of their ENT
country so then this is um is sort of
evolved into just basically person in
stey room which is which is the most
sort of like the PG version of sauna no
and there's no spoon they're all dressed
it's very odd but um so you can see the
evolution of what it started out what we
submitted and what it ended up so
there's a lot of like Evolution
throughout the entire process um and
like companies can submit Emoji
proposals too so Google actually worked
on this one I love this one okay so just
to give you some context as of 2015
there are many ways you could be or have
an occupation as a male on the Emoji
Keyboard right like like for example you
could be a police officer you could be a
detective you could be a Buckingham
Palace guard you could even be Santa
Claus like these are so many jobs that
you could have but if you were a woman
as of 2015 there were four things that
you could be you could be a princess you
could be a bride you could be a dancer
or you could be a Playboy Bunny these
were the sum total of all the
occupations that we can have so so we
there was sort of this movement at that
time there was like this like video on
YouTube that like went viral there was
like a New York Times op that was like
where are the women with professions so
um basically they came up with a set of
emoji for professions and what's nice is
not only did women have these
professions now men have them too so of
emoji Nation Emoji these are some of the
ones that we've worked on I think about
130 of the Emoji on your keyboard
probably came through touched our system
in in some way including I I have to say
uh microbe or virus I think I have the
opinion that every Emoji has its day
right like it might not be like today it
might not be next year but I have to say
virus was not doing anything then came
2020 and that was like such a good
moment for it um along with soap we had
also done soap so um you know among the
other emoji that we have worked on are
sari moon cake llama like uh teddy bear
there were no toys I felt really sad for
toys we have like giraffe um there was
Hut bubble te bubble tea was very
controversial actually I have to say it
kind we tried to slide it in originally
with the um takeout box and the
dumplings and people were not not having
it I understand that CU there's not a
lot like compared to like beer or wine
like bubble tea does not is not long
does not have a long history on this
planet um but I will say that um they
submitted again actually kind of
originally proposing that it was not
just bubble tea but but like a black
ball and milk and tea it was It was kind
of cool and I I have to say there was
definitely a generational divide between
like the Asian women who sit in that
room and are like this absolutely is a
thing that we consume like almost like
every week of our life and people who
are a little bit older who are like that
looks like a parfait how do you not know
that's a parfet and we're like we
absolutely know it is uh not a parfait
and so so it got in eventually so it
does sort of influence it kind of shows
like who is in the room influences you
know the decisions um that get made or
sometimes in the room now sometimes more
more likely in the zoom um I actually I
just say beaver Emoji if you see Beaver
Emoji that's one of one of the ones I'm
most proud of so that is actually
co-authored by a professor here at
Harvard um who is both lesbian and was
married to a woman from Canada so it was
very important to her to get um the
beaver Emoji passed and she promised me
it would always be the first line of her
bio so and indeed if you go to her
Twitter handle uh it's like Joan Donovan
creator of the Beaver Emoji comma is
headed research at the shoren scene
Center at the Harvard Kennedy School
It's Kind it's pretty impressive um and
then we did greens actually greens was
really interesting because people this
was also like a generational cultural
thing people were like why do we need
greens we have salad and I was like
we're Chinese we don't eat raw greens
cuz like you don't know where it's been
or if it's clean so we cook our greens
so salad is not something that we have
So eventually I got my greens and um so
that was kind of fun and then so these
are some of the people who sort of have
contributed to our little Emoji Nation
things including a number of Native
Americans who help get feather so why do
I care so part of it is because I'm
Chinese I grew up speaking Chinese and
English at the same time and it's really
interesting to see like Chinese and
English characters in terms of emoji and
Chinese together right so this is fire
you have like Fire characters and now
you have the Emoji things and it's kind
of It kind of shows that there is a
longevity in The Human Experience of
something that was designed 4,000 years
ago as the same visual cues in the human
experiences as now so mouth Tre tree
Moon Sun you can mix and match them
which is super fun um so you know two
trees kind of make a forest oops sorry
oh well okay then the um Moon and Sun
together means bright which I like um I
like this one so if you stop and you
think about this so this is a basically
a pig under a roof and what does that
mean
it does not mean Farm as you might think
it um it actually means home or family
so in the Chinese kind of structure and
outlook on The View it's like where you
keep your pigs is actually where your
home is and what your farm is um so it
gets kind of weird in all kinds of ways
so one of my favorite radicals so this
character means woman uh KN
and as I was learning Chinese you kind
of notice like how it shows up so so
this is a woman underneath a roof and
you're like oh it means mom or wife or
or like whatever like home um it does
not it means peace because things are at
home when the woman is or things are at
peace when the woman is at home
underneath a roof which I always thought
was a little bit odd um then there is
also uh woman plus child so you're like
oh and actually specifically Boy Child
the connotation there is a little
unclear so you're like a woman plus
child family mom you know whatever um it
is not it means good so the standard for
goodness in ancient China was a woman
who had a male child child so that kind
of kind of just like kind of irked me um
growing up and then you know three women
together means evil which is like very
like
MCB this character means greed this
character means slave this marriage
let's see I think this one is jealousy
and this means means adultery or
betrayal so like definitely not loving
the way women were P you know portrayed
um on the emoji keyboard so uh in case
you're wondering we just came out with a
kids book called had emoji that kind of
Compares emoji and uh Chinese and I
think I I think they sent a bunch of
books so that you guys can do some kind
of contest some like later on with cs50
um so but the mixing and matching is
really interesting right for example the
skin tones are actually the same yellow
character plus a layer of skin tone on
top of this so I kind of took my lessons
from Chinese in terms of seeing how
things can be binded so there's
something you should know about which is
zge this is also an invisible emoji
character it stands for zero with Joiner
and it was actually originally created
mostly for I think Arabic where you
would you would basically kind of force
something to have like be in the
beginning of of a word or an end of the
word by kind of having this like
invisible character so the rainbow flag
for example is actually a rainbow plus
the white flag
um and we we could have all kinds of fun
combinations if you look at polar bear
it actually is if you have an older
device or it breaks apart it is bear
plus snow which is really cute it was
originally I had bear plus white and
then we decided that bear plus snow made
a lot more sense so uh another one this
is new I I think if you guys should have
it if you've updated your phones in the
last year or so so mending heart is
heart plus
Band-Aid um um what is this one oh this
is interesting um there was a
breastfeeding woman for a long time and
people felt like there was not gender
par was actually really interesting all
the people who wrote it and were like I
want to I want to be a dad showing that
I'm holding my baby why is there only a
woman holding my baby so so we kind of
created a whole set so this is man plus
bottle Tada um and so this is and all of
these occupations are actually often
times a woman plus like you know the
fried egg or like um a school or a
tractor and that's how you got the
occupations if you if you if you send an
emoji over into an older system
sometimes you'll it'll break apart so
one of my kind of favorite kind of
contributions in this in this world is
interracial couple Emoji which we did
with um Tinder which is super fun
because then you could have you know
different couples that are and and like
so many combin this is like this is a
fun if you guys ever have to do a
combinatoric test um this is really fun
because you have two genders plus a
third like gender plus two people plus
five skin tones plus yellow like how
many Emoji couples can you come come up
with when you introduce this Factor so
this is um and underneath it it's just a
wige sequence it's like two people
standing together that are like glued
together now this actually gets
interesting from a cs-50 perspective
because in many cases even though you
only see one character underneath the
hood depending on how your system works
they're counting each one of these as an
individual character so your string
length actually might be five and
instead of one and this this kind of
became a problem with things like
Twitter where things had a hard skin um
length so gender inclusivity um is
actually one of the things that we've
been dealing most with um in the last
couple years so it's kind of interesting
if you think about both what a pictorial
language looks like versus the
abstractness of a of a spoken language
so because you know we had boy and we
had
girl but there was no way to say a
generic child right like if you were on
you wanted to say child you had to pick
a boy or a girl but not a way to say
like just some little person and that's
really key cuz in English at least there
is no gender implied by
child um so how do we mimic that and it
also is key for something like doctor
right doctor and teacher those are those
have don't have gender implied but when
we have them on on the Emoji Keyboard
you to pick a male teacher or um you
know a a a female doctor or whatnot so
there was actually uh a guy at Adobe who
can considers himself non-gender binary
also The Man Behind the orange um the
orange heart he fought and got basically
uh the first three non-gender uh
non-gender binary emojis so child adult
and old older adults so those are
creative and then we started having to
propagate them through actually all the
occupations so these are the gender
neutral versions of many of those um but
then uh we got into this whole thing
where every emoji that had a gender
originally had to be mirrored so
originally we had bearded man and then
we're like okay well we actually have to
get bearded woman so that is on your
keyboard there is pregnant woman there
is now pregnant man which is interesting
um there is you know woman in a bridal
gown there's now man in a bridal gown um
and then there were ones that actually
had to be created that were neither man
or woman so this is a mer person so
there was merman there was mermaid and
there was M person it was really
interesting to figure out like how do
you draw a gender neutral M person like
a bunch of them in the beginning
actually had the arms crossed around
sort of the chest um Monarch so there
was prince and princess and now there is
monarch and one of my favorite actually
is there was Santa Claus and there was
Mrs Claus and now there's MX Claus like
the name of this character literally in
Unicode is MX claw so I feel like it's
sort of like a very official enshrining
of gender non biner in like the world um
not everyone loved it New York Post did
not love this that they like you know
we're we're cing into like Emoji woke
Wars um so some Emoji stats for you this
is very fascinating this is sort of like
the Gen the General Distribution by far
the single emoji that used more than
anything else is the face with tears of
joy about 10% of all Emoji scent is that
one character and then number two is
heart red heart and then it kind of goes
down so um there's a frequency of emoji
use these this is sort of done by um
order magnitude so one is half of two
two is half of one so it's really
interesting it's a very very steep drop
off after the first couple um in case
you ever want to go onto the the Emoji
kind of Unicode website you can you too
can see all the frequency things so I
think it's really funny so basically
it's green going this way it increased
in usage between 2019 and uh 2021 and
it's red going this way it drop and so
pleading face which is a relatively new
emoe you just sort of shut up on the
charts um and whereas actually like
smiling face with heart eyes
like kind of kind of slipped which is
interesting so we just closed our Emoji
proposal round for 2022 these were sort
of the breakdowns people love submitting
Smileys and food and beverages animals
and nature da da da I don't I mean these
are very googly colors um so what is the
future of emoji I will um I will tell
you because we just had a meeting two
weeks ago so I can now publicly talk
about it so historically there was this
whole idea like Unico doesn't want to be
in the world of like encoding glyphs for
like devices everywhere like there was
very controversial when it started doing
that because mostly what Unicode used to
do was you take an existing language
could be dead you know and then it would
just take it and digitize it right it
took languages that existed and just
digitize them and uh then when it kind
of wandered into Emoji World Suddenly
It's like deciding what deserves to be
like an emoji decides to be digitized so
um trying to get kind of get out of it
and they have proposals over time where
it's like oh maybe we should like come
up with a a way to just send pictures
back and forth where you you it's a
fixed picture and you like use a hash so
that you know like we would look at the
picture and then like go do a lookup
somewhere like that did not go over well
then there was actually a really
interesting proposal I kind of like uh
didn't go over well which is using
something called the qid which is in
Wiki in the Wikipedia world so in
Wikipedia World items all have uh
numbers across the different language
Wikipedia so Obama human Earth they will
have an ID number so that the page in
English and the page in German the page
in Chinese all know that they're
pointing to the same thing so the
question so one idea came up like why
don't we use the numbering system so we
can use like Eiffel Tower in you know
see the number and then like oh people
know like oh you're trying to say Eiffel
Tower that did not go over well so those
are both both of those proposals seem
dead as of yet um and it's too bad cuz
and you'll see kind of what's happening
okay so what's coming in 22 so these are
the Emoji that I actually sort of
thought they would be on your phones by
now but cuz we're in mid November and
they usually update early November so
three more Hearts people love hearts
like uh wing blackbird Goose Birds also
purple flowers jellyfish moose face
donkey donkey was a little bit late for
the kind of Elections um Ginger peep pod
Wireless cond shaking face um folding
hand pan that one was interesting cuz
when people first proposed it they
proposed it as like an electric fan and
that didn't like who knows what electric
fans will look like in 100 years because
the thing is Once An Emoji always an
emoji they never retire so they're
always looking for things that have a
long visual longevity floppy disc did
not actually do that so there's always
like we don't want another floppy disc
um and then hairpick is interesting so
there was a whole debate about how to
convey um like afro African hair like
the the curly hair that they introduced
a couple years ago was supposed to do
that and most of the vendors actually
have it in a sort of Afro way except for
Apple so there's a lot of complaints but
um hairpick was sort of a an interesting
way it means both comb but also has sort
of an interesting historic connotation
and it's been around for about 2,000
years uh a couple music things maracus
and flute uh Beyond 2022 one of the
things that's going to die oops can I go
back no I can't oh well uh we're going
to retire the the family Emoji um they
didn't go over so well there were so
many of them combinatorically if you had
all the everything in in uh you know all
the race all the races all because you
wanted to have skin tones because you
didn't want to imply that families can
only be one race it was such an ordeal
uh essentially we're all like no one
uses them and there's so many and it's
like the fonts like in terms of the load
is like too large so they're just going
to make them all into like basically
little like bathroom symbol Type U folks
um so I think that is those will
disappear what what's actually really
interesting about the family Emoji is
they had gay when they introduced the
family they had gay family emoji and the
Russian government went berserk and
actually you can Google this in 2015
you'll see a bunch of articles about
like the Russian government considering
it homosexual propaganda to Youth and
there was a big debate about whether or
not they were going to ban Apple devices
and what so you can see a lot of the
media coverage from that time but I
thought it was really interesting how
upset a national government can get
about little pictures on your phone um
another thing that's going to that's on
the agenda as of you know a couple of
weeks ago is directionality in terms of
emoji so as you know most emojis kind of
just flip one way or another and the
reason why it matters is because not all
languages run in the same direction so
for example Arabic so we are used to
left to right but a lot of languages go
right to left um so and this kind of It
kind of changes the meaning of emoji for
example right to left I send this a lot
to my friends when I'm going flying from
the Bay Area to New York um if you do it
from left to right however that is what
it looks like so it looks like um you
know you're in NE Bay but the plane is
still going that you know kind of up and
to the right and then now it looks like
you're going from New York to the Bay
Area the other place is like oh it's
it's a girl and she's running really
fast right uh that is left to right to
left in our world wait left to right
sorry sorry that was that's that's
supposed to be left to right and in here
it would be she's like behind like
pollution or something like that so
sorry about so so an example this is
actually in The Proposal like in one
case if it's left or right you're
running away from a line of cars and the
other one it's a warning to not run
behind car fumes so they are trying to
figure out like how do we mirror a bunch
of the Emoji um but the LA the main
thing that I think sort of I don't know
when it's going to happen I'm really
hopeful is going to happen is trying to
come up with a system that supports
little stickers in line that don't need
Unicode so this is like slack or on um
twitch you can embed little pictures on
in line and all all all the vendors have
to get together and agree to come up
with a standard way to do that they have
not yet come up with that but that is
sort of one of the ways that unic coded
like want it wants to back away from
actually being like a global regulator
for like little colorful glyphs and so
if you ever need to reach me um on in my
emoji world you can find me um Jenny
EmojiNation org there will
be um the it will be actually a while I
think before we see a next generation of
emoji showing up in it used to be like
every year they would get new code
points it might be a little bit less
than every year now as they work on
things like directionality over time so
that uh if anyone has questions you can
ask questions you can find me afterwards
I think I've I feel like there's
supposed to be some some hubub right now
about maybe maybe
um microphones but maybe not but maybe
I'm just done and if if there are
questions or if David is around I'm
happy you know he can I'm I'm happy to
to answer any questions that folks have
yes hi yes I was wondering what were
your thoughts on the
emo so the question is what are my
thoughts on the Emoji Movie you're
talking about the Sony animated one yes
okay my thought on that is it is better
than a 6% rating on um Rotten Tomatoes
would lead you to believe so that's my
one thought and my my next thought is
that um that was a rush job from an
animation perspective that was that was
was about 18 months of whereas a typical
animated movie takes four years so in my
spare time I also produce movies and
documentaries so one thing that is key
to know
about about movies and animated movies
and this is very important they take a
very long time but you can always fix it
because you haven't shot anything and a
very good example of that is I assume
you guys have seen Frozen if you haven't
seen you seen of the age you would have
seen Frozen um I do not understand like
how huge and a phenomenon or why it was
such a huge phenomenon but
um they actually did a original cut of
Frozen and it did so I don't know you
guys know the the Eye the the sort of
Snow Queen thing but she's like super
dark and like not fun and like kind of
evil and like not someone you want to
like get behind as a character so they
actually did sort of a rough cut of that
of Frozen and they came out of that with
um it's just storyboarding and they're
like that is not good and they killed it
so they were like we can't go with this
and then started from scratch more or
less again starting with the song um Let
It Go which is actually written by a kid
from my elementary school Bobby Lopez or
co-written by Bobby Lopez um I also
actually fun fact I also went I would
took the school bus with uh Lyn mmel
Miranda so I was a fourth grader when he
was like a kindergartener so we had a
very musical Elementary School in New
York City but the thing is they could
fix it because they had enough time and
have enough money not like movies where
you shoot humans much harder to fix so
you have the footage that you have and
you can do little pickups but you can't
fix it so essentially what happened in
that case I think um it's 18 months and
it could have gotten better and a lot of
the movies that you see with Pixar like
it's very it's actually sort emotionally
similar to the movie called inside out
and uh but inside they just have more
time and so it's better so as opposed to
18 months which is not long enough to
make a animated movie good but uh the
other fun thing is is it was the it it
was so weird cuz they sold sponsorships
it was like like oh my God here comes
the Bots and the malware let's go into
Dropbox and protect ourselves and was so
I think that it got a lot of like bad
kind of um kind of uh vibes from the
from the press for doing things like
that but from a kids perspective it's
it's fine I think if um I don't know
that I would like put into my top 10 of
animated pictures but it's better than
6% on Rotten Tomatoes
and then actually if you guys ever care
we we have done uh I did a documentary
about Emoji so and all the people that
create helped create emoji and uh we did
a cs50x movie night I think during the
pandemic was it during the pandemic
everything sort of like blurred together
but it was during the pandemic yeah Are
we more questions yes um I wanted to
know you mentioned that one of the
criteria for
AC do or there's demand
yeah yeah that's a very good question
yeah so the question is one of the
propos one of our criterias of of um
getting an emoji accepted is to sort of
to demonstrate demand and how do we
demonstrate demand and I would say in a
in a pretty um clumsy way actually at
this point so the main thing that you
have in our in our current proposal
process is we have um a median Emoji
which is elephant so elephant is like if
you stack ranked all the emoji for
popularity elephant is like right there
in the middle and it's also a concept
that's like universally understood
across all
languages so um elephant shows up
somewhere between 500 million and 700
million in Google search results like if
you type it into a laptop you'll see you
know elephant 500,000 uh 500 million
search results and generally you're
you're trying to when you're comparing
your term to elephant you want to see
very roughly how many Google search
results B search results sometimes
Instagram so actually something that was
really surprising to me was someone
proposed hummingbird I think hummingbird
is uh a good proposal and um but if you
look at Hummingbird it's only like 21
million in terms of the stat so which I
thought was like very surprisingly low
so that's one of the main ways that we
kind of we kind of see like is it also
visually used and all of that yeah any
other questions are we good I didn't
even need my water or anything oh can I
take I'm going to take a picture I'm
going to take a picture for because now
you guys are actually human and not
Muppets so I'm very very excited about
this so I will send this to like my
block mates and be like I just lectured
at CS you know in Sanders Theater my
thanks to Jenny Lee thank
you yeah you can stay up here for give
me one
second
so if up until now thought it would be
appropriate to toss this up on the board
if up until now you've not yet gotten
cs50 stress ball on the way out please
do grab one we got some extras as well
off to the side but I would also keep in
mind back in week zero where again we
began we asked you to categorize
yourselves as to whether you are among
those less comfortable those more
comfortable or those somewhere in
between uh please know now that you are
officially all some uh please know now
that you are all officially among those
more comfortable and indeed even though
a couple of more Milestones await we
cannot wait to see what you accomplish
with your final projects in the meantime
as always this is and now this was
cs50
[Laughter]
[Music]
Mr when
I in CS I'll say truth be told I thought
i' be real coding hero because I did
so it picked up so fast turn out that
harder scratch hell world and
goodby
[Applause]
[Music]
because
Mr I was on
the trying so hard not fall behind
attending section and wanting a stuck in
the in void of my
computer to pyth in why on because this
is
[Music]
s Mr s we completed
JavaScript sequ CSS
and every language our to reset don't
[Music]
get again I repli
obviously because
cie
[Applause]
because
[Music]
all right so this is cs50 my name is
David May and this is Harvard
University's introduction to the
intellectual Enterprises of computer
science and the Art of programming and
this of course is our special family
weekend wherein not only are cs50's own
students here in the audience but also
some family members as well now you're
showing up in the semester a little bit
late we've just tackled week eight which
is really our ninth week since computer
scientists start counting from zero so
we've done a whole lot of work over the
past few weeks as you might have heard
via emails or text messages home
including a language known here as binar
so on the screen here of course is a lot
of zeros and ones and suffice it to say
let me sum up the past nine weeks with
this is what's going on underneath the
hood but of course today we thought we'd
make things a little more accessible a
little more broadly applicable and
indeed our Focus today will not be on
what these patterns of zeros and ones
represent which in astute eye might
notice are replicated visually with
these light bulbs being in a pattern on
and off and as your child might have
hinted uh before class or perhaps now
this might very well spell a word up to
eight characters long because you can
encode even in the real world things
digital too but today we'll focus on
things much more high level this notion
of cyber security like our the security
of our data our privacy of our systems
particularly on the internet nowadays
because presumably all of us are
carrying Technologies around in our
pocket using laptops and desktops every
day and so the goal today is to
stipulate that this is what's going on
underneath the hood but let's solve some
problems at a higher level so that your
homework when you go back to wherever
you're visiting from can actually be to
apply some of today's Lessons Learned so
with that said perhaps the most common
familiar defense uh of one's systems and
data phone and laptops and desktops
would just be these simple passwords
unfortunately you and I are frankly as
humans not all that good at choosing
passwords and this is in itself a
relatively weak form of Defense even
though each of us has dozens hundreds of
passwords nowadays or at least dozens or
hundreds of accounts Maybe fives or tens
of dozens of passwords indeed if you're
in the habit of reusing passwords we'll
see today probably among our first
Lessons Learned so for instance if we
look back at the past year 2021 thanks
to security researchers who take a look
at data that has been hacked or leaked
online by way of public databases we
have a sense as computer scientists of
what the most popular or equivalently
what some of the worst passwords are
that you and I are choosing for our
system so as of this past year according
to one measure the most commonly used
password in systems everywhere was 1 2 3
4 5 6 all right number two password in
our top 10 here list was only slightly
longer 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 after that we
took a turn in the other direction 1 2 3
4 five alone after that got a little
more interesting quiry which might sound
pretty cryptic but not if you look down
at your US keyboard and it's the top
leftand row of the keys on a an American
keyboard so also not all that hard uh
perhaps not surprisingly uh a little
disconcertingly number five was
password meanwhile number six returns us
to digits 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 after that
really less effort 111 111 uh after that
a little more variation but not all that
much 1 two 3 one two 3 after that it's
getting even less interesting 1 2 3 4 5
6 7
890 and then lastly topping the list is
just 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 so this is not a good
top 10 list to be on so among today's
first takeaways is if you see your
password on the screen like you didn't
make the list in a good way this means
hundreds thousands millions of other
people probably have that password of
yours now in of itself that's not
necessarily worrisome because I don't
know who has these passwords in a room
as large as this but just intuitively
why is this a bad thing either parent or
child welcome to raise a hand here why
might this be
intuitively yeah access to it so access
to it like I mean we literally as
computer scientists now have a database
of really common passwords and your your
thoughts password and can just find it
out quickly yeah you can just find it
out quickly I mean you could imagine
trying to guess someone's password by
just typing in random letters random
numbers random words but not if you have
a top 10 list like the the adversaries
in the world might as well just start
with this list now you'll notice that
even absent from this are slight
variants like some of you might be
thinking I'm not on the list cuz I do
something clever like I use an
exclamation point for the number one or
a three for an e or a five for an S and
based on the smiles in the room right
now you're not all that clever it turns
out because other people are smiling too
which is to say that an adversary can
take those same fistic that you might
think are making things more secure by
just tweaking some letters to numbers or
vice versa but if you're doing it and
other people are doing it the bad guys
so to speak are going to be doing it as
well so unfortunately when it comes to
passwords better is longer and random
and really unguessable but that's not
what most of us have in fact case in
point on our phones whether you have an
Android device or an iPhone nowadays you
know odds are you have something
relatively simplistic protecting it if
you have anything at all but at least
Apple and Google are pretty good at
least nudging us to choose these kinds
of passcodes now and a four-digit
passcode is quite common nowadays and so
here's where we have an opportunity
thanks to uh the URL that you saw on the
screen earlier to conjecture as a group
just how long might it take an adversary
someone out there who's out to get us or
get one of us uh how long might it take
an adversary to figure out your phone's
4digit passcode this is a cs50 is on
Carter Carter if we could switch over
and poll the audience here if you take
out your phone or laptop whatever device
you might have used a few minutes ago to
scan that QR code or to visit that same
URL you can see these questions on your
browser and if you can't that's fine
we'll share some aggregate data
nonetheless but you should have an
opportunity to tap one of your answers
and we'll give folks a few more
seconds if you'd like to play along at
home and here in just a
moment probably have many people
reporting but why don't we go ahead and
take a look at some percentages it looks
like most of you 67% are proposing just
a few seconds so that's not all that
good news if it's a four-digit passcode
some of you are hoping it's a few
minutes uh 8% are hoping a few hours
four more than 4% of you are really
hoping perhaps it's a few days well
let's actually consider how we can
answer this question and make today not
just conceptual but a little
quantitative too and see if we can't
slap some numbers on questions like
these so ultimately you can make more
informed decisions with your system
security so for instance when it comes
to four digigit passcodes rather than
just consider how secure it is well
let's make it a more precise question
like what are the forms of attack well
the simplest attack might be just
someone grabbing your phone be it in
your family or maybe at Starbucks or the
airport or the like and just starting
all possible combinations maybe 00000000
then 00001 and 00002 we could maybe
automate this a little bit so for
instance I might potentially be able to
do something like uh roboticize this
here let me go ahead and full screen a
quick video here that's just going to
paint a picture in just a moment on the
screen of how if we're a really clever
adversary and know how to build things
well at least maybe we could automate
some of that process so here's an
Android phone on a counter here's a very
simple tripod and a little touch device
robotically doing all of that hacking
for you starting at 0000 Z probably all
the way up to 9999 now that too wasn't
necessarily all of that all that fast
but at least you the adversary can step
away and doesn't actually have to be
bothered with the time involved the cost
involved in actually hacking that
particular device well let's go one
level deeper a little more interestingly
and consider here um the how much much
time really this so-called Brute Force
attack would take and that's actually a
term of art much like in yester year
when maybe there was a battering ram
trying to brute force their way into a
castle or something like that a Brute
Force attack digitally is just someone
trying manually all possible codes or
maybe robotically trying all possible
codes but generally automating the
process in some way to go through all
possibilities well if you've got for
instance um a 4digit passcode let's ask
maybe a follow-up question here not how
long will take but how many possible
4digit passcodes are there because then
maybe we can do some quick math and if
every passcode takes me a second or a
few milliseconds or the like then I
think we can try to extrapolate from
that whether the first answer was
seconds or minutes or days or hours or
something else so how many four-digit
passcodes are possible if you take out
your same device it should have just
changed automatically if it doesn't seem
to have maybe reload your browser with
some menu option and then tap in here
how many four digigit passcodes are
possible four total 40 99,999 10,000 or
unsure is okay
too so let's see we'll give you a few
more moments how many four digigit
passcodes are possible and shall we
reveal the results so now it looks like
uh a a few of you uh 2% of you are
saying just four passcodes 40 99,999
there's definitely some contention here
and 6% are un sure well how do we wrap
our minds around this well let's just
kind of do this real simply here let me
switch back over to doing a bit of math
and if we have here 10 possibilities for
each digit if there's four digits each
digit can be 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 nine so
that's 10 possibilities so if you think
about the number of permutations that's
10 possibilities for the first digit
times 10 for the next time 10 to the for
the next times 10 for the next and so if
we do that out 10 * 10 * 10 * 10 or 10
the 4th there are indeed as 66% of you
uh found uh 10,000 possibilities and so
now we can kind of work backwards and
decide how long is it going to take for
an adversary to hack into this phone
because if it's one attack one guess per
second well that's going to map out to
10,000 seconds but maybe not if the
adversary isn't a roboticist or a human
what if they're like at a software
programmer someone who's taken even a
class introductory like cs50 and learned
a little bit of programming well a
little bit frighteningly it's not all
that hard to hack into systems if you
just know how to code to and really have
the computer do your work for you so in
fact let me go ahead and change over to
another screen on my computer here um
this is different for students in the
group from vs code this is just a black
and white version of it that we've used
briefly in the past and I'm just going
to go ahead and create a program called
crack.pie to crack something just
technically means to figure out what it
is figure out a password in this case
and dop means I'm going to use a
programming language that we here in
cs50 have been dabbling in in the past
couple of weeks with more to come next
week as well so it turns out and you
need not understand each of these lines
of code if I want to try maybe
generating all 10,000 possible codes I'm
not going to bother with a robot I've
got all these cables coming out of my
computer and odds are one of them is a
USB cable or a lightning cable surely we
could figure out how to connect like
laptop or desktop to phone and just like
automate the process nowadays by just
sending all of the numbers into the
phone until one uh unlocks the trick
just like in the movies or TV well in
Python I could write a program that does
this as follows I can import so to speak
all of the decimal digits 0 through n
and this for students in the room is
just a slightly better version of typing
out 10 different numbers manually I can
also import from a library so to speak
called iter tools for iteration tools
which means to do something again and
again I can import a function called
Product which means the cross product
like combine this with this some number
of times and then it's just two more
lines of code I can use what's called a
loop and programming so for every
passcode in the cross product of all 10
of those digits repeated a total of four
times let me go ahead and rather than
bother connecting my phone and hacking
my own phone let me just print out every
one of those 10,000 codes on the screen
and we'll see how fast the hacker could
do this let me go ahead and print and
with an asterisk which is a little trick
to format it nicely I'm going to print
out each of those passcodes and that's
it four lines of code maybe 40 seconds
of talking but maybe really four seconds
of code if I actually did this without
the audience and now let me go ahead and
save the file and I'm going to run as we
do every in class of late python of
crack.pie and when I hit enter I should
see on the screen all 10,000
possibilities from 000000 to 9999 so
let's see is it a few seconds minutes
hours or days done so barely even
seconds plural if that so that should be
a little disconcerting because all that
adversary needs to do is grab your phone
off the counter plug in a cable and boom
they're done like there's no ticking
clock or worries as in the movies or TV
that maybe you're going to come into the
room you don't need that much of a
window of time so what would be better
than this well let's consider what our
options might be if we don't want to
just use four-digit passcode some of you
indeed might have better passcodes than
that and maybe you use four letter
passcodes instead so A through Z maybe
uppercase and lowercase that starts to
make things a little more interesting so
should we pull this question too if we
upgrade from four digits to just four
letters English letters a through z
uppercase and lowercase why don't we go
ahead and pull the grip here and ask how
many four letter passcodes are there
instead so this time the range starts at
four still not the right answer though
this time how many four-letter passcodes
are
possible not just just take a couple
more
seconds
all right almost a couple hundred
responses in already few more
seconds
and why don't we go ahead and reveal now
the answers which are Okay so we've
solved a couple problems at least so we
well we well okay someone's just messing
with us now all right so it looks like
most of you 76% of you have claimed it's
7 million plus possibilities so that's
encouraging cuz that's a whole order of
magnitude more than before well let's
figure out how we might do this
mathematically so if we've got 26
lowercase 26 uppercase that's 52
possibilities now for each of those four
digits so that's 52 times itself four
times which indeed either off the top of
your head a good guess a calculator on
the same device you're using right now
indeed gives us 7 million instead well
what might be slightly better than that
well maybe four characters and this
indeed is what your Macs PCS and phones
are urging us to do nowadays not just
numbers not just letters but like really
annoying punctuation so it really looks
cryptic not just to the adversary but
also to you and me unfortunately and
that's the downside but here now we have
a mental model and really a
computational framework via which we can
evaluate the security of these and I'll
go ahead and spoil some of the math here
if we've got 52 uh letters of the
alphabet uppercase and lowercase 10
digits and if I count them out on my
keyboard about 32 punctuation symbols in
typical English grammar that actually
gives us 94 possibilities now which is
up from 52 which is up from 10 so now
we're really moving and now that would
give us 78 million possibility so
another order of magnitude now it's
still going to be relatively fast
because you know what I can actually do
this let me go back into my code here
let me reopen the same program and I can
point out just how easy it is to make
these changes instead of importing
digits as before I can import as your uh
child might know asky letters which are
a through z uppercase lowercase and I
can just change this here asky letters
and so this was that first version where
we just changed to letters let me now
rerun the code and instead of seeing
numbers we'll see letters flying across
the screen and if I walk over here to
the screen we'll see that by the time I
get here we're halfway through the
entire alphabet lowercase if I now start
walking away I think yep we're already
done now with uppercase as well if I
upgrade this slightly further let's go
ahead and take it one more level and
perhaps do let's say ask letters and
digits and punctuation and this would be
the pythonic way to say that and I'm
going to add to those letters those same
digits those same punctuation symbols
let me shrink my font just so the code
still fits on the screen and what we now
have is with a two seconds of changes a
program that if I run this version
whoops without the typographical error
this is what we call in cs50 a bug so
now we run the same this is what we call
in cs50 a second
bug
punctuation okay this is where I cross
my fingers okay so now it's going to be
a little hard to see as it flies across
the screen but you probably are seeing
glimpses of some weird punctuation
characters as well and I won't waste our
time trying to talk through this because
this is going to take longer we're still
in the lower case I'm still over here
already we've not even gotten to n now O
then P so this is going to run longer
but let's end with one final question on
the security of all these systems I'm
going to cancel that by hitting contrl C
on my keyboard and let's ask the
question instead if we use eight
character passwords so twice as many
characters but even that is not terribly
long right this is eight characters
alone on the stage eight characters
using letters numbers and punctuation
might be better let's do one final vote
here if we could on your same device how
many eight character possibilities are
there now
for these
passcodes and now for didn't even make
the list this
time all right few more seconds about
100 responses so
far how about we go ahead and Carter if
you would't mind let's reveal the
results based on the vote a pretty
decent spread here although the
quadrillions are quickly buzzing in and
they're contending with the others here
looks like 44% of you said quintilian
34% said quadrillion and this time for
the first time uh you overbid so indeed
if we go back to the math here at least
the majority overbid if we have eight
character passcodes that gives us 94
times itself 8 times or 94 to the eth
power and in fact that gives us roughly
6 quadrillion 95 trillion 689 Bill 385
mil 410,000 and
86 possible passcodes now what does that
mean well the adversary's algorithm the
step-by-step code that they write to try
to hack into your phone is no different
and honestly if your passcode is eight
characters long but there're zeros
00000000000000 you're no more secure
fundamentally you really want to be
somewhere in The Sweet Spot of that
massive range of values so that if the
adversary tries this Brute Force attack
just running through all possibilities
they will eventually reach your passcode
just mathematically it will be there
hopefully though well maybe not
hopefully you and I and they will be
gone from this world because that much
time will have passed and if we fact if
we do out the math here uh this number
of seconds for instance is long past uh
when uh uh we will uh no longer be here
so that's the sort of measure is we
don't sort of fundamentally change the
equation for the adversary it's still
the same risk it's still the same attack
but you significantly drive down the
probability of success on their part or
conceptually you drive up the cost to
the adversary and indeed even in the
physical world this is true you just
want your passcode in the digital world
really to be better than someone else's
because you want someone else's passcode
to be the one that the adversary does
something with with just like in the
physical world even though it's a bit uh
uncomfortable to consider your house
doesn't need to be 100% secure and
indeed it's difficult to make it such
there's always going to be a a point of
weakness maybe it's that window the door
or something like that but if your home
is more secure than the next door home
just probabilistically you are more
secure you're not secure and indeed any
website you see down the road that says
we are secure because we do X Y or Z
like that's nonsense security is really
about comparisons and Val ating things
if quantitatively relative to some other
system relative to some other code so
what's the takeaway here well hopefully
a non-trivial number of you we'll go
home this weekend on Monday and change
at least one passcode um but there's
going to be a trade-off here and we talk
about this all the time in cs50 anytime
we improve something we pay some price
in time and performance and cost
somewhere else so what's the downside
then of this advice that you should use
minimally eight character
passcodes why might you want to say nay
and not do
this say again you have to remember you
have to remember it right and so here
there's sort of some sociology there's
some human behavior you know some of you
might have colleagues if you're working
in the real world at least back in
healthier times when you had colleagues
with desks and cubicles and there's
probably one person in the office with
like a Post-It note on their monitor
with their passcode you know it's a bit
of a cyber security offense but it's
also a sort of real world side effect
maybe of corporate policies that aren't
really calibrated for human behavior so
we'll see if there's some other defenses
and indeed let me propose that we talk
briefly about one that actually tends to
kick in automatically even if your
passcode is not as strong as we've just
seen one of these six quadrillion
possibilities well what could we do
instead well as anyone and I'll zoom in
on this here accidentally locked themsel
out of their own phone before like when
does that happen yeah when you try the
password too many times yeah so too many
times maybe your finger's slightly off
maybe you're slightly off and you just
don't input the same passcode correctly
after like five times 10 times there's
some reasonable threshold and why does
that happen well Apple and Google
equivalently figure just
probabilistically if after 10 guesses
you still haven't typed in the right
passcode probably you're not you you're
someone else who's picked up your phone
so we're just going to go ahead and lock
you out now what's the effect of this
well this means now that each of those
possible passcodes no longer takes
roughly 1 second now it takes roughly 1
minute so the attack is still the same
but if it's now one passcode or 10
guesses per minute we have significantly
by a factor of 60 in this story slowed
things down and unfortunately does
anyone know what happens if you screw up
again after a
minute yeah it goes longer it's like
five minutes and then 10 minutes and uh
Google is kind of obnoxious about it
they don't even give you a time frame
they just say try again later and so
that keeps not only the adversary out
but also potentially you so there in
lies that trade-off if you've forgotten
your code if nowadays your finger is
slightly wet so the screen isn't
responding correctly these could be
usability downsides too so security is
really just about finding The Sweet Spot
among these various tradeoffs here but
there's other mechanisms too and some of
you might recognize this screen from
Gmail via which of course you log in but
after you log into Gmail or similar
websites or apps or systems at work
nowadays especially you might be
presented with uh what's called
two-factor authentication and what is
this in a nutshell in Lay person
terms most many of you if you do
anything digitally at work might have to
do this now
yeah exactly you get texted at your
phone an additional code that's not your
same password it's typically a numeric
code maybe six digits long it expires
after a minute or 10 minutes but why is
this a good thing well one it's no
longer just a piece of information that
you know or that you might have written
down it's information that changes every
time you try to log in but more
importantly it's a fundamentally second
factor which means it's not just
something you know now it's something
you have so you for instance are the
only one theoretically that should be
receiving that code and so now the
adversary if they want to get into your
account not only have to guess or brute
force or maybe read off of a Post-It
note your password they also have to
physically have access now to that phone
so there's still a threat absolutely but
it's not everyone on the internet with
an internet connection now it's only the
people in Starbucks now it's only the
people at work now it's only the people
in your home who might have access to
that second Factor so there too it just
raises the bar to the adversary making
it harder more timec consuming more
geographically impossible for them to
attack you but what's the downside of
two-factor authentication whether it's a
device or even nowadays it's in software
whether it's on your keychain or on your
phone where you're prompted for this
code what's a downside as some of us
have probably experienced
too forg you forget your cell phone
absolutely right the the factor that you
have you don't have with you or maybe
you're in a basement somewhere don't
have reception you're on a plane you
can't get the code and so there too are
these tradeoffs and even it departments
need to keep that in mind because what
does that mean for them well if you
don't have your phone with you and you
are in the habit of calling it to help
you fix this now there's a a cost a
human cost maybe even a financial cost
and so it policy nowadays is really just
about finding the right balance and
where we want to spend our resources but
at least raise the bar to the adversary
but of course there's other ways too and
this is going to be one of our homework
assignments if you will after today
there's this software called password
managers and no need to buzz in on your
phone but maybe with a physical hand how
many folks here use a password manager
okay let me ballpark this at 10 20%
perhaps Okay so we've got 80% upside
here and a lesson learned potentially so
a password manager is just a piece of
software on your Mac your PC or your
phone nowadays that manages your
passwords well what is that mean when
you go to a website for the first time
or you download an app for the first
time and you have to create an account
you can can still use your email address
or David as your username or whatever
your name might be so you don't have to
change that methodology but instead of
typing in one 2 3 4 5 six as your same
password for that website or app as well
as for every other now you use the
password manager software to generate
something difficult to guess for you
that is you tell the password manager
give me an8 character random passcode
not 0000 but something with punctuation
with numbers with letters and better yet
the password manager is the name
suggests remembers that password for you
and the next time you go to another
website you do it again with a
completely different password maybe same
username maybe two-factor authentication
but different password different
password different password and it
doesn't have to be eight I mean I'm in
the habit of using a dozen two dozen
characters in total and at that point I
can't even pronounce the number of
possibilities because it goes well be
Beyond uh the quadrillions so the
probability that someone's going to get
into one of those accounts for me now is
very very very low and they're going to
take less interest in me and maybe more
interest in someone else that's not
using as good of a password now what
does this mean in real terms well when
you go to log into that managed site you
don't manually type your password
anymore in fact you don't generally even
need to know it nowadays I probably
don't know 90 plus 99% of my passwords I
entrust them to this password manager
now of course you'd like to think that
the password manager itself is secure so
what might that mean well those of you
who do use a password manager how do you
access that software itself what's
protecting your data in your
understanding so maybe Biometrics like
your your face ID or maybe your
fingerprint or maybe more simply what
else password maybe just a password and
hopefully that password that primary
password that gatekeeper is not itself 1
2 3 4 5 6 otherwise it doesn't matter
how secure all of the others are but if
you're willing to put in the effort and
pick one pretty long somewhat random
very unguessable password that you just
promise to commit to memory and maybe
for backup you literally print it out
and put it in a safe deposit box or a
safe or just kind of hide it somewhere
physically that there's very low
probability someone's going to find the
backup copy that might be Al loan but of
course the flip side is now if you
forget that Ma that primary password
you've now lost all of the eggs in the
basket if someone gets that primary
password now they have access to
everything so that's rather the
trade-off but I dare say you're probably
less threatened depending on your family
uh uh by the people immediately around
you than the billions of other people on
the internet that have access
potentially to those same systems so
there to it's a trade-off and it's up to
you to decide whether or not to manage
your passwords in this way but if you
were on that top 10 list or even if
you're not but you can think of several
accounts that all have the same password
you're probably going to benefit from
something like this and why is it bad to
be clear to use the same password on
multiple sites in case that's never sort
of dawned
in thought why is that a bad thing to
reuse a password on different websites
different apps any intuition yeah and
back exactly once it's attacked you can
the adversary presumably by transitivity
can see oh well if this user's username
is mailin harvard.edu on this website
and their password is foolishly 1 2 3 4
56 or even something way more
complicated they can probably just
assume with high probability that if I'm
being a little reckless let's try access
mailin at harvard.edu other accounts
other apps using that exact same
password and so by transitivity
essentially you're putting your other uh
Accounts at risk so what's maybe a
takeaway minimally here I would start to
reconsider your passcodes on your most
important data Maybe it's medical maybe
it's Financial maybe it's email anything
remotely personal that you really
wouldn't want to have access uh do you
necessarily need the same form level of
security on eCommerce sites or sites
that you don't really care about or that
you signed up for once and after that H
that's it probably not so you can decide
for yourself but again software like a
password manager and these are just some
of the possibilities out there um are
probably to be your friend a couple of
these are free they come with Windows or
Mac OS a couple are commercial Harvard
has a site license for students for uh
one of these as well so there are
options out there but what else do
people use what else can people use to
keep their system secure so most of us
nowadays have probably heard of
encryption this technique for just kind
of scrambling information so when you
want to send a message an email or
upload a a photograph or use your credit
card hopefully it's not just being sent
out for all to see but there's some kind
of scrambling going on and some fancy
mathematics ensure that encryption
ensures that only you the sender and
someone else the receiver can
theoretically see what that credit card
number is what that message is what that
photograph is instead so encryption is
sort of Common Place nowadays both in
websites and apps and ATMs and other
such devices but how does it work well
back in week two of cs50 uh your child
learned learned a little something about
encryption otherwise known as
cryptography and one of the algorithms
we talked about was quite simply
something like this this is what we
might call uh not only cs50 but plain
text so very plain text that in this
case is English and obviously everyone
in the room can read it but what if I
wanted to send this message out to
someone in this room or out on the
Internet or maybe equivalently back in
the day maybe write a message down on a
scrap of paper in grade school and pass
a secret note a secret love note to
someone in class with hopes that the
teach or any other students in the class
can't intercept it and read it well you
probably don't want to say this is cs50
or I love you or anything remotely
sensitive but rather maybe you want to
encrypt it and let's change the the T to
a u maybe change the H to an i the I to
a j the S to a t the I to a j the S to a
t again the C to a d the S to a T and
we'll just leave the numbers alone even
though I worry someone could probably
guess what this now does say nonetheless
but what was the algorithm as I rattled
those ch changes off whether student
from week two or parent from week now
yeah a on shift just a onlet shift and
this is more sophisticatedly called a
rotational Cipher or a Caesar Cipher
after Caesar back in the day it's
relatively simplistic but back in the
day it's not so simplistic if you're the
first person in the world to ever use it
or think of it but nowadays this is not
actually what we use but it's similarly
mathematical in nature it's not quite as
simple as just adding one or subtracting
one to go from now what we'd call text
to plain test but it's similarly math
that's involved and let me just
stipulate that the way the math works is
that the sender and the receiver just
have to have in mind some kind of secret
and the Secret in this case would very
trivially be one but it could be a much
bigger much more unguessable number or
maybe some other secret we share the
presumption being that my classmates my
teacher in that grade school classroom
if they don't know what that secret is
that number is yeah they could try to
brute force it and try all possible
mathematics plus one plus 2 plus three
but that's going to take them some time
and they probably don't care enough and
so my data might be therefore relatively
secure but we use encryption all the
time nowadays and so for instance this
is at the start of most URLs nowadays
even if you don't type it yourself with
that said Safari and even Chrome now or
kind of simplifying if not dumbing down
user interfaces to just hide details
that you and I as sort of normal users
don't need to see 24/7 but it is there
and if in fact on your phone or laptop
you click on the URL even if it's super
short initially you'll probably see the
whole thing starting with this and the s
means secure the s means that encryption
is being used but there's other forms of
this not just when you visit websites
there's this endtoend encryption which
is being talked about more nowadays
especially during coid times with so
many more of us on video and talking
about uh more sensitive things tele
medicine talking to doctors things that
you also wouldn't want to verbally or
visually get out into the wild just like
text what's different about endtoend
encryption versus HTT GPS and the type
of encryption that most of us use every
day on websites
alone end to end encryption is sort of a
better feature that you want to
increasingly seek when using services
like Zoom or Microsoft teams or Whatsapp
or the
like any instincts here yeah over on the
right good so the encryption the
scrambling of information happens in The
Source the sender and the destination
the receiver without a so-called
middleman in between and this is
actually very different from most
contexts nowadays that use just https
because when you're using https to buy
something on Amazon securely with your
credit card well of course Amazon needs
to be able to decrep the message at the
end of the day and so that's fine but
even when you're using services like
video conferencing or maybe text
messaging nowadays well if you're using
Whatsapp that's owned by meta and if
you're using Instagram that's owned by
meta there's a lot of middlemen in these
apps that we're using and if they were
only using encryption period or only
using something like https yes your en
your connection from you to WhatsApp and
in turn to the recipient might very well
be secure on each end of that channel
but meta in the between the company and
any other company in between could
theoretically For Better or For Worse be
looking at that data whether it's to
mine it for advertising purposes whether
it's to Snoop on data that you're
sending that is not end to-end
encryption if the middleman a company
typically has technically access to that
data now zoom and Microsoft teams and
WhatsApp and iMessage and other services
with which you're familiar increasingly
are offering stronger guarantees of
encryption whereby it's indeed between
parties A and B and not the one in the
middle now there's downsides here and
you can actually see this kind of
functionality manifest in certain
settings for instance besides iMessage
uh which just does this for you on
iPhones or Macs besides Zoom um you can
actually fine-tune these settings indeed
within Zoom itself s so here's a
screenshot that I took last night of
just what the user interface looks like
today to create a new Zoom meeting with
the latest version of Zoom software and
maybe unbeknownst to you there's a
choice of buttons down here and most
likely yours is by default on enhanced
encryption which is brilliant marketing
speak because it's just encryption it's
not enhanced it actually ironically
means worse than this um but they want
you using it most likely why well it's a
little easier to implement it's a little
less expensive for them computationally
and to be fair enhanced encryption does
scramble the data but not in a way that
Zoom can't see it Zoom can indeed see it
but that's actually a plus in some
context because if you want to do like
Cloud recordings and you want a meeting
recorded not on your Mac or PC but like
let Zoom deal with that if you want
automatic transcription nowadays so the
words to appear whether it's English or
something else on the screen well you
can't really lock Zoom or any other
middleman out of that because someone
needs to save it to the cloud someone
needs to translate the voice to those
English or some other language words so
enhanced encryption enables those
features but they also allow a bad actor
malicious employee someone who's just
nosy at Zoom or the equivalent middleman
to just kind of poke around your video
conference and hear what you've said or
see what you've typed as well unless you
instead check this box as well so
increasingly look for mentions of end
to-end encryption or give that some
thought when you choose a technology via
which to communicate with someone
whether it's within your family or
without as well now last but not least
there's other applications of encryption
too and this too might be a lesson
learned as well full dis encryption so a
dis is like where your data stored in
your Mac or PC or even your phone and
full dis encryption just means ideally
that all of your data is encrypted that
is somehow scrambled now hopefully your
password for your computer or phone is
good enough that even though the device
is encrypted with that password at least
you'll remember it and your phone or
your Mac or PC will automatically
decrypt it for you of course you can't
scramble the information and hide it
from from ourselves one of us at least
for these devices needs to have access
but full dis encryption typically means
that at least when you close the laptop
lid or power down for the night that
even if someone else steals that device
opens the lid unless they don't unless
they have your passcode they can't even
plug in fancy cables to the device and
just rip the zeros and ones off of the
device and see what's actually there
full dis encryption means they could do
that but they would just see seemingly
random zeros and ones now there's a
downside here too this might slow things
down potentially but it is a feature
increasingly that's offered and is
absolutely something you should consider
enabling um in general especially if
your laptop or phone travels with you
and certainly your phone does or if you
plan to donate or sell or give away a
device you don't want to leave all of
the zeros and ones the remnants of your
own sensitive data passed on there so
Windows has a feature called bit Locker
Mac OS has a feature called file Vault
there's commercial options as well but
generally we're at the point now in 2022
we're clicking a button is suff
efficient to enable these features with
that said don't rush into all of these
decisions I would make backups of your
data and don't maybe email cs50 if
something goes wrong with that process
but I would do your own due diligence
but this too would be a menu of
possibilities and now the bad side the
downside of what seems to be great this
notion of full dis encryption
unfortunately just as we can encrypt our
data to protect it from the adversaries
so can the adversaries if they get into
our devices encrypt our data and do what
not tell us that secret key and so this
is generally applied in the context of
ransomware which tragically you
increasingly hear about in Hospital
Systems school systems municipalities
where systems are getting attacked and
the data is not just getting stolen
because what is the adversary typically
need with like local municipal or even
Hospital data the value to the adversary
is encrypting all of the hospital all of
the mpali data preventing them from
accessing it if they have no backups or
the like and so ransomware is liter
Lally about trying to convince someone
to pay you money or pay you Bitcoin or
something like that to give you that
secret key and this key in this case is
surely more sophisticated than the
number one but it's really the same idea
so here too yet again a trade-off just
as we sort of invent something for good
it can also be used for evil and so to
speak as well but it's really the same
underlying principles even though we
keep seeing it and hearing about it in
these different forms and lastly if only
because folks are generally familiar but
don't necessarily know what it is that
it's doing for them browsers nowadays
have what's often called incognito mode
or private mode which has nothing to do
with encryption but does have to do with
cyber security or really cyber privacy
keeping your data from prying eyes uh
incognito mode if you open it in Chrome
for instance looks a little something
like this and we use it in cs50 when
introducing students as we did last week
to web programming because it in effect
lets you start with a clean slate like a
brand new browser that has never visited
any websites before which is good for
just diagnosing problems but it's often
commonly used if you want to log into
maybe your Gmail account on someone
else's computer and you don't want your
password being saved or you want to
visit some website where you don't want
the URL or the Search terms ending up in
your autocomplete history so there's
multiple uses for incognito mode but
what does it really do well it doesn't
stop your company it doesn't stop your
University your internet service
provider be it Comcast Verizon or the
like from knowing what websites you go
to because ask your student a couple
weeks ago we talked about actually a
week ago we talked about how the
internet works and unfortunately
computer has an IP address which is
unique identifier which goes out anytime
you go anywhere incognito mode or not so
this isn't really covering your tracks
outside of your office or outside of
your home or outside of your company but
it is at least throwing away local
information and so we'll talk in fact in
cs50 is week nine this coming Monday
about cookies which you might generally
know about and what are called sessions
and so long story short what incognito
mode does is it throws away when you
close the window any locally stored
information to the these things called
cookies which are sort of like virtual
handstamps that just remember what
you've logged in as or what's in your
shopping cart or the like but it doesn't
hide any information from anyone outside
of your own Mac or PC it only prevents
those local prying eyes so there too
even though we have tools that many of
you are probably in the habit of using
or thinking you should use to um be more
private be more secure on the internet
what we do really in cs50 boast week's
uh past and future is talk about how
these Technologies work so that
ultimately we have all the more of an
educated citizenry um here among
undergrads and here as well as on line
so that you can apply these same Lessons
Learned to problems you'll encounter in
the future so as promised the homework
one should probably use a password
manager doesn't have to be one of those
ones on the list but at least starting
that conversation maybe with someone who
does maybe the you know it's often the
you know the the the student in your
family perhaps who can advise you on
some of these Technologies consider
using a password manager to using
two-factor authentication whether it's
your phone or some key fob or or the
like but at least seeking out that
feature at least for accounts that you
really care about your email social
media Financial medical anything where
you'd be embarrassed at best or really
violated at worst if that kind of
information got out and then
increasingly using not just encryption
which you kind of get automatically for
most Technologies today but increasingly
choosing technologies that offer
stronger guarantees that keep those
middlemen those companies out of the way
if only so that you can trust with
higher probability that only party B
knows what party a has said or sent now
this of course was a whirlwind tour
there's so much more that you can do
online indeed this course cs50 can be
taken for free online via platforms like
edex at edx.org cs50 I thought it might
be appropriate to end on this note if
anyone would like to conjecture before
we start playing music and adjourn for
lunch what our final message here
is if we reverse the plus one and maybe
start minus one here minus one here and
indeed thank you so much for coming this
was
[Applause]
[Music]
cs50